<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. II:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.   250 K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. II</title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> 62 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LONDON:BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher><date>1849</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number RBC Dickens 20  (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi>
</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.
 </p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords scheme="LCSH"><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-11-05"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-26">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_verso_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"> No. II. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate> JUNE.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER. <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docAuthor><docImprint>

<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:—J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW: J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><head >HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head><p >THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of Bedding, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest stock and greatest variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES, <lb/> Of which they were the Original Introducers: these Mattresses are made of the finest materials, quite equal to the best made in Paris. Also, <lb/> GERMAN SPRING MATTRESSES.</p><p >These HEAL and SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are selling at a much lower price than any other house, and can recommend one of them, with a FRENCH MATTRESS on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p><p >THE EIDER DOWN QUILT, <lb/> also, is to be seen <hi rend="italics">only</hi> at their House. It is the warmest, the lightest, and the most elegant covering ever introduced, suitable to the <hi rend="italics">Bed,</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Couch,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">Carriage.</hi> All who have travelled on the Continent are aware that no covering produces such extreme warmth with the same weight; so that for Invalids they are a perfect luxury. Their <lb/> BED FEATHERS <lb/> are also PURIFIED BY STEAM, WITH PATENT MACHINERY, by which the offensive properties of the quill are evaporated and carried off, without subjecting the Feathers to the unpleasant smell of the stove, to which all Feathers dressed in the ordinary way are liable.</p><p >OLD FEATHER-BEDS re-dressed by this process are perfectly freed from all impurities; and, by expanding the Feathers, the bulk is greatly increased, and the Bed consequently rendered much fuller and softer, at 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb.</p><p >OLD AND MOTHY MATTRESSES effectually cured and re-made.</p><p >Every description of BLANKETS, QUILTS, and SHEETINGS.</p><div type="section"><head >HEAL AND SON'S LIST OF BEDDING</head><p >CONTAINS FULL PARTICULARS OF <lb/> WEIGHTS, SIZES, AND PRICES, <lb/> Of every description of Bedding, and is so arranged that purchasers are enabled to judge of the articles best suitable to make a comfortable Bed.</p><p >SENT FREE BY POST, on application to their Factory,</p><closer >196, (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL), <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. II—June, 1849.</opener><head >COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head><div><head >VALUABLE STANDARD BOOKS, <lb/> AT VERY LOW PRICES.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Just Published,</hi>
<lb/> NEW WORK ON EMIGRATION: <lb/> CANADA, THE UNITED STATES, TEXAS, OREGON, VANCOUVER'S ISLAND, CALIFORNIA, <lb/> PRINCE EDWARD'S ISLAND, NEW BRUNSWICK, CAPE BRETON, NOVA SCOTIA, <lb/> &amp;c. &amp;c. <lb/> THE SETTLER'S NEW HOME; <lb/> Or, The Emigrant's Location.</p><p >BY SYDNEY SMITH.</p><p >CONTAINING: <hi rend="italics">Whether to go, and Whither; Colonisation; The Outfit; Ship; Voyage; Landing; Inland Journey; Settlement; Climate; Health; Cost of Land and Living; Society; Management of Capital; Wages; Occupation; Life in the New Home; The St. Lawrence; The Lukes; The Valley of the Mississippi; The Prairies; The Backwoods; The South; The East; Prospects in the Towns; Sports in the Flood and Field; Work on the Farm, &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi></p><div type="section"><head >PRICE ONE SHILLING.</head><p >PICTORIAL BIBLE. By Dr. JOHN KITTO. 4 vols., enlarged Edition, very numerous Steel Plates, and Woodcuts, and Maps, beautifully bound, calf, gilt edges. 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >PICTORIAL HISTORY OF ENGLAND; complete. 8 vols., many hundred Woodcuts, and 104 Steel Portraits, handsomely bound, calf extra, 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >_____The same, cloth binding, 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p><p >PICTORIAL SHAKESPEARE; Knight's Original Edition; including the Biography, &amp;c. 8 vols. royal 8vo, cloth, 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 7<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>)</p><p >“This edition is now out of print, and very scarce.”</p><p >PICTORIAL SHAKESPEARE; Knight's Standard Edition; complete in 7 vols. royal 8vo, in handsome binding, half morocco, full gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >PICTORIAL HISTORY OF LONDON. By CHARLES KNIGHT. 6 vols. in 3, cloth, 600 Engravings, 35s. (pub. at 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p><p >“The most interesting and amusing account of the City of the World ever published.”</p><p >PENNY CYCLOPÆDIA; complete. 27 vols., strongly half-bound morocco, 8.</p><p >_____The same, in cloth, with the Supplement. 29 vols., 7<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 8<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p><p >SIR WALTER SCOTT'S WAVERLEY NOVELS; the Abbotstord Edition; complete in 12 vols. royal 8vo, containing 2,120 Engravings, half-bound, green morocco, ornamented, 8<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>); in cloth, or in cloth binding, with handsome designs, for 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >SIR WALTER SCOTT'S WORKS; including the WAVERLEY NOVELS, POETICAL WORKS, LIFE OF NAPOLEON, MISCELLANEOUS PROSE WORKS, TALES OF A GRANDFATHER, and LIFE OF SIR WALTER SCOTT, by LOCKHART. “THE ABBOTSFORD EDITION.” 17 vols. royal 8vo, 2,200 Illustrations on Steel and Wood, by TURNER, LANDSEER, STANFIELD, and others, handsomely half-bound morocco, 12<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> being less than half price.</p><p >_____The same, in handsome cloth binding, for 9<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >SIR WALTER SCOTT'S NOVELS. 48 vols. Plates, large type, half-bound in morocco, gilt, 7<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >_____The same, in cloth binding, for 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >_____25 vols., complete; the Portable Edition; a Novel complete in a volume, half-morocco, gilt, 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or in cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >_____5 vols. 8vo, cloth, 35<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >SIR WALTER SCOTT'S COMPLETE WORKS; the Author's own favourite Edition. 93 vols. 12mo. Plates by TURNER, &amp;c. 10<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >_____The same, 10 vols. royal 8vo, half-bound calf. 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >IRELAND; its SCENERY, CHARACTER, &amp;c. By Mr. and Mrs. S. C. HALL. 3 vols. 8vo, 548 Illustrations, handsomely bound in cloth, 35<hi rend="italics">s</hi> (pub. at 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p><p >HALL'S BOOK OF BALLADS. 2 vols. impl. 8vo, 400 Illustrations, 28s (pub. at 3<hi rend="italics">l</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p><p >MONTGOMERY'S SACRED GIFT. Fine Engravings on Steel, impl. 8vo, handsomely bound. 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 21<hi rend="italics">s</hi>)</p><p >ALLOM'S CHARACTER AND COSTUME IN TURKEY. 20 Plates, 4to, red cloth, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>)</p><p >THE MEDITERRANEAN ILLUSTRATED, in a series of 65 beautiful Engravings; with Descriptions by the Rev. G. N. WRIGHT, M. A. 2 vols cloth, ornamented, 16s. (pub. at 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p><p >WRIGHT'S HISTORY &amp; TOPOGRAPHY OF THE COUNTY OF ESSEX; comprising its Ancient and Modern History, a general view of its Physical Character, Productions, Agricultural Condition, Statistics, &amp;c. &amp;c. 2 vols. 4to, cloth gilt, illustrated with 101 beautiful Engravings, 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub at 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p><p >BYRON'S (LORD) WORKS, 8vo. Illustrated with a Series of 72 beautiful Portraits and Views, engraved by FINDEN. Elegantly bound in white vellum and gold, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">Murray,</hi> 1848</p><p >POPE'S WORKS; with his Translations of Homer. Edited by CARY. Royal 8vo, half-morocco, gilt, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; or calf gilt, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.)</p><p >COWPER'S WORKS; with his Translations of Homer. Edited by CARY. Royal 8vo, half-morocco, gilt, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; or calf gilt, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >MILTON, THOMSON, AND YOUNG'S POETICAL WORKS: complete in one vol. 8vo. half morocco, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; or calf gilt, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.)</p><p >MEREWETHER AND STEPHENS' HISTORY of the BOROUGHS and MUNICIPAL CORPORATIONS of the UNITED KINGDOM, from the Earliest Time to the Present Time; with Charters, &amp;c. &amp;c. 3 vols. royal 8vo, half calf, 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>)</p><p >1835</p><closer >JOHN KENDRICK, No. 4, CHARLOTTE ROW, MANSION HOUSE, LONDON.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >MR. COLBURN'S NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Now ready, complete in One Volume, with a New Preface, and Portrait, 6s. bound, the</hi>
<lb/> POPULAR EDITION OF MR. DISRAELI'S CONINGSBY.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Also, now ready, in Two Volumes,</hi>
<lb/> THE NEW WORK BY CAPTAIN MARRYAT.</p><p >VALERIE: AN AUTOBIOGRAPHY.</p><p >The Lottery of Marriage.</p><p >BY MRS. TROLLOPE.</p><p >3 vols.</p><p >English Homes and Foreign <lb/> Wanderings.</p><p >BY LADY LISTER KAYE.</p><p >2 vols.</p><p >Adventures of a Greek Lady, <lb/> (THE COUNTESS DE STEPHANO,) <lb/> The Adopted Daughter of the late Queen Caroline, <lb/> WRITTEN BY HERSELF.</p><p >Comprising Curious Anecdotes and Particulars of <lb/> Queen Caroline and her Suite, not hitherto known.</p><p >2 vols.</p><closer >HENRY COLBURN, PUBLISHER, 13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >POPULAR NATURAL HISTORY.</head><p >EPISODES OF INSECT LIFE, Crown Svo. 36 Engravings. Fancy cloth, <lb/> 16<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> coloured and bound in silk, 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The letter-press is illustrated with vignettes clearly and cleverly drawn on stone, and the whole pile of natural history—fable, poetry, theory, and fact—is stuck over with quaint apopthegms and shrewd maxims deduced for the benefit of man from the contemplation of such tiny monitors as gnats and moths.—Altogether the book is a curious and interesting one—quaint and clever, genial and well informed.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“Professor Nichol has done much to make astronomy a lightsome science; Mr. Miller has thrown the influence of eloquent and powerful writing around the fossils of the old red sandstone. Neither, however, has produced a work equal in the particular above mentioned to the ‘Episodes of Insect Life.’”—<hi rend="italics">Tait's Magazine.</hi></p><p >POPULAR BRITISH SEA-WEEDS; comprising a familiar and technical description of the MARINE PLANTS common to the shores of the British Isles. By the Rev. DAVID LANDSBOROUGH, A.L.S. One vol. royal 16mo, with twenty plates of figures. Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured. <hi rend="italics">In the Press.</hi></p><p >POPULAR BRITISH ORNITHOLOGY, comprising all the British Birds. By P. H. GOSSE. Royal 16mo. 20 Plates of Figures. 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> plain; 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured.</p><p >POPULAR BRITISH ENTOMOLOGY. By MARIA E. CATLOW. Royal 16mo. 16 Plates of Figures. 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> plain; 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured.</p><p >POPULAR FIELD BOTANY. By AGNES CATLOW. Royal 16mo. 20 Plates of Figures. 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> plain; 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured.</p><closer >REEVE, BENHAM, &amp; REEVE, KING WILLIAM STREET, STRAND.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >POPULAR EDITION OF MR. TUPPER'S TALES.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">On July 1st will be published, price 2s. 6d., a cheap Reprint of</hi>
<lb/> THE CROCK OF GOLD.</p><p >BY MARTIN F. TUPPER, ESQ.</p><p >With an Illustration by John Leech.</p><closer >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi></opener><p >COURT ETIQUETTE. A Guide to Levees, Drawing Rooms, Courts and Audiences, the Usages of Social Life, the Formal Modes of Addressing Letters, Memorials, Addresses and Petitions, the Rules of Precedence, the Composition of Dedications, the Etiquette of Public Meetings, and every other formality of business or pleasure. By a MAN OF THE WORLD. Royal 18mo, handsomely bound, Illustrated with Engravings, gilt and lettered, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >Published by C. MITCHELL, Red Lion Court, Fleet Street, London, who sends the work, <hi rend="italics">post free,</hi> to any address, on receipt of Postage Stamps of the above value. May also be had (by order) of any Bookseller.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">This day is Published, in small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., with numerous Illustrations by</hi> RICHARD DOYLE,</opener><head >THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</head><p >A Faird Cale for Little People.</p><p >BY MARK LEMON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now Ready, in crown octavo, price 16s.</hi></opener><head >PAXTON'S BOTANICAL DICTIONARY.</head><p >A NEW EDITION, CORRECTED TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Comprising the Names, History, and Culture of all Plants known in Britain, with a full</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Explanation of Technical Terms.</hi></p><p >Prepared as an instant resource and standard of consultation, and invaluable to all lovers of horticulture in all its branches and of every grade. Within its columns is compressed all the most important information relative to admired plants, which its size and avowed design would admit, and with this volume in his pocket the cultivator of plants may perambulate his own garden, and visit those of his friends, or public exhibitions, in the full assurance of deriving every fact of interest respecting any particular object that may engage his attention.</p><p >For the convenience of persons possessing the First Edition, a SUPPLEMENT, containing all the New <lb/> Plants since its appearance, is published, price 5s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now publishing in Monthly Numbers, price One Shilling each, with Illustrations on Steel</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">and Wood by the Author, to be completed in Twenty Numbers,</hi></opener><head >PENDENNIS: <lb/> His Fortunes and Misfortunes, His Friends, and His Greatest Enemy.</head><p >BY, W. M. THACKERAY, <lb/> Author of “Vanity Fair,” “The Great Hoggarty Diamond,” &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >“We recognise in ‘Pendennis’ the able and vigorous intellect which evinced so intimate a knowledge of life and such inimitable powers of portraiture in ‘Vanity Fair.’ Mr. Thackeray's sympathies are all healthy and invigorating—there is an indomitable spirit of English frankness and manliness about him—he is the sworn enemy of all humbug and pretension, and the good humoured but effective satire and ridicule with which he assails them, his extraordinary aptitude in the delineation of character, and his happy facility in seizing its salient points, the quiet unpremeditatedness with which his thoughts flow from his pen, and the tone of wholesome morality which pervades his writings, all combine to render him deservedly popular.” <hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now complete in One Volume, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s., with Twelve Illustrations by</hi> JOHN LEECH,</opener><head >A MAN MADE OF MONEY.</head><p >BY DOUGLAS JERROLD.</p><p >“This, Mr. Jerrold's last work, is without comparison, his greatest. It displays a rare combination of fancy, philosophy, and kindliness, which will cause it to be kept warm in the memory of the public when many a production now at the summit of popularity shall be swept into the gulf of oblivion. <hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11 BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price 7s., handsomely bound in cloth, with numerous Woodcuts representing the</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Processes of Grafting, Budding, Layering, &amp;c.,</hi></opener><head >THE LADIES' COMPANION TO THE <lb/> FLOWER GARDEN.</head><p >Being an Alphabetical Arrangement of all the Ornamental Plants grown in Gardens and Shrubberies; <lb/> with Full Directions for their Culture.</p><p >BY MRS. LOUDON.</p><p >THE FIFTH EDITION, CORRECTED TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p><closer >London: Published, for the Proprietor, by Bradbury &amp; Evans, 11, Bourerie Street.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >WORKS BY MR. CHARLES DICKENS.</head><p >I. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Complete in One thick Volume</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s. in cloth, or</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. half-bound in morocco,</hi>
<lb/> DOMBEY AND SON.</p><p >WITH FORTY ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</p><p >II. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In One Volume demy</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo. Price</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s., uniform with “Pickwick Papers.”</hi></p><p >THE <lb/> LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF OLIVER TWIST.</p><p >This Edition has been carefully corrected by the Author throughout, and contains the whole of the <lb/> Original Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p><p >III. <lb/> PICTURES FROM ITALY.</p><p >SECOND EDITION. FCAP 8vo. PRICE 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >CONTENTS.</p><p >Paris to Chalons.—Lyons, the Rhone, and the Goblin of Avignon.—Avignon to Genoa.—Genoa and its Neighbourhood.—Parma, Modena and Bologna.—Ferrara.—Verona, Mantus, Milan, and the Simplon.—Rome, Naples, and Florence.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound in cloth, with gill edges,</hi>
<lb/> THE ILLUSTRATIONS BY D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, <lb/> JOHN TENNIEL, AND RICHARD DOYLE.</p><p >IV. <lb/> THE CHIMES.</p><p >A GOBLIN STORY OF SOME BELLS THAT RANO AN OLD <lb/> YEAR OUT AND A NEW YEAR IN.</p><p >V. <lb/> THE HAUNTED MAN AND THE <lb/> GHOST'S BARGAIN.</p><p >A FANCY FOR CHRISTMAS-TIME.</p><p >VI. <lb/> THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH. </p><p >A FAIRY TALE OF HOME.</p><p >VII. <lb/> A CHRISTMAS CAROL, IN PROSE.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> THE BATTLE OF LIFE.</p><p >A LOVE STORY.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BOTANICAL WORKS BY PROFESSOR LINDLEY.</head><p >I. <lb/> THE VEGETABLE KINGDOM; <lb/> OR, <lb/> THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS.</p><p >ILLUSTRATED UPON THE NATURAL SYSTEM.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Second Edition, with additional Genera, in one large volume</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, with upwards of Five Hundred</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Illustrations, price</hi> 30<hi rend="italics">s. in cloth,</hi> II. <lb/> THE ELEMENTS OF BOTANY, <lb/> STRUCTURAL, PHYSIOLOGICAL, AND MEDICAL.</p><p >Being a Sixth Edition of the Outline of the First Principles of Botany, a Sketch of the Artificial Methods of <lb/> Classification, and a Glossary of Technical Terms.</p><p >Price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Glossary may be had separately, price Five Shillings.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> SCHOOL BOTANY; <lb/> OR, <lb/> THE RUDIMENTS OF BOTANICAL SCIENCE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A New Edition, in demy</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, with Nearly Four Hundred Illustrations, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. half-bound.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">In the Press, and shortly will be published, in One Volume</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi>
<lb/> THE ELEMENTS OF MEDICAL AND ECONOMICAL BOTANY.</p><p >WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS.</p><closer >BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><opener >Now ready, in 8vo, cloth lettered, price 10s.</opener><p >LONDON CATALOGUE OF BOOKS—SUPPLEMENT, 1846-49, containing all the New Works published during that period, with their sizes, prices, and publishers' names; also the New Editions, altered in price WITH A CLASSIFIED INDEX TO THE NEW WORKS.</p><p >T. HODGSON, 13, Paternoster Row, and sold by all Booksellers. Of whom also may be had, the LONDON CATALOGUE of BOOKS, with the Supplement, complete from 1814 to 1849, in One large Volume, 8vo.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE LAST OF THE BARONS.</head><p >BY <lb/> SIR EDWARD BULWER LYTTON, BART., <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Is now in course of Publication, in Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d., and in Monthly Parts, price 7d.,</hi>
<lb/> IN THE <lb/> NEW POPULAR EDITION <lb/> OF <lb/> SIR EDWARD BULWER LYTTON'S WORKS.</p><p >
<table><head>TALES ALREADY COMPLETED IN THIS EDITION, WITH A FRONTISPIECE AND NEW PREFACE, handsomely bound in cloth, gilt back:—</head><row><cell> EUGENE ARAM (<hi rend="italics">Just published</hi>) </cell><cell> price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> PELHAM </cell><cell> price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> PAUL CLIFFORD </cell><cell> price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> RIENZI </cell><cell> price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row></table>
</p><closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.<lb/>SOLD BY ALL BOOKSELLERS AND NEWSMEN, AND AT THE RAILWAY STATIONS.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just Published, in One vol., 8vo, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head >HOMŒOPATHY IN ACUTE DISEASES,</head><p >WITH NUMEROUS CASES.</p><p >BY STEPHEN YELDHAM, M.R.C.S., &amp;c.</p><p >“Mr. Yeldham's book is incomparably the boldest challenge which has ever been conveyed by the press of this country to the impugners of Homœopathy.”—<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><closer >H. BAILLIERE, 219, Regent-street, and AYLOTT &amp; JONES, 8, Paternoster-row.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Just delivered to the Trade, price</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></opener><head >OLD LONDON BRIDGE.</head><p >An Historical Romance.</p><p >BY GEORGE HERBERT RODWELL, ESQ., <lb/> Illustrated with Twenty-four Steel Engravings by ASHLEY, and an elaborate Frontispiece of the Bridge, built by the Priest Architect, Peter of Colechurch, the first which ever crossed the River Thames, and which withstood the raging of nearly a million of floods during the lapse of six entire centuries.</p><p >THE WORK IS HANDSOMELY BOUND IN THE ANTIQUE STYLE.</p><p >“The graceful musical composer—the facetious biographer of the ‘Umbrella,’ has adventured upon a novel theme, even for a novelist: he has invested the recollections of an old bridge with the interest and fascination of romance. But that bridge is one of historical celebrity—the first stone bridge ever built on the Thames—the master-piece of the priest architect, Peter of Colechurch—the structure built in thirty years, dating from 1176—‘Old London Bridge.’ Now that the narrative is completed, we may commend it as a companion story with the ‘Windsor Castle,’ the ‘Old St. Paul's,’ and the ‘Tower of London,’ by Harrison Ainsworth; and while we may speak thus eulogistically of Mr. Rodwell, we may say that, in several of the engravings before us, the illustrator, Mr. Ashley, may fear no comparison, even with such eminent and practical designers as ‘Phiz’ and Cruikshank.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p><closer >J. &amp; D. A. DARLING, 126, BISHOPSGATE STREET; <lb/> SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; CO., STATIONERS' HALL COURT.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >NEW and IMPORTANT WORK on BLIGHT.—</head><p >Just published, price 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> cloth boards and beautifully Illustrated with Woodcuts, the LETTERS of RUSTICUS on BLIGHT.</p><p >“There is a woodcut, some of them most exquisite, to each chapter, and tail-pieces, after the delightful manner of Bewick, are scattered through the work. It is a most delightful book.”—<hi rend="italics">Jerrold's Weekly News, January</hi> 6, 1849.</p><p >“The most charming contribution to Natural History since the days of good old Gilbert White. These letters are well worthy of consultation by all gardeners and agriculturalists, since the descriptions of these facts are perfectly trustworthy, being in all cases the result of observation.”—<hi rend="italics">Westminster Review, January</hi> 1849.</p><p >“The collection of facts and observations respecting blights, or insects injurious to vegetation, are especially worthy attention, and we recommend them strongly.”—<hi rend="italics">Gardeners' and Farmers' Journal, January</hi> 20, 1849.</p><p >“A very am using and instructive volume.”—<hi rend="italics">Chambers' Edinburgh Journal, February</hi> 3, 1849.</p><p >“This work contains by far the best account extant of those insects which are injurious to vegetation, and known by the name of <hi rend="italics">blight:</hi> the descriptions are no less remarkable for their accuracy than for their popular style and graphic power.”—<hi rend="italics">Knox's Ornithological Rambles.</hi></p><closer >JOHN VAN VOORST, Paternoster Row.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Published, this day, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >THE ART of MODELLING WAXEN FLOWERS, FRUIT, &amp;c.</head><p >By G. W. FRANCIS, F.L.S. This work contains every information connected with this delightful Art, and is Illustrated with numerous Wood Engravings of Moulds, Patterns, Parts of Flowers, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><closer >SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co., Stationers' Hall Court; D. FRANCIS, 21, Mile End Road; and all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just Published, Third Edition, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></opener><head >THE LITTLE ENGLISH FLORA,</head><p >or a Botanical and Popular Account of all our common Field Flowers, with Engravings on Steel of every Species, and numerous Woodcuts. By G. W. FRANCIS, F.L.S.</p><closer >SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co., Stationers' Hall Court; D. FRANCIS, 21, Mile End Road; and all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >LIFE ASSURANCE.—</head><p >An Historical and Statistical Account of the Population, the Law of Mortality, and the Different Systems of Life Assurance: including the Validity and non-validity of Life Policies: with Observations on FRIENDLY SOCIETIES and SAVINGS' BANKS; to which is added a Review of Life Assurance, explanatory of the Nature, Advantages, and the Various Purposes to which it may be applied. By ALFRED BURT, Esq., Secretary to a Life Office.</p><p >“Quam quisque novit artem, in eâ se exerceat.”—CIC.</p><closer >London: EFFINGHAM WILSON, Royal Exchange; and all other Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >GLENNY'S HAND-BOOK</head><p >to the FLOWER GARDEN and GREENHOUSE, <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>compl te</sic><corr>complete</corr></choice> in Twelve Monthly Parts, contains the Description, Culture, and Management of all the popular Flowers grown in this country, with a Calendar of Gardening Operations for every month.</p><p >Parts I., II., III., and IV., price 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, now ready, and sold by all Booksellers.</p><closer >C. Cox, 12, King William Street, Strand.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CIRCULATING LIBRARY.</head><p >A BARGAIN.</p><p >FOUR HUNDRED VOLUMES of MODERN NOVELS for £20, by the most popular Authors; namely, DICKENS, COOPER, JAMES, BULWEE, MARRYAT, Mrs. GOEE, Mrs. TROLLOPE, Mrs. MARSH, &amp;c. &amp;c.; in good condition.</p><p >Apply to W. HYDE, Bookseller, 17, Titchfield Street, Oxford Street, three doors from Mortimer Street.</p><p >A Catalogue of 3,000 volumes will be published in June. Sent post-free on application.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >TO secure Household Linen and Wearing Apparel against Loss or mistake, use</opener><head >BOND'S PERMANENT MARKING INK.</head><p >The Original, and by far the best, requiring no preparation.</p><p >Prepared by the Inventor, JOHN BOND, 28, Long Lane, West Smithfield, City, and sold by most Chemists, Stationers, and Medicine Vendors. Price One Shilling a bottle.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >COPY YOUR LETTERS.</head><p >No man of business should write a letter, or transmit any document of importance, without keeping a copy of it. The additional labour of copying by hand, caused by the introduction of cheap postage, may be entirely saved; as twenty letters may be copied in five minutes; by WATERLOW &amp; SONS'<lb/>Improved Patent Copying Machines, <lb/> The Working Parts manufactured of Steel, and finished with the greatest accuracy.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Machine. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Machine. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Mach. wrt. iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell><cell> Copying Books, 4to, Type-Paged. </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> LAROE 4to </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 0s. </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3s. </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15s. </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 11s. </cell><cell> 500 leaves, </cell><cell> 8s. </cell></row><row><cell> FOOLSCAP FOLIO </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 750 leaves, </cell><cell> 10 </cell></row><row><cell> POST FOLIO </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 1,000 leaves,
12 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >The above Presses, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and <lb/> will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p><closer >WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, &amp; 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >TRELOAR'S COCOA-NUT FIBRE WAREHOUSE, <lb/> 42, LUDGATE HILL.</head><p >The articles made from COCOA-NUT FIBRE consist of Matting, Hearth-rugs, Door-mats, Mattresses, Cushions, Hassocks, Netting for sheep folds, Clothes-lines, Cordage, Scrubbing Brushes, and Brushes for stable use. To ensure good quality at the lowest prices, apply direct to the Manufacturer, T. TRELOAR, 42, Ludgate Hill.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p >In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">e.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p><p >HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinatores, 10½<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p><p >INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p><p >An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head><p >FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.—Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >AMPUTATION AGAIN PREVENTED BY HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.—</head><p >Extract of a letter from Mr. S. Smith, 69, Capel Street, Dublin, dated March 13, 1849:—“To Professor Holloway.—Dear Sir,—I think it only my duty to inform you and the public of the wonderful cure your Ointment and Pills have effected on me. For three years I had a dreadful wound in my leg. I tried all the faculty in this city, but to no purpose; they informed me that nothing could save my life but amputation. I was then advised by a celebrated doctor to use your remedies, which in a brief period have healed my leg, and made it as strong as it formerly was.” Sold by all vendors of Medicine, and at Professor Holloway's establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET of BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy, and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.—“Robert Shaw, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >UNDER HER MAJESTY'S ROYAL LETTERS PATENT</head><p >The best and safest Medicine for Ladies. An eminent Physician says, “Ladies who take No. 1, from 14 to 20, and No. 2, from 20 to 50 years of age, pass through lite comparatively free from complaint, and never suffer from the painful diseases of advanced life.” Consumption is prevented—Chlorosis—General Weakness, accompanied by weariness and sinking at the pit of the stomach—Feverishness—Indigestion—Constipation—Loss of appetite—Flatulence—Heartburn—Giddiness—Palpitation—Pains in the Head, Stomach, Loins, and all Hysterical Affections are completely removed by their peculiar effects.</p><p >Sold by all the London Wholesale Houses: Barclay, Edwards, Sutton, Sanger, Dietrichsen, Prout, at Locock's Female Pill Warehouse, 16, King Street, Covent Garden, and all established Patent Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom. N.B “Locock's Female Pills” is engraved on the Government Stamp outside each Box.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BEAUTY.—</head><p >The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal—the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed “G. H. HOGARD” for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><opener >NO MORE PILLS NOR ANY OTHER MEDICINE.</opener><head >DU BARRY'S REVALENTA ARABICA FOOD.</head><p >THIS light delicious breakfast food, possessing those delicate, nutritive, and restorative properties so indispensable to invalids and the feeble, permanently removes dyspepsia (indigestion), habitual constipation, nausea and sickness at the stomach during pregnancy, at sea, or after meals, hemorrhoidal affections, nervousness, bilousness, heartburn, liver complaint, distension, flatulency, debility, asthma, low spirits, &amp;c., without inconvenience, medicine, or expense, as it saves other more costly food. DU BARRY &amp; Co., 127, New Bond Street, London. Agents in London: HEDGES &amp; BUTLER, FORTNUM, MASON, &amp; Co., purveyors to Her Majesty, the Queen; in Edinburgh, RAIMES &amp; Co.; in Dublin, BEWLEY, FISHER, &amp; Co,; and all respectable Dealers.</p><div type="section"><head >CASES.</head><p >From the Right Hon, the Lord Stuart De Decies, Dromana, Capoquin, County Waterford, Feb. 15, 1849.—“Gentlemen, I have derived much benefit from the use of the ‘Revalenta Food.’</p><p >“STUART DE DECIES.”</p><p >“4, Park Walk, Little Chelsea, London, Oct. 2, 1848.</p><p >“Twenty-seven years' dyspepsia has been effectually removed by your excellent ‘Revalenta Arabica Food’ in six weeks' time, &amp;c.</p><p >“PARKER D. BINGHAM, Captain, Royal Navy.”</p><p >“Pool Anthony, Tiverton, November 8, 1848.</p><p >“All that I had suffered from for twenty-five years, and which no medicine could remove or relieve, seems to vanish under the influence of ‘Revalenta.’ I enjoy sound and refreshing sleep, which, until now, I could not procure. Nervousness is passing away rapidly, and I am much more calm and collected in everything I do, and it has quite sweetened my poor temper. It now affords me pleasure to do for others what before I did not dare to do for nervous irritation, &amp;c.</p><p >“W.M. R. REEVES.”</p><p >“Bromley, Middlesex, March 31, 1849.</p><p >“Gentlemen,—The lady for whom I ordered your Food is six months advanced in pregnancy, and was suffering severely from indigestion, constipation, throwing up her meals shortly after eating them, having a great deal of heartburn, and being constantly obliged to resort to physic or the enema, and sometimes both. I am happy to inform you that your Food produced immediate relief. She has never been sick since, had but little heartburn, and the functions are more regular, &amp;c. I authorise the publication of this note if you think it may benefit other sufferers, and remain, gentlemen, faithfully yours, <lb/> “THOS. WOODHOUSE.”</p><p >“3, Sidney Terrace, Reading, Berks., Dec. 3, 1847.</p><p >“Gentlemen.—I am happy to be able to inform you that the person for whom the former quantity was procured has derived very great benefit from its use; distressing symptoms of long standing have been removed, and a feeling of restored health induced. Having witnessed the beneficial effects in the above-mentioned case, I can with confidence recommend it, and shall have much pleasure in so doing whenever an opportunity offers. I am, gentlemen, very truly yours, <lb/> “JAMES SHORLAND, late Surgeon, 96th Regiment.”</p><p >“21, Broad Street, Golden Square, London, Nov. 20, 1847.</p><p >(Details of nineteen years' dyspepsia, nervousness, sickness at the stomach and vomiting, and liver complaint, and three weeks' “Revalenta” treatment.)—“I humbly and sincerely thank God, and yourselves, as His instruments, &amp;c.</p><p >“ISABELLA GRELLIERE.”</p><p >“Winslow, Bucks, Jan. 22, 1848.</p><p >“I have found it to be a simple, though very efficacious and pleasant food, doing good to my own and others' functional disorders.</p><p >“(Rev.) CHARLES KERR.”</p><p >“Athol-street, Perth, May 2, 1848.</p><p >“Some time has now elapsed since the lady (who had been an invalid for thirteen years from want of digestion, accompanied with cough and general prostration of strength) for whom I procured your ‘Arabica’ Food, has been using it daily as directed, and I am happy to say that it has produced a most salutary change in her system, &amp;c.</p><p >“JAMES PORTER.”</p><p >“Southwick Park, Fareham, Hants, Oct. 31, 1848.</p><p >“Gentlemen,—I sincerely thank you for your kind attention. When I began taking the ‘Revalenta’ I was in as deplorable a condition as can well be imagined. I was confined to bed, and so weak that I could neither stand nor walk, &amp;c. &amp;c. I am happy to say that I get stronger, and my health better every day, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >“JOHN VASS, <hi rend="italics">Land Steward.</hi>”</p><p >Similar expressions of gratitude from William Hunt, Esq., Barrister-at-law, King's College, Cambridge James Shorland, Esq., late Surgeon, 96th Regt., Reading, Berks, and 5,000 other correspondents.</p><p >In canisters at 4s. 6d.; 4lb. at 11s.; 10lb, at 22s.; super-refined quality, 4lb. 22s.; and 8lb. 33s.; suitably packed for all climates. 8lb. and 10lb. canisters forwarded by Du Barry &amp; Co., on receipt of Post-office or bankers' orders (carriage free) to any town or railroad station connected by rail with London.</p><closer >DU BARRY &amp; Co., 127, New Bond Street, London.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><opener >Under Royal Patronage.<lb/>PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES, <lb/> AND INSTANT RELIEF AND A RAPID CURE OF <lb/> ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, COLDS, <lb/> AND ALL DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS, <lb/> ARE INSURED BY</opener><head >DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated Testimonials, may be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">had from every Agent.</hi></p><p >THE FOLLOWING ARE A FEW LETTERS WHICH HAVE JUST BEEN RECEIVED:—</p><div><head >Cure of 50 years' Asthma.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Extract of a letter from Mr. J. Cunningham, farmer,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Ardingly, near Brighton.</hi></p><p >Sir,—I feel it a duty incumbent on me to inform you, for the benefit of others similarly afflicted, of the astonishing relief afforded to my wife by Dr. Locock's Wafers.</p><p >She was affected with confirmed asthma for fifty years, from which her sufferings were dreadful. She was recommended last winter by a friend to try the wafers; she did so, and the effect was truly astonishing; indeed, the first box gave her immediate relief.</p><closer >
<signed>(Signed) J. CUNNINGHAM.</signed>
</closer><trailer >Witness, Mr. W. W. Payne, 18, North Street, Brighton.</trailer></div><div><head >Important to all who Sing.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">From S. Pearsall, Esq., Her Majesty's Concerts, and</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Vicar Choral of Lichfield Cathedral.</hi></p><p >Lichfield, July 10, 1848.</p><p >Gentlemen,—A lady of distinction, having pointed out to me the qualities of Dr. Locock's Wafers. I was induced to make a trial of a box, and from this trial I am happy to give my testimonial in their favour. I find by allowing a few of the wafers (taken in the course of the day) to gradually dissolve in the mouth, my voice become bright and clear, and the tone full and distinct. They are decidedly the most efficacious of any I have ever used.</p><closer >
<signed>S. PEARSALL.</signed>
</closer></div><div><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >They have a pleasant taste. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >AGENTS: DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors.</p><p >PRICE, 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >The only Medicine recommended to be <lb/> taken by Females!</p><p >BEWARE OF IMITATIONS!</p><p >Unprincipled Persons Counterfeit this medicine in the form of PILLS, &amp;c. Purchasers must therefore observe that none are Genuine but “WAFERS,” and that the words <lb/> “DR. LOCOCK'S WAFERS” <lb/> are in the Stamp outside each Box.</p><p >OBSERVE.—<hi rend="italics">There are various Counterfeit Medicines, having words on the Stamp so</hi> NEARLY RESEMBLING THESE, <hi rend="italics">as to mislead the unwary. Purchasers must therefore strictly observe the above Caution.</hi></p><closer >Prepared only by the Proprietor's Agents, DA SILVA &amp; CO., <lb/> 1, Bride Lane, Fleet St., London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><head >USE <lb/> KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Co.'s <lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES.</head><p >Sold by every Draper &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE NEW PATENT SHOWER BATH.</head><p >R. AND J. SLACK, 335, STRAND, <lb/> Opposite Somerset House, <lb/> Beg to call attention to their new Shower Bath as an article far superior to any bath ever introduced, its action being so simple that a child can fill it. The great inconvenience in the old shower bath was the difficulty in raising the water, the pump requiring great labour, and consequent liability to get out of order; all these objections are obviated in this bath. May be seen in operation at 336, Strand, where may be inspected the most extensive assortment of baths, toilet sets, nickel and electro-plated ware, and every article in furnishing ironmongery at prices much lower than any other house where quality is considered. Sponging Baths, from <hi rend="italics">7s. 6d.</hi>; Hip ditto, 19s. and 21s.; Portable Shower Baths and Curtains, <hi rend="italics">7s 6d.</hi></p><closer >Their Catalogue, containing Two Hundred Drawings and Prices, may be had <lb/> gratis, or sent, post-free, to any part.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE INVISIBLE VENTILATING HEADS OF HAIR.</head><head >ROSS &amp; SON'S METHOD OF MEASURING <lb/> THE HEAD.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> The Round of the Head </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From Ear to Ear </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From Forehead to Poll </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >These inimitable works of art, for both Ladies and Gentlemen, from One Guinea-and-a-half upwards.</p><p >THE ATRAPILATORY, OR LIQUID HAIR DYE, the only Dye that really answers for all colours. Ross &amp; SONS can recommend the above Dye as intallible.</p><p >BOTANIC WATER AND BEAR'S GREASE. When the Hair is becoming thin, and falling off, the only effectual remedy is the use of the above named articles, applied alternately; the Botanic Water to cleanse and stimulate, and the Bear's Grease to nourish it.</p><p >THE NEW TOOTH-PICK TOOTH-BRUSH, thoroughly cleansing between the Teeth when used up and down, and polishing the surface when used crossways, the hair warranted never to come out. In four strengths. viz., No. 1, hard; No. 2, less hard; No. 3. medium; No. 4, soft.</p><p >THE DOUBLE ANTI-PRESSURE NAIL BRUSH: THE TRIPLE HAIR BRUSH; THE MEDIUM SHAVING BRUSH: THE “RENOVATOR” CLOTHES BRUSH. These articles being the inventions of Ross &amp; SONS, the public are requested to observe their names stamped on each.</p><p >If you wish to avoid all the torture “which Shaving has entailed upon your chins,” try ROSS &amp; SON'S RAILWAY STROP AND RAZOR, and if Travellers, supply yourselves with the ROSSIAN DRESSING CASE, which contains the largest number of conveniences in the smallest compass.</p><closer >Address, ROSS &amp; SONS, 119 and 120 Bishopsgate Street, London.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >J. INDERWICK.</head><p >58, PRINCES STREET, LEICESTER SQUARE, Begs to announce that he has just received from the Continent a large and well selected Stock of <lb/> “PURE MEERSCHAUM PIPES,” <lb/> Warranted of the finest quality and most approved shapes.</p><p >INDERWICK'S REGISTERED HYDRAULIC TUBE, The latest improvement in Smoking, <hi rend="italics">2s. 6d.</hi> each.</p><p >WHOLESALE AND RETAIL WAREHOUSE, for every description of Smoking Apparatus,</p><closer >58, PRINCES STREET, LEICESTER SQUARE.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p >and all other medicines of a nauseous character, may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT ORGANIC CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>wich</sic><corr>with</corr></choice> Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p><p >Ask for the Patent Flexible Capsules.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><head >ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head><p >THE superiority of Alpaca over every other material for Umbrellas, being now generally acknowledged, and the Patentees having granted licenses to several of the largest Manufacturers, the Public are respectfully informed that they may be procured of most Umbrella Dealers in the Kingdom, at the price of 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and upwards.</p><p >W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, <lb/> 140, Regent Street; 94, Fleet Street; and 10, Royal Exchange.</p><p >N.B. Upwards of 35,000 of these Umbrellas have been already sold.</p><p >W. &amp; J. S. have also always on hand a very extensive Stock of cheap <lb/> SILK UMBRELLAS, <lb/> From 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> and best ditto from 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head><p >EAGLAND'S newly invested INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORTERS will be found well deserving the attention of the Medical Profession, and of persons suffering under Spinal deformity and its consequences. As any attempt at a description must needs fall short of giving a correct idea of the plan itself, Mr. EAGLAND solicits an inspection. They are beautifully simple and eminently successful, quite imperceptible, and conceal the deformity from the keenest observer. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add, that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the highest respectability as to the remedial effects produced by their use.</p><closer >21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET, <lb/> LONDON.</closer><trailer >Hours Twelve to Five.</trailer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>overt o</sic><corr>over to</corr></choice> the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.</head><p >A CERTAIN REMEDY for disorders of the PULMONARY ORGANS—Difficulty of Breathing—in Redundancy of Phlegm-in Incipient CONSUMPTION (of which COUGH is the most positive indication) they are of unerring efficacy. In ASTHMA, and in WINTER COUGH, they have <hi rend="italics">never</hi> been known to fail.</p><p >Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and Tins, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Church Yard, London, and Retail by all Druggists and Patent Medicine Vendors in the Kingdom.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx3"/><head >FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS.</head><p >DOUDNEYS <lb/> Waterproofers, Habit Makers, and Tailors <lb/> TO QUEEN VICTORIA, QUEEN ADELAIDE, <lb/> H.R.H. Prince Albert, H.R.H. The Duchess of Kent, <lb/> KING LOUIS PHILIPPE, <lb/> And the ROYAL FAMILIES of ENGLAND and FRANCE.</p><p >The DOUDNEYS motto is “none but Good Articles can be cheap,” and with this ever in view, they have, by increasing efforts, established a Ready Money business of great extent among the strong holds of the old fashioned usurious Credit System. As to the character, and recommendatory influence of the approbation which has been bestowed upon their endeavours; let their Five Royal Appointments. and their Patronage Book filled with the Royal, Illustrious, and Noble names of their customers, testify.</p><p >The New Patterns for Spring and Summer wear are now ready for inspection at the Old Prices, so famous in seasons past, viz.:—Summer Waistcoats 7s. each, or 3 for 20s.-Summer Trousers 10s. 6d. per pair, or 3 for 30s.—Summer Coats, the beautiful light material 10s. 6d.—21s. and 30s.</p><p >The Queens Victoria and Adelaide, and the Royal and Noble Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge, Sutherland and Buccleuch, constantly wear Doudney's elegant Registered Cloak, in a variety of Waterproof, materials for Winter Wraps and the Promenade.—“Every Lady should see these graceful Garments.” <hi rend="italics">(Vide Morning Post, September</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">th.)</hi> They surpass all others for School Cloaks for the sons and daughters.</p><p >For Gentlemen.—The Royal Registered Cloak, as made for H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, the Nobility, the Army, and Navy, and all who study comfort, coupled with a truly Gentlemanly exterior. These cloaks are pronounced by those who understand the matter, “The most sensible Garment ever introduced,” at prices to suit all customers from the Superb down to the useful Guinea Cloak.</p><p >The New Patent Belt for Riding or general exercise, the only really effectual protection against rupture; the support commencing at the <hi rend="italics">bottom edge</hi> of the belt, and producing an uniform upward pressure. They may be enlarged or tightened to the extent of six inches at pleasure, and never produce indigestion either in Ladies or Gentlemen. They are attached to Drawers with excellent effect. The most eminent of the Faculty are recommending these in preference to all others.</p><p >LIVERIES. Three Guineas the Plain Suit of Best Quality. <hi rend="italics">Ready Money does it !!!</hi> and a very extensive practice among families of first distinction insures satisfactory results.</p><p >Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria and the Ladies of the Court. A Superfine Cloth Habit for 4 Guineas.</p><p >Waterproof Irish Poplin. The DOUDNEYS are the sole manufacturers of this beautiful article to HER MAJESTY AND THE PRINCE CONSORT. Gentlemen's Coats, Ladies Cloaks, and lengths for Dresses can be obtained only at their Establishment.</p><p >Country Gentlemen wishing to be Respectably Dressed at low Prices should send for a Book of detail, self-measurement and all the System of business, or if 3 or 4 Gentlemen unite, a Traveller will wait upon them.</p><closer >17, OLD BOND ST., 25, BURLINGTON ARCADE <lb/> AND 49, LOMBARD STREET—Established 1784.</closer></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">My musical breakfast.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p >
<figure><p><hi rend="italics">The friendly Waiter and I.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="p33"/><head >[THE 
<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER IV. <lb/> I FALL INTO DISGRACE.</head><p >IF the room to which my bed was removed, were a sentient thing that could give evidence, I might appeal to it at this day—who sleeps there now, I wonder!—to bear witness for me what a heavy heart I carried to it. I went up there, hearing the dog in the yard bark after me all the way while I climbed the stairs; and, looking as blank and strange upon the room as the room looked upon me, sat down with my small hands crossed, and thought.</p><p >I thought of the oddest things. Of the shape of the room, of the cracks in the ceiling, of the paper on the wall, of the flaws in the window-glass making ripples and dimples on the prospect, of the washing-stand being ricketty on its three legs, and having a discontented something about it, which reminded me of Mrs. Gummidge under the influence of the old one. I was crying all the time, but, except that I was conscious of being cold and dejected, I am sure I never thought why I cried. At last in my desolation I began to consider that I was dreadfully in love with little Em'ly, and had been torn away from her to come here where no one seemed to want me, or to care about me, half as much as she did. This made such a very miserable piece of business of it, that I rolled myself up in a corner of the counterpane, and cried myself to sleep.</p><p >I was awoke by somebody saying “Here he is!” and uncovering my hot head. My mother and Peggotty had come to look for me, and it was one of them who had done it.</p><p >“Davy,” said my mother. “What's the matter?”</p><p >I thought it very strange that she should ask me, and answered, “Nothing.” I turned over on my face, I recollect, to hide my trembling lip, which answered her with greater truth.</p><p >“Davy,” said my mother. “Davy, my child!”</p><p >I dare say no words she could have uttered, would have affected me so much, then, as her calling me her child. I hid my tears in the bedclothes, and pressed her from me with my hand, when she would have raised me up.</p><p >“This is your doing, Peggotty, you cruel thing!” said my mother. “I have no doubt at all about it. How can you reconcile it to your conscience, I wonder, to prejudice my own boy against me, or against anybody who is dear to me? What do you mean by it, Peggotty?”</p><p >Poor Peggotty lifted up her hands and eyes, and only answered, in a sort of paraphrase of the grace I usually repeated after dinner, “Lord forgive you, Mrs. Copperfield, and for what you have said this minute, may you never be truly sorry!”</p><p >“It's enough to distract me,” cried my mother. “In my honeymoon, too, when my most inveterate enemy might relent, one would think, and not envy me a little peace of mind and happiness. Davy, you naughty boy! Peggotty, you savage creature! Oh, dear me!” cried my mother,
<pb xml:id="p34"/>
turning from one of us to the other, in her pettish wilful manner, “what a troublesome world this is, when one has the most right to expect it to be as agreeable as possible!”</p><p >I felt the touch of a hand that I knew was neither her's nor Peggotty's, and slipped to my feet at the bed-side. It was Mr. Murdstone's hand, and he kept it on my arm as he said:</p><p >“What's this? Clara, my love, have you forgotten?—Firmness, my dear!”</p><p >“I am very sorry, Edward,” said my mother. “I meant to be very good, but I am so uncomfortable.”</p><p >“Indeed!” he answered. “That's a bad hearing, so soon, Clara.”</p><p >“I say it's very hard I should be made so now,” returned my mother, pouting; “and it is—very hard—isn't it?”</p><p >He drew her to him, whispered in her ear, and kissed her. I knew as well, when I saw my mother's head lean down upon his shoulder, and her arm touch his neck—I knew as well that he could mould her pliant nature into any form he chose, as I know, now, that he did it.</p><p >“Go you below, my love,” said Mr. Murdstone. “David and I will come down, together. My friend,” turning a darkening face on Peggotty, when he had watched my mother out, and dismissed her with a nod and a smile: “do you know your mistress's name?”</p><p >“She has been my mistress a long time, sir,” answered Peggotty. “I ought to it.”</p><p >“That's true,” he answered. “But I thought I heard you, as I came up-stairs, address her by a name that is not hers. She has taken mine, you know. Will you remember that?”</p><p >Peggotty, with some uneasy glances at me, curtseyed herself out of the room without replying; seeing, I suppose, that she was expected to go, and had no excuse for remaining. When we two were left alone, he shut the door, and sitting on a chair, and holding me standing before him, looked steadily into my eyes. I felt my own attracted, no less steadily, to his. As I recall our being opposed thus, face to face, I seem again to hear my heart beat fast and high.</p><p >“David,” he said, making his lips thin, by pressing them together, “if I have an obstinate horse or dog to deal with, what do you think I do?”</p><p >“I don't know.”</p><p >“I beat him.”</p><p >I had answered in a kind of breathless whisper, but I felt, in my silence, that my breath was shorter now.</p><p >“I make him wince, and smart. I say to myself, ‘I'll conquer that fellow;’ and if it were to cost him all the blood he had, I should do it. What is that upon your face?”</p><p >“Dirt,” I said.</p><p >He knew it was the mark of tears as well as I. But if he had asked the question twenty times, each time with twenty blows, I believe my baby heart would have burst before I would have told him so.</p><p >“You have a good deal of intelligence for a little fellow,” he said, with a grave smile that belonged to him, “and you understood me very well, I see. Wash that face, sir, and come down with me.”</p><pb  xml:id="p35"/><p >He pointed to the washing-stand, which I had made out to be like Mrs. Gummidge, and motioned me with his head to obey him directly. I had little doubt then, and I have less doubt now, that he would have knocked me down without the least compunction, if I had hesitated.</p><p >“Clara, my dear,” he said, when I had done his bidding, and he walked me into the parlor, with his hand still on my arm; “you will not be made uncomfortable any more, I hope. We shall soon improve our youthful humours.”</p><p >God help me, I might have been improved for my whole life, I might have been made another creature perhaps, for life, by a kind word at that season. A word of encouragement and explanation, of pity for my childish ignorance, of welcome home, of reassurance to me that it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> home, might have made me dutiful to him in my heart henceforth, instead of in my hypocritical outside, and might have made me respect instead of hate him. I thought my mother was sorry to see me standing in the room so scared and strange, and that, presently, when I stole to a chair, she followed me with her eyes more sorrowfully still—missing, perhaps, some freedom in my childish tread—but the word was not spoken, and the time for it was gone.</p><p >We dined alone, we three together. He seemed to be very fond of my mother—I am afraid I liked him none the better for that—and she was very fond of him. I gathered from what they said, that an elder sister of his was coming to stay with them, and that she was expected that evening. I am not certain whether I found out then, or afterwards, that, without being actively concerned in any business, he had some share in, or some annual charge upon the profits of, a wine-merchant's house in London, with which his family had been connected from his great-grandfather's time, and in which his sister had a similar interest; but I may mention it in this place, whether or no.</p><p >After dinner, when we were sitting by the fire, and I was meditating an escape to Peggotty without having the hardihood to slip away, lest it should offend the master of the house, a coach drove up to the garden-gate, and he went out to receive the visitor. My mother followed him. I was timidly following her, when she turned round at the parlordoor, in the dusk, and taking me in her embrace as she had been used to do, whispered me to love my new father and be obedient to him. She did this hurriedly and secretly, as if it were wrong, but tenderly; and, putting out her hand behind her, held mine in it, until we came near to where he was standing in the garden, where she let mine go, and drew her's through his arm.</p><p >It was Miss Murdstone who was arrived, and a gloomy-looking lady she was; dark, like her brother, whom she greatly resembled in face and voice; and with very heavy eyebrows, nearly meeting over her large nose, as if, being disabled by the wrongs of her sex from wearing whiskers, she had carried them to that account. She brought with her, two uncompromising hard black boxes, with her initials on the lids in hard brass nails. When she paid the coachman she took her money out of a hard steel purse, and she kept the purse in a very jail of a bag which hung upon her arm by a heavy chain, and shut up like a bite. I had never, at that time, seen such a metallic lady altogether as Miss Murdstone was.</p><pb  xml:id="p36"/><p >She was brought into the parlor with many tokens of welcome, and there formally recognised my mother as a new and near relation. Then she looked at me, and said:</p><p >“Is that your boy, sister-in-law?”</p><p >My mother acknowledged me.</p><p >“Generally speaking,” said Miss Murdstone, “I don't like boys. How d' ye do, boy?”</p><p >Under these encouraging circumstances, I replied that I was very well, and that I hoped she was the same; with such an indifferent grace, that Miss Murdstone disposed of me in two words:</p><p >“Wants manner!”</p><p >Having uttered which, with great distinctness, she begged the favor of being shewn to her room, which became to me from that time forth a place of awe and dread, wherein the two black boxes were never seen open or known to be left unlocked, and where (for I peeped in once or twice when she was out) numerous little steel fetters and rivets, with which Miss Murdstone embellished herself when she was dressed, generally hung upon the looking-glass in formidable array.</p><p >As well as I could make out, she had come for good, and had no intention of ever going again. She began to “help” my mother next morning, and was in and out of the store-closet all day, putting things to rights, and making havoc in the old arrangements. Almost the first remarkable thing I observed in Miss Murdstone was, her being constantly haunted by a suspicion that the servants had a man secreted somewhere on the premises. Under the influence of this delusion, she dived into the coal-cellar at the most untimely hours, and scarcely ever opened the door of a dark cupboard without clapping it to again, in the belief that she had got him.</p><p >Though there was nothing very airy about Miss Murdstone, she was a perfect Lark in point of getting up. She was up (and, as I believe to this hour, looking for that man) before anybody in the house was stirring. Peggotty gave it as her opinion that she even slept with one eye open; but I could not concur in this idea; for I tried it myself after hearing the suggestion thrown out, and found it couldn't be done.</p><p >On the very first morning after her arrival she was up and ringing her bell at cock-crow. When my mother came down to breakfast and was going to make the tea, Miss Murdstone gave her a kind of peck on the cheek, which was her nearest approach to a kiss, and said:</p><p >“Now, Clara, my dear, I am come here, you know, to relieve you of all the trouble I can. You're much too pretty and thoughtless”—my mother blushed but laughed, and seemed not to dislike this character—“to have any duties imposed upon you that can be undertaken by me. If you'll be so good as give me your keys, my dear, I'll attend to all this sort of thing in future.”</p><p >From that time, Miss Murdstone kept the keys in her own little jail all day, and under her pillow all night, and my mother had no more to do with them than I had.</p><p >My mother did not suffer her authority to pass from her without a shadow of protest. One night when Miss Murdstone had been developing certain household plans to her brother, of which he signified his approbation,
<pb xml:id="p37"/>
my mother suddenly began to cry, and said she thought she might have been consulted.</p><p >“Clara!” said Mr. Murdstone sternly. “Clara! I wonder at you.”</p><p >“Oh, it's very well to say you wonder, Edward!” cried my mother, “and it's very well for you to talk about firmness, but you wouldn't like it yourself.”</p><p >Firmness, I may observe, was the grand quality on which both Mr. and Miss Murdstone took their stand. However I might have expressed my comprehension of it at that time, if I had been called upon, I nevertheless did clearly comprehend in my own way, that it was another name for tyranny; and for a certain gloomy, arrogant, devil's humour, that was in them both. The creed, as I should state it now, was this. Mr. Murdstone was firm; nobody in his world was to be so firm as Mr. Murdstone; nobody else in his world was to be firm at all, for everybody was to be bent to his firmness. Miss Murdstone was an exception. She might be firm, but only by relationship, and in an inferior and tributary degree. My mother was another exception. She might be firm, and must be; but only in bearing their firmness, and firmly believing there was no other firmness upon earth.</p><p >“It's very hard,” said my mother, “that in my own house—”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">My</hi> own house?” repeated Mr. Murdstone. “Clara!”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Our</hi> own house, I mean,” faltered my mother, evidently frightened—“I hope you must know what I mean, Edward—it's very hard that in <hi rend="italics">your</hi> own house I may not have a word to say about domestic matters. I am sure I managed very well before we were married. There's evidence,” said my mother, sobbing; “ask Peggotty if I didn't do very well when I wasn't interfered with!”</p><p >“Edward,” said Miss Murdstone, “let there be an end of this. I go to-morrow.”</p><p >“Jane Murdstone,” said her brother, “be silent! How dare you to insinuate that you don't know my character better than your words imply?”</p><p >“I am sure,” my poor mother went on, at a grievous disadvantage, and with many tears, “I don't want anybody to go. I should be very miserable and unhappy if anybody was to go. I don't ask much. I am not unreasonable. I only want to be consulted sometimes. I am very much obliged to anybody who assists me, and I only want to be consulted as a mere form, sometimes. I thought you were pleased, once, with my being a little inexperienced and girlish, Edward—I am sure you said so—but you seem to hate me for it now, you are so severe.”</p><p >“Edward,” said Miss Murdstone, again, “let there be an end of this. I go to-morrow.”</p><p >“Jane Murdstone,” thundered Mr. Murdstone. “Will you be silent? How dare you?”</p><p >Miss Murdstone made a jail-delivery of her pocket-handkerchief, and held it before her eyes.</p><p >“Clara,” he continued, looking at my mother, “you surprise me! You astound me! Yes, I had a satisfaction in the thought of marrying an inexperienced and artless person, and forming her character, and infusing into it some amount of that firmness and decision of which it stood in need. But when Jane Murdstone is kind enough to come to my assistance
<pb xml:id="p38"/>
in this endeavour, and to assume, for my sake, a condition something like a housekeeper's, and when she meets with a base return—”</p><p >“Oh, pray, pray, Edward,” cried my mother, “don't accuse me of being ungrateful. I am sure I am not ungrateful. No one ever said I was, before. I have many faults, but not that. Oh, don't, my dear!”</p><p >“When Jane Murdstone meets, I say,” he went on, after waiting until my mother was silent, “with a base return, that feeling of mine is chilled and altered.”</p><p >“Don't, my love, say that!” implored my mother, very piteously. “Oh, don't, Edward! I can't bear to hear it. Whatever I am, I am affectionate. I know I am affectionate. I wouldn't say it, if I wasn't certain that I am. Ask Peggotty. I am sure she'll tell you I'm affectionate.”</p><p >“There is no extent of mere weakness, Clara,” said Mr. Murdstone in reply, “that can have the least weight with me. You lose breath.”</p><p >“Pray let us be friends,” said my mother, “I couldn't live under coldness or unkindness. I am so sorry. I have a great many defects, I know, and it's very good of you, Edward, with your strength of mind, to endeavour to correct them for me. Jane, I don't object to anything. I should be quite broken-hearted if you thought of leaving—” My mother was too much overcome to go on.</p><p >“Jane Murdstone,” said Mr. Murdstone to his sister, “any harsh words between us are, I hope, uncommon. It is not my fault that so unusual an occurrence has taken place to-night. I was betrayed into it by another. Nor is it your fault. You were betrayed into it by another. Let us both try to forget it. And as this,” he added, after these magnanimous words, “is not a fit scene for the boy—David, go to bed!”</p><p >I could hardly find the door, through the tears that stood in my eyes. I was so sorry for my mother's distress; but I groped my way out, and groped my way up to my room in the dark, without even having the heart to say good night to Peggotty, or to get a candle from her. When her coming up to look for me, an hour or so afterwards, awoke me, she said that my mother had gone to bed poorly, and that Mr. and Miss Murdstone were sitting alone.</p><p >Going down next morning rather earlier than usual, I paused outside the parlor-door, on hearing my mother's voice. She was very earnestly and humbly entreating Miss Murdstone's pardon, which that lady granted, and a perfect reconciliation took place. I never knew my mother afterwards to give an opinion on any matter, without first appealing to Miss Murdstone, or without having first ascertained, by some sure means, what Miss Murdstone's opinion was; and I never saw Miss Murdstone, when out of temper (she was infirm that way), move her hand towards her bag as if she were going to take out the keys and offer to resign them to my mother, without seeing that my mother was in a terrible fright.</p><p >The gloomy taint that was in the Murdstone blood, darkened the Murdstone religion, which was austere and wrathful. I have thought, since, that its assuming that character was a necessary consequence of Mr. Murdstone's firmness, which wouldn't allow him to let any body off from the utmost weight of the severest penalties he could find any excuse for. Be this as it may, I well remember the tremendous visages with
<pb xml:id="p39"/>
which we used to go to church, and the changed air of the place. Again, the dreaded Sunday comes round, and I file into the old pew first, like a guarded captive brought to a condemned service. Again, Miss Murdstone, in a black velvet gown, that looks as if it had been made out of a pall, follows close upon me; then my mother; then her husband. There is no Peggotty now, as in the old time. Again, I listen to Miss Murdstone mumbling the responses, and emphasising all the dread words with a cruel relish. Again, I see her dark eyes roll round the church when she says “miserable sinners,” as if she were calling all the congregation names. Again, I catch rare glimpses of my mother, moving her lips timidly between the two, with one of them muttering at each ear like low thunder. Again, I wonder with a sudden fear whether it is likely that our good old clergyman can be wrong, and Mr. and Miss Murdstone right, and that all the angels in Heaven can be destroying angels. Again, if I move a finger or relax a muscle of my face, Miss Murdstone pokes me with her prayer-book, and makes my side ache.</p><p >Yes, and again, as we walk home, I note some neighbours looking at my mother, and at me, and whispering. Again, as the three go on arm-in-arm, and I linger behind alone, I follow some of those looks, and wonder if my mother's step be really not so light as I have seen it, and if the gaiety of her beauty be really almost worried away. Again, I wonder whether any of the neighbours call to mind, as I do, how we used to walk home together, she and I; and I wonder stupidly about that, all the dreary dismal day.</p><p >There had been some talk on occasions of my going to boarding-school. Mr. and Miss Murdstone had originated it, and my mother had of course agreed with them. Nothing, however, was concluded on the subject yet. In the meantime, I learnt lessons at home.</p><p >Shall I ever forget those lessons! They were presided over nominally by my mother, but really by Mr. Murdstone and his sister, who were always present, and found them a favourable occasion for giving my mother lessons in that miscalled firmness, which was the bane of both our lives. I believe I was kept at home, for that purpose. I had been apt enough to learn, and willing enough, when my mother and I had lived alone together. I can faintly remember learning the alphabet at her knee. To this day, when I look upon the fat black letters in the primer, the puzzling novelty of their shapes, and the easy good-nature of O and Q and S, seem to present themselves again before me as they used to do. But they recall no feeling of disgust or reluctance. On the contrary, I seem to have walked along a path of flowers as far as the crocodile-book, and to have been cheered by the gentleness of my mother's voice and manner all the way. But these solemn lessons which succeeded those, I remember as the deathblow at my peace, and a grievous daily drudgery and misery. They were very long, very numerous, very hard—perfectly unintelligible, some of them, to me—and I was generally as much bewildered by them as I believe my poor mother was herself.</p><p >Let me remember how it used to be, and bring one morning back again.</p><p >I come into the second-best parlor after breakfast, with my books, and an exercise-book, and a slate. My mother is ready for me at her
<pb xml:id="p40"/>
writing-desk, but not half so ready as Mr. Murdstone in his easy-chair by the window (though he pretends to be reading a book), or as Miss Murdstone, sitting near my mother stringing steel beads. The very sight of these two has such an influence over me, that I begin to feel the words I have been at infinite pains to get into my head, all sliding away, and going I don't know where. I wonder where they <hi rend="italics">do</hi> go, by-the-by?</p><p >I hand the first book to my mother. Perhaps it is a grammar, perhaps a history, or geography. I take a last drowning look at the page as I give it into her hand, and start off aloud at a racing pace while I have got it fresh. I trip over a word. Mr. Murdstone looks up. I trip over another word. Miss Murdstone looks up. I redden, tumble over half-a-dozen words, and stop. I think my mother would show me the book if she dared, but she does not dare, and she says softly:</p><p >“Oh, Davy, Davy!”</p><p >“Now, Clara,” says Mr. Murdstone, “be firm with the boy. Don't say ‘Oh, Davy, Davy!’ That's childish. He knows his lesson, or he does not know it.”</p><p >“He does <hi rend="italics">not</hi> know it,” Miss Murdstone interposes awfully.</p><p >“I am really afraid he does not,” says my mother.</p><p >“Then you see, Clara,” returns Miss Murdstone, “you should just give him the book back, and make him know it.”</p><p >“Yes, certainly,” says my mother; “that is what I intend to do, my dear Jane. Now, Davy, try once more, and don't be stupid.”</p><p >I obey the first clause of the injunction by trying once more, but am not so successful with the second, for I am very stupid. I tumble down before I get to the old place, at a point where I was all right before, and stop to think. But I can't think about the lesson. I think of the number of yards of net in Miss Murdstone's cap, or of the price of Mr. Murdstone's dressing-gown, or any such ridiculous problem that I have no business with, and don't want to have anything at all to do with. Mr. Murdstone makes a movement of impatience which I have been expecting for a long time. Miss Murdstone does the same. My mother glances submissively at them, shuts the book, and lays it by as an arrear to be worked out when my other tasks are done.</p><p >There is a pile of these arrears very soon, and it swells like a rolling snowball. The bigger it gets, the more stupid <hi rend="italics">I</hi> get. The case is so hopeless, and I feel that I am wallowing in such a bog of nonsense, that I give up all idea of getting out, and abandon myself to my fate. The despairing way in which my mother and I look at each other, as I blunder on, is truly melancholy. But the greatest effect in these miserable lessons is when my mother (thinking nobody is observing her) tries to give me the cue by the motion of her lips. At that instant, Miss Murdstone, who has been lying in wait for nothing else all along, says in a deep warning voice:</p><p >“Clara!”</p><p >My mother starts, colors, and smiles faintly. Mr. Murdstone comes out of his chair, takes the book, throws it at me or boxes my ears with it, and turns me out of the room by the shoulders.</p><p >Even when the lessons are done, the worst is yet to happen, in the shape of an appalling sum. This is invented for me, and delivered to me orally by Mr. Murdstone, and begins, “If I go into a cheesemonger's
<pb xml:id="p41"/>
shop, and buy five thousand double-Gloucester cheeses at fourpence-halfpenny each, present payment”—at which I see Miss Murdstone secretly overjoyed. I pore over these cheeses without any result or enlightenment until dinner-time; when, having made a Mulatto of myself by getting the dirt of the slate into the pores of my skin, I have a slice of bread to help me out with the cheeses, and am considered in disgrace for the rest of the evening.</p><p >It seems to me, at this distance of time, as if my unfortunate studies generally took this course. I could have done very well if I had been without the Murdstones; but the influence of the Murdstones upon me was like the fascination of two snakes on a wretched young bird. Even when I did get through the morning with tolerable credit, there was not much gained but dinner; for Miss Murdstone never could endure to see me untasked, and if I rashly made any show of being unemployed, called her brother's attention to me by saying, “Clara, my dear, there's nothing like work—give your boy an exercise;” which caused me to be clapped down to some new labor, there and then. As to any recreation with other children of my age, I had very little of that; for the gloomy theology of the Murdstones made all children out to be a swarm of little vipers (though there <hi rend="italics">was</hi> a child once set in the midst of the Disciples), and held that they contaminated one another.</p><p >The natural result of this treatment, continued, I suppose, for some six months or more, was to make me sullen, dull, and dogged. I was not made the less so, by my sense of being daily more and more shut out and alienated from my mother. I believe I should have been almost stupified but for one circumstance.</p><p >It was this. My father had left a small collection of books in a little room up-stairs, to which I had access (for it adjoined my own) and which nobody else in our house ever troubled. From that blessed little room, Roderick Random, Peregrine Pickle, Humphrey Clinker, Tom Jones, The Vicar of Wakefield, Don Quixote, Gil Blas, and Robinson Crusoe, came out, a glorious host, to keep me company. They kept alive my fancy, and my hope of something beyond that place and time,—they, and the Arabian Nights, and the Tales of the Genii,—and did me no harm; for whatever harm was in some of them was not there for me; <hi rend="italics">I</hi> knew nothing of it. It is astonishing to me now, how I found time, in the midst of my porings and blunderings over heavier themes, to read those books as I did. It is curious to me how I could ever have consoled myself under my small troubles (which were great troubles to me), by impersonating my favorite characters in them—as I did—and by putting Mr. and Miss Murdstone into all the bad ones—which I did too. I have been Tom Jones (a child's Tom Jones, a harmless creature) for a week together. I have sustained my own idea of Roderick Random for a month at a stretch, I verily believe. I had a greedy relish for a few volumes of Voyages and Travels—I forget what, now—that were on those shelves; and for days and days I can remember to have gone about my region of our house, armed with the centre-piece out of an old set of boot-trees—the perfect realisation of Captain Somebody, of the Royal British Navy, in danger of being beset by savages, and resolved to sell his life at a great price. The Captain never lost dignity, from having his ears boxed with the Latin Grammar. I did; but the
<pb xml:id="p42"/>
Captain was a Captain and a hero, in despite of all the grammars of all the languages in the world, dead or alive.</p><p >This was my only and my constant comfort. When I think of it, the picture always rises in my mind, of a summer evening, the boys at play in the churchyard, and I sitting on my bed, reading as if for life. Every barn in the neighbourhood, every stone in the church, and every foot of the churchyard, had some association of its own, in my mind, connected with these books, and stood for some locality made famous in them. I have seen Tom Pipes go climbing up the church-steeple; I have watched Strap, with the knapsack on his back, stopping to rest himself upon the wicket-gate; and I <hi rend="italics">know</hi> that Commodore Trunnion held that club with Mr. Pickle, in the parlor of our little village alehouse.</p><p >The reader now understands as well as I do, what I was when I came to that point of my youthful history to which I am now coming again.</p><p >One morning when I went into the parlor with my books, I found my mother looking anxious, Miss Murdstone looking firm, and Mr. Murdstone binding something round the bottom of a cane—a lithe and limber cane, which he left off binding when I came in, and poised and switched in the air.</p><p >“I tell you, Clara,” said Mr. Murdstone, “I have been often flogged myself.”</p><p >“To be sure; of course,” said Miss Murdstone.</p><p >“Certainly, my dear Jane,” faltered my mother, meekly. “But—but do you think it did Edward good?”</p><p >“Do you think it did Edward harm, Clara?” asked Mr. Murdstone, gravely.</p><p >“That's the point!” said his sister.</p><p >To this my mother returned, “Certainly, my dear Jane,” and said no more.</p><p >I felt apprehensive that I was personally interested in this dialogue, and sought Mr. Murdstone's eye as it lighted on mine.</p><p >“Now, David,” he said—and I saw that cast again, as he said it—“you must be far more careful to-day than usual.” He gave the cane another poise, and another switch; and having finished his preparation of it, laid it down beside him, with an expressive look, and took up his book.</p><p >This was a good freshener to my presence of mind, as a beginning. I felt the words of my lessons slipping off, not one by one, or line by line, but by the entire page. I tried to lay hold of them; but they seemed, if I may so express it, to have put skates on, and to skim away from me with a smoothness there was no checking.</p><p >We began badly, and went on worse. I had come in, with an idea of distinguishing myself rather, conceiving that I was very well prepared; but it turned out to be quite a mistake. Book after book was added to the heap of failures, Miss Murdstone being firmly watchful of us all the time. And when we came at last to the five thousand cheeses (canes he made it that day, I remember), my mother burst out crying.</p><p >“Clara!” said Miss Murdstone, in her warning voice.</p><p >“I am not quite well, my dear Jane, I think,” said my mother.</p><p >I saw him wink, solemnly, at his sister, as he rose and said, taking up the cane:</p><p >“Why, Jane, we can hardly expect Clara to bear, with perfect firmness,
<pb xml:id="p43"/>
the worry and torment that David has occasioned her to-day. That would be stoical. Clara is greatly strengthened and improved, but we can hardly expect so much from her. David, you and I will go up-stairs, boy.”</p><p >As he took me out at the door, my mother ran towards us. Miss Murdstone said, “Clara! are you a perfect fool?” and interfered. I saw my mother stop her ears then, and I heard her crying.</p><p >He walked me up to my room slowly and gravely—I am certain he had a delight in that formal parade of executing justice—and when we got there, suddenly twisted my head under his arm.</p><p >“Mr. Murdstone! Sir!” I cried to him. “Don't! Pray don't beat me! I have tried to learn, sir, but I can't learn while you and Miss Murdstone are by. I can't indeed!”</p><p >“Can't you, indeed, David?” he said. “We'll try that.”</p><p >He had my head as in a vice, but I twined round him somehow, and stopped him for a moment, entreating him not to beat me. It was only for a moment that I stopped him, for he cut me heavily an instant afterwards, and in the same instant I caught the hand with which he held me in my mouth, between my teeth, and bit it through. It sets my teeth on edge to think of it.</p><p >He beat me then, as if he would have beaten me to death. Above all the noise we made, I heard them running up the stairs, and crying out—I heard my mother crying out—and Peggotty. Then he was gone; and the door was locked outside; and I was lying, fevered and hot, and torn, and sore, and raging in my puny way, upon the floor.</p><p >How well I recollect, when I became quiet, what an unnatural stillness seemed to reign through the whole house! How well I remember, when my smart and passion began to cool, how wicked I began to feel!</p><p >I sat listening for a long while, but there was not a sound. I crawled up from the floor, and saw my face in the glass, so swollen, red, and ugly, that it almost frightened me. My stripes were sore and stiff, and made me cry afresh, when I moved; but they were nothing to the guilt I felt. It lay heavier on my breast than if I had been a most atrocious criminal, I dare say.</p><p >It had begun to grow dark, and I had shut the window (I had been lying, for the most part, with my head upon the sill, by turns crying, dozing, and looking listlessly out), when the key was turned, and Miss Murdstone came in with some bread and meat, and milk. These she put down upon the table without a word, glaring at me the while with exemplary firmness, and then retired, locking the door after her.</p><p >Long after it was dark I sat there, wondering whether anybody else would come. When this appeared improbable for that night, I undressed, and went to bed; and, there, I began to wonder fearfully what would be done to me. Whether it was a criminal act that I had committed? Whether I should be taken into custody, and sent to prison? Whether I was at all in danger of being hanged?</p><p >I never shall forget the waking, next morning; the being cheerful and fresh for the first moment, and then the being weighed down by the stale and dismal oppression of remembrance. Miss Murdstone reappeared before I was out of bed; told me, in so many words, that I was free to
<pb xml:id="p44"/>
walk in the garden for half an hour and no longer; and retired, leaving the door open, that I might avail myself of that permission.</p><p >I did so, and did so every morning of my imprisonment, which lasted five days. If I could have seen my mother alone, I should have gone down on my knees to her and besought her forgiveness; but I saw no one, Miss Murdstone excepted, during the whole time—except at evening prayers in the parlor; to which I was escorted by Miss Murdstone after everybody else was placed; where I was stationed, a young outlaw, all alone by myself near the door; and whence I was solemnly conducted by my jailer, before anyone arose from the devotional posture. I only observed that my mother was as far off from me as she could be, and kept her face another way so that I never saw it; and that Mr. Murdstone's hand was bound up in a large linen wrapper.</p><p >The length of those five days I can convey no idea of to any one. They occupy the place of years in my remembrance. The way in which I listened to all the incidents of the house that made themselves audible to me; the ringing of bells, the opening and shutting of doors, the murmuring of voices, the footsteps on the stairs; to any laughing, whistling, or singing, outside, which seemed more dismal than anything else to me in my solitude and disgrace—the uncertain pace of the hours, especially at night, when I would wake thinking it was morning, and find that the family were not yet gone to bed, and that all the length of night had yet to come—the depressed dreams and nightmares I had—the return of day, noon, afternoon, evening, when the boys played in the churchyard, and I watched them from a distance within the room, being ashamed to show myself at the window lest they should know I was a prisoner—the strange sensation of never hearing myself speak—the fleeting intervals of something like cheerfulness, which came with eating and drinking, and went away with it—the setting in of rain one evening, with a fresh smell, and its coming down faster and faster between me and the church, until it and gathering night seemed to quench me in gloom, and fear, and remorse—all this appears to have gone round and round for years instead of days, it is so vividly and strongly stamped on my remembrance.</p><p >On the last night of my restraint, I was awakened by hearing my own name spoken in a whisper. I started up in bed, and putting out my arms in the dark, said:</p><p >“Is that you, Peggotty?”</p><p >There was no immediate answer, but presently I heard my name again, in a tone so very mysterious and awful, that I think I should have gone into a fit, if it had not occurred to me that it must have come through the keyhole.</p><p >I groped my way to the door, and putting my own lips to the keyhole, whispered:</p><p >“Is that you, Peggotty, dear?”</p><p >“Yes, my own precious Davy,” she replied. “Be as soft as a mouse, or the Cat 'll hear us.”</p><p >I understood this to mean Miss Murdstone, and was sensible of the urgency of the case; her room being close by.</p><p >“How's mama, dear Peggotty? Is she very angry with me?”</p><pb  xml:id="p45"/><p >I could hear Peggotty crying softly on her side of the keyhole, as I was doing on mine, before she answered. “No. Not very.”</p><p >“What is going to be done with me, Peggotty dear? Do you know?”</p><p >“School. Near London,” was Peggotty's answer. I was obliged to get her to repeat it, for she spoke it the first time quite down my throat, in consequence of my having forgotten to take my mouth away from the keyhole and put my ear there; and though her words tickled me a good deal, I didn't hear them.</p><p >“When, Peggotty?”</p><p >“To-morrow.”</p><p >“Is that the reason why Miss Murdstone took the clothes out of my drawers?” which she had done, though I have forgotten to mention it.</p><p >“Yes,” said Peggotty. “Box.”</p><p >“Shan't I see mama?”</p><p >“Yes,” said Peggotty. “Morning.”</p><p >Then Peggotty fitted her mouth close to the keyhole, and delivered these words through it with as much feeling and earnestness as a keyhole has ever been the medium of communicating, I will venture to assert: shooting in each broken little sentence in a convulsive little burst of its own.</p><p >“Davy, dear. If I ain't ben azackly as intimate with you. Lately, as I used to be. It ain't becase I don't love you. Just as well and more, my pretty poppet. It's because I thought it better for you. And for some one else besides. Davy, my darling, are you listening? Can you hear?”</p><p >“Ye—ye—ye—yes, Peggotty!” I sobbed.</p><p >“My own!” said Peggotty, with infinite compassion. “What I want to say, is. That you must never forget me. For I'll never forget you. And I'll take as much care of your mama, Davy. As ever I took of you. And I won't leave her. The day may come when she'll be glad to lay her poor head. On her stupid, cross old Peggotty's arm again. And I'll write to you, my dear. Though I ain't no scholar. And I'll—I'll—” Peggotty fell to kissing the keyhole, as she couldn't kiss me.</p><p >“Thank you, dear Peggotty!” said I. “Oh, thank you! Thank you! Will you promise me one thing, Peggotty? Will you write and tell Mr. Peggotty and little Em'ly and Mrs. Gummidge and Ham, that I am not so bad as they might suppose, and that I sent 'em all my love—especially to little Em'ly? Will you, if you please, Peggotty?”</p><p >The kind soul promised, and we both of us kissed the keyhole with the greatest affection—I patted it with my hand, I recollect, as if it had been her honest face—and parted. From that night there grew up in my breast, a feeling for Peggotty, which I cannot very well define. She did not replace my mother; no one could do that; but she came into a vacancy in my heart, which closed upon her, and I felt towards her something I have never felt for any other human being. It was a sort of comical affection too; and yet if she had died, I cannot think what I should have done, or how I should have acted out the tragedy it would have been to me.</p><p >In the morning Miss Murdstone appeared as usual, and told me I was going to school; which was not altogether such news to me as she supposed. She also informed me that when I was dressed, I was to come down-stairs into the parlor, and have my breakfast. There, I found my
<pb xml:id="p46"/>
mother, very pale and with red eyes: into whose arms I ran, and begged her pardon from my suffering soul.</p><p >“Oh, Davy!” she said. “That you could hurt any one I love! Try to be better, pray to be better! I forgive you; but I am so grieved, Davy, that you should have such bad passions in your heart.”</p><p >They had persuaded her that I was a wicked fellow, and she was more sorry for that, than for my going away. I felt it sorely. I tried to eat my parting breakfast, but my tears dropped upon my bread-and-butter, and trickled into my tea. I saw my mother look at me sometimes, and then glance at the watchful Miss Murdstone, and then look down, or look away.</p><p >“Master Copperfield's box there!” said Miss Murdstone, when wheels were heard at the gate.</p><p >I looked for Peggotty, but it was not she; neither she nor Mr. Murdstone appeared. My former acquaintance, the carrier, was at the door; the box was taken out to his cart, and lifted in.</p><p >“Clara!” said Miss Murdstone, in her warning note.</p><p >“Ready, my dear Jane,” returned my mother. “Good bye, Davy. You are going for your own good. Good bye, my child. You will come home in the holidays, and be a better boy.”</p><p >“Clara!” Miss Murdstone repeated.</p><p >“Certainly, my dear Jane,” replied my mother, who was holding me. “I forgive you, my dear boy. God bless you!”</p><p >“Clara!” Miss Murdstone repeated.</p><p >Miss Murdstone was good enough to take me out to the cart, and to say on the way that she hoped I would repent, before I came to a bad end; and then I got into the cart, and the lazy horse walked off with it.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER V. <lb/> I AM SENT AWAY FROM HOME.</head><p >WE might have gone about half a mile, and my pocket-handkerchief was quite wet through, when the carrier stopped short.</p><p >Looking out to ascertain what for, I saw, to my amazement, Peggotty burst from a hedge and climb into the cart. She took me in both her arms, and squeezed me to her stays until the pressure on my nose was extremely painful, though I never thought of that till afterwards when I found it very tender. Not a single word did Peggotty speak. Releasing one of her arms, she put it down in her pocket to the elbow, and brought out some paper bags of cakes which she crammed into my pockets, and a purse which she put into my hand, but not one word did she say. After another and a final squeeze with both arms, she got down from the cart and ran away; and, my belief is, and has always been, without a solitary button on her gown. I picked up one, of several that were rolling about, and treasured it as a keepsake for a long time.</p><p >The carrier looked at me, as if to enquire if she were coming back.
<pb xml:id="p47"/>
I shook my head, and said I thought not. “Then come up,” said the carrier to the lazy horse; who came up accordingly.</p><p >Having by this time cried as much as I possibly could, I began to think it was of no use crying any more, especially as neither Roderick Random, nor that Captain in the Royal British Navy, had ever cried, that I could remember, in trying situations. The carrier, seeing me in this resolution, proposed that my pocket-handkerchief should be spread upon the horse's back to dry. I thanked him, and assented; and particularly small it looked, under those circumstances.</p><p >I had now leisure to examine the purse. It was a stiff leather purse, with a snap, and had three bright shillings in it, which Peggotty had evidently polished up with whitening, for my greater delight. But its most precious contents were two half-crowns folded together in a bit of paper, on which was written, in my mother's hand, “For Davy. With my love.” I was so overcome by this, that I asked the carrier to be so good as reach me my pocket-handkerchief again; but he said he thought I had better do without it; and I thought I really had; so I wiped my eyes on my sleeve and stopped myself.</p><p >For good, too; though, in consequence of my previous emotions, I was still occasionally seized with a stormy sob. After we had jogged on for some little time, I asked the carrier if he was going all the way.</p><p >“All the way where?” enquired the carrier.</p><p >“There,” I said.</p><p >“Where's there?” enquired the carrier.</p><p >“Near London?” I said.</p><p >“Why that horse,” said the carrier, jerking the rein to point him out, “would be deader than pork afore he got over half the ground.”</p><p >“Are you only going to Yarmouth then?” I asked.</p><p >“That's about it,” said the carrier. “And there I shall take you to the stage-cutch, and the stage-cutch that'll take you to—wherever it is.”</p><p >As this was a great deal for the carrier (whose name was Mr. Barkis) to say—he being, as I observed in a former chapter, of a phlegmatic temperament, and not at all conversational—I offered him a cake as a mark of attention, which he ate at one gulp, exactly like an elephant, and which made no more impression on his big face than it would have done on an elephant's.</p><p >“Did <hi rend="italics">she</hi> make 'em, now?” said Mr. Barkis, always leaning forward, in his slouching way, on the footboard of the cart with an arm on each knee.</p><p >“Peggotty, do you mean, sir?”</p><p >“Ah!” said Mr. Barkis. “Her.”</p><p >“Yes. She makes all our pastry, and does all our cooking.”</p><p >“Do she though?” said Mr. Barkis.</p><p >He made up his mouth as if to whistle, but he didn't whistle. He sat looking at the horse's ears, as if he saw something new there; and sat so, for a considerable time. By-and-by, he said:</p><p >“No sweethearts, I b'lieve?”</p><p >“Sweetmeats did you say, Mr. Barkis?” For I thought he wanted something else to eat, and had pointedly alluded to that description of refreshment.</p><pb  xml:id="p48"/><p >“Hearts,” said Mr. Barkis. “Sweet hearts; no person walks with her!”</p><p >“With Peggotty?”</p><p >“Ah!” he said. “Her.”</p><p >“Oh, no. She never had a sweetheart.”</p><p >“Didn't she though!” said Mr. Barkis.</p><p >Again he made up his mouth to whistle, and again he didn't whistle, but sat looking at the horse's ears.</p><p >“So she makes,” said Mr. Barkis, after a long interval of reflection, “all the apple parsties, and doos all the cooking, do she?”</p><p >I replied that such was the fact.</p><p >“Well. I'll tell you what,” said Mr. Barkis. “P'raps you might be writin' to her?”</p><p >“I shall certainly write to her,” I rejoined.</p><p >“Ah!” he said, slowly turning his eyes towards me. “Well! If you was writin' to her, p'raps you'd recollect to say that Barkis was willin'; would you.”</p><p >“That Barkis is willing,” I repeated, innocently. “Is that all the message?”</p><p >“Ye—es,” he said, considering. “Ye—es. Barkis is willin'.”</p><p >“But you will be at Blunderstone again to-morrow, Mr. Barkis,” I said, faltering a little at the idea of my being far away from it then, “and could give your own message so much better.”</p><p >As he repudiated this suggestion, however, with a jerk of his head, and once more confirmed his previous request by saying, with profound gravity, “Barkis is willin'. That's the message,” I readily undertook its transmission. While I was waiting for the coach in the hotel at Yarmouth that very afternoon, I procured a sheet of paper and an inkstand, and wrote a note to Peggotty which ran thus: “My dear Peggotty. I have come here safe. Barkis is willing. My love to mama. Yours affectionately. P. S. He says he particularly wants you to know—<hi rend="italics">Barkis is willing.”</hi></p><p >When I had taken this commission on myself prospectively, Mr. Barkis relapsed into perfect silence; and I, feeling quite worn out by all that had happened lately, lay down on a sack in the cart and fell asleep. I slept soundly until we got to Yarmouth; which was so entirely new and strange to me in the inn-yard to which we drove, that I at once abandoned a latent hope I had had of meeting with some of Mr. Peggotty's family there, perhaps even with little Em'ly herself.</p><p >The coach was in the yard, shining very much all over, but without any horses to it as yet; and it looked in that state as if nothing was more unlikely than its ever going to London. I was thinking this, and wondering what would ultimately become of my box, which Mr. Barkis had put down on the yard-pavement by the pole (he having driven up the yard to turn his cart), and also what would ultimately become of me, when a lady looked out of a bow-window where some fowls and joints of meat were hanging up, and said:</p><p >“Is that the little gentleman from Blunderstone?”</p><p >“Yes, ma'am,” I said.</p><p >“What name?” enquired the lady.</p><p >“Copperfield, ma'am,” I said.</p><pb  xml:id="p49"/><p >“That won't do,” returned the lady. “Nobody's dinner is paid for here, in that name.”</p><p >“Is it Murdstone, ma'am?” I said.</p><p >“If you're Master Murdstone,” said the lady, “why do you go and give another name, first?”</p><p >I explained to the lady how it was, who then rang a bell, and called out, “William! show the coffee-room!” upon which a waiter came running out of a kitchen on the opposite side of the yard to show it, and seemed a good deal surprised when he found he was only to show it to me.</p><p >It was a large long room with some large maps in it. I doubt if I could have felt much stranger if the maps had been real foreign countries, and I cast away in the middle of them. I felt it was taking a liberty to sit down, with my cap in my hand, on the corner of the chair nearest the door; and when the waiter laid a cloth on purpose for me, and put a set of castors on it, I think I must have turned red all over with modesty.</p><p >He brought me some chops, and vegetables, and took the covers off in such a bouncing manner that I was afraid I must have given him some offence. But he greatly relieved my mind by putting a chair for me at the table, and saying, very affably, “Now, six-foot! come on!”</p><p >I thanked him, and took my seat at the board; but found it extremely difficult to handle my knife and fork with anything like dexterity, or to avoid splashing myself with the gravy, while he was standing opposite, staring so hard, and making me blush in the most dreadful manner every time I caught his eye. After watching me into the second chop, he said:</p><p >“There's half a pint of ale for you. Will you have it now?”</p><p >I thanked him, and said “Yes.” Upon which he poured it out of a jug into a large tumbler, and held it up against the light, and made it look beautiful.</p><p >“My eye!” he said. “It seems a good deal, don't it?”</p><p >“It does seem a good deal,” I answered with a smile. For it was quite delightful to me, to find him so pleasant. He was a twinkling-eyed, pimplefaced man, with his hair standing upright all over his head; and as he stood with one arm a-kimbo, holding up the glass to the light with the other hand, he looked quite friendly.</p><p >“There was a gentleman here, yesterday,” he said—“a stout gentleman, by the name of Topsawyer—perhaps you know him!”</p><p >“No,” I said, “I don't think—”</p><p >“In breeches and gaiters, broad-brimmed hat, grey coat, speckled choaker,” said the waiter.</p><p >“No,” I said bashfully, “I haven't the pleasure—”</p><p >“He came in here,” said the waiter, looking at the light through the tumbler, “ordered a glass of this ale—<hi rend="italics">would</hi> order it—I told him not—drank it, and fell dead. It was too old for him. It oughtn't to be drawn; that's the fact.”</p><p >I was very much shocked to hear of this melancholy accident, and said I thought I had better have some water.</p><p >“Why you see,” said the waiter, still looking at the light through the tumbler, with one of his eyes shut up, “our people don't like things being ordered and left. It offends 'em. But <hi rend="italics">I</hi>'ll drink it, if you like. I'm
<pb xml:id="p50"/>
used to it, and use is everything. I don't think it'll hurt me, if I throw my head back, and take it off quick. Shall I?”</p><p >I replied that he would much oblige me by drinking it, if he thought he could do it safely, but by no means otherwise. When he did throw his head back, and take it off quick, I had a horrible fear, I confess, of seeing him meet the fate of the lamented Mr. Topsawyer, and fall lifeless on the carpet. But it didn't hurt him. On the contrary, I thought he seemed the fresher for it.</p><p >“What have we got here?” he said, putting a fork into my dish. “Not chops?”</p><p >“Chops,” I said.</p><p >“Lord bless my soul!” he exclaimed, “I didn't know they were chops. Why, a chop's the very thing to take off the bad effects of that beer! Ain't it lucky?”</p><p >So he took a chop by the bone in one hand, and a potato in the other, and ate away with a very good appetite, to my extreme satisfaction. He afterwards took another chop, and another potato; and after that, another chop and another potato. When we had done, he brought me a pudding, and having set it before me, seemed to ruminate, and to become absent in his mind for some moments.</p><p >“How's the pie?” he said, rousing himself.</p><p >“It's a pudding,” I made answer.</p><p >“Pudding!” he exclaimed. “Why, bless me, so it is! What!” looking at it nearer. “You don't mean to say it's a batter-pudding!”</p><p >“Yes, it is indeed.”</p><p >“Why, a batter-pudding,” he said, taking up a table-spoon, “is my favorite pudding! Ain't that lucky? Come on, little 'un, and let's see who 'll get most.”</p><p >The waiter certainly got most. He entreated me more than once to come in and win, but what with his table-spoon to my tea-spoon, his dispatch to my dispatch, and his appetite to my appetite, I was left far behind at the first mouthful, and had no chance with him. I never saw any one enjoy a pudding so much, I think; and he laughed, when it was all gone, as if his enjoyment of it lasted still.</p><p >Finding him so very friendly and companionable, it was then that I asked for the pen and ink and paper, to write to Peggotty. He not only brought it immediately, but was good enough to look over me while I wrote the letter. When I had finished it, he asked me where I was going to school.</p><p >I said, “Near London,” which was all I knew.</p><p >“Oh, my eye!” he said, looking very low-spirited, “I am sorry for that.”</p><p >“Why?” I asked him.</p><p >“Oh, Lord!” he said, shaking his head, “that's the school where they broke the boy's ribs—two ribs—a little boy he was. I should say he was—let me see—how old are you, about?”</p><p >I told him between eight and nine.</p><p >“That's just his age,” he said. “He was eight years and six months old when they broke his first rib; eight years and eight months old when they broke his second, and did for him.”</p><p >I could not disguise from myself, or from the waiter, that this was an
<pb xml:id="p51"/>
uncomfortable coincidence, and enquired how it was done. His answer was not cheering to my spirits, for it consisted of two dismal words, “With whopping.”</p><p >The blowing of the coach-horn in the yard was a seasonable diversion, which made me get up and hesitatingly enquire, in the mingled pride and diffidence of having a purse (which I took out of my pocket), if there were anything to pay.</p><p >“There's a sheet of letter-paper,” he returned. “Did you ever buy a sheet of letter-paper?”</p><p >I could not remember that I ever had.</p><p >“It's dear,” he said, “on account of the duty. Threepence. That's the way we're taxed in this country. There's nothing else, except the waiter. Never mind the ink. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> lose by that.”</p><p >“What should you—what should I—how much ought I to—what would it be right to pay the waiter, if you please?” I stammered, blushing.</p><p >“If I hadn't a family, and that family hadn't the cowpock,” said the waiter, “I wouldn't take a sixpence. If I didn't support a aged pairint, and a lovely sister,”—here the waiter was greatly agitated—“I wouldn't take a farthing. If I had a good place, and was treated well here, I should beg acceptance of a trifle, instead of taking of it. But I live on broken wittles—and I sleep on the coals”—here the waiter burst into tears.</p><p >I was very much concerned for his misfortunes, and felt that any recognition short of ninepence would be mere brutality and hardness of heart. Therefore I gave him one of my three bright shillings, which he received with much humility and veneration, and spun up with his thumb, directly afterwards, to try the goodness of.</p><p >It was a little disconcerting to me, to find, when I was being helped up behind the coach, that I was supposed to have eaten all the dinner without any assistance. I discovered this, from overhearing the lady in the bow-window, say to the guard, “Take care of that child, George, or he 'll burst!” and from observing that the women-servants who were about the place came out to look and giggle at me as a young phenomenon. My unfortunate friend the waiter, who had quite recovered his spirits, did not appear to be disturbed by this, but joined in the general admiration without being at all confused. If I had any doubt of him, I suppose this half-awakened it; but I am inclined to believe that with the simple confidence of a child, and the natural reliance of a child upon superior years (qualities I am very sorry any children should prematurely change for worldly wisdom), I had no serious mistrust of him on the whole, even then.</p><p >I felt it rather hard, I must own, to be made, without deserving it, the subject of jokes between the coachman and guard as to the coach drawing heavy behind, on account of my sitting there, and as to the greater expediency of my travelling by waggon. The story of my supposed appetite getting wind among the outside passengers, they were merry upon it likewise; and asked me whether I was going to be paid for, at school, as two brothers or three, and whether I was contracted for, or went upon the regular terms; with other pleasant questions. But the worst of it was, that I knew I should be ashamed to eat anything, when an opportunity offered, and that, after a rather light dinner, I should remain hungry
<pb xml:id="p52"/>
all night—for I had left my cakes behind, at the hotel, in my hurry. My apprehensions were realised. When we stopped for supper I couldn't muster courage to take any, though I should have liked it very much, but sat by the fire and said I didn't want anything. This did not save me from more jokes, either; for a husky-voiced gentleman with a rough face, who had been eating out of a sandwich-box nearly all the way, except when he had been drinking out of a bottle, said I was like a boa constrictor who took enough at one meal to last him a long time; after which, he actually brought a rash out upon himself with boiled beef.</p><p >We had started from Yarmouth at three o'clock in the afternoon, and we were due in London about eight next morning. It was Midsummer weather, and the evening was very pleasant. When we passed through a village, I pictured to myself what the insides of the houses were like, and what the inhabitants were about; and when boys came running after us, and got up behind and swung there for a little way, I wondered whether their fathers were alive, and whether they were happy at home. I had plenty to think of, therefore, besides my mind running continually on the kind of place I was going to—which was an awful speculation. Sometimes, I remember, I resigned myself to thoughts of home and Peggotty; and to endeavouring, in a confused blind way, to recall how I had felt, and what sort of boy I used to be, before I bit Mr. Murdstone: which I couldn't satisfy myself about by any means, I seemed to have bitten him in such a remote antiquity.</p><p >The night was not so pleasant as the evening, for it got chilly; and being put between two gentlemen (the rough-faced one and another) to prevent my tumbling off the coach, I was nearly smothered by their falling asleep, and completely blocking me up. They squeezed me so hard sometimes, that I could not help crying out, “Oh! If you please!”—which they didn't like at all, because it woke them. Opposite me was an elderly lady in a great fur cloak, who looked in the dark more like a haystack than a lady, she was wrapped up to such a degree. This lady had a basket with her, and she hadn't known what to do with it, for a long time, until she found that on account of my legs being short, it could go underneath me. It cramped and hurt me so, that it made me perfectly miserable; but if I moved in the least, and made a glass that was in the basket rattle against something else (as it was sure to do), she gave me the cruellest poke with her foot, and said, “Come, don't <hi rend="italics">you</hi> fidget. <hi rend="italics">Your</hi> bones are young enough, <hi rend="italics">I</hi>'m sure!”</p><p >At last the sun rose, and then my companions seemed to sleep easier. The difficulties under which they had laboured all night, and which had found utterance in the most terrific gasps and snorts, are not to be conceived. As the sun got higher, their sleep became lighter, and so they gradually one by one awoke. I recollect being very much surprised by the feint everybody made, then, of not having been to sleep at all, and by the uncommon indignation with which every one repelled the charge. I labor under the same kind of astonishment to this day, having invariably observed that of all human weaknesses, the one to which our common nature is the least disposed to confess (I cannot imagine why) is the weakness of having gone to sleep in a coach.</p><p >What an amazing place London was to me when I saw it in the distance, and how I believed all the adventures of all my favorite heroes to be constantly enacting and re-enacting there, and how I vaguely made it out
<pb xml:id="p53"/>
in my own mind to be fuller of wonders and wickedness than all the cities of the earth, I need not stop here to relate. We approached it by degrees, and got, in due time, to the inn in the Whitechapel district, for which we were bound. I forget whether it was the Blue Bull, or the Blue Boar; but I know it was the Blue Something, and that its likeness was painted up on the back of the coach.</p><p >The guard's eye lighted on me as he was getting down, and he said at the booking-office door:</p><p >“Is there anybody here for a yoongster booked in the name of Murdstone, from Bloonderstone, Sooffolk, to be left till called for?”</p><p >Nobody answered.</p><p >“Try Copperfield, if you please, sir,” said I, looking helplessly down.</p><p >“Is there anybody here for a yoongster, booked in the name of Murdstone, from Bloonderstone, Sooffolk, but owning to the name of Copperfield, to be left till called for?” said the guard. “Come! <hi rend="italics">Is</hi> there anybody?”</p><p >No. There was nobody. I looked anxiously around; but the enquiry made no impression on any of the bystanders, if I except a man in gaiters, with one eye, who suggested that they had better put a brass collar round my neck, and tie me up in the stable.</p><p >A ladder was brought, and I got down after the lady, who was like a haystack: not daring to stir, until her basket was removed. The coach was clear of passengers by that time, the luggage was very soon cleared out, the horses had been taken out before the luggage, and now the coach itself was wheeled and backed off by some hostlers, out of the way. Still, nobody appeared, to claim the dusty youngster from Blunderstone, Suffolk.</p><p >More solitary than Robinson Crusoe, who had nobody to look at him and see that he was solitary, I went into the booking-office, and, by invitation of the clerk on duty, passed behind the counter, and sat down on the scale at which they weighed the luggage. Here, as I sat looking at the parcels, packages, and books, and inhaling the smell of stables (ever since associated with that morning), a procession of most tremendous considerations began to march through my mind. Supposing nobody should ever fetch me, how long would they consent to keep me there? Would they keep me long enough to spend seven shillings? Should I sleep at night in one of those wooden binns with the other luggage, and wash myself at the pump in the yard in the morning; or should I be turned out every night, and expected to come again to be left till called for, when the office opened next day? Supposing there was no mistake in the case, and Mr. Murdstone had devised this plan to get rid of me, what should I do? If they allowed me to remain there until my seven shillings were spent, I couldn't hope to remain there when I began to starve. That would obviously be inconvenient and unpleasant to the customers, besides entailing on the Blue Whatever-it-was, the risk of funeral expenses. If I started off at once, and tried to walk back home, how could I ever find my way, how could I ever hope to walk so far, how could I make sure of any one but Peggotty, even if I got back? If I found out the nearest proper authorities, and offered myself to go for a soldier, or a sailor, I was such a little fellow that it was most likely they wouldn't take me in. These thoughts, and a hundred other such thoughts, turned me burning hot, and made me giddy with apprehension and dismay. I was in the height of my fever
<pb xml:id="p54"/>
when a man entered and whispered to the clerk, who presently slanted me off the scale, and pushed me over to him, as if I were weighed, bought, delivered, and paid for.</p><p >As I went out of the office, hand in hand with this new acquaintance, I stole a look at him. He was a gaunt, sallow young man, with hollow cheeks, and a chin almost as black as Mr. Murdstone's; but there the likeness ended, for his whiskers were shaved off, and his hair, instead of being glossy, was rusty and dry. He was dressed in a suit of black clothes which were rather rusty and dry too, and rather short in the sleeves and legs; and he had a white neck-kerchief on that was not over-clean. I did not, and do not, suppose that this neck-kerchief was all the linen he wore, but it was all he showed or gave any hint of.</p><p >“You're the new boy?” he said.</p><p >“Yes, sir,” I said.</p><p >I supposed I was. I didn't know.</p><p >“I'm one of the masters at Salem House,” <hi rend="italics">he</hi> said.</p><p >I made him a bow and felt very much overawed. I was so ashamed to allude to a common-place thing like my box, to a scholar and a master at Salem House, that we had gone some little distance from the yard before I had the hardihood to mention it. We turned back, on my humbly insinuating that it might be useful to me hereafter; and he told the clerk that the carrier had instructions to call for it at noon.</p><p >“If you please, sir,” I said, when we had accomplished about the same distance as before, “is it far?”</p><p >“It's down by Blackheath,” he said.</p><p >“Is <hi rend="italics">that</hi> far, sir?” I diffidently asked.</p><p >“It's a good step,” he said. “We shall go by the stage-coach. It's about six miles.”</p><p >I was so faint and tired, that the idea of holding out for six miles more, was too much for me. I took heart to tell him that I had had nothing all night, and that if he would allow me to buy something to eat, I should be very much obliged to him. He appeared surprised at this—I see him stop and look at me now—and after considering for a few moments, said he wanted to call on an old person who lived not far off, and that the best way would be for me to buy some bread, or whatever I liked best that was wholesome, and make my breakfast at her house, where we could get some milk.</p><p >Accordingly we looked in at a baker's window, and after I had made a series of proposals to buy everything that was bilious in the shop, and he had rejected them one by one, we decided in favour of a nice little loaf of brown bread, which cost me threepence. Then, at a grocer's shop, we bought an egg and a slice of streaky bacon; which still left what I thought a good deal of change, out of the second of the bright shillings, and made me consider London a very cheap place. These provisions laid in, we went on through a great noise and uproar that confused my weary head beyond description, and over a bridge which, no doubt, was London Bridge (indeed I think he told me so, but I was half asleep), until we came to the poor person's house, which was a part of some alms-houses, as I knew by their look, and by an inscription on a stone over the gate, which said they were established for twenty-five poor women.</p><pb  xml:id="p55"/><p >The Master at Salem House lifted the latch of one of a number of little black doors that were all alike, and had each a little diamond-paned window on one side, and another little diamond-paned window above; and we went into the little house of one of these poor old women, who was blowing a fire to make a little saucepan boil. On seeing the master enter, the old woman stopped with the bellows on her knee, and said something that I thought sounded like “My Charley!” but on seeing me come in too, she got up, and rubbing her hands made a confused sort of half curtsey.</p><p >“Can you cook this young gentleman's breakfast for him, if you please?” said the Master at Salem House.</p><p >“Can I?” said the old woman. “Yes can I, sure!”</p><p >“How's Mrs. Fibbitson to-day?” said the Master, looking at another old woman in a large chair by the fire, who was such a bundle of clothes that I feel grateful to this hour for not having sat upon her by mistake.</p><p >“Ah, she's poorly,” said the first old woman. “It's one of her bad days. If the fire was to go out, through any accident, I verily believe she'd go out too, and never come to life again.”</p><p >As they looked at her, I looked at her also. Although it was a warm day, she seemed to think of nothing but the fire. I fancied she was jealous even of the saucepan on it; and I have reason to know that she took its impressment into the service of boiling my egg and broiling my bacon, in dudgeon; for I saw her, with my own discomfited eyes, shake her fist at me once, when those culinary operations were going on, and no one else was looking. The sun streamed in at the little window, but she sat with her own back and the back of the large chair towards it, screening the fire as if she were sedulously keeping <hi rend="italics">it</hi> warm, instead of it keeping her warm, and watching it in a most distrustful manner. The completion of the preparations for my breakfast, by relieving the fire, gave her such extreme joy that she laughed aloud—and a very unmelodious laugh she had, I must say.</p><p >I sat down to my brown loaf, my egg, and my rasher of bacon, with a bason of milk besides, and made a most delicious meal. While I was yet in the full enjoyment of it, the old woman of the house said to the Master:</p><p >“Have you got your flute with you?”</p><p >“Yes,” he returned.</p><p >“Have a blow at it,” said the old woman, coaxingly. “Do!”</p><p >The Master, upon this, put his hand underneath the skirts of his coat, and brought out his flute in three pieces, which he screwed together, and began immediately to play. My impression is, after many years of consideration, that there never can have been anybody in the world who played worse. He made the most dismal sounds I have ever heard produced by any means, natural or artificial. I don't know what the tunes were—if there were such things in the performance at all, which I doubt—but the influence of the strain upon me was, first, to make me think of all my sorrows until I could hardly keep my tears back; then to take away my appetite; and lastly to make so sleepy that I couldn't keep my eyes open. They begin to close again, and I begin to nod, as the recollection rises fresh upon me. Once more the little room with its open corner cupboard, and its square-backed chairs, and its angular little staircase leading to the room above, and its three peacock's feathers displayed over the mantelpiece—I remember wondering when I first went in,
<pb xml:id="p56"/>
what that peacock would have thought if he had known what his finery was doomed to come to—fades from before me, and I nod, and sleep. The flute becomes inaudible, the wheels of the coach are heard instead, and I am on my journey. The coach jolts, I wake with a start, and the flute has come back again, and the Master at Salem House is sitting with his legs crossed, playing it dolefully, while the old woman of the house looks on delighted. She fades in her turn, and he fades, and all fades, and there is no flute, no Master, no Salem House, no David Copperfield, no anything but heavy sleep.</p><p >I dreamed, I thought, that once while he was blowing into this dismal flute, the old woman of the house, who had gone nearer and nearer to him in her ecstatic admiration, leaned over the back of his chair and gave him an affectionate squeeze round the neck, which stopped his playing for a moment. I was in the middle state between sleeping and waking, either then or immediately afterwards; for, as he resumed—it was a real fact that he had stopped playing—I saw and heard the same old woman ask Mrs. Fibbitson if it wasn't delicious (meaning the flute), to which Mrs. Fibbitson replied, “Ay, ay! Yes!” and nodded at the fire: to which, I am persuaded, she gave the credit of the whole performance.</p><p >When I seemed to have been dozing a long while, the Master at Salem House unscrewed his flute into the three pieces, put them up as before, and took me away. We found the coach very near at hand, and got upon the roof; but I was so dead sleepy, that when we stopped on the road to take up somebody else, they put me inside where there were no passengers, and where I slept profoundly, until I found the coach going at a footpace up a steep hill among green leaves. Presently, it stopped, and had come to its destination.</p><p >A short walk brought us—I mean the Master and me—to Salem House, which was enclosed with a high brick wall, and looked very dull. Over a door in this wall was a board with SALEM HOUSE upon it; and through a grating in this door we were surveyed when we rang the bell by a surly face, which I found, on the door being opened, belonged to a stout man with a bull-neck, a wooden leg, overhanging temples, and his hair cut close all round his head.</p><p >“The new boy,” said the Master.</p><p >The man with the wooden leg eyed me all over—it didn't take long, for there was not much of me—and locked the gate behind us, and took out the key. We were going up to the house, among some dark heavy trees, when he called after my conductor.</p><p >“Hallo!”</p><p >We looked back, and he was standing at the door of a little lodge, where he lived, with a pair of boots in his hand.</p><p >“Here! The cobbler's been,” he said, “since you've been out, Mr. Mell, and he says he can't mend'em any more. He says there an't a bit of the original boot left, and he wonders you expect it.”</p><p >With these words he threw the boots towards Mr. Mell, who went back a few paces to pick them up, and looked at them (very disconsolately, I was afraid), as we went on together. I observed then, for the first time, that the boots he had on were a good deal the worse for wear, and that his stocking was just breaking out in one place, like a bud.</p><pb  xml:id="p57"/><p >Salem House was a square brick building with wings; of a bare and unfurnished appearance. All about it was so very quiet, that I said to Mr. Mell I supposed the boys were out; but he seemed surprised at my not knowing that it was holiday-time. That all the boys were at their several homes. That Mr. Creakle, the proprietor, was down by the sea-side with Mrs. and Miss Creakle; and that I was sent in holiday-time as a punishment for my misdoing, all of which he explained to me as we went along.</p><p >I gazed upon the schoolroom into which he took me, as the most forlorn and desolate place I had ever seen. I see it now. A long room with three long rows of desks, and six of forms, and bristling all round with pegs for hats and slates. Scraps of old copybooks and exercises, litter the dirty floor. Some silkworms' houses, made of the same materials, are scattered over the desks. Two miserable little white mice, left behind by their owner, are running up and down in a fusty castle made of pasteboard and wire, looking in all the corners with their red eyes for anything to eat. A bird, in a cage a very little bigger than himself, makes a mournful rattle now and then in hopping on his perch, two inches high, or dropping from it; but neither signs nor chirps. There is a strange unwholesome smell upon the room, like mildewed corduroys, sweet apples wanting air, and rotten books. There could not well be more ink splashed about it, if it had been roofless from its first construction, and the skies had rained, snowed, hailed, and blown ink through the varying seasons of the year.</p><p >Mr. Mell having left me while he took his irreparable boots up-stairs, I went softly to the upper end of the room, observing all this as I crept along. Suddenly I came upon a pasteboard placard, beautifully written, which was lying on the desk, and bore these words—<hi rend="italics">“Take care of him. He bites.”</hi></p><p >I got upon the desk immediately, apprehensive of at least a great dog underneath. But, though I looked all round with anxious eyes, I could see nothing of him. I was still engaged in peering about, when Mr. Mell came back, and asked me what I did up there.</p><p >“I beg your pardon, sir,” says I, “if you please, I'm looking for the dog.”</p><p >“Dog?” says he. “What dog?”</p><p >“Isn't it a dog, sir?”</p><p >“Isn't what a dog?”</p><p >“That's to be taken care of, sir; that bites.”</p><p >“No, Copperfield,” says he gravely, “that's not a dog. That's a boy. My instructions are, Copperfield, to put this placard on your back. I am sorry to make such a beginning with you, but I must do it.”</p><p >With that, he took me down, and tied the placard, which was neatly constructed for the purpose, on my shoulders like a knapsack; and wherever I went, afterwards, I had the consolation of carrying it.</p><p >What I suffered from that placard, nobody can imagine. Whether it was possible for people to see me or not, I always fancied that somebody was reading it. It was no relief to turn round and find nobody; for wherever my back was, there I imagined somebody always to be. That cruel man with the wooden leg, aggravated my sufferings. He was in authority; and if he ever saw me leaning against a tree, or a wall, or the house, he roared out from his lodge-door in a
<pb xml:id="p58"/>
stupendous voice, “Hallo, you sir! You Copperfield! Show that badge conspicuous, or I'll report you!” The playground was a bare gravelled yard, open to all the back of the house and the offices; and I knew that the servants read it, and the butcher read it, and the baker read it; that everybody, in a word, who came backwards and forwards to the house, of a morning when I was ordered to walk there, read that I was to be taken care of, for I bit. I recollect that I positively began to have a dread of myself, as a kind of wild boy who did bite.</p><p >There was an old door in this playground, on which the boys had a custom of carving their names. It was completely covered with such inscriptions. In my dread of the end of the vacation and their coming back, I could not read a boy's name, without enquiring in what tone and with what emphasis <hi rend="italics">he</hi> would read, “Take care of him. He bites.” There was one boy—a certain J. Steerforth—who cut his name very deep and very often, who, I conceived, would read it in a rather strong voice, and afterwards pull my hair. There was another boy, one Tommy Traddles, who I dreaded would make game of it, and pretend to be dreadfully frightened of me. There was a third, George Demple, who I fancied would sing it. I have looked, a little shrinking creature, at that door, until the owners of all the names—there were five-and-forty of them in the school then, Mr. Mell said—seemed to send me to Coventry by general acclamation, and to cry out, each in his own way, “Take care of him. He bites!”</p><p >It was the same with the places at the desks and forms. It was the same with the groves of deserted bedsteads I peeped at, on my way to, and when I was in, my own bed. I remember dreaming night after night, of being with my mother as she used to be, or of going to a party at Mr. Peggotty's, or of travelling outside the stage-coach, or of dining again with my unfortunate friend the waiter, and in all these circumstances making people scream and stare, by the unhappy disclosure that I had nothing on but my little night-shirt, and that placard.</p><p >In the monotony of my life, and in my constant apprehension of the reopening of the school, it was such an insupportable affliction! I had long tasks every day to do with Mr. Mell; but I did them, there being no Mr. and Miss Murdstone here, and got through them without disgrace. Before, and after them, I walked about—supervised, as I have mentioned, by the man with the wooden leg. How vividly I call to mind the damp about the house, the green cracked flagstones in the court, an old leaky water-butt, and the discolored trunks of some of the grim trees, which seemed to have dripped more in the rain than other trees, and to have blown less in the sun! At one we dined, Mr. Mell and I, at the upper end of a long bare dining-room, full of deal tables, and smelling of fat. Then, we had more tasks until tea, which Mr. Mell drank out of a blue teacup, and I out of a tin pot. All day long, and until seven or eight in the evening, Mr. Mell, at his own detached desk in the schoolroom, worked hard with pen, ink, ruler, books, and writing-paper, making out the bills (as I found) for last half-year. When he had put up his things for the night he took out his flute, and blew at it, until I almost thought he would gradually blow his whole being into the large hole at the top, and ooze away at the keys.</p><pb  xml:id="p59"/><p >I picture my small self in the dimly-lighted rooms, sitting with my head upon my hand, listening to the doleful performance of Mr. Mell, and conning to-morrow's lessons. I picture myself with my books shut up, still listening to the doleful performance of Mr. Mell, and listening through it to what used to be at home, and to the blowing of the wind on Yarmouth flats, and feeling very sad and solitary. I picture myself going up to bed, among the unused rooms, and sitting on my bed-side crying for a comfortable word from Peggotty. I picture myself coming down stairs in the morning, and looking through a long ghastly gash of a staircase-window, at the school-bell hanging on the top of an outhouse, with a weathercock above it; and dreading the time when it shall ring J. Steerforth and the rest to work: which is only second, in my foreboding apprehensions, to the time when the man with the wooden leg shall unlock the rusty gate to give admission to the awful Mr. Creakle. I cannot think I was a very dangerous character in any of these aspects, but in all of them I carried the same warning on my back.</p><p >Mr. Mell never said much to me, but he was never harsh to me. I suppose we were company to each other, without talking. I forgot to mention that he would talk to himself sometimes, and grin, and clench his fist, and grind his teeth, and pull his hair in an unaccountable manner. But he had these peculiarities: and at first they frightened me, though I soon got used to them.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER VI. <lb/> I ENLARGE MY CIRCLE OF ACQUAINTANCE.</head><p >I HAD led this life about a month, when the man with the wooden leg began to stump about with a mop and a bucket of water, from which I inferred that preparations were making to receive Mr. Creakle and the boys. I was not mistaken; for the mop came into the schoolroom before long, and turned out Mr. Mell and me, who lived where we could, and got on how we could, for some days, during which we were always in the way of two or three young women, who had rarely shown themselves before, and were so continually in the midst of dust that I sneezed almost as much as if Salem House had been a great snuff-box.</p><p >One day I was informed by Mr. Mell, that Mr. Creakle would be home that evening. In the evening, after tea, I heard that he was come. Before bed-time, I was fetched by the man with the wooden leg to appear before him.</p><p >Mr. Creakle's part of the house was a good deal more comfortable than ours, and he had a snug bit of garden that looked pleasant after the dusty playground, which was such a desert in miniature, that I thought no one but a camel, or a dromedary, could have felt at home in it. It seemed to me a bold thing even to take notice that the passage looked comfortable, as I went on my way, trembling, to Mr. Creakle's presence: which so
<pb xml:id="p60"/>
abashed me, when I was ushered into it, that I hardly saw Mrs. Creakle or Miss Creakle (who were both there, in the parlor), or anything but Mr. Creakle, a stout gentleman with a bunch of watch-chain and seals, in an arm-chair, with a tumbler and bottle beside him.</p><p >“So!” said Mr. Creakle. “This is the young gentleman whose teeth are to be filed! Turn him round.”</p><p >The wooden-legged man turned me about so as to exhibit the placard; and having afforded time for a full survey of it, turned me about again, with my face to Mr. Creakle, and posted himself at Mr. Creakle's side. Mr. Creakle's face was fiery, and his eyes were small, and deep in his head; he had thick veins in his forehead, a little nose, and a large chin. He was bald on the top of his head; and had some thin wet-looking hair that was just turning grey, brushed across each temple, so that the two sides interlaced on his forehead. But the circumstance about him which impressed me most, was, that he had no voice, but spoke in a whisper. The exertion this cost him, or the consciousness of talking in that feeble way, made his angry face so much more angry, and his thick veins so much thicker, when he spoke, that I am not surprised, on looking back, at this peculiarity striking me as his chief one.</p><p >“Now,” said Mr. Creakle. “What's the report of this boy?”</p><p >“There's nothing against him yet,” returned the man with the wooden leg. “There has been no opportunity.”</p><p >I thought Mr. Creakle was disappointed. I thought Mrs. and Miss Creakle (at whom I now glanced for the first time, and who were, both, thin and quiet) were not disappointed.</p><p >“Come here, sir!” said Mr. Creakle, beckoning to me.</p><p >“Come here!” said the man with the wooden leg, repeating the gesture.</p><p >“I have the happiness of knowing your father-in-law,” whispered Mr. Creakle, taking me by the ear; “and a worthy man he is, and a man of a strong character. He knows me, and I know him. Do <hi rend="italics">you</hi> know me? Hey?” said Mr. Creakle, pinching my ear with ferocious playfulness.</p><p >“Not yet, sir,” I said, flinching with the pain.</p><p >“Not yet? Hey?” repeated Mr. Creakle. “But you will soon. Hey?”</p><p >“You will soon. Hey?” repeated the man with the wooden leg. I afterwards found that he generally acted, with his strong voice, as Mr. Creakle's interpreter to the boys.</p><p >I was very much frightened, and said, I hoped so, if he pleased. I felt, all this while, as if my ear were blazing; he pinched it so hard.</p><p >“I'll tell you what I am,” whispered Mr. Creakle, letting it go at last, with a screw at parting that brought the water into my eyes. “I'm a Tartar.”</p><p >“A Tartar,” said the man with the wooden leg.</p><p >“When I say I'll do a thing, I do it,” said Mr. Creakle; “and when I say I will have a thing done, I will have it done.”</p><p >“—Will have a thing done, I will have it done,” repeated the man with the wooden leg.</p><p >“I am a determined character,” said Mr. Creakle. “That's what I am. I do my duty. That's what <hi rend="italics">I</hi> do. My flesh and blood”—he
<pb xml:id="p61"/>
looked at Mrs. Creakle as he said this—“when it rises against me, is not my flesh and blood. I discard it. Has that fellow,” to the man with the wooden leg, “been here again?”</p><p >“No,” was the answer.</p><p >“No,” said Mr. Creakle. “He knows better. He knows me. Let him keep away. I say let him keep away,” said Mr. Creakle, striking his hand upon the table, and looking at Mrs. Creakle, “for he knows me. Now you have begun to know me too, my young friend, and you may go. Take him away.”</p><p >I was very glad to be ordered away, for Mrs. and Miss Creakle were both wiping their eyes, and I felt as uncomfortable for them, as I did for myself. But I had a petition on my mind which concerned me so nearly, that I couldn't help saying, though I wondered at my own courage:</p><p >“If you please, sir—”</p><p >Mr. Creakle whispered, “Hah? What's this?” and bent his eyes upon me, as if he would have burnt me up with them.</p><p >“If you please, sir,” I faltered, “if I might be allowed (I am very sorry indeed, sir, for what I did) to take this writing off, before the boys come back—”</p><p >Whether Mr Creakle was in earnest, or whether he only did it to frighten me I don't know, but he made a burst out of his chair, before which I precipitately retreated, without waiting for the escort of the man with the wooden leg, and never once stopped until I reached my own bedroom, where, finding I was not pursued, I went to bed, as it was time, and lay quaking, for a couple of hours.</p><p >Next morning Mr. Sharp came back. Mr. Sharp was the first master, and superior to Mr. Mell. Mr. Mell took his meals with the boys, but Mr. Sharp dined and supped at Mr. Creakle's table. He was a limp, delicate-looking gentleman, I thought, with a good deal of nose, and a way of carrying his head on one side, as if it were a little too heavy for him. His hair was very smooth and wavy; but I was informed by the very first boy who came back that it was a wig (a second-hand one <hi rend="italics">he</hi> said), and that Mr. Sharp went out every Saturday afternoon to get it curled.</p><p >It was no other than Tommy Traddles who gave me this piece of intelligence. He was the first boy who returned. He introduced himself by informing me that I should find his name on the right-hand corner of the gate, over the top bolt; upon that I said, “Traddles?” to which he replied, “The same,” and then he asked me for a full account of myself and family.</p><p >It was a happy circumstance for me that Traddles came back first. He enjoyed my placard so much, that he saved me from the embarrassment of either disclosure or concealment, by presenting me to every other boy who came back, great or small, immediately on his arrival, in this form of introduction, “Look here! Here's a game!” Happily, too, the greater part of the boys came back low-spirited, and were not so boisterous at my expense as I had expected. Some of them certainly did dance about me like wild Indians, and the greater part could not resist the temptation of pretending that I was a dog, and patting and smoothing me lest I should bite, and saying, “Lie down, sir!” and calling me Towzer. This was naturally
<pb xml:id="p62"/>
confusing, among so many strangers, and cost me some tears, but on the whole it was much better than I had anticipated.</p><p >I was not considered as being formally received into the school, however, until J. Steerforth arrived. Before this boy, who was reputed to be a great scholar, and was very good-looking, and at least half-a-dozen years my senior, I was carried as before a magistrate. He enquired, under a shed in the playground, into the particulars of my punishment, and was pleased to express his opinion that it was “a jolly shame;” for which I became bound to him ever afterwards.</p><p >“What money have you got, Copperfield?” he said, walking aside with me when he had disposed of my affair in these terms.</p><p >I told him seven shillings.</p><p >“You had better give it to me to take care of,” he said. “At least, you can if you like. You needn't if you don't like.”</p><p >I hastened to comply with his friendly suggestion, and opening Peggotty's purse, turned it upside down into his hand.</p><p >“Do you want to spend anything now?” he asked me.</p><p >“No, thank you,” I replied.</p><p >“You can if you like, you know,” said Steerforth. “Say the word.”</p><p >“No, thank you, sir,” I repeated.</p><p >“Perhaps you'd like to spend a couple of shillings or so, in a bottle of currant wine by-and-by, up in the bedroom?” said Steerforth. “You belong to my bedroom, I find.”</p><p >It certainly had not occurred to me before, but I said, Yes, I should like that.</p><p >“Very good,” said Steerforth. “You'll be glad to spend another shilling or so, in almond cakes, I dare say?”</p><p >I said, Yes, I should like that, too.</p><p >“And another shilling or so in biscuits, and another in fruit, eh?” said Steerforth. “I say, young Copperfield, you're going it!”</p><p >I smiled because he smiled, but I was a little troubled in my mind, too.</p><p >“Well!” said Steerforth. “We must make it stretch as far as we can; that's all. I'll do the best in my power for you. I can go out when I like, and I'll smuggle the prog in.” With these words he put the money in his pocket, and kindly told me not to make myself uneasy; he would take care it should be all right.</p><p >He was as good as his word, if that were all right which I had a secret misgiving was nearly all wrong—for I feared it was a waste of my mother's two half-crowns—though I had preserved the piece of paper they were wrapped in: which was a precious saving. When we went up-stairs to bed, he produced the whole seven shillings' worth, and laid it out on my bed in the moonlight, saying:</p><p >“There you are, young Copperfield, and a royal spread you've got!”</p><p >I couldn't think of doing the honors of the feast, at my time of life, while he was by; my hand shook at the very thought of it. I begged him to do me the favor of presiding; and my request being seconded by the other boys who were in that room, he acceded to it, and sat upon my pillow, handing round the viands—with perfect fairness, I must say—and dispensing the currant wine in a little glass without a foot, which was his own property. As to me, I sat on his left hand, and the rest were grouped about us, on the nearest beds and on the floor.</p><pb  xml:id="p63"/><p >How well I recollect our sitting there, talking in whispers; or their talking, and my respectfully listening, I ought rather to say; the moonlight falling a little way into the room, through the window, painting a pale window on the floor, and the greater part of us in shadow, except when Steerforth dipped a match into a phosphorous-box, when he wanted to look for anything on the board, and shed a blue glare over us that was gone directly! A certain mysterious feeling, consequent on the darkness, the secresy of the revel, and the whisper in which everything was said, steals over me again, and I listen to all they tell me with a vague feeling of solemnity and awe, which makes me glad that they are all so near, and frightens me (though I feign to laugh) when Traddles pretends to see a ghost in the corner.</p><p >I heard all kinds of things about the school and all belonging to it. I heard that Mr. Creakle had not preferred his claim to being a Tartar without reason; that he was the sternest and most severe of masters; that he laid about him, right and left, every day of his life, charging in among the boys like a trooper, and slashing away, unmercifully. That he knew nothing himself, but the art of slashing, being more ignorant (J. Steerforth said) than the lowest boy in the school; that he had been, a good many years ago, a small hop-dealer in the Borough, and had taken to the schooling business after being bankrupt in hops, and making away with Mrs. Creakle's money. With a good deal more of that sort, which I wondered how they knew.</p><p >I heard that the man with the wooden leg, whose name was Tungay, was an obstinate barbarian who had formerly assisted in the hop business, but had come into the scholastic line with Mr. Creakle, in consequence, as was supposed among the boys, of his having broken his leg in Mr. Creakle's service, and having done a deal of dishonest work for him, and knowing his secrets. I heard that with the single exception of Mr. Creakle, Tungay considered the whole establishment, masters and boys, as his natural enemies, and that the only delight of his life was to be sour and malicious. I heard that Mr. Creakle had a son, who had not been Tungay's friend, and who, assisting in the school, had once held some remonstrance with his father on an occasion when its discipline was very cruelly exercised, and was supposed, besides, to have protested against his father's usage of his mother. I heard that Mr. Creakle had turned him out of doors, in consequence; and that Mrs. and Miss Creakle had been in a sad way, ever since.</p><p >But the greatest wonder that I heard of Mr. Creakle was, there being one boy in the school on whom he never ventured to lay a hand, and that boy being J. Steerforth. Steerforth himself confirmed this when it was stated, and said that he should like to begin to see him do it. On being asked by a mild boy (not me) how he would proceed if he did begin to see him do it, he dipped a match into his phosphorous-box on purpose to shed a glare over his reply, and said he would commence by knocking him down with a blow on the forehead from the seven-and-sixpenny ink-bottle that was always on the mantelpiece. We sat in the dark for some time, breathless.</p><p >I heard that Mr. Sharp and Mr. Mell were both supposed to be wretchedly paid; and that when there was hot and cold meat for dinner at Mr. Creakle's table, Mr. Sharp was always expected to say he preferred
<pb xml:id="p64"/>
cold; which was again corroborated by J. Steerforth, the only parlorboarder. I heard that Mr. Sharp's wig didn't fit him; and that he needn't be so “bounceable”—somebody else said “bumptious”—about it, because his own red hair was very plainly to be seen behind.</p><p >I heard that one boy, who was a coal-merchant's son, came as a set-off against the coal-bill, and was called on that account “Exchange or Barter”—a name selected from the arithmetic-book as expressing this arrangement. I heard that the table-beer was a robbery of parents, and the pudding an imposition. I heard that Miss Creakle was regarded by the school in general as being in love with Steerforth; and I am sure, as I sat in the dark, thinking of his nice voice, and his fine face, and his easy manner, and his curling hair, I thought it very likely. I heard that Mr. Mell was not a bad sort of fellow, but hadn't a sixpence to bless himself with; and that there was no doubt that old Mrs. Mell, his mother, was as poor as Job. I thought of my breakfast then, and what had sounded like “My Charley!” but I was, I am glad to remember, as mute as a mouse about it.</p><p >The hearing of all this, and a good deal more, outlasted the banquet some time. The greater part of the guests had gone to bed as soon as the eating and drinking were over; and we, who had remained whispering and listening half undressed, at last betook ourselves to bed, too.</p><p >“Good night, young Copperfield,” said Steerforth, “I'll take care of you.”</p><p >“You're very kind,” I gratefully returned. “I am very much obliged to you.”</p><p >“You haven't got a sister, have you?” said Steerforth, yawning.</p><p >“No,” I answered.</p><p >“That's a pity,” said Steerforth. “If you had had one, I should think she would have been a pretty, timid, little, bright-eyed sort of girl. I should have liked to know her. Good night, young Copperfield.”</p><p >“Good night, sir,” I replied.</p><p >I thought of him very much after I went to bed, and raised myself, I recollect, to look at him where he lay in the moonlight, with his handsome face turned up, and his head reclining easily on his arm. He was a person of great power in my eyes; that was of course the reason of my mind running on him. No veiled future dimly glanced upon him in the moonbeams. There was no shadowy picture of his footsteps, in the garden that I dreamed of walking in all night.</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><head >COMPLETION <lb/> OF <lb/> KNIGHT'S SHILLING VOLUMES <lb/> FOR ALL READERS,</head><opener >PUBLISHED BY <lb/> C. COX, 12, KING WILLIAM STREET, STRAND.</opener><div><head >POSTSCRIPT, BY THE EDITOR,</head><p >TO THE CONCLUDING VOLUME OF THE SERIES, ENTITLED <lb/> “RAMBLES BY RIVERS: THE THAMES,” VOL. II.</p><p >THIS Series was commenced in June, 1844. It has been continued, first in Weekly Volumes, and subsequently in Monthly Volumes, for five years. The Series is now terminated with the publication of the 186th volume.</p><p >The Series divides itself into three distinct portions:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> The Weekly and Monthly Volumes </cell><cell> 148 </cell></row><row><cell> The Cabinet Portrait Gallery of British Worthies </cell><cell> 12 </cell></row><row><cell> The Cabinet History of England </cell><cell> 26—186 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >In the original announcement of this work I thus stated the objects which it would endeavour to attain:—</p><p >“We propose to place within the reach of all readers a series of books which shall ultimately comprehend something like that range of literature which well-educated persons desire to have at their command. In this series there will be no attempt at exclusiveness. We shall not take up the most false and dangerous opinion that the understandings of the masses should be written down to, nor will mere didactic instruction only be attempted. A taste for knowledge is not so induced. The recreation of genial and amusing reading should be offered in connexion with what is solid and serious. The publishers possess many valuable copyrights which may be readily adapted to this purpose. There is a great deal also to be done anew, in the way or judicious compilations, of translations from foreign works, and of original productions by authors of ability, conceived in a right spirit. We have many offers of assistance from writers of established reputation, who feel that the circulation of their thoughts in a cheap pocket volume is a tribute to their usefulness and their reputation. We have no want of materials to conduct this undertaking steadily and extensively.”</p><p >I now venture to believe that I have accomplished what I proposed to do.</p><p >First,—I have endeavoured to produce a series of books which comprehends something like that range of literature which well-educated persons desire to have at their command. Without attempting any very exact classification of
<pb xml:id="p2a"/>
the various subjects of these volumes, they may be thus distributed into large departments of knowledge:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> Analytical Accounts of great Writers, English and Foreign </cell><cell> 13 </cell></row><row><cell> Biography </cell><cell> 33 </cell></row><row><cell> General History </cell><cell> 5 </cell></row><row><cell> English History </cell><cell> 26 </cell></row><row><cell> Geography, Travels, and Topography </cell><cell> 33 </cell></row><row><cell> Natural History </cell><cell> 17 </cell></row><row><cell> Fine Arts and Antiquities </cell><cell> 8 </cell></row><row><cell> Arts and Sciences, Political Philosophy, &amp;c. </cell><cell> 14 </cell></row><row><cell> Natural Theology and Philosophy </cell><cell> 15 </cell></row><row><cell> General Literature </cell><cell> 16 </cell></row><row><cell> Original Fiction </cell><cell> 6—186 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Secondly,—The very nature of the subjects thus comprised in this series will show that mere didactic instruction has not been attempted; and that genial and amusing reading is presented in connexion with the solid and serious. It would be contrary to the principles upon which I have always regarded the duties of those who labour in the great cause of making good literature cheap, if I had in this series presumed it necessary to write down to the understandings of the masses. I shall never cease to believe that whatever is best and most permanent in literature has a character of universality; and that whenever attempts are made to “write down” to a class, or “write up” to a class, the thing so produced is worthy of small regard, and has little influence in its own day, and less upon the future.</p><p >Lastly,—In stating that I should introduce valuable copyrights into this Series, and that I had offers of assistance from writers of established reputation, it may be sufficient to point to the names of the various authors<ref xml:id="ref1" target="#n1">*</ref>
<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p >* See List of Contributors to the Series, next page.</p></note>
of these volumes, all of which are original, to show that I have fulfilled this portion of my undertaking.</p><p >The property of this large Series passed out of my hands as its publisher in the beginning of 1847, in consequence of business arrangements connected with a dissolution of partnership. Since then the additions to the Series have been, for the most part, reprints of copyright works, which were formerly published by me. I have never ceased to consider myself responsible for the general character of the work, although my editorial labours had terminated when about two-thirds of the Series were completed. I may truly add, that my desire for the constant and increasing circulation of these Volumes continues unabated; for I may venture to hope that each and all have a tendency to carry forward that intellectual progress upon which the future destiny of this country so essentially depends. And I may confidently state that in this extensive series no single work, and no portion of a work, can be found, that may not safely be put into the hands of the young and the uninformed, with the security that it will neither mislead nor corrupt.</p><closer >
<signed>CHARLES KNIGHT.</signed>
<dateline>St. John's Wood, <lb/> April 24, 1849.</dateline>
</closer></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p3a"/><head >A COMPLETE CATALOGUE OF <lb/> Knight's Shilling Volumes</head><p >FOR ALL READERS, <lb/> AND OF <lb/> Kníght's pictoríal Works, <lb/> PUBLISHED BY CHARLES COX, 12, KING WILLIAM STREET, STRAND.</p><list  type="simple"><head><hi rend="italics">List of Contributors to the Series.</hi></head><item>LORD BROUGHAM.</item><item>LORD NUGENT.</item><item>CHARLES KNIGHT, <hi rend="italics">Editor.</hi></item><item>PROFESSOR LONG.</item><item>E. W. LANE.</item><item>CHARLES LAMB.</item><item>A. T. MALKIN, A.M.</item><item>MRS. JAMESON.</item><item>MISS MARTINEAU.</item><item>G. L. CRAIK, A.M.</item><item>C. MAC FARLANE.</item><item>A. DE MORGAN.</item><item>REV. C. G. NICOLAY.</item><item>W. YOUATT.</item><item>JAMES RENNIE, A.M.</item><item>W. MARTIN.</item><item>DR. KITTO.</item><item>SIR CHARLES BELL.</item><item>SIR JOHN FRANCIS DAVIS.</item><item>MRS. POOLE.</item><item>DR. LANKESTER.</item><item>DR. SOUTHWOOD SMITH.</item><item>T. R. PLANCHÉ.</item><item>RALPH N. WORNUM.</item><item>W. WITTICH.</item><item>A. VIEUSSEUX.</item><item>G. H. LEWES.</item><item>MADAME BlAZ DE BURY.</item><item>A. RAMSAY.</item><item>T. C. BANFIELD.</item><item>GEORGE DENNIS.</item><item>JAMES THORNE.</item><item>GEORGE DODD.</item><item>JOHN SAUNDERS.</item></list><p >‘In every house in the Kingdom, from the palace of the peer to the humble cottage of the peasant, ought to be found <hi rend="italics">“Knight's Shilling Volumes for all Readers.”</hi>’—<hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Each volume, sewed </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> In cloth </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Elegantly bound </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Or in Double Volumes, with gilt edges </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >LORD BROUGHAM'S WORKS.</head><p >6 vols., price 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lord Brougham's Statesmen of the Time of George III. A new edition, corrected by the Author.</p><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lord Brougham's Dialogues on Instinct.</p><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lord Brougham's Two Discourses on the Objects, Pleasures, and Advantages of Science, and of Political Science.</p><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lord Brougham and Sir C. Bell's Edition of Paley's Natural Theology.</p><p >“These are among the best of Lord Brougham's writings, and we are satisfied will be cherished as valuable contributions to the literature of his country ages after the names and works of many of his enemies are forgotten.”—<hi rend="italics">Economist.</hi></p><list  type="simple"><head><hi rend="italics">LIST OF STATESMEN WHO APPEAR IN THE HISTORICAL SKETCHES:—</hi></head><item>George III.</item><item>Lord Chatham.</item><item>Lord North.</item><item>Lord Loughborough.</item><item>Lord Thurlow.</item><item>Lord Mansfield.</item><item>Loard Chief-Justice Gibbs.</item><item>Sir William Grant.</item><item>Mr. Burke.</item><item>Mr. Fox.</item><item>Mr. Pitt.</item><item>Mr. Sheridan.</item><item>Mr. Windham.</item><item>Mr. Dundas.</item><item>Mr. Erskine.</item><item>Mr. Perceval.</item><item>Lord Grenville.</item><item>Mr. Grattan.</item><item>Mr. Wilberforce.</item><item>Mr. Canning.</item><item>Sir Samuel Romilly.</item><item>Franklin.</item><item>Frederic H.</item><item>Gustavus III.</item><item>The Emperor Joseph.</item><item>The Empress Catherine</item><item>George IV.</item><item>Sir John Leach.</item><item>Lord Eldon.</item><item>Lord Stowell.</item><item>Dr. Lawrence.</item><item>Sir Philip Francis.</item><item>Mr. Horne Tooke.</item><item>Lord Castlereagli.</item><item>Lord Liverpool.</item><item>Mr. Tierney.</item><item>Lord Nelson.</item><item>Lord King.</item><item>Mr. Horner.</item><item>Mr. Ricardo.</item><item>Note on Mr. Curran.</item><item>Neckar.</item><item>Madame de Staël.</item><item>Mirabeau family.</item><item>Carnot.</item><item>Lafayette.</item><item>Prince Talleyrand.</item><item>Napoleon.</item><item>Washington.</item><item>The French Revolution.</item><item>Robespierre.</item><item>Danton.</item><item>Camille Desmoulins—St. Just.</item><item>Sièyes.</item><item>Fouché.</item><item>John, 4th Duke of Bedford.</item><item>Earl Camden.</item><item>John Wilkes.</item><item>Lord Ellenborough.</item><item>Lord Chief - Justice</item><item>Bushe.</item><item>Jefferson.</item><item>Wellesley.</item><item>Lord Holland.</item><item>John Allen.</item><item>Walpole.</item><item>Bolingbroke.</item></list><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p4a"/><head >Davis's Chinese.</head><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Sir John Davis's Chinese and Sketches of China. New editions.</p><p >“In Mr. Davis's account of China we find every subject brought forward that can throw light on the laws and institutions of a people to whom, we think, that justice has not been rendered by foreigners, which is their due.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Lord Nugent's Lands, Classical, &amp;c.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lord Nugent's Lands, Classical and Sacred. Second edition.</p><p >“No work of recent date on the same topics better merits and will better repay the attention of the reader.”</p></div><div type="section"><head >Miss Martineau.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Miss Martineau's Tales:—Feats on the Fiord; and the Billow and the Rock.</p><p >“These volumes will be read with delight through every generation in a house.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Mrs. Jameson.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Mrs. Jameson's Lives of the Early Italian Painters, and of the Progress of the Art in Italy.</p><list  type="simple"><item>Giovanni Cimabue.</item><item>Giotto.</item><item>Lorenzo Ghiberti.</item><item>Masaccio.</item><item>Filippo Lippi and Angelico da Fiesole.</item><item>Benozzo Gozzoli.</item><item>Andrea Castagno and Luca Signorelli.</item><item>Domenico dal Ghirlandajo.</item><item>Andrea Mantegna.</item><item>The Bellini.</item><item>Pietro Perugino.</item><item>Francesco Raibolini, called II Francia.</item><item>Fra Bartolomeo, called also Baccio della Porta and II Frate.</item><item>Lionardo da Vinci.</item><item>Michael Angelo.</item><item>Andrea del Sarto.</item><item>Raphael Sanzio d'Urbino.</item><item>The Scholars of Raphael.</item><item>Correggio and Giorgione, and their Scholars.</item><item>Parmigiano.</item><item>Giorgione.</item><item>Titian.</item><item>Tintoretto.</item><item>Panl Veronese.</item><item>Jacopo Bassano.</item></list></div><div type="section"><head >Knight's Caxton.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Knight's Life of Caxton, the First English Printer.</p><p >“The Father of Printing could not have found a more suitable or a more enthusiastic biographer.”—<hi rend="italics">Patriot.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Results of Machinery.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Knight's Results of Machinery, and Capital and Labour.</p><p >The two tracts, originally published separately, are here incorporated and remodelled, the general subject of the Production of Wealth being thus fully, though popularly, expounded. The statistical details are brought up to the present time.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Knight's Volume of Varieties.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> A Volume of Varieties. By CHARLES KNIGHT.</p><p >A collection of scattered papers written by Mr. Knight at various periods of a long literary life, chiefly with the view of “doing something to advance the Education of the people.”</p></div><div type="section"><head >Lamb's Tales from <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Shakspere</sic><corr>Shakspeare</corr></choice>.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lamb's Tales from Shakspere, with Scenes selected by C. KNIGHT, and Wood Engravings by W. HARVEY.</p><p >In this edition Mr. Knight has added to each Tale a few <hi rend="italics">Scenes</hi> from Shakspere, which may be advantageously read after the perusal of the Tale, to furnish some notion of the original excellence of the wonderful dramas upon which the Tales are founded.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Insect and Bird Architecture.</head><p >5 vols., price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Insect and Bird Architecture, and Miscellanies. On the Ravages, the Preservation for the Purposes of Study, and the Classification of Insects: and on the Habits and Faculties of Birds. By JAMES RENNIE, A.M. New editions.</p><p >“So clear and untechnical are the descriptions, that the most uninitiated, after perusing them, will see <hi rend="italics">wonders</hi> where formerly he saw <hi rend="italics">nothing.</hi>”—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Examiner.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >The Elephant, Horse, and Dog.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Elephant, the Horse, and the Dog—the Three Friends of Man. By C. KNIGHT and W. MARTIN. And a Chapter on the Diseases of the Horse. By W. YOUATT.</p><p >The object of these works is to furnish very complete details of the three quadrupeds who have been the great instruments furnished by Divine Providence to man, to enable him to “replenish the earth and subdue it;” and who by their remarkable sagacity have, in various states of society, deserved to be regarded as his especial friends.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Monkeys—Sketches of Natural History.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Sketch of the History of Monkeys. 100 Woodcuts.</p><p >6 vols., price 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Sketches in Natural History—Mammalia. 600 Woodcuts.</p><p >These volumes, with the Elephant, Horse, and Dog, complete the Class Mammalia.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p5a"/><head >Tasso's Jerusalem.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Tasso's Recovery of Jerusalem.</p><p >Translated by FAIRFAX. With Lives of Tasso and Fairfax, by C. KNIGHT.</p><p >“It is at least doubtful whether any of the modern renderings of the Tuscan epic are, on the whole, superior in strength and richness of expression to this of our ‘British Fairfax,’ which secured the praise of Milton, Waller, Hume, and Collins.”—<hi rend="italics">Sheffield Mercury.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Mind amongst the Spindles.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Mind amongst the Spindles: a Selection from the Lowell Offering. With Introduction, by C. KNIGHT.</p><p >“We believe that great good may be effected by a knowledge diffused in every building throughout the land where there is a mule or a loom, of what the factory girls of Lowell have done to exhibit the cheering influences of ‘Mind amongst the Spindles.’”—<hi rend="italics">C. Knight.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Working Man.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Memoirs of a Working Man. With Preface, by C. KNIGHT.</p><p >This work shows how a man, through self-education and self-government, may become intelligent, respectable, and happy, even in the humblest walks of life.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Food of Man.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Food of Man. By Dr. LANKESTER. New edition.</p><p >“We should recommend every house-keeper and every farmer to have a copy of this most useful publication in his house for the benefit of his family.”—<hi rend="italics">Cork Examiner.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Literature and Learning.</head><p >6 vols., price 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> History of Literature and Learning in England, from the Earliest Time to the Present Day; with <hi rend="italics">Specimens</hi> of the Principal Writers. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M.</p><p >“An invaluable text-book to all students of English literature.”—<hi rend="italics">Critic.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Spenser and his Poetry.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Spenser and his Poetry. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M.</p><p >The object of this publication is to present not merely an account of Spenser and his works, but such an edition of his poetry as shall contain all of it that is of universal and indestructible interest.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Bacon and his Works, &amp;c.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Bacon, his Writings and his Philosophy.</p><p >“Combining in one book the uses and attractions of a life of Bacon; a complete bibliography of his different works; a history of each from its first conception to its finished form; a distinct exposition of its scope and tendency; a selection of their most beautiful and instructive passages; and a general estimate of the philosopher and his writings, at once characterised by logical acumen, and a deep, fresh sense of imaginative grandeur.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Pursuit of Knowledge.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Pursuit of Knowledge under Difficulties. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. New edition.</p><p >A body of examples to show how the most unpropitious circumstances have been unable to conquer an ardent desire for the acquisition of knowledge.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Female Examples, <lb/> Pursuit of Knowledge.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Female Examples of the Pursuit of Knowledge under Difficulties. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. A New Work.</p><p >“In proportion as a better understanding has crept into the world—and Woman the Companion has taken place of Woman the Prey, the Toy, or the Drudge, have female authorship risen in tone and in temper, and female knowledge increased in scope and accuracy. The book before us, then, produces no longer the pain excited by the statement of grievances unredressed. As a record, it is full of anecdote and interest. The book, as it stands, is a pleasant one—worthy of being accepted by all thoughtful women and honourable men.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Wittich's Norway.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> A Visit to the Western Coast of Norway. By W. WITTICH. With a Memoir of the Author, by GEORGE LONG.</p><p >“Mr. Wittich was one of the most distinguished geographers of modern times; in knowledge of the subject, and in the method of handling it, inferior to none; and only less known because his labours have not appeared, like those of Ritter and others, in voluminous works that bear the author's name. He has contributed more largely to the diffusion of geographical knowledge, and more largely to the giving to it some scientific method and precision, than any person who has yet lived in the British Islands.”—<hi rend="italics">Memoir, by G. Long.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p6a"/><head >British Commerce.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> History of British Commerce, from the Earliest Time to the Present Day. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M.</p><p >“To the merchant, the capitalist, the manufacturer, the tradesman, to all who are desirous of knowing by what means England has arrived at her present state of commercial greatness and prosperity, we recommend this work as the cheapest and by far the best mode of obtaining the desired information.”—<hi rend="italics">Lincoln Standard.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Physical Geography.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Curiosities of Physical Geography. By W. WITTICH.</p><p >CONTENTS:—Snow-Mountains—Glaciers—Avalanches—Mountain-Slips—Ieebergs and Icefields—The Gulf-Stream—The Samoom—Trade-Winds—Monsoons—Plains and Deserts—The Sahara—The Selva, or Forest Desert of the Amazonas—The Pampas—The Llanos—Earthquakes—Volcanoes.</p><p >“An account of some of the most remarkable of these phenomena is offered to the public in these volumes. The author has endeavoured to avoid all minute details, but tried to convey to the reader a complete idea of the most prominent characteristics of these phenomena. He has also tried to point out the effects which some of these phenomena have had in promoting the interests of the human race, and the dispersion of civilization over the surface of the globe.”—<hi rend="italics">Extract from Preface.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Englishwoman in Egypt.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Englishwoman in Egypt. By Mrs. POOLE.</p><p >“One of the most interesting books of travels we ever met with. The descriptions of the manners and customs of the Egyptian ladies are minute and graphic.”—<hi rend="italics">Derbyshire Courier.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Lane's Modern Egyptians.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lane's Modern Egyptians. A new edition.</p><p >“Mr. Lane's ‘Account of the Manners and Customs of the Modern Egyptians’ forms an admirable <hi rend="italics">pendant</hi> to the ‘Manners and Customs of the Chinese’ by Mr. Davis. These two authors are perfect masters of their subjects. Both are well acquainted with the languages, and both have been domesticated with the people, of the two countries respectively, whose manners and customs they have undertaken to describe; the former after a residence of seven, the latter of nearly twenty years. These circumstances give their books a strong claim to be considered as books of standard value.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Lane's Arabian Tales.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Lane's Arabian Tales and Anecdotes. Selected from the Arabian Nights.</p><p >“One of the peculiar and most interesting features of Mr. Lane's new translation of ‘The Thousand and One Nights’ is the introduction, by the way of notes, of many short tales or anecdotes, which form an integral portion of the vast collection of stories, the principal of which are known in England as ‘The Arabian Nights' Entertainments,’ but which have been for the most part omitted by all previous European translators. It appeared to the Editor of the Weekly Volume that these Anecdotes would form of themselves a valuable little work, illustrating as they do many Oriental customs and modes of thought.”—<hi rend="italics">Editor's Preface.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >The Lost Senses.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Lost Senses—Deafness and Blindness. By Dr. KITTO.</p><p >Dr. Kitto, when twelve years old, was deprived of his hearing by falling from a ladder; and the work is a record of his experience, observations, and reflections with regard to his calamity during a deafness of twenty-eight years.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Molière, Racine, &amp;c.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi><lb/> Molière, Racine, and the French Classical Drama. By Madame BLAZ DE BURY.</p><p >“To those who are ignorant of the French language this little work will be comprehensible and most charming.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Spanish Drama.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Spanish Drama—Lope de Vega and Calderon. By G. H. LEWES.</p><p >“A lively and brief account of the two most eminent dramatists of Spain.”—<hi rend="italics">Atheæum.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >The Cid.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Cid: a Short Chronicle, founded on the Early Poetry of Spain. By G. DENNIS, Author of ‘The Cities and Cemeteries of Etruria.’</p><p >“One of the most absorbing and romantic narratives we ever read.”</p></div><div type="section"><head >Gresham.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Life of Gresham, the Founder of the Royal Exchange. By C. MAC FARLANE.</p><p >“A well written and very interesting biography of this remarkable English merchant.”—<hi rend="italics">John o' Groat Journal.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p7a"/><head >Old England Novelets.</head><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Old England Novelets:—</p><p >The Camp of Refuge—The Dutch in the Medway—A Legend of Reading Abbey. By C. MAC FARLANE.</p><p >The object of this series is “to illustrate some leading causes of the social condition of our country in times essentially different from our own.”</p></div><div type="section"><head >Italy.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Popular Customs and Recollections of Italy. By C. MAC FARLANE.</p><p >“An exceedingly interesting and agreeable little book.”—<hi rend="italics">Sheffield Times.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Romance of Travel.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Romance of Travel—The East. By C. MAC FARLANE.</p><p >“We should feel disposed to utter a somewhat lengthened commendation upon the Oriental sketches of Mr. Mac Farlane, but that we deem such eulogiums altogether superfluous from the popularity already acquired by his writings.”—<hi rend="italics">San.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Plutarch's Lives.</head><p >5 vols., price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Civil Wars of Rome:</p><p >Select Lives from Plutarch, newly translated, by GEORGE LONG, late Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge. With Notes.</p><p >“The manner in which the translation is executed demands the highest praise.....The style will be found much more precise and vigorous than that of the version by the Langhornes. But what give the book its chief value are Mr. Long's notes, which are equally learned and judicious.”—<hi rend="italics">Classical Museum, No. X.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Chaucer.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Chaucer's Canterbury Tales and Pictures of English Life. By JOHN SAUNDERS.</p><p >“Readers who are only beginning to initiate themselves into the mysteries of antique spelling, Gallic construction, and other peculiarities inseparable from the age in which the father of English poets lived, will find this book of great assistance to their future studies.”—<hi rend="italics">The Apprentice.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Hudibras.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Hudibras, and other Works of Samuel Butler. Edited by A. RAMSAY.</p><p >“A careful analysis, with ample extracts; such as may be read with pleasure by the most fastidious.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Historical Parallels.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Historical Parallels. By A. MALKIN, A.M. New edition.</p><p >A collection of narratives of great interest to those who are not largely read in history.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Rambles by Rivers.</head><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></p><p >Rambles by Rivers. By JAMES THORNE.</p><p >The Thames, the Avon, the Duddon, the Lea, and the Dove.</p><p >“Delightful volumes.....The reader finds himself rambling along some of the most interesting and celebrated streams of England, in company of an intelligent, well-informed, and pleasant guide.”—<hi rend="italics">John o' Groat Journal.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Napoleon Buonaparte.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Napoleon Buonaparte; his Sayings <lb/> and his Deeds. By A. VIEUSSEUX.</p><p >A concise and popular sketch, and an endeavour to trace the inner workings of Napoleon's mind, elicited from his familiar conversations.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Flowers, &amp;c.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></p><p >Flowers and their Associations, and the Field, Garden, and Woodland. By Miss PRATT.</p><p >“An agreeable gossiping book—instructive and entertaining.”—<hi rend="italics">Gardeners' Chronicle.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Biographical History of Philosophy.</head><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></p><p >Biographical History of Ancient and Modern Philosophy. By G. H. LEWES.</p><p >“A more readable book we scarcely know.”—<hi rend="italics">Cheltenham Journal.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Philosophy of Health.</head><p >4 vols., price 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></p><p >Dr. Southwood Smith's Philosophy of Health, written with a View to the Promotion of Human Longevity and Happiness. New edition.</p><p >“The distinguished medical reputation of the Author, and his extreme simplicity of style, arising from a thorough mastery of his subject, must recommend his complete exposition of the structure and functions of the body to all classes of persons who desire any knowledge of the fearful and wonderful organization of the human frame. Dr. South wood Smith's work has a practical aim, as all his observations have reference to health and disease, and are intended to promote the eagerly desired blessings of ‘human longevity and happiness.’”—<hi rend="italics">The Britannia, April</hi> 17, 1847.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Industry of the Rhine.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Industry of the Rhine—Agriculture and Manufactures. By T. C. BANFIELD.</p><p >“These very interesting volumes contain a great deal of valuable information.”—<hi rend="italics">Gardeners' Chronicle.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Secret Societies.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Secret Societies of the Middle Ages.</p><p >An Account of the Rise and Progress of the celebrated Eastern Association, known as THE ASSASSINS; of the Foundation, History, and violent Suppression of the KNIGHTS TEMPLARS; and of the Origin, Proceedings, and Decline of the FEHMGERICHTE, or SECRET SOCIETIES OF WESTPHALIA.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p8a"/><head >Cabinet History of England.</head><p >26 vols., price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Cabinet History of England, abridged from the Pictorial History of England, and continued to the Present Time. By C. MAC FARLANE. With Illustrations by HARVEY.</p><p >The chapters in the ‘ Pictorial History of England’ entitled “Civil and Military History” supply the only complete History of England in our language, written by one author. Mr. MAC FARLANE, the author of these chapters, has abridged them, and continued them to the present day, so as to produce an original, complete, and really full narrative of our country's great story from the earliest time. Small as the price of this work is, no other can compete with it in the minuteness of its details and the labour of its research. The Histories of Hume and Smollett, excellent as they are in many respects, are only fragments with reference to the periods embraced by each, and since their days a flood of light has been shed upon English history, which leaves their pages, in spite of their attractions as compositions, dark by comparison with a history founded upon all we now know.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Cabinet Portrait Gallery.</head><p >12 vols., price 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Cabinet Portrait Gallery of British Worthies. With 72 Steel Engravings.</p><p >“We cordially recommend the work to those who would read elegantly written biographies of their country's greatest men.”—<hi rend="italics">Douglas Jerrold's Newspaper.</hi></p><list  type="simple"><head><hi rend="italics">LIST OF PORTRAITS AND BIOGRAPHIES.</hi></head><item>Henry II.</item><item>Roger Bacon.</item><item>Edward III.</item><item>Wiclif.</item><item>Chaucer.</item><item>William of Wykeham.</item><item>Henry V.</item><item>James I. of Scotland.</item><item>Henry VII.</item><item>Dean Colet.</item><item>Cardinal Wolsey.</item><item>Sir Thomas More.</item><item>Thomas Lord Cromwell.</item><item>Earl of Surrey.</item><item>Lady Jane Grey.</item><item>Archb. Cranmer.</item><item>Bishop Latimer.</item><item>John Knox.</item><item>Sir Thomas Gresham.</item><item>Buchanan.</item><item>Sir Philip Sidney.</item><item>Sir F. Drake.</item><item>Cecil, Lord Burleigh.</item><item>Spenser.</item><item>Queen Elizabeth.</item><item>Shakspere.</item><item>Raleigh.</item><item>Camden.</item><item>Bacon.</item><item>B. Jonson.</item><item>Strafford.</item><item>Hampden.</item><item>Laud.</item><item>Charles I.</item><item>Selden.</item><item>Blake.</item><item>W. Harvey, M.D.</item><item>Cromwell.</item><item>Thomas Fuller.</item><item>Jeremy Taylor.</item><item>Clarendon.</item><item>Milton.</item><item>Sir M. Hale.</item><item>A. Marvell.</item><item>I. Barrow.</item><item>Hobbes.</item><item>S. Butler.</item><item>Wm. Lord Russell.</item><item>Algernon Sidney.</item><item>Sir W. Petty.</item><item>T. Sydenham.</item><item>Robert Boyle.</item><item>Richard Baxter.</item><item>H. Purcell.</item><item>Sir Wm. Temple.</item><item>Dryden.</item><item>William III.</item><item>Locke.</item><item>Ray.</item><item>Lord Somers.</item><item>Wm. Penn.</item><item>Addison.</item><item>Marlborough.</item><item>Sir C. Wren.</item><item>Sir Isaac Newton.</item><item>De Foe.</item><item>Halley.</item><item>Pope.</item><item>Walpole.</item><item>Swift.</item><item>Wm. Hogarth.</item><item>Smeaton.</item></list></div><div type="section"><head >Backwoods of Canada and Oregon <lb/> Territory.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Backwoods of Canada. New edition. By a LADY. And the Oregon Territory. By the Rev. G. C. NICOLAY.</p><p >“An endeavour to afford every possible information to the wives and daughters of emigrants who contemplate seeking a home amid our Canadian wilds.”—<hi rend="italics">Preface.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Australia—Settlers and Convicts.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Settlers and Convicts; or, Recollections of Sixteen Years' Labour in the Backwoods of Australia. By an EMIGRANT MECHANIC.</p><p >“A valuable manual for all those whose circumstances or inclination lead to contemplate emigration as a means of relief from distress or difficulty at home.”—<hi rend="italics">Hertford Mercury.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >The Manufactures of Great Britain.</head><p >6 vols., price 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Manufactures of Great Britain. By G. DODD.</p><p >“A book eminently suited to the times—should be read by all who would know how it is that England has acquired the character of being the great workshop of the world.”—<hi rend="italics">British Friend of India Magazine.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Wornum's History of Painting.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Epochs of Painting characterized: a Sketch of the History of Painting, Ancient and Modern, showing its gradual and various Development from the Earliest Ages to the Present Time. By RALPH N. WORNUM.</p><p >“A clear and well-written sketch, comprehending a review of the progress of painting in every country where the art has obtained a cognizable degree of development, extending over a period of nearly three thousand years, and including biographical notices of many of the most eminent painters. It displays an intimate knowledge of the subject and considerable learning.”—<hi rend="italics">Builder.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Pompeii.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Pompeii: its Destruction and Rediscovery. New edition. 300 Woodcuts.</p><p >“In this work is given a detailed account of the ruins as they now exist, together with a description of their former state, as far as it can be made out; with occasional digressions upon points connected with the history or antiquities of the place, and notices of the most important and curious articles which have been discovered. The first portion of the work contains the public edifices, so far as they have as yet been disinterred; the second portion is devoted to the houses and private habits of their tenants.”—<hi rend="italics">Introduction.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Evils of Popular Tumults.</head><p >1 vol., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Popular Tumults; Illustrative of the Evils of Social Ignorance.</p><p >This volume contains Accounts of Tumults of Religious Fanaticism—Tumults of Political Excitement—and Tumults for raising the Rate of Wages.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Planche's British Costume.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> History of British Costume, from the Earliest Period to the Close of the Eighteenth Century. By J. R. PLANCHÉ, Esq., F.S.A. With numerous Illustrations. New Edition, corrected and enlarged, and an Index added.</p><p >“On presenting this new edition of ‘The History of British Costume’ to the public, the author has merely to state that it has undergone thorough revision and correction; that he has supplied many deficiencies, incorporated the most important discoveries and opinions which have resulted from the latest researches, or been promulgated in recent archæological publications; and added an Index to facilitate the reader's reference to any particular article mentioned or described in its pages.”—<hi rend="italics">Preface to New Edition.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Book of Table Talk.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> The Book of Table-Talk. By several CONTRIBUTORS.</p><p >“An excellent book for railway reading.”—<hi rend="italics">Critic.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p9a"/><head >Physical Geography of the Holy Land.</head><p >2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Physical Geography of the Holy Land. By JOHN KITTO, D.D., F.S.A., Editor of the Pictorial Bible.</p><p >“The country which God especially set apart for his great designs, and which, in consequence, contains no spot of ground on which some commissioned angel has not trod, or which does not suggest some incident in the histories of patriarchs, prophets, apostles, priests, and kings, whose names supply the familiar links by which our minds measure old times—this country must needs excite a peculiar interest in us, scarcely inferior to that with which our own native land is regarded.”—<hi rend="italics">Author's Introduction.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >Paris.</head><p >3 vols., price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> Paris: its Historical Buildings and its Revolutions. New edition, continued to the Present Time.</p><p >“The account of the Revolution of Paris in 1848 is the best we have read of the many narratives that have been published on that popular subject. It is closer, more complete. and impresses the causes of the catastrophe more clearly; while the Introduction conveys an idea of the power and numbers of the Republicans, by briefly bringing together the insurrections or disturbances that have taken place since 1830. It is a well-timed book; for the previous part enables the reader to get beyond the ignorant present, and see what Paris has always been.”—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p></div></div><div type="section"><head >LIST OF KNIGHT'S WEEKLY AND MONTHLY VOLUMES,</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Arranged according to the Numerical Order in which they were published.</hi></p><p >
<table><head>KNIGHT'S WEEKLY VOLUME.</head><row><cell> I. </cell><cell> William Caxton: a Biography. </cell></row><row><cell> II. </cell><cell> Mind amongst the Spindles. </cell></row><row><cell> III. XII. </cell><cell> The Englishwoman in Egypt: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> IV. VII. </cell><cell> Lamb's Tales from Shakspere: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> V. XXV. XXXVIII. LXI. LXX. LXXX. </cell><cell> British Manufactures: 6 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> VI. IX. XIII. XXXII. </cell><cell> The Chinese: 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> VIII. </cell><cell> Feats on the Fiord. </cell></row><row><cell> X. XIV. </cell><cell> Tasso's Jerusalem Delivered: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XI. </cell><cell> Bird Architecture. </cell></row><row><cell> XV. </cell><cell> The Elephant. </cell></row><row><cell> XVI. XLVIII. </cell><cell> Rambles by Rivers. </cell></row><row><cell> XVII. XVIII. XXXVI. XXXVII. XLIX. L. </cell><cell> History of Literature and Learning in England: 6 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XIX. </cell><cell> Dialogues on Instinct. </cell></row><row><cell> XX. XXIV. XXVI. </cell><cell> History of British Commerce: 3 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XXI. </cell><cell> A Volume of Varieties. </cell></row><row><cell> XXII. XXIII. </cell><cell> The Camp of Refuge: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XXVII. LVIII. LXXXII. CXV. CXVI. </cell><cell> Civil Wars of Rome: 5 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XXVIII. </cell><cell> Life of Sir T. Gresham. </cell></row><row><cell> XXIX. XXXI. XXXIII. </cell><cell> Pursuit of Knowledge: 3 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XXX. </cell><cell> Pictures of English Life.—Chaucer. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXIV. </cell><cell> Memoirs of a Working Man. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXV. </cell><cell> The Cid. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXIX. XL. </cell><cell> Insect Architecture, &amp;c.: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XLI. LI. </cell><cell> The Lost Senses: Deafness—Blindness. </cell></row><row><cell> XLII. XCVI. </cell><cell> Curiosities of Physical Geography: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XLIII. </cell><cell> The Dutch in the Medway. </cell></row><row><cell> XLIV. </cell><cell> The History of the Dog. </cell></row><row><cell> XLV. XLVI. LXXXVIII. XC. </cell><cell> Biographical History of Philosophy: 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XLVII. </cell><cell> Arabian Tales and Anecdotes. </cell></row><row><cell> LII. LIII. LXIII. LXV. LXXIV. LXXVIII. </cell><cell> Statesmen of the Time of George III.: 6 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LIV. LIX. LXIV. LXIX. LXXVI. LXXXIV. XCII. CII. CVII. CIX. CX. CXII. </cell><cell> Cabinet Portrait Gallery: 12 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LV. LVII. </cell><cell> Memoirs of the Early Italian Painters: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LVI. </cell><cell> Racine, and the French Classical Drama. </cell></row><row><cell> LX. LXVI. LXXI. </cell><cell> Spenser and his Poetry: 3 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXII. </cell><cell> A Legend of Reading Abbey. </cell></row><row><cell> LXVII. </cell><cell> Capital and Labour. </cell></row><row><cell> LXVIII. </cell><cell> The History of the Horse. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXII. LXXIII. LXXVII. LXXIX. </cell><cell> Paley's Natural Theology: 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXV. CXIV. </cell><cell> Canterbury Tales: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXXI. CXI. </cell><cell> The Romance of Travel: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXXIII. XCIII. </cell><cell> Napoleon Buonaparte: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXXV. LXXXVI. LXXXVII. </cell><cell> Historical Parallels: 3 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> LXXXIX. </cell><cell> The Oregon Territory. </cell></row><row><cell> XCI. CVIII. </cell><cell> The Food of Man: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XCIV. </cell><cell> Industry of the Rhine: Series I.—Agriculture. </cell></row><row><cell> XCV. </cell><cell> Hudibras. </cell></row><row><cell> XCVII. CVI. CXIII. </cell><cell> Bacon and his Writings: 3 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XCVIII. XCIX. </cell><cell> Lands, Classical and Sacred: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> C. </cell><cell> Flowers and their Associations. </cell></row><row><cell> CI. </cell><cell> The Backwoods of Canada. </cell></row><row><cell> CIII. CIV. CV. </cell><cell> Modern Egyptians: 3 Vols. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>KNIGHT'S MONTHLY VOLUME.</head><row><cell> I. </cell><cell> Popular Customs, &amp;c., of the South of Italy. </cell></row><row><cell> II. </cell><cell> Englishwoman in Egypt. Second Series, written in 1845-6. </cell></row><row><cell> III. </cell><cell> Lord Brougham's Discourses on Science and Political Science. </cell></row><row><cell> IV. </cell><cell> The Spanish Drama. </cell></row><row><cell> V. </cell><cell> The Billow and the Rock. </cell></row><row><cell> VI. </cell><cell> Molière, and the French <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Classica</sic><corr>Classical</corr></choice> Drama. </cell></row><row><cell> VII. VIII. IX. X. </cell><cell> Philosophy of Health: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XI. XLIV. </cell><cell> Rambles by Rivers.—Thames. </cell></row><row><cell> XII. XIII. </cell><cell> Settlers and Convicts. </cell></row><row><cell> XIV. XV. </cell><cell> Pursuit of Knowledge.—Female Examples. </cell></row><row><cell> XVI. </cell><cell> Field, Garden, and Woodland. </cell></row><row><cell> XVII. XVIII. </cell><cell> History of Painting. </cell></row><row><cell> XIX. XX. </cell><cell> Pompeii. </cell></row><row><cell> XXI. </cell><cell> Popular Tumults. </cell></row><row><cell> XXII. XXIII. </cell><cell> British Costume. </cell></row><row><cell> XXIV. XXV. </cell><cell> Bird Miscellanies. </cell></row><row><cell> XXVI. XXVII. </cell><cell> Book of Table-Talk: 2 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> XXVIII. </cell><cell> Industry of the Rhine: Series II.—Manufactures. </cell></row><row><cell> XXIX. </cell><cell> History of Monkeys. </cell></row><row><cell> XXX. XXXI. </cell><cell> Secret Societies. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXII. </cell><cell> Western Coast of Norway. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXIII. XXXIV. </cell><cell> Physical Geography of the Holy Land. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXV. XXXVI. XXXVII. </cell><cell> History of Paris. </cell></row><row><cell> XXXVIII. XXXIX. XL. XLI. XLII. XLIII. </cell><cell> History of the Mammalia. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p10a"/><head >PLAN FOR BINDING KNIGHT'S SHILLING VOLUMES <lb/> FOR ALL READERS.</head><p >
<table><head>TWO VOLUMES IN ONE.</head><row><cell> History of Literature and Learning in England </cell><cell> 6 in 3 </cell></row><row><cell> The Manufactures of Great Britain </cell><cell> 6 in 3 </cell></row><row><cell> Davis's Chinese 3 </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Sketches of China 1 </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> Lord Brougham's Statesmen: 6 </cell><cell> 12 in 6 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ Paley 4 </cell><cell> 12 in 6 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ Instinct 1 </cell><cell> 12 in 6 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ Discourses 1 </cell><cell> 12 in 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Lamb's Tales from Shakspere </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Vieusseux's Bonaparte </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Lost Senses </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Lewes's History of Philosophy </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> The Oregon Territory 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Backwoods of Canada 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Mrs. Jameson's Lives of Painters </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Rambles by Rivers </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> Lord Nugent's Lands, Classical and Sacred </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Fairfax's Tasso </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Old England Novelets </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> Physical Geography (Kitto's Holy Land) </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Insect Architecture </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Mind amongst the Spindles 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Memoirs of a Working Man 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Life of Caxton 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Gresham 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Knight's Capital and Labour 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Varieties 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Monkeys 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Bird Architecture 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Bird Miscellanies </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Flowers and their Associations 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Field, Garden, and Woodland 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Banfield's Agriculture of the Rhine 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Manufactures 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Romance of Travel </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Food of Man </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Racine 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Molière 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> The Cid 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Spanish Drama 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Cabinet Portrait Gallery </cell><cell> 12 in 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Plutarch, vols. 1 and 2 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ vols. 3, 4, and: 5 (among the treble vols.) </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Martineau's Feats on the Fiord 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Billow and Rock 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Lane's Arabian Tales 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Mac Farlane's Popular Customs of Italy 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Philosophy of Health </cell><cell> 4 in 2 </cell></row><row><cell> Settlers and Convicts </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Wornum's History of Painting </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Pompeii </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Planché's British Costume </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Book of Table Talk </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Cabinet History of England </cell><cell> 26 in 13 </cell></row><row><cell> Mammalia </cell><cell> 6 in 3 </cell></row><row><cell> Female Examples—Pursuit of Knowledge </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Chaucer's Canterbury Tales </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Pictures of English Life, Chaucer 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____, Hudibras 1 </cell><cell> 2 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell> 150 in 75 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>THREE VOLUMES IN ONE.</head><row><cell> British Commerce </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Spenser </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Bacon </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Wittich's Physical Geography 2 </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ Travels in Norway 1 </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Pursuit of Knowledge </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Historical Parallels </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Elephant, Horse, and Dog </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Lane's Modern Egyptians </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Mrs. Poole's Englishwoman in Egypt </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Paris and its Historical Scenes </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Plutarch, vols. 3, 4, and 5 </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> _____ vols. 1 and 2 (among the double vols.) </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Secret Societies 2 </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell> Popular Tumults 1 </cell><cell> 3 in 1 </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell> 36 in 12 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >75 Double Volumes</p><p >12 Treble Volumes</p><p >Total 87</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11a"/><head >Knight's pictorial Works.</head><div type="section"><head >THE BEST EDITION OF SHAKSPERE IN ONE VOLUME.</head><p >Price 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, cloth, or in Twelve Shilling Parts, <lb/> THE WORKS OF WILLIAM SHAKSPERE; <lb/> Containing HIS PLAYS AND POEMS, from the Text of the Editions by CHARLES KNIGHT; with Explanatory Notes and Facts connected with his Life and Writings, abridged from ‘William Shakspere, a Biography.’ Illustrated by W. HARVEY.</p></div><div type="section"><head >MUSEUM OF ANIMATED NATURE.</head><p >With 4000 Woodcuts, in Twenty-Seven Shilling parts, or 34<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>, in 2 handsome volumes, cloth, <lb/> THE PICTORIAL MUSEUM OF ANIMATED NATURE.</p><p >The reader, at the very smallest price, is put in possession of, by far, the most extensive collection that has ever been produced of pictorial representations of all the important quadrupeds, birds, fishes, reptiles, and insects which fill the earth; with a corresponding description of the animal, its structure, its habits, its localities, its use; not given in a dry and repulsive form, but with that simplicity which may furnish just conceptions to all, but especially to the young, of the wonders and beauties of God's creation.</p></div><div type="section"><head >GALLERY OF ARTS.</head><p >With about 4000 Engravings, in Twenty-Seven Shilling Parts, <lb/> or 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in 2 handsome volumes, cloth, <lb/> THE PICTORIAL GALLERY OF ARTS.</p><p >Vol. I., USEFUL ARTS; Vol. II., FINE ARTS.</p><p >‘The great purpose which is to be kept in mind, in this and similar works which teach by pictures as well as words, is the expansion of the intellect of all who see and read. What our “PICTORIAL MUSEUM” is to the world of “ANIMATED NATURE” our “PICTORIAL GALLERY” is to the world of “ART.” The “Museum” exhibits the great Author of Good displaying His power and wisdom in the creation of the wonderful varieties of life with which the earth is filled, all His creatures accomplishing the purposes of their being in harmony with the great scheme of His Providence. The “Gallery” exhibits the same benevolent teacher of Man leading him forward from the humblest exercise of his faculties to the most complete development of his intellectual powers; and, through the agency of these powers, enabling him “to subdue the earth,” and elevate himself in the scale of being, by the aid of the accumulated knowledge of society, heaped up for him by the experience of many generations. The one work is a sequel to the other. Each has especial reference to the instruction of the people, particularly the young.’ —<hi rend="italics">Original Prospectus.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >PICTORIAL SUNDAY-BOOK.</head><p >With 1500 Woodcuts and 13 Coloured Maps, forming a SCRIPTURE ATLAS; price 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in Parts, <lb/> or in handsome cloth, 24<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> THE PICTORIAL SUNDAY-BOOK.</p><p >By J. KITTO, Editor of the Pictorial Bible.</p><p >The publication now submitted to Christian families is intended to present, at the very cheapest rate, a series of engravings illustrative of the Bible History, the Prophecies, the Psalms, the Life of Our Saviour, and the Acts of his Apostles; exhibiting the Scenes of the great Events recorded in Scripture, the Customs of the Jews, the Natural History of the Holy Land, and the Antiquities which throw a light upon the Sacred Writings, with a body of Scriptural Narrative and Explanation, continuing from number to number; each number forming, as it is judged, a fitting portion for a Sunday's leisure.</p><p >THE SCRIPTURE ATLAS, with the Geography of the Holy Land, is sold separately.</p><p >Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> sewed, or 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p12"/><head >LIFE OF OUR SAVIOUR.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">In handsome cloth, gilt edges, price 7s. 6d.,</hi>
<lb/> A PICTORIAL LIFE OF OUR SAVIOUR.</p><p >By. J. KITTO, Editor of the Pictorial Bible.</p></div><div type="section"><head >OLD ENGLAND'S WORTHIES.</head><p >Price 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in Parts, or 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in handsome cloth.</p><p >OLD ENGLAND'S WORTHIES.</p><p >A Gallery of 72 Portraits on Steel, and 12 splendid Illuminated Engravings of some remarkable place or monument associated with the life of some one of ‘OLD ENGLAND'S WORTHIES,’ arranged in a chronological order, thus enabling the reader to become familiar with the greatest names of his countrymen in illustrative succession.</p></div><div type="section"><head >A PICTORIAL COMPANION AND KEY TO EVERY HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</head><p >With 3000 Woodcuts and 24 Coloured Engravings, price 36<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in Twenty-four Parts, or 2 handsome <lb/> volumes, cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> OLD ENGLAND; <lb/> A PICTORIAL MUSEUM OF NATIONAL ANTIQUITIES.</p><p >This Work opens to all ranks, at the cheapest rate, a view of the REGAL, ECCLESIASTICAL, RARONJAI, MUNICIPAL, and POPULAR ANTIQUITIES of England, given in a chronological order; and thus the work is a Companion and a Key to every English History. The Engravings embrace the most remarkable of our buildings from the earliest times—DRUIDICAL REMAINS, CATHEDRALS, ABBEYS, CHURCHES, COLLEGES, CASTLES, CIVIC HALLS, MANSIONS, SEPULCHRAL MONUMENTS of our Princes and Nobles, portraits of British Worthies and representations of localities associated with their names, ancient Pictures and Illuminations of Historical Events, the Great Seals and Arms of the Monarchy, Coins and Medals, Autographs; with the fullest pictorial indications of the INDUSTRY, the ARTS, the SPORTS, the DRESSES, and the DAILY LIFE of the People.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOUTH'S HINTS ON EMERGENCIES.</head><p >Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> HOUSEHOLD SURGERY; <lb/> OR, <lb/> HINTS ON EMERGENCIES.</p><p >By JOHN F. SOUTH, Surgeon to St. Thomas's Hospital.</p><p >The object of this Work is to afford some useful hints as to the means which people have in their own power to employ when accidents happen which require immediate attention and no medical man is at hand, and often cannot be obtained for hours. Such cases are neither few nor unimportant, and many serious consequences—nay, even death—may be prevented if a judicious person, having been put on the track, make use of the simple remedies almost every house affords.</p><p >“We have seldom seen a book of wider or more sound practical utility than this unpretending little volume. We can conscientiously recommend Mr. South's Manual to the notice of the public. It is not a class-book; IT IS EVERYBODY'S BOOK; and above all, travellers, emigrants, and residents in remote country places should not fail to provide themselves with it.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p><closer >C. COX, 12, KING WILLIAM STREET, STRAND.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13b"/><head >OPINIONS OF THE PRESS <lb/> OF <lb/> MOSES AND SON'S ATTIRE.</head><p >“We cannot allude to the fashions of the present season without making special mention of the name of MOSES &amp; SON. Most assuredly these famous merchant-tailors will add to their already great celebrity by the stock of well designed dress, which is now on sale at their immense emporium in the city, and at their branch houses in Bradford and Sheffield.”—<hi rend="italics">Gentleman's Journal.</hi></p><p >“The votaries of fashion should propose a vote of thanks to Messrs. MOSES &amp; SON for the beautiful improvements brought to bear in attire for the present summer months; which improvements, in our opinion, have no equal in the trade.”—<hi rend="italics">Wardrobe News.</hi></p><p >“Without lending ourselves to ‘puff paragraphing’ (so to speak), we may honestly recommend the elegant summer overcoats, and other attire, of the Messrs. MOSES to all lovers of gentility and superiority in dress.”—<hi rend="italics">Tasty Times.</hi></p><p >“The Messrs. MOSES seem determined to captivate persons of taste by the beautiful DRESS BOOTS and SHOES, HATS, HOSIERY, &amp;c.: we wish the proprietors encouragement, so justly deserved by their present stock.”—<hi rend="italics">Billy Button's Note Book.</hi></p><p >“If quality and economy are recommendations in the tailoring trade, then, undoubtedly, Messrs, MOSES &amp; SON have these recommendations in an eminent degree.”—<hi rend="italics">Guide to Gentility.</hi></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><head>Ready Made.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Spring and Summer Wrappers, from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Bulwer, paeha, Paletot, and every description of Light Overcoat from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture, and handsomely trimmed from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Cloth Overcoats lined with Silk from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Cloth Overcoats superior quality — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Jean and Holland Blouses — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 9 </cell></row><row><cell> Fancy Victoria Blouses — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Tweed Blouses — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Dress Coats — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Frock Coats — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Spring and Summer Trousers — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Doeskin and Buckskin Trousers — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Spring and Summer Vests, in every variety— </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black and Figured Satin Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black superior quality — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> White Marcella Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Cloth Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Hussar and Tunic Suits — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Spring and Summer Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Fishing Coats, in every variety — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Made to Measure.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Paletots, made from a variety of materials, fitted for Summer wear from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Paletots, made from a variety of materials, in every style, elegantly trimmed, from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Cloth in every style, of a light texture — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Cloth in every style, lined with Silk — </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Cloth Dress Coat — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Dress Coat for </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Frock Dress Coat from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Dress Coat for </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Fancy Doeskin Trousers from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Doeskin Trousers — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Doeskin Trousers — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Cloth Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Cloth Vests for </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Splendid Satin Cloth Vests from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Satin Cloth Vests for </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Hussar and Tunic Suits — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Tunic Suits — </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Men's White Marcella Vests — </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Fishing Coats, in endless variety, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> <hi rend="italics">6d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Elegant Dressing Robes, in great variety, from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >LIVERIES OF ALL KINDS AT THE SHORTEST NOTICE.</p><p >MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Clothes complete for £1 10s.</hi></p><p >The New Book, entitled “The Great Fact,” with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >NOTICE.—The Shawl and Parasol Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p><p >OBSERVE.—Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >E. MOSES &amp; SON,</head><p >TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p><p >ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p><p >CAUTION.—E MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike flasehood of being connected with them, or it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p><p >TAKE NOTICE.—This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14b"/><head >THE NICOLL, RECENT STREET, <lb/> AND 22, CORNHILL, LONDON.</head><p >BESIDES the above Patented Article of Dress (called THE NICOLL), there is another Novelty introduced for this Season, which is, however, Registered under the name of NICOLL'S MORNING COAT, it being especially intended for morning wear, in riding or walking exercise, when it necessarily avoids the stiff formality to be observed in the cut and form of the dress-coat. The price is TWO GUINEAS.</p><p >The premises (extending from 114 to 120, Regent Street), as illuminated in honour of <lb/> Her Majesty's and the Prince's Birthdays.</p><p >THE REGISTERED PALETOT is now ready for the Spring Months, with all the new and patented improvements, included in the moderate price of TWO GUINEAS. Thus it deservedly bears the name of being not only the most fashionable, but also the cheapest and most durable garment ever offered to the public; the intrinsic value of the material known as NICOLLIAN, or LLAMA CLOTH, being, within the last few months, much enhanced; the same durability being retained, with an increased fineness and beauty in appearance. It can be seen, ready for immediate wear, in every size, at the Patentees' Warerooms.</p><closer >114, 116, &amp; 120, REGENT STREET, <lb/> OR <lb/> 22, CORNHILL, FACING ROYAL EXCHANGE.</closer><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer></div></back></text></TEI>