<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XI:</emph>
 Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.  150K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XI</title><author>Charles  Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> 47 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LONDON:BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher><date>1850</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p/></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords scheme="LCSH"><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-11-18"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-10-04">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_verso_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"> No.  XI. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate> MARCH.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>Which He never meant to be Published on any Account. </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docAuthor><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:—J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN DUBLIN.
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><epigraph ><p>Trouser straps superseded by the DOUDNEY SPRING. 17, Old Bond Street, and 49, Lombard Street.</p></epigraph><head >FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS.</head><p >DOUDNEYS <lb/> Waterproofers, Habit Makers, and Tailors <lb/> TO QUEEN VICTORIA, QUEEN ADELAIDE, <lb/> H.R.H. Prince Albert, H.R.H. The Duchess of Kent, <lb/> KING LOUIS PHILIPPE, <lb/> And the ROYAL FAMILIES of ENGLAND and FRANCE.</p><p >The DOUDNEYS motto is “none but Good Articles can be cheap,” and with this ever in view, they have, by increasing efforts, established a Ready Money business of great extent among the strong holds of the old fashioned usurious Credit System. As to the character, and recommendatory influence of the approbation which has been bestowed upon their endeavours; let their Five Royal Appointments and their Patronage Book filled with the Royal, Illustrious, and Noble names of their customers, testify.</p><p >The New Patterns for Spring and Summer wear are now ready for inspection at the Old Prices, so famous in seasons past, viz. :—Summer Waistcoats 7s. each, or 3 for 20s.—Summer Trousers 10s. 6d. per pair, or 3 for 30<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.—Summer Coats, the beautiful light material 10s. 6d.—21s. and 30s.</p><p >The Queens Victoria and Adelaide, and the Royal and Noble Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge, Sutherland and Bucoleuch, constantly wear Doudney's elegant Registered Cloak, in a variety of Waterproof, materials for Winter Wraps and the Promenade.—“Every Lady should see these graceful Garments.” <hi rend="italics">(Vide Morning Post, September 26th.)</hi> They surpass all others for School Cloaks for the sons and daughters.</p><p >For Gentlemen.—The Royal Registered Cloak, as made for H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, the Nobility, the Army, and Navy, and all who study comfort, coupled with a truly Gentlemanly exterior. These cloaks are pronounced by those who understand the matter, “The most sensible Garment ever introduced,” at prices to suit all customers from the Superb down to the useful Guinea Cloak.</p><p >The New Patent Belt for Riding or general exercise, the only really effectual protection against rupture; the support commencing at the <hi rend="italics">bottom edge</hi> of the belt, and producing an uniform upward pressure. They may be enlarged or tightened to the extent of six inches at pleasure, and never produce indigestion either in Ladies or Gentlemen. They are attached to Drawers with excellent effect. The most eminent of the Faculty are recommending these in preference to all others.</p><p >LIVERIES. Three Guineas the Plain Suit of Best Quality. <hi rend="italics">Ready Money does it!!!</hi> and a very extensive practice among families of first distinction insures satisfactory results.</p><p >Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria and the Ladies of the Court. A Superfine Cloth Habit for 4 Guineas.</p><p >Waterproof Irish Poplin. The DOUDNEYS are the sole manufacturers of this beautiful article to HER MAJESTY AND THE PRINCE CONSORT. Gentlemen's Coats, Ladies Cloaks, and lengths for Dresses can be obtained only at their Establishment.</p><p >Country Gentlemen wishing to be Respectably Dressed at low Prices should send for a Book of detail, self-measurement and all the System of business, or if 3 or 4 Gentlemen unite, a Traveller will wait upon them.</p><closer >17, OLD BOND ST., 25, BURLINGTON ARCADE AND 49. LOMBARD STREET—Established 1784.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. XI.— MARCH, 1850.</opener><head >COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head><div type="section"><head >NEW WORK ON GARDENING AND BOTANY.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., No. I. of</hi> <lb/> PAXTON'S FLOWER GARDEN, <lb/> EDITED BY DR. LINDLEY AND JOSEPH PAXTON.</p><p >AND <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>I:LLUSTRATED</sic><corr>ILLUSTRATED</corr></choice> BY HIGHLY FINISHED PLATES AND WOODCUTS.</p><p >This Work, for which Monsieur CONSTANS, a French Botanical Draughtsman of great taste and skill, and a pupil of Mons. Decaisne, has been expressly engaged, will be confined to the proper business of an illustrated book, namely the representation and description of all new plants which may appear in gardens. The species which are of most importance will be illustrated by coloured plates, one species or genus only to a plate, with a leaf or more of letter-press, explaining the principal scientific and horticultural facts which belong to each plant. The species of less importance will be treated of more briefly, and will be illustrated when necessary by copious woodcuts and vignettes. The object, in short, will be to combine Scientific Botany with Gardening, and exact delineations of plants with pictorial effect. It is believed that by such means this periodical will not only be indispensable to the BOTANIST and GARDENER, but be also a mine of invaluable hints by which the ARTIST and MANUFACTURER will be able to profit.</p><p >It is not intended to admit any other kind of matter than such as is now described. All special treatises on cultivation, and all disquisitions respecting subjects incidental to gardening will be transferred to the <hi rend="italics">Gardeners' Chronicle</hi> and similar periodicals, in which there is ample space for such discussions, and to which they have now become better adapted than to a pictorial work.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >New and Enlarged Edition of Paxton's Botanical <lb/> Dictionary.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">In Crown octavo, price</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >PAXTON'S BOTANICAL DICTIONARY.</p><p >A NEW EDITION, CORRECTED TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p><p >COMPRISING THE NAMES, HISTORY, AND CULTURE OF ALL PLANTS KNOWN IN BRITAIN, WITH A FULL <lb/> EXPLANATION OF TECHNICAL TERMS.</p><p >[For the convenience of persons possessing the First Edition, the SUPPLEMENT, containing all the New <lb/> Plants since its appearance, is published separately, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s., handsomely bound in cloth, with numerous Woodcuts representing the Processes of Grafting,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Budding, Layering, &amp;c.</hi></opener><head >THE <lb/> LADIES' COMPANION TO THE FLOWER GARDEN.</head><p >BEING AN ALPHABETICAL ARRANGEMENT OF ALL THE ORNAMENTAL PLANTS <lb/> GROWN IN GARDENS AND SHRUBBERIES; WITH FULL DIRECTIONS FOR THEIR CULTURE.</p><p >BY MRS. LOUDON.</p><p >THE FIFTH EDITION, CORRECTED TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p><closer >London: Published (for the Proprietor) by BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, II, Bouvetis Street.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >SMITH, ELDER, &amp; Co.'s NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >Now ready.</p><p >WOMAN IN FRANCE during the <lb/> 18th Century.</p><p >BY JULIA KAVANAGH.</p><p >In 2 vols, post 8vo, with Eight Portraits of remarkable French Women, price 24s., elegantly bound in embossed cloth.</p><p >THE SEVEN LAMPS OF ARCHITECTURE.</p><p >BY JOHN RUSKIN, Author of “Modern <lb/> Painters.”</p><p >1 vol. imp. 8vo, with Fourteen Etchings by the Author. Price One Guinea, bound in embossed cloth, with top edge gilt.</p><p >“This eloquent and deeply-instructive volume is a book for amateurs to read; for it will make the thoughtless thoughtful, and suggest and strengthen important principles to all.”—<hi rend="italics">Ecclesiologist.</hi></p><p >“The politician, the moralist, the divine, will find in it ample store of instructive matter, as well as the artist.”—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p><p >“A lively, poetical, and thoughtful book; rich in refined criticism and glowing eloquence.”—<hi rend="italics">Fraser's Magazine.</hi></p><p >“From the series of works upon which Mr. Ruskin is engaged, we can scarcely hope too much for art. They are amongst the books that <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be read.”—<hi rend="italics">British Quarterly Review.</hi></p><p >MODERN PAINTERS.</p><p >BY A GRADUATE OF OXFORD.</p><p >Fourth Edition, 2 vols. imp. 8vo, £1 8s. 6d.</p><p >THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF <lb/> LEIGH HUNT.</p><p >In 3 vols., post 8vo, with Portrait.</p><p >In May,</p><p >THE TOWN.</p><p >BY LEIGH HUNT.</p><p >2 vols. post 8vo, with Forty-five Illustrations, price <lb/> 24s. cloth.</p><p >“We will allow no higher enjoyment for a rational Englishman than to stroll leisurely through this marvellous town arm-in-arm with Mr. Leigh Hunt. He gives us the outpourings of a mind enriched with the most agreeable knowledge. There is not a page of this book which does not glow with interest.”—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p><p >SHIRLEY: a Tale.</p><p >BY CURRER BELL, <lb/> Author of “Jane Eyre.”</p><p >3 vols. post 8vo, £1 11s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >“ ‘Shirley’ is an admirable book; genuine English in the independence and uprightness of the tone of thought, in the purity of heart and feeling which pervade it. It is a tale of passion and character, and a veritable triumph of psychology.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“ ‘Shirley’ is very clever. Gems of rare thought and glorious passion shine here and there throughout the volumes.”—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p><p >“The book possesses deep interest, and an irresistible grasp of reality. There are scenes which, for strength and delicacy of emotion, are not transcended in the range of English fiction.”—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p><p >“We like the book as a whole, we like its spirit. We sympathise with the author's general charity, with her special love for the old country, the old church, and the Old Duke; we kindle with her fervid bursts of eloquence, and recognise the truth of her pictures from life.”—<hi rend="italics">Fraser's Magazine.</hi></p><p >JANE EYRE: an Autobiography.</p><p >BY CURRER BELL.</p><p >Third Edition, with Preface by the Aut or, 3 vols. post 8vo.</p><closer >LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, &amp; CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">This day is Published, Price One Shilling,</hi></opener><head >LATTER DAY PAMPHLETS. No. II.</head><p >EDITED BY THOMAS CARLYLE.</p><p >“MODEL PRISONS.”</p><closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Will be published during March, price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >THE HORSE GUARDS,</head><p >BY THE TWO MOUNTED SENTRIES.</p><p >EMBELLISHED WITH TWELVE COLOURED ILLUSTRATIONS.</p><p >“Thus saith the Duke—thus hath the Duke inferred.”</p><closer >J. &amp; D. A. DARLING, 126, BISHOPSGATE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><head >Works by Mr. Charles Dickens.</head><p >I. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Complete in One thick Volume 8vo, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s. in cloth, or</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. half-bound.</hi></p><p >DOMBEY AND SON.</p><p >WITH FORTY ILLUSTRATIONS ON STEEL, BY H. K. BROWNE.</p><p >II. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In One Volume demy 8vo, price</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s., uniform with “The Pickwick Papers.”</hi></p><p >THE LIFE &amp; ADVENTURES OF OLIVER TWIST.</p><p >This Edition has been carefully corrected by the Author throughout, and contains the whole of the <lb/> Original Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p><p >III. <lb/> PICTURES FROM ITALY.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Second Edition. Fcp.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><div type="advertisement"><head >MR. DICKENS'S CHRISTMAS BOOKS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo. Price 5s. each, bound in cloth, with gilt edges.</hi></p><p >THE ILLUSTRATIONS BY D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, <lb/> JOHN TENNIEL, AND RICHARD DOYLE.</p><list  type="simple"><item>A Christmas Carol. In Prose.</item><item>The Chimes. A Goblin Story of some Bells that rang an Old Year Out, and a New Year In.</item><item>The Battle of Life. A Love Story.</item><item>The Cricket on the Hearth. A Fairy Tale of Home.</item><item>The Haunted Man and the Ghost's Bargain.</item></list></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW WORK BY MR. W. M. THACKERAY.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. (to be completed in Two Volumes,) No.</hi> 14, <hi rend="italics">of</hi> <lb/> PENDENNIS.</p><p >WITH ILLUSTRATIONS ON STEEL AND WOOD BY THE AUTHOR.</p><p >Volume the First, price 13s., in cloth, is now ready.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Works by DR. LINDLEY.</head><p >SCHOOL BOTANY; or, THE RUDIMENTS OF BOTANICAL SCIENCE. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> half-bound.</p><p >ELEMENTS OF BOTANY (THE), STRUCTURAL AND PHYSIOLOGICAL, with a Copious Glossary of Terms. Fifth Edition. 8vo. Price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">N.B.—The Glossary may be had separately, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >VEGETABLE KINGDOM (THE); or, THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS. Illustrated upon the Natural System. Second Edition, with Additional Genera. Price 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p><p >MEDICAL AND OECONOMICAL BOTANY; completing the Elements of Botany, Structural, Physiological, and Medical. 8vo. Price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MACREADY'S EDITION OF POPE.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">In Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</p><p >REVISED AND ARRANGED EXPRESSLY FOR YOUNG PERSONS AND SCHOOLS.</p><p >BY W. C. MACREADY.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><opener >13, Great Marlborough Street.</opener><head >MR. COLBURN'S NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >I. <lb/> MEMOIRS of a HUNGARIAN LADY.</p><p >By THERESA PULSZKY; with an Historical Introduction, by FRANCIS PULSZKY, late Under Secretary of State to the Emperor Ferdinand and King of Hungary. 2 vols., 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> bound.</p><p >II. <lb/> PRIDE AND IRRESOLUTION.</p><p >By the author of “The Discipline of Life.” 3 vols.</p><p >“ ‘The Discipline of Life’ is, we believe, the first production of Lady Emily Ponsonby. It cannot fail to place the authoress in the first rank of female novelists.”—<hi rend="italics">Britannis.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> VOL. II. of EVELYN'S DIARY AND <lb/> CORRESPONDENCE.</p><p >New, Revised, and Cheaper Edition, with numerous additional Notes, to be completed in 4 vols, price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, bound, uniform with the new edition of Pepys' Diary.</p><p >IV. <lb/> THE SCOTTISH CAVALIER.</p><p >An Historical Romance. By JAMES GRANT, ESQ., author of “The Romance of War; or, the Gordon Highlanders,” “Adventures of Kirkaldy of Grange,” &amp;c., 3 vols.</p><p >V. <lb/> ADVENTURES of a GOLD FINDER.</p><p >Written by himself. 3 vols.</p><p >“What is here? <lb/> Gold?—yellow, glittering, precious gold?”</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Timon of Athens.</hi></p><p >VI. <lb/> BURKE'S LANDED GENTRY for 1850.</p><p >Corrected to the Present Time, and comprising particulars of upwards of 100,000 persons. Complete in 2 vols., royal 8vo, (equal to 30 ordinary volumes) price only £2 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> bound.</p><p >VII. <lb/> THE PETREL, a TALE of the SEA.</p><p >By a NAVAL OFFICER. 3 vols.</p><p >“The author of this interesting work is, we believe, Admiral Fisher, who commanded at the Blockade of Alexandria in 1840. By his skill in depicting Life on the Ocean, he will doubt not, supply the place in nautical literature, vacant by the death of the lamented Capt. Marryat.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >VIII. <lb/> SECOND EDITION OF <lb/> PASSAGES IN THE LIFE OF MRS. <lb/> MARGARET MAITLAND <lb/> OF SUNNY SIDE.</p><p >Written by Herself. 3 vols.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The following are Just Ready:—</hi></p><p >I. <lb/> REGINALD HASTINGS.</p><p >A Tale of the Troubles in 16—. By ELIOT WARBURTON, ESQ., author of “The Crescent and the Cross,” &amp;c. 3 vols.</p><p >II. <lb/> HISTORIC SCENES.</p><p >BY AGNES STRICKLAND, authoress of “Lives of the Queens of England.” 1 vol., post 8vo, elegantly bound, with Portrait of the Author.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHEAP EDITION of Mr. AINSWORTH'S WORKS.</head><p >Just Published, <lb/> THE MISER'S DAUGHTER.</p><p >WITH A PORTRAIT OF THE AUTHOR BY DANIEL MACLISE R.A.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Complete, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. boards, or</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d, cloth.</hi></p><p >NOW READY, <lb/> CRICHTON. ROOKWOOD <lb/> AND <lb/> WINDSOR CASTLE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Complete, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. each, boards, or</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth.</hi></p><p >ON THE 9TH OF MARCH WILL BE PUBLISHED, <lb/> THE TOWER OF LONDON.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Vol. I., price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. bound, or</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth.</hi></p><p >The Second Volume, completing the work, will be published on the 20th March.</p><closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer><trailer ><hi rend="italics">Sold by all Booksellers, and at all Railway Stations.</hi></trailer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><head >Warren's Sketches of Character.</head><p >MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HANDWRITING.</p><p >Specimens of Writing, with an enclosure of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's age to be addressed as above.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PATENT LEVER COPYING PRESSES,</head><p >AT CONSIDERABLY REDUCED PRICES.</p><p >Lever Press.</p><p >Screw Press.</p><p >First Quality Screw.</p><p >Wrot. Iron Beam Screw.</p><p >These Presses, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged if any fault is discovered.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press, wrt.iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell></row><row><cell> Large 4to </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell></row><row><cell> Post Folio </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Copying Paper, very best quality, 2 reams for 17s.—5 reams for 37s. 6d.—10 reams for 65s.—Ditto French ditto, 2 reams for 16s.—5 reams for 35s.—10 reams for 60s. Copying Ink, per quart, 3s.; per dozen quarts, 30s.</p><closer >WATERLOW AND SONS, <lb/> WHOLESALE &amp; RETAIL MANUFACTURING STATIONERS, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, AND 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >AN EXCELLENT cure of a DISORDER IN THE STOMACH effected by HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.—</head><p >A Lady, an intimate friend of the family of General Rosas, Governor of the Republic of La Plata, declares that she was lately cured of a disorder in the stomach, and restored to perfect health, by the use of this admirable remedy. She had consulted the most eminent physicians in the country, but had not been able to obtain any relief from the complaint that was killing her by inches until she took Holloway's Pills. John Eastman, Esq., an eminent merchant of Buenos Ayres, communicated these particulars to Professor HOLLOWAY in a letter dated the 4th September, 1840.—Sold by all druggists, and at Professor HOLLOWAY's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p >and all other Medicines of a nauseous character, may now he taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p><p >The recent discovery that the low priced Gelatine Capsules contain a compound of train and other oils, and in many cases no Copaiba whatever, renders it important that the public should be made aware that the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES are <hi rend="italics">guaranteed</hi> to contain <hi rend="italics">genuine Copaiba only.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.—</head><p >A CERTAIN REMEDY for disorders of the Pulmonary Organs—in Difficulty of Breathing—in Redundancy of Phlegm—in Incipient Consumption (of which Cough is the most positive indication)—they are of unerring efficacy. In Asthma and in Winter Cough, they have never been known to fail.—Prepared and sold in boxes, 1s. 1½d., and tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATINO, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Churchyard, London. Sold retail by all druggists.</p><div type="section"><head >TESTIMONIAL.</head><p >“Church-street, Folkestone, Nov. 22nd, 1848.</p><p >“SIR,—Having been troubled with a very bad cough for the last eight months, I applied to Mr. Hammon, Chemist, of this town, for some relief; he recommended me your “Cough Lozenges,” which I am happy to say cured me in a week. I beg most cordially to recommend them, and beg you will not hesitate to make this letter public: such a valuable remedy cannot be too highly recommended.—I have the honour to be, Sir, your obedient humble servant, JOHN HILL, Bart.</p><p >“To Mr. Keating.”</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET of BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature.—“Robert Shaw, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Prices 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ARROWSMITH'S NEW PATENT.—</head><p >In consequence of the impossibility of executing all the demands last season for ARROWSMITH'S PATENT CURTAINS, (rich, costly, and elegant at 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, such as manufactured for Her Majesty, the King of Belgium, &amp;c.,) orders are solicited immediately, to prevent disappointment, at ARROWSMITH'S, (only) Her Majesty's Upholsterers, 80, New Bond-street. Houses elegantly decorated and furnished throughout with all the novelties of the season, at moderate prices.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >For Purifying the Blood and Strength- <lb/> ening the Digestive Organs.</head><p >FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well-known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.—Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PRICE ONE FLORIN EACH.</head><p >MILTON'S HAIR: LUBRICANT.—A new and elegant preparation for the Hair, compounded on rational principles, and which once used will at once supersede the filthy stuff sold as Bears' Grease, Circassian Cream, or various oils with nonsensical names, which possess not the slightest power to render a benefit.</p><p >MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT, used as directed in a Treatise on the Hair sold with each pot, will soon render the Hair clean, lustrous, and curly. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Medicine Vendors in town and country. Wholesale London Agents—Messrs. BARCLAY &amp; SONS, Farringdon-street; EDWARDS, St. Paul's Churchyard; SUTTON &amp; Co., Bow Churchyard; SANGAR, 151, Oxford-street; and HANNAY &amp; Co., Oxford-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><opener >Under Royal Patronage.<lb/>PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES, AND INSTANT RELIEF <lb/> AND A RAPID CURE OF ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, <lb/> COLDS, AND ALL DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS, <lb/> ARE INSURED BY</opener><head >DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated Testimonials, may be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">had from every Agent.</hi></p><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >They have a pleasant taste. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per box.</p><p >AGENTS: DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors.</p><p >Also, Protected by Royal Letters Patent.</p><p >DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS.</p><p >HAVE NO TASTE OF MEDICINE, and are the only remedy recommended to be taken by Ladies. They fortify the constitution at all periods of life, and in all Nervous Affections act like a Charm. They remove Heaviness, Fatigue on Slight Exertion, Palpitation of the Heart, Lowness of Spirits, Weakness, and Allay Pain.</p><p >They create Appetite, and remove Indigestion, Heart-burn, Wind, Head-aches, Giddiness, &amp;c.</p><p >In Hysterical Diseases, a proper perseverance in the use of this Medicine will be found to effect a Cure after all other means have failed.</p><p >Full Directions are given with every box.</p><p >NOTE.—These Wafers do not contain any Mineral, and may be taken either dissolved in water, or whole.</p><p >Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per Box.</p><p >The 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Boxes contain nearly three of the small size, and the 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Boxes five of those at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><closer >BEWARE OF IMITATIONS.—IMITATIONS IN THE FORM OF PILLS, &amp;c.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head><p >ENGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.—Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fall to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p><closer >21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >PARASOLS.</head><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER, <lb/> Will, on the 1st of March, have the honour of submitting to the Nobility, Gentry, and the Public in general an entirely new Silk Parasol. It will be perfectly plain, and much larger than those worn last year, and, instead of being fringed as formerly, it will be finished in a peculiar style at once novel and elegant. These Parasols will be extremely light, and very moderate in price.</p><p >W. and J. SANGSTER are making up an extensive assortment of the Swiss Parasols, which were so much worn last year, especially at the sea side; upwards of 30,000 having been sold in the course of the season.</p><p >Their stock will also comprise every variety of Carriage and other Parasols. They trust the quality and price of these goods will secure to them a continuance of the patronage with which they have been so long honoured, for an article forming in Summer so prominent a feature in a Lady's Toilet, in the selection of which her taste is so conspicuously displayed.</p><closer >140, Regent-street; 94, Fleet-street; 75, Cheapside; <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE INVISIBLE VENTILATING HEADS OF HAIR.</head><p >
<table><head>ROSS &amp; SONS' METHOD OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the Head </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From Ear to Ear </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From Forehead to Poll </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >These Inimitable works of art, for both Ladies and Gentlemen, from One Guinea-and-a-half.</p><closer >Address, ROSS &amp; SONS, 119 and 120, Bishops-gate Street, London.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><p >KIRBY, BEARD &amp; CO'S <lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES, <lb/> &amp; NE PLUS ULTRA PINS, <lb/> WITH PERFECT SOLID HEADS.</p><p >Sold by every Draper, &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">My Aunt astonishes me.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Mr. Peggotty and Mr. Steerforth.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pv"/><opener >“Familiar in their Mouths as HOUSEHOLD WORDS.”<lb/><hi rend="italics">Shakspeare.</hi><lb/>On SATURDAY, MARCH 30, will be published, price Twopence, or stamped for post, Threepence, (also in Monthly Parts.)<lb/>No. I. OF</opener><head >HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A Weekly Journal.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND ENTERTAINMENT <lb/> OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS.</p><p >CONDUCTED BY <lb/> CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >LONDON: <lb/> OFFICE, 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH, <lb/> (Where all communications to the Editor must be addressed.)</p><p ><hi rend="italics">And Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen, and at all Railway Stations.</hi></p><closer >Bradbury &amp; Evans, Printers, Whitefriars.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="narrative"><pb  xml:id="p321"/><head >[THE 

<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXII. <lb/> THE BEGINNING OF A LONG JOURNEY.</head><p >WHAT is natural in me, is natural in many other men, I infer, and so I am not afraid to write that I never had loved Steerforth better than when the ties that bound me to him were broken. In the keen distress of the discovery of his unworthiness, I thought more of all that was brilliant in him, I softened more towards all that was good in him, I did more justice to the qualities that might have made him a man of a noble nature and a great name, than ever I had done in the height of my devotion to him. Deeply as I felt my own unconscious part in his pollution of an honest home, I believe that if I had been brought face to face with him, I could not have uttered one reproach. I should have loved him so well still—though he fascinated me no longer—I should have held in so much tenderness the memory of my affection for him, that I think I should have been as weak as a spirit-wounded child, in all but the entertainment of a thought that we could ever be re-united. That thought I never had. I felt, as he had felt, that all was at an end between us. What his remembrances of me were, I have never known—they were light enough, perhaps, and easily dismissed—but mine of him were as the remembrances of a cherished friend, who was dead.</p><p >Yes, Steerforth, long removed from the scenes of this poor history! My sorrow may bear involuntary witness against you at the Judgment Throne; but my angry thoughts or my reproaches never will, I know!</p><p >The news of what had happened soon spread through the town; insomuch that as I passed along the streets next morning, I overheard the people speaking of it at their doors. Many were hard upon her, some few were hard upon him, but towards her second father and her lover there was but one sentiment. Among all kinds of people a respect for them in their distress prevailed, which was full of gentleness and delicacy. The seafaring men kept apart, when those two were seen early, walking with slow steps on the beach; and stood in knots, talking compassionately among themselves.</p><p >It was on the beach, close down by the sea, that I found them. It would have been easy to perceive that they had not slept all last night, even if Peggotty had failed to tell me of their still sitting just as I left them, when it was broad day. They looked worn; and I thought Mr. Peggotty's head was bowed in one night more than in all the years I had known him. But they were both as grave and steady as the sea itself: then lying beneath a dark sky, waveless—yet with a heavy roll upon it, as if it breathed in its rest—and touched, on the horizon, with a strip of silvery light from the unseen sun.</p><p >“We have had a mort of talk, sir,” said Mr. Peggotty to me, when we
<pb xml:id="p322"/>
had all three walked a little while in silence, “of what we ought and doen't ought to do. But we see our course now.”</p><p >I happened to glance at Ham, then looking out to sea upon the distant light, and a frightful thought came into my mind—not that his face was angry, for it was not; I recal nothing but an expression of stern determination in it—that if ever he encountered Steerforth, he would kill him.</p><p >“My dooty here, sir,” said Mr. Peggotty, “is done. I'm a going to seek my—” he stopped, and went on in a firmer voice: “I'm a going to seek her. That's my dooty evermore.”</p><p >He shook his head when I asked him where he would seek her, and inquired if I were going to London to-morrow? I told him I had not gone to-day, fearing to lose the chance of being of any service to him; but that I was ready to go when he would.</p><p >“I'll go along with you, sir,” he rejoined, “if you're agreeable, to-morrow.”</p><p >We walked again, for a while, in silence.</p><p >“Ham,” he presently resumed, “he'll hold to his present work, and go and live along with my sister. The old boat yonder—”</p><p >“Will you desert the old boat, Mr. Peggotty?” I gently interposed.</p><p >“My station, Mas'r Davy,” he returned, “ain't there no longer; and if ever a boat foundered, since there was darkness on the face of the deep, that one's gone down. But no, sir, no; I doen't mean as it should be deserted. Fur from that.”</p><p >We walked again for a while, as before, until he explained:</p><p >“My wishes is, sir, as it shall look, day and night, winter and summer, as it has always looked, since she first know'd it. If ever she should come a wandering back, I wouldn't have the old place seem to cast her off, you understand, but seem to tempt her to draw nigher to 't, and to peep in, maybe, like a ghost, out of the wind and rain, through the old winder at the old seat by the fire. Then, maybe, Mas'r Davy, seein' none but Missis Gummidge there, she might take heart to creep in, trembling; and might come to be laid down in her old bed, and rest her weary head where it was once so gay.”</p><p >I could not speak to him in reply, though I tried.</p><p >“Every night,” said Mr. Peggotty, “as reg'lar as the night comes, the candle must be stood in its old pane of glass, that if ever she should see it, it may seem to say ‘Come back, my child, come back!’ If ever there's a knock, Ham (partic'ler a soft knock), arter dark, at your aunt's door, doen't you go nigh it. Let it be her—not you—that sees my fallen child!”</p><p >He walked a little in front of us, and kept before us for some minutes. During this interval, I glanced at Ham again, and observing the same expression on his face, and his eyes still directed to the distant light, I touched his arm.</p><p >Twice I called him by his name, in the tone in which I might have tried to rouse a sleeper, before he heeded me. When I at last inquired on what his thoughts were so bent, he replied:</p><p >“On what's afore me, Mas'r Davy; and over you.”</p><p >“On the life before you, do you mean?” He had pointed confusedly at to sea.</p><pb  xml:id="p323"/><p >“Ay, Mas'r Davy. I doen't rightly know how 'tis, but from over von there seemed to me to come—the end of it like;” looking at me as if he were waking, but with the same determined face.</p><p >“What end?” I asked, possessed by my former fear.</p><p >“I doen't know,” he said thoughtfully; “I was calling to mind that the beginning of it all did take place here—and then the end come. But it's gone! Mas'r Davy,” he added; answering, as I think, my look; “you han't no call to be afeerd of me: but I'm kiender muddled; I doen't fare to feel no matters,”—which was as much as to say that he was not himself, and quite confounded.</p><p >Mr. Peggotty stopping for us to join him: we did so, and said no more. The remembrance of this, in connexion with my former thought, however, haunted me at intervals, even until the inexorable end came at its appointed time.</p><p >We insensibly approached the old boat, and entered. Mrs. Gummidge, no longer moping in her especial corner, was busy preparing breakfast. She took Mr. Peggotty's hat, and placed his seat for him, and spoke so comfortably and softly, that I hardly knew her.</p><p >“Dan'l, my good man,” said she, “you must eat and drink, and keep up your strength, for without it you'll do nowt. Try, that's a dear soul! And if I disturb you with my clicketten,” she meant her chattering, “tell me so, Dan'l, and I won't.”</p><p >When she had served us all, she withdrew to the window, where she sedulously employed herself in repairing some shirts and other clothes belonging to Mr. Peggotty, and neatly folding and packing them in an old oilskin bag, such as sailors carry. Meanwhile, she continued talking, in the same quiet manner:</p><p >“All times and seasons, you know, Dan'l,” said Mrs. Gummidge, “I shall be allus here, and every think will look accordin' to your wishes. I'm a poor scholar, but I shall write to you, odd times, when you're away, and send my letters to Mas'r Davy. Maybe you'll write to me too, Dan'l, odd times, and tell me how you fare to feel upon your lone lorn journies.”</p><p >“You'll be a solitary woman heer, I'm afeerd!” said Mr. Peggotty.</p><p >“No, no, Dan'l,” she returned, “I shan't be that. Doen't you mind me. I shall have enough to do to keep a Beein for you” (Mrs. Gummidge meant a home), “again you come back—to keep a Beein here for any that may hap to come back, Dan'l. In the fine time, I shall set outside the door as I used to do. If any <hi rend="italics">should</hi> come nigh, they shall see the old widder woman true to 'em, a long way off.”</p><p >What a change in Mrs. Gummidge in a little time! She was another woman. She was so devoted, she had such a quick perception of what it would be well to say, and what it would be well to leave unsaid, she was so forgetful of herself, and so regardful of the sorrow about her, that I held her in a sort of veneration. The work she did that day! There were many things to be brought up from the beach and stored in the outhouse—as oars, nets, sails, cordage, spars, lobsterpots, bags of ballast, and the like; and though there was abundance of assistance rendered, there being not a pair of working hands on all that shore but would have labored hard for Mr. Peggotty, and been well paid
<pb xml:id="p324"/>
in being asked to do it, yet she persisted, all day long, in toiling under weights that she was quite unequal to, and fagging to and fro on all sorts of unnecessary errands. As to deploring her misfortunes, she appeared to have entirely lost the recollection of ever having had any. She preserved an equable cheerfulness in the midst of her sympathy, which was not the least astonishing part of the change that had come over her. Querulousness was out of the question. I did not even observe her voice to falter, or a tear to escape from her eyes, the whole day through, until twilight; when she and I and Mr. Peggotty being alone together, and he having fallen asleep in perfect exhaustion, she broke into a half-suppressed fit of sobbing and crying, and taking me to the door, said, “Ever bless you, Mas'r Davy, be a friend to him, poor dear!” Then, she immediately ran out of the house to wash her face, in order that she might sit quietly beside him, and be found at work there, when he should awake. In short I left her, when I went away at night, the prop and staff of Mr. Peggotty's affliction; and I could not meditate enough upon the lesson that I read in Mrs. Gummidge, and the new experience she unfolded to me.</p><p >It was between nine and ten o'clock when, strolling in a melancholy manner through the town, I stopped at Mr. Omer's door. Mr. Omer had taken it so much to heart, his daughter told me, that he had been very low and poorly all day, and had gone to bed without his pipe.</p><p >“A deceitful, bad-hearted girl,” said Mrs. Joram. “There was no good in her, ever!”</p><p >“Don't say so,” I returned. “You don't think so.”</p><p >“Yes, I do!” cried Mrs. Joram, angrily.</p><p >“No, no,” said I.</p><p >Mrs. Joram tossed her head, endeavouring to be very stern and cross; but she could not command her softer self, and began to cry. I was young, to be sure; but I thought much the better of her for this sympathy, and fancied it became her, as a virtuous wife and mother, very well indeed.</p><p >“What will she ever do!” sobbed Minnie. “Where will she go! What will become of her! Oh, how could she be so cruel, to herself and him!”</p><p >I remembered the time when Minnie was a young and pretty girl; and I was glad that she remembered it too, so feelingly.</p><p >“My little Minnie,” said Mrs. Joram, “has only just now been got to sleep. Even in her sleep she is sobbing for Em'ly. All day long, little Minnie has cried for her, and asked me, over and over again, whether Em'ly was wicked? What can I say to her, when Em'ly tied a ribbon off her own neck round little Minnie's the last night she was here, and laid her head down on the pillow beside her till she was fast asleep! The ribbon's round my little Minnie's neck now. It ought not to be, perhaps, but what can I do? Em'ly is very bad, but they were fond of one another. And the child knows nothing!”</p><p >Mrs. Joram was so unhappy, that her husband came out to take care of her. Leaving them together, I went home to Peggotty's; more melancholy myself, if possible, than I had been yet.</p><p >That good creature—I mean Peggotty—all untired by her late anxieties
<pb xml:id="p325"/>
and sleepless nights, was at her brother's, where she meant to stay till morning. An old woman, who had been employed about the house for some weeks past, while Peggotty had been unable to attend to it, was the house's only other occupant besides myself. As I had no occasion for her services, I sent her to bed, by no means against her will; and sat down before the kitchen fire a little while, to think about all this.</p><p >I was blending it with the deathbed of the late Mr. Barkis, and was driving out with the tide towards the distance at which Ham had looked so singularly in the morning, when I was recalled from my wanderings by a knock at the door. There was a knocker upon the door, but it was not that which made the sound. The tap was from a hand, and low down upon the door, as if it were given by a child.</p><p >It made me start as much as if it had been the knock of a footman to a person of distinction. I opened the door; and at first looked down, to my amazement, on nothing but a great umbrella that appeared to be walking about of itself. But presently I discovered underneath it, Miss Mowcher.</p><p >I might not have been prepared to give the little creature a very kind reception, if, on her removing the umbrella, which her utmost efforts were unable to shut up, she had shown me the “volatile” expression of face which had made so great an impression on me at our first and last meeting. But her face, as she turned it up to mine, was so earnest; and when I relieved her of the umbrella (which would have been an inconvenient one for the Irish Giant), she wrung her little hands in such an afflicted manner; that I rather inclined towards her.</p><p >“Miss Mowcher!” said I, after glancing up and down the empty street, without distinctly knowing what I expected to see besides; “how do you come here? What is the matter?”</p><p >She motioned to me, with her short right arm, to shut the umbrella for her; and passing me hurriedly, went into the kitchen. When I had closed the door, and followed, with the umbrella in my hand, I found her sitting on the corner of the fender—it was a low iron one, with two flat bars at top to stand plates upon—in the shadow of the boiler, swaying herself backwards and forwards, and chafing her hands upon her knees like a person in pain.</p><p >Quite alarmed at being the only recipient of this untimely visit, and the only spectator of this portentous behaviour, I exclaimed again: “Pray tell me, Miss Mowcher, what is the matter! are you ill?</p><p >“My dear young soul,” returned Miss Mowcher, squeezing her hands upon her heart one over the other. “I am ill here, I am very ill. To think that it should come to this, when I might have known it and perhaps prevented it, if I hadn't been a thoughtless fool!”</p><p >Again her large bonnet (very disproportionate to her figure) went backwards and forwards, in her swaying of her little body to and fro; while a most gigantic bonnet rocked, in unison with it, upon the wall.</p><p >“I am surprised,” I began, “to see you so distressed and serious”—when she interrupted me.</p><p >“Yes, it's always so!” she said. “They are all surprised, these inconsiderate young people, fairly and full grown, to see any natural
<pb xml:id="p326"/>
feeling in a little thing like me! They make a plaything of me, use me for their amusement, throw me away when they are tired, and wonder that I feel more than a toy horse or a wooden soldier! Yes, yes, that's the way. The old way!”</p><p >“It may be, with others,” I returned, “but I do assure you it is not with me. Perhaps I ought not to be at all surprised to see you as you are now: I know so little of you. I said, without consideration, what I thought.”</p><p >“What can I do?” returned the little woman, standing up, and holding out her arms to show herself. “See! What I am, my father was; and my sister is; and my brother is. I have worked for sister and brother these many years—hard, Mr. Copperfield—all day. I must live. I do no harm. If there are people so unreflecting or so cruel, as to make a jest of me, what is left for me to do but to make a jest of myself, them, and every thing? If I do so, for the time, whose fault is that? Mine?”</p><p >No. Not Miss Mowcher's, I perceived.</p><p >“If I had shown myself a sensitive dwarf to your false friend,” pursued the little woman, shaking her head at me, with reproachful earnestness, “how much of his help or good will do you think <hi rend="italics">I</hi> should ever have had? If little Mowcher (who had no hand, young gentleman, in the making of herself) addressed herself to him, or the like of him, because of her misfortunes, when do you suppose her small voice would have been heard? Little Mowcher would have as much need to live, if she was the bitterest and dullest of pigmies; but she couldn't do it. No. She might whistle for her bread and butter till she died of Air!”</p><p >Miss Mowcher sat down on the fender again, and took out her handkerchief, and wiped her eyes.</p><p >“Be thankful for me, if you have a kind heart as I think you have,” she said, “that while I know well what I am, I can be cheerful and endure it all. I am thankful for myself, at any rate, that I can find my tiny way through the world, without being beholden to any one; and that in return for all that is thrown at me, in folly or vanity, as I go along, I can throw bubbles back. If I don't brood over all I want, it is the better for me, and not the worse for any one. If I am a plaything for you giants, be gentle with me.</p><p >Miss Mowcher replaced her handkerchief in her pocket, looking at me with very intent expression all the while, and pursued:</p><p >“I saw you in the street just now. You may suppose I am not able to walk as fast as you, with my short legs and short breath, and I couldn't overtake you; but I guessed where you came, and came after you. I have been here before, to-day, but the good woman wasn't at home.”</p><p >“Do you know her?” I demanded.</p><p >“I know <hi rend="italics">of</hi> her, and about her,” she replied, “from Omer and Joram. I was there at seven o'clock this morning. Do you remember what Steerforth said to me about this unfortunate girl, that time when I saw you both at the inn?”</p><p >The great bonnet on Miss Mowcher's head, and the greater bonnet on the wall, began to go backwards and forwards again when she asked this question.</p><pb  xml:id="p327"/><p >I remembered very well what she referred to, having had it in my thoughts many times that day. I told her so.</p><p >“May the Father of all Evil confound him,” said the little woman, holding up her forefinger between me and her sparkling eyes, “and ten times more confound that wicked servant; but I believed it was <hi rend="italics">you</hi> who had a boyish passion for her!”</p><p >“I?” I repeated.</p><p >“Child, child! In the name of blind ill-fortune,” cried Miss Mowcher, wringing her hands impatiently, as she went to and fro again upon the fender, “why did you praise her so, and blush, and look disturbed?”</p><p >I could not conceal from myself that I had done this, though for a reason very different from her supposition.</p><p >“What did I know?” said Miss Mowcher, taking out her handkerchief again, and giving one little stamp on the ground whenever, at short intervals, she applied it to her eyes with both hands at once. “He was crossing you and wheedling you, I saw; and you were soft wax in his hands, I saw. Had I left the room a minute, when his man told me that ‘Young Innocence’ (so he called you, and you may call him ‘Old Guilt’ all the days of your life) had set his heart upon her, and she was giddy and liked him, but his master was resolved that no harm should come of it—more for your sake than for hers—and that that was their business here? How could I <hi rend="italics">but</hi> believe him? I saw Steerforth soothe and please you by his praise of her! You were the first to mention her name. You owned to an old admiration of her. You were hot and cold, and red and white, all at once when I spoke to you of her. What could I think—what <hi rend="italics">did</hi> I think—but that you were a young libertine in everything but experience, and had fallen into hands that had experience enough, and could manage you (having the fancy) for your own good? Oh! oh! oh! They were afraid of my finding out the truth,” exclaimed Miss Mowcher, getting off the fender, and trotting up and down the kitchen with her two short arms distressfully lifted up, “because I am a sharp little thing—I need be, to get through the world at all!—and they deceived me altogether, and I gave the poor unfortunate girl a letter, which I fully believe was the beginning of her ever speaking to Littimer, who was left behind on purpose!”</p><p >I stood amazed at the revelation of all this perfidy, looking at Miss Mowcher as she walked up and down the kitchen until she was out of breath: when she sat upon the fender again, and, drying her face with her handkerchief, shook her head for a long time, without otherwise moving, and without breaking silence.</p><p >“My country rounds,” she added at length, “brought me to Norwich, Mr. Copperfield, the night before last. What I happened to find out there, about their secret way of coming and going, without you—which was strange—led to my suspecting something wrong. I got into the coach from London last night, as it came through Norwich, and was here this morning. Oh, oh, oh! too late!”</p><p >Poor little Mowcher turned so chilly after all her crying and fretting, that she turned round on the fender, putting her poor little wet feet in among the ashes to warm them, and sat looking at the fire, like a large doll. I sat in a chair on the other side of the hearth, lost in unhappy reflections, and looking at the fire too, and sometimes at her.</p><pb  xml:id="p328"/><p >“I must go,” she said at last, rising as she spoke. “It's late. You don't mistrust me?”</p><p >Meeting her sharp glance, which was as sharp as ever when she asked me, I could not on that short challenge answer no, quite frankly.</p><p >“Come!” said she, accepting the offer of my hand to help her over the fender, and looking wistfully up into my face, “you know you wouldn't mistrust me, if I was a full-sized woman!”</p><p >I felt that there was much truth in this; and I felt rather ashamed of myself.</p><p >“You are a young man,” she said, nodding. “Take a word of advice, even from three foot nothing. Try not to associate bodily defects with mental, my good friend, except for a solid reason.”</p><p >She had got over the fender now, and I had got over my suspicion. I told her that I believed she had given me a faithful account of herself, and that we had both been hapless instruments in designing hands. She thanked me, and said I was a good fellow.</p><p >“Now, mind!” she exclaimed, turning back on her way to the door, and looking shrewdly at me, with her forefinger up again. “I have some reason to suspect, from what I have heard—my ears are always open; I can't afford to spare what powers I have—that they are gone abroad. But if ever they return, if ever any one of them returns, while I am alive, I am more likely than another, going about as I do, to find it out soon. Whatever I know, you shall know. If ever I can do anything to serve the poor betrayed girl, I will do it faithfully, please Heaven! And Littimer had better have a bloodhound at his back, than little Mowcher!”</p><p >I placed implicit faith in this last statement, when I marked the look with which it was accompanied.</p><p >“Trust me no more, but trust me no less, than you would trust a full-sized woman,” said the little creature, touching me appealingly on the wrist. “If ever you see me again, unlike what I am now, and like what I was when you first saw me, observe what company I am in. Call to mind that I am a very helpless and defenceless little thing. Think of me at home with my brother like myself and sister like myself, when my day's work is done. Perhaps you wont, then, be very hard upon me, or surprised if I can be distressed and serious. Good night!”</p><p >I gave Miss Mowcher my hand, with a very different opinion of her from that which I had hitherto entertained, and opened the door to let her out. It was not a trifling business to get the great umbrella up, and properly balanced in her grasp; but at last I successfully accomplished this, and saw it go bobbing down the street through the rain, without the least appearance of having anybody underneath it, except when a heavier fall than usual from some overcharged water-spout sent it toppling over, on one side, and discovered Miss Mowcher struggling violently to get it right. After making one or two sallies to her relief, which were rendered futile by the umbrella's hopping on again, like an immense bird, before I could reach it, I came in, went to bed, and slept till morning.</p><p >In the morning I was joined by Mr. Peggotty and by my old nurse, and we went at an early hour to the coach office, where Mrs. Gummidge and Ilam were waiting to take leave of us.</p><pb  xml:id="p329"/><p >“Mas'r Davy,” Ham whispered, drawing me aside, while Mr. Peggotty was stowing his bag among the luggage, “his life is quite broke up. He doen't know wheer he's going; he doen't know what's afore him; he's bound upon a voyage that'll last, on and off, all the rest of his days, take my wured for't, unless he finds what he's a seeking of. I am sure you'll be a friend to him, Mas'r Davy?”</p><p >“Trust me, I will indeed,” said I, shaking hands with Ham earnestly.</p><p >“Thankee. Thankee, very kind, sir. One thing furder. I'm in good employ, you know, Mas'r Davy, and I han't no way now of spending what I gets. Money's of no use to me no more, except to live. If you can lay it out for him, I shall do my work with a better art. Though as to that, sir,” and he spoke very steadily and mildly, “you're not to think but I shall work at all times, like a man, and act the best that lays in my power!”</p><p >I told him I was well convinced of it; and I hinted that I hoped the time might even come, when he would cease to lead the lonely life he naturally contemplated now.</p><p >“No sir,” he said, shaking his head, “all that's past and over with me, sir. No one can never fill the place that's empty. But you'll bear in mind about the money, as theer's at all times some laying by for him?”</p><p >Reminding him of the fact, that Mr. Peggotty derived a steady, though certainly a very moderate income from the bequest of his late brother-in-law, I promised to do so. We then took leave of each other. I cannot leave him, even now, without remembering with a pang, at once his modest fortitude and his great sorrow.</p><p >As to Mrs. Gummidge, if I were to endeavour to describe how she ran down the street by the side of the coach, seeing nothing but Mr. Peggotty on the roof, through the tears she tried to repress, and dashing herself against the people who were coming in the opposite direction, I should enter on a task of some difficulty. Therefore I had better leave her sitting on a baker's door-step, out of breath, with no shape at all remaining in her bonnet, and one of her shoes off, lying on the pavement at a considerable distance.</p><p >When we got to our journey's end, our first pursuit was to look about for a little lodging for Peggotty, where her brother could have a bed. We were so fortunate as to find one, of a very clean and cheap description, over a chandler's shop, only two streets removed from me. When we had engaged this domicile, I bought some cold meat at an eating-house, and took my fellow-travellers home to tea; a proceeding, I regret to state, which did not meet with Mrs. Crupp's approval, but quite the contrary. I ought to observe, however, in explanation of that lady's state of mind, that she was much offended by Peggotty's tucking up her widow's gown before she had been ten minutes in the place, and setting to work to dust my bed-room. This Mrs. Crupp regarded in the light of a liberty, and a liberty, she said, was a thing she never allowed.</p><p >Mr. Peggotty had made a communication to me on the way to London, for which I was not unprepared. It was, that he purposed first seeing Mrs. Steerforth. As I felt bound to assist him in this, and also to mediate between them; with the view of sparing the mother's feelings as
<pb xml:id="p330"/>
much as possible, I wrote to her that night. I told her as mildly as I could what his wrong was, and what my own share in his injury. I said he was a man in very common life, but of a most gentle and upright character; and that I ventured to express a hope that she would not refuse to see him in his heavy trouble. I mentioned two o'clock in the afternoon as the hour of our coming, and I sent the letter myself by the first coach in the morning.</p><p >At the appointed time, we stood at the door—the door of that house where I had been, a few days since, so happy: where my youthful confidence and warmth of heart had been yielded up so freely: which was closed against me henceforth: which was now a waste, a ruin.</p><p >No Littimer appeared. The pleasanter face which had replaced his, on the occasion of my last visit, answered to our summons, and went before us to the drawing-room. Mrs. Steerforth was sitting there. Rosa Dartle glided, as we went in, from another part of the room, and stood behind her chair.</p><p >I saw, directly, in his mother's face, that she knew from himself what he had done. It was very pale; and bore the traces of deeper emotion than my letter alone, weakened by the doubts her fondness would have raised upon it, would have been likely to create. I thought her more like him than ever I had thought her; and I felt, rather than saw, that the resemblance was not lost on my companion.</p><p >She sat upright in her arm-chair, with a stately, immoveable, passionless air, that it seemed as if nothing could disturb. She looked very stedfastly at Mr. Peggotty when he stood before her; and he looked, quite as stedfastly, at her. Rosa Dartle's keen glance comprehended all of us. For some moments not a word was spoken.</p><p >She motioned to Mr. Peggotty to be seated. He said, in a low voice, “I shouldn't feel it nat'ral, ma'am, to sit down in this house. I'd sooner stand.” And this was succeeded by another silence, which she broke thus:</p><p >“I know, with deep regret, what has brought you here. What do you want of me? What do you ask me to do?”</p><p >He put his hat under his arm, and feeling in his breast for Emily's letter, took it out, unfolded it, and gave it to her.</p><p >“Please to read that, ma'am. That's my niece's hand!”</p><p >She read it, in the same stately and impassive way,—untouched by its contents, as far as I could see,—and returned it to him.</p><p >“ ‘Unless he brings me back a lady,’ ” said Mr. Peggotty, tracing out that part with his finger. “I come to know, ma'am, whether he will keep his wured?”</p><p >“No,” she returned.</p><p >“Why not?” said Mr. Peggotty.</p><p >“It is impossible. He would disgrace himself. You cannot fail to know that she is far below him.”</p><p >“Raise her up!” said Mr. Peggotty.</p><p >“She is uneducated and ignorant.”</p><p >“Maybe she's not; maybe she is,” said Mr. Peggotty. “<hi rend="italics">I</hi> think not, ma'am; but I'm no judge of them things. Teach her better!”</p><pb  xml:id="p331"/><p >“Since you oblige me to speak more plainly, which I am very unwilling to do, her humble connexions would render such a thing impossible, if nothing else did.”</p><p >“Hark to this, ma'am,” he returned, slowly and quietly. “You know what it is to love your child. So do I. If she was a hundred times my child, I couldn't love her more. You doen't know what it is to lose your child. I do. All the heaps of riches in the wureld would be nowt to me (if they was mine) to buy her back! But, save her from this disgrace, and she shall never be disgraced by us. Not one of us that she's growed up among, not one of us that's lived along with her, and had her for their all in all, these many year, will ever look upon her pritty face again. We'll be content to let her be; we'll be content to think of her, far off, as if she was underneath another sun and sky; we'll be content to trust her to her husband,—to her little children p'raps,—and bide the time when all of us shall be alike in quality afore our God!”</p><p >The rugged cloquence with which he spoke, was not devoid of all effect. She still preserved her proud manner, but there was a touch of softness in her voice, as she answered:</p><p >“I justify nothing. I make no counter-accusations. But I am sorry to repeat, it is impossible. Such a marriage would irretrievably blight my son's career, and ruin his prospects. Nothing is more certain than that it never can take place, and never will. If there is any other compensation—”</p><p >“I am looking at the likeness of the face,” interrupted Mr. Peggotty, with a steady but a kindling eye, “that has looked at me, in my home, at my fireside, in my boat—wheer not?—smiling and friendly, when it was so treacherous, that I go half wild when I think of it. If the likeness of that face don't turn to burning fire, at the thought of offering money to me for my child's blight and ruin, it's as bad. I doen't know, being a lady's, but what it's worse.”</p><p >She changed now, in a moment. An angry flush overspread her features; and she said, in an intolerant manner, grasping the arm-chair tightly with her hands:</p><p >“What compensation can you make to <hi rend="italics">me</hi> for opening such a pit between me and my son? What is your love to mine? What is your separation to ours?”</p><p >Miss Dartle softly touched her, and bent down her head to whisper, but she would not hear a word.</p><p >“No, Rosa, not a word! Let the man listen to what I say! My son, who has been the object of my life, to whom its every thought has been devoted, whom I have gratified from a child in every wish, from whom I have had no separate existence since his birth,—to take up in a moment with a miserable girl, and avoid me! To repay my confidence with systematic deception, for her sake, and quit me for her! To set this wretched fancy, against his mother's claims upon his duty, love, respect, gratitude—claims that every day and hour of his life should have strengthened into ties that nothing could be proof against! Is this no injury?”</p><p >Again Rosa Dartle tried to soothe her; again ineffectually.</p><p >“I say, Rosa, not a word! If he can stake his all upon the lightest object, I can stake my all upon a greater purpose. Let him go where he
<pb xml:id="p332"/>
will, with the means that my love has secured to him! Does he think to reduce me by long absence? He knows his mother very little if he does. Let him put away his whim now, and he is welcome back. Let him not put her away now, and he never shall come near me, living or dying, while I can raise my hand to make a sign against it, unless, being rid of her for ever, he comes humbly to me and begs for my forgiveness. This is my right. This is the acknowledgment I <hi rend="italics">will have.</hi> This is the separation that there is between us! And is this,” she added, looking at her visitor with the proud intolerant air with which she had begun, “no injury?”</p><p >While I heard and saw the mother as she said these words, I seemed to hear and see the son, defying them. All that I had ever seen in him of an unyielding, wilful spirit, I saw in her. All the understanding that I had now of his misdirected energy, became an understanding of her character too, and a perception that it was, in its strongest springs, the same.</p><p >She now observed to me, aloud, resuming her former restraint, that it was useless to hear more, or to say more, and that she begged to put an end to the interview. She rose with an air of dignity to leave the room, when Mr. Peggotty signified that it was needless.</p><p >“Doen't fear me being any hindrance to you, I have no more to say, ma'am,” he remarked, as he moved towards the door. “I come heer with no hope, and I take away no hope. I have done what I thowt should be done, but I never looked fur any good to come of my stan'ning where I do. This has been too evil a house fur me and mine, fur me to be in my right senses and expect it.”</p><p >With this, we departed; leaving her standing by her elbow chair, a picture of a noble presence and a handsome face.</p><p >We had, on our way out, to cross a paved hall, with glass sides and roof, over which a vine was trained. Its leaves and shoots were green then, and the day being sunny, a pair of glass doors leading to the garden were thrown open. Rosa Dartle, entering this way with a noiseless step, when we were close to them, addressed herself to me:</p><p >“You do well,” she said, “indeed, to bring this fellow here!”</p><p >Such a concentration of rage and scorn as darkened her face, and flashed in her jet-black eyes, I could not have thought compressible even into that face. The scar made by the hammer was, as usual in this excited state of her features, strongly marked. When the throbbing I had seen before, came into it as I looked at her, she absolutely lifted up her hand, and struck it.</p><p >“This is a fellow,” she said, “to champion and bring here, is he not? You are a true man!”</p><p >“Miss Dartle,” I returned, “you are surely not so unjust as to condemn <hi rend="italics">me!</hi>”</p><p >“Why do you bring division between these two mad creatures?” she returned. “Don't you know that they are both mad with their own self-will and pride?”</p><p >“Is it my doing?” I returned.</p><p >“Is it your doing!” she retorted. “Why do you bring this man here?”</p><pb  xml:id="p333"/><p >“He is a deeply-injured man, Miss Dartle,” I replied. “You may not know it.”</p><p >“I know that James Steerforth,” she said, with her hand on her bosom, as if to prevent the storm that was raging there, from being loud, “has a false, corrupt heart, and is a traitor. But what need I know or care about this fellow, and his common niece?”</p><p >“Miss Dartle,” I returned, “you deepen the injury. It is sufficient already. I will only say, at parting, that you do him a great wrong.”</p><p >“I do him no wrong,” she returned. “They are a depraved worthless set. I would have her whipped!”</p><p >Mr. Peggotty passed on, without a word, and went out at the door.</p><p >“Oh, shame, Miss Dartle! shame!” I said indignantly. “How can you bear to trample on his undeserved affliction!”</p><p >“I would trample on them all,” she answered. “I would have his house pulled down. I would have her branded on the face, drest in rags, and cast out in the streets to starve. If I had the power to sit in judgment on her, I would see it done. See it done? I would do it! I detest her. If I ever could reproach her with her infamous condition, I would go anywhere to do so. If I could hunt her to her grave, I would. If there was any word of comfort that would be a solace to her in her dying hour, and only I possessed it, I wouldn't part with it for Life itself.”</p><p >The mere vehemence of her words can convey, I am sensible, but a weak impression of the passion by which she was possessed, and which made itself articulate in her whole figure, though her voice, instead of being raised, was lower than usual. No description I could give of her would do justice to my recollection of her, or to her entire deliverance of herself to her anger. I have seen passion in many forms, but I have never seen it in such a form as that.</p><p >When I joined Mr. Peggotty, he was walking slowly and thoughtfully down the hill. He told me, as soon as I came up with him, that having now discharged his mind of what he had purposed doing in London, he meant “to set out on his travels,” that night. I asked him where he meant to go? He only answered, “I'm a going, sir, to seek my niece.”</p><p >We went back to the little lodging over the chandler's shop, and there I found an opportunity of repeating to Peggotty what he had said to me. She informed me, in return, that he had said the same to her that morning. She knew no more than I did, where he was going, but she thought he had some project shaped out in his mind.</p><p >I did not like to leave him, under such circumstances, and we all three dined together off a beefsteak pie—which was one of the many good things for which Peggotty was famous—and which was curiously flavoured on this occasion, I recollect well, by a miscellaneous taste of tea, coffee, butter, bacon, cheese, new loaves, firewood, candles, and walnut ketchup, continually ascending from the shop. After dinner we sat for an hour or so near the window, without talking much; and then Mr. Peggotty got up, and brought his oilskin bag and his stout stick, and laid them on the table.</p><p >He accepted, from his sister's stock of ready money, a small sum on account of his legacy; barely enough, I should have thought, to keep
<pb xml:id="p334"/>
him for a month. He promised to communicate with me, when anything befel him; and he slung his bag about him, took his hat and stick, and bade us both “Good bye!”</p><p >“All good attend you, dear old woman,” he said, embracing Peggotty, “and you too, Mas'r Davy!” shaking hands with me. “I'm a going to seek her, fur and wide. If she should come home while I'm away,—but ah, that ain't like to be!—or if I should bring her back, my meaning is, that she and me shall live and die where no one can't reproach her. If any hurt should come to me, remember that the last words I left for her was, ‘My unchanged love is with my darling child, and I forgive her!’”</p><p >He said this solemnly, bare-headed; then, putting on his har, he went down the stairs, and away. We followed to the door. It was a warm, dusty evening, just the time when, in the great main thoroughfare out of which that bye-way turned, there was a temporary lull in the eternal tread of feet upon the pavement, and a strong red sunshine. He turned, alone, at the corner of our shady street, into a glow of light, in which we lost him.</p><p >Rarely did that hour of the evening come, rarely did I wake at night, rarely did I look up at the moon, or stars, or watch the falling rain, or hear the wind, but I thought of his solitary figure toiling on, poor pilgrim, and recalled the words:</p><p >“I'm a going to seek her, fur and wide. If any hurt should come to me, remember that the last words I left for her was, ‘My unchanged love is with my darling child, and I forgive her!’”</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXIII. <lb/> BLISSFUL.</head><p >ALL this time, I had gone on loving Dora, harder than ever. Her idea was my refuge in disappointment and distress, and made some amends to me, even for the loss of my friend. The more I pitied myself, or pitied others, the more I sought for consolation in the image of Dora. The greater the accumulation of deceit and trouble in the world, the brighter and the purer shone the star of Dora high above the world. I don't think I had any definite idea where Dora came from, or in what degree she was related to a higher order of beings; but I am quite sure I should have scouted the notion of her being simply human, like any other young lady, with indignation and contempt.</p><p >If I may so express it, I was steeped in Dora. I was not merely over head and ears in love with her, but I was saturated through and through. Enough love might have been wrung out of me, metaphorically speaking, to drown anybody in; and yet there would have remained enough within me, and all over me, to pervade my entire existence.</p><p >The first thing I did, on my own account, when I came back, was to
<pb xml:id="p335"/>
take a night-walk to Norwood, and, like the subject of a venerable riddle of my childhood to go “round and round the house, without ever touching the house,” thinking about Dora. I believe the theme of this incomprehensible conundrum was the moon. No matter what it was, I, the moon-struck slave of Dora, perambulated round and round the house and garden for two hours, looking through crevices in the palings, getting my chin by dint of violent exertion above the rusty nails on the top, blowing kisses at the lights in the windows, and romantically calling on the night, at intervals, to shield my Dora—I don't exactly know what from, I suppose from fire. Perhaps from mice, to which she had a great objection.</p><p >My love was so much on my mind, and it was so natural to me to confide in Peggotty, when I found her again by my side of an evening with the old set of industrial implements, busily making the tour of my wardrobe, that I imparted to her, in a sufficiently roundabout way, my great secret. Peggotty was strongly interested, but I could not get her into my view of the case at all. She was audaciously prejudiced in my favour, and quite unable to understand why I should have any misgivings, or be low-spirited about it. ‘The young lady might think herself well off,’ she observed, ‘to have such a beau. And as to her Pa,’ she said, ‘what <hi rend="italics">did</hi> the gentleman expect, for gracious sake!’</p><p >I observed, however, that Mr. Spenlow's Proctorial gown and stiff cravat took Peggotty down a little, and inspired her with a greater reverence for the man who was gradually becoming more and more etherealized in my eyes every day, and about whom a reflected radiance seemed to me to beam when he sat erect in Court among his papers, like a little light-house in a sea of stationery. And by-the-by, it used to be uncommonly strange to me to consider, I remember, as I sat in Court too, how those dim old judges and doctors wouldn't have cared for Dora, if they had known her; how they wouldn't have gone out of their senses with rapture, if marriage with Dora had been proposed to them; how Dora might have sung, and played upon that glorified guitar, until she led <hi rend="italics">me</hi> to the verge of madness, yet not have tempted one of those slow-goers an inch out of his road!</p><p >I despised them, to a man. Frozen-out old gardeners in the flowerbeds of the heart, I took a personal offence against them all. The Bench was nothing to me but an insensible blunderer. The Bar had no more tenderness or poetry in it, than the Bar of a public-house.</p><p >Taking the management of Peggotty's affairs into my own hands, with no little pride, I proved the will, and came to a settlement with the Legacy Duty-office, and took her to the Bank, and soon got everything into an orderly train. We varied the legal character of these proceedings by going to see some perspiring Wax-work, in Fleet Street (melted, I should hope, these twenty years); and by visiting Miss Linwood's Exhibition, which I remember as a Mausoleum of needlework, favorable to self-examination and repentance; and by inspecting the Tower of London; and going to the top of St. Paul's. All these wonders afforded Peggotty as much pleasure as she was able to enjoy, under existing circumstances: except, I think, St. Paul's, which, from her long attachment to her workbox, became a rival of the picture on the lid, and was, in some particulars, vanquished, she considered, by that work of art.</p><p >Peggotty's business, which was what we used to call “common form
<pb xml:id="p336"/>
business” in the Commons (and very light and lucrative the commonform business was), being settled, I took her down to the office one morning to pay her bill. Mr. Spenlow had stepped out, old Tiffey said, to get a gentleman sworn for a marriage license; but as I knew he would be back directly, our place lying close to the Surrogate's, and to the Vicar-General's office too, I told Peggotty to wait.</p><p >We were a little like undertakers, in the Commons, as regarded Probate transactions; generally making it a rule to look more or less cut up, when we had to deal with clients in mourning. In a similar feeling of delicacy, we were always blithe and light-hearted with the license clients. Therefore I hinted to Peggotty that she would find Mr. Spenlow much recovered from the shock of Mr. Barkis's decease; and indeed he came in like a bridegroom.</p><p >But neither Peggotty nor I had eyes for him, when we saw, in company with him, Mr. Murdstone. He was very little changed. His hair looked as thick, and was certainly as black, as ever; and his glance was as little to be trusted as of old.</p><p >“Ah, Copperfield?” said Mr. Spenlow. “You know this gentleman, I believe?”</p><p >I made my gentleman a distant bow, and Peggotty barely recognised him. He was, at first, somewhat disconcerted to meet us two together; but quickly decided what to do, and came up to me.</p><p >“I hope,” he said, “that you are doing well?”</p><p >“It can hardly be interesting to you,” said I. “Yes, if you wish to know.”</p><p >We looked at each other, and he addressed himself to Peggotty.</p><p >“And you,” said he. “I am sorry to observe that you have lost your husband.”</p><p >“It's not the first loss I have had in my life, Mr. Murdstone,” replied Peggotty, trembling from head to foot. “I am glad to hope that there is nobody to blame for this one,—nobody to answer for it.”</p><p >“Ha!” said he; “that's a comfortable reflection. You have done your duty?”</p><p >“I have not worn any body's life away,” said Peggotty, “I am thankful to think! No, Mr. Murdstone, I have not worrited and frightened any sweet creetur to an early grave!”</p><p >He eyed her gloomily—remorsefully I thought—for an instant; and said, turning his head towards me, but looking at my feet instead of my face:</p><p >“We are not likely to encounter soon again;—a source of satisfaction to us both, no doubt, for such meetings as this can never be agreeable. I do not expect that you, who always rebelled against my just authority, exerted for your benefit and reformation, should owe me any good will now. There is an antipathy between us—”</p><p >“An old one, I believe?” said I, interrupting him.</p><p >He smiled, and shot as evil a glance at me as could come from his dark eyes.</p><p >“It rankled in your baby breast,” he said. “It embittered the life of your poor mother. You are right. I hope you may do better, yet; I hope you may correct yourself.”</p><pb  xml:id="p337"/><p >Here he ended the dialogue, which had been carried on in a low voice, in a corner of the outer office, by passing into Mr. Spenlow's room, and saying aloud, in his smoothest manner:</p><p >“Gentlemen of Mr. Spenlow's profession are accustomed to family differences, and know how complicated and difficult they always are!” With that, he paid the money for his license; and, receiving it neatly folded from Mr. Spenlow, together with a shake of the hand, and a polite wish for his happiness and the lady's, went out of the office.</p><p >I might have had more difficulty in constraining myself to be silent under his words, if I had had less difficulty in impressing upon Peggotty (who was only angry on my account, good creature!) that we were not in a place for recrimination, and that I besought her to hold her peace. She was so unusually roused, that I was glad to compound for an affectionate hug, elicited by this revival in her mind of our old injuries, and to make the best I could of it, before Mr. Spenlow and the clerks.</p><p >Mr. Spenlow did not appear to know what the connexion between Mr. Murdstone and myself was; which I was glad of, for I could not bear to acknowledge him, even in my own breast, remembering what I did of the history of my poor mother. Mr. Spenlow seemed to think, if he thought anything about the matter, that my aunt was the leader of the state party in our family, and that there was a rebel party commanded by somebody else—so I gathered at least from what he said, while we were waiting for Mr. Tiffey to make out Peggotty's bill of costs.</p><p >“Miss Trotwood,” he remarked, “is very firm, no doubt, and not likely to give way to opposition. I have an admiration for her character, and I may congratulate you, Copperfield, on being on the right side. Differences between relations are much to be deplored—but they are extremely general—and the great thing is, to be on the right side:” meaning, I take it, on the side of the moneyed interest.</p><p >“Rather a good marriage this, I believe?” said Mr. Spenlow.</p><p >I explained that I knew nothing about it.</p><p >“Indeed!” he said. “Speaking from the few words Mr. Murdstone dropped—as a man frequently does on these occasions—and from what Miss Murdstone let fall, I should say it was rather a good marriage.”</p><p >“Do you mean that there is money, sir?” I asked.</p><p >“Yes,” said Mr. Spenlow, “I understand there's money. Beauty too, I am told.”</p><p >“Indeed? Is his new wife young?”</p><p >“Just of age,” said Mr. Spenlow. “So lately, that I should think they had been waiting for that.”</p><p >“Lord deliver her!” said Peggotty. So very emphatically and unexpectedly, that we were all three discomposed; until Tiffey came in with the bill.</p><p >Old Tiffey soon appeared, however, and handed it to Mr. Spenlow, to look over. Mr. Spenlow, settling his chin in his cravat and rubbing it softly, went over the items with a deprecatory air—as if it were all Jorkins's doing—and handed it back to Tiffey with a bland sigh.</p><p >“Yes,” he said. “That's right. Quite right. I should have been extremely happy, Copperfield, to have limited these charges to the actual expenditure out of pocket; but it is an irksome incident in my professional
<pb xml:id="p338"/>
life, that I am not at liberty to consult my own wishes. I have a partner—Mr. Jorkins.”</p><p >As he said this with a gentle melancholy, which was the next thing to making no charge at all, I expressed my acknowledgments on Peggotty's behalf, and paid Tiffey in bank notes. Peggotty then retired to her lodging, and Mr. Spenlow and I went into Court, where we had a divorce-suit coming on, under an ingenious little statute (repealed now, I believe, but in virtue of which I have seen several marriages annulled), of which the merits were these. The husband, whose name was Thomas Benjamin, had taken out his marriage license as Thomas only; suppressing the Benjamin, in case he should not find himself as comfortable as he expected. <hi rend="italics">Not</hi> finding himself as comfortable as he expected, or being a little fatigued with his wife, poor fellow, he now came forward by a friend, after being married a year or two, and declared that his name was Thomas Benjamin, and therefore he was not married at all. Which the Court confirmed, to his great satisfaction.</p><p >I must say that I had my doubts about the strict justice of this, and was not even frightened out of them by the bushel of wheat which reconciles all anomalies. But Mr. Spenlow argued the matter with me. He said, Look at the world, there was good and evil in that; look at the ecclesiastical law, there was good and evil in <hi rend="italics">that.</hi> It was all part of a system. Very good. There you were!</p><p >I had not the hardihood to suggest to Dora's father that possibly we might even improve the world a little, if we got up early in the morning, and took off our coats to the work; but I confessed that I thought we might improve the Commons. Mr. Spenlow replied that he would particularly advise me to dismiss that idea from my mind, as not being worthy of my gentlemanly character; but that he would be glad to hear from me of what improvement I thought the Commons susceptible?</p><p >Taking that part of the Commons which happened to be nearest to us—for our man was unmarried by this time, and we were out of Court, and strolling past the Prerogative Office—I submitted that I thought the Prerogative Office rather a queerly managed institution. Mr. Spenlow inquired in what respect? I replied, with all due deference to his experience (but with more deference, I am afraid, to his being Dora's father), that perhaps it was a little nonsensical that the Registry of that Court, containing the original wills of all persons leaving effects within the immense province of Canterbury, for three whole centuries, should be an accidental building, never designed for the purpose, leased by the registrars for their own private emolument, unsafe, not even ascertained to be fireproof, chocked with the important documents it held, and positively, from the roof to the basement, a mercenary speculation of the registrars, who took great fees from the public, and crammed the public's wills away anyhow and anywhere, having no other object than to get rid of them cheaply. That, perhaps, it was a little unreasonable that these registrars in the receipt of profits amounting to eight or nine thousand pounds a year (to say nothing of the profits of the deputy registrars, and clerks of seats), should not be obliged to spend a little of that money, in finding a reasonably safe place for the important documents which all classes of people were compelled to hand over to them, whether they would or no.
<pb xml:id="p339"/>
That, perhaps, it was a little unjust that all the great offices in this great office, should be magnificent sinecures, while the unfortunate working-clerks in the cold dark room up-stairs were the worst rewarded, and the least considered men, doing important services, in London. That perhaps it was a little indecent that the principal registrar of all, whose duty it was to find the public, constantly resorting to this place, all needful accommodation, should be an enormous sinecurist in virtue of that post (and might be, besides, a clergyman, a pluralist, the holder of a stall in a cathedral, and what not),—while the public was put to the inconvenience of which we had a specimen every afternoon when the office was busy, and which we knew to be quite monstrous. That, perhaps, in short, this Prerogative Office of the diocese of Canterbury was altogether such a pestilent job, and such a pernicious absurdity, that but for its being squeezed away, in a corner of Saint Paul's Churchyard, which few people knew, it must have been turned completely inside out, and upside down, long ago.</p><p >Mr. Spenlow smiled as I became modestly warm on the subject, and then argued this question with me as he had argued the other. He said, what was it after all? It was a question of feeling. If the public felt that their wills were in safe keeping, and took it for granted that the office was not to be made better, who was the worse for it? Nobody? Who was the better for it? All the Sinecurists. Very well. Then the good predominanted. It might not be a perfect system; nothing <hi rend="italics">was</hi> perfect; but what he objected to, was, the insertion of the wedge. Under the Prerogative Office, the country had been glorious. Insert the wedge into the Prerogative Office, and the country would cease to be glorious. He considered it the principle of a gentleman to take things as he found them; and he had no doubt the Prerogative Office would last our time. I deferred to his opinion, though I had great doubts of it myself. I find he was right, however; for it has not only lasted to the present moment, but has done so in the teeth of a great parliamentary report made (not too willingly) eighteen years ago, when all these objections of mine were set forth in detail, and when the existing stowage for wills was described as equal to the accumulation of only two years and a half more. What they have done with them since; whether they have lost many, or whether they sell any, now and then, to the butter shops; I don't know. I am glad mine is not there, and I hope it may not go there, yet awhile.</p><p >I have set all this down, in my present blissful chapter, because here it comes into its natural place. Mr. Spenlow and I falling into this conversation, prolonged it and our saunter to and fro, until we diverged into general topics. And so it came about, in the end, that Mr. Spenlow told me this day week was Dora's birthday, and he would be glad if I would come down and join a little pic-nic on the occasion. I went out of my senses immediately; became a mere driveller next day, on receipt of a little lace-edged sheet of note paper, “Favoured by papa. To remind;” and passed the intervening period in a state of dotage.</p><p >I think I committed every possible absurdity, in the way of preparation for this blessed event. I turn hot when I remember the cravat I bought. My boots might be placed in any collection of instruments of torture. I provided, and sent down by the Norwood coach the night before, a
<pb xml:id="p340"/>
delicate little hamper, amounting in itself, I thought, almost to a declaration. There were crackers in it with the tenderest mottos that could be got for money. At six in the morning, I was in Covent Garden Market, buying a bouquet for Dora. At ten I was on horseback (I hired a gallant grey, for the occasion), with the bouquet in my hat, to keep it fresh, trotting down to Norwood.</p><p >I suppose that when I saw Dora in the garden and pretended not to see her, and rode past the house pretending to be anxiously looking for it, I committed two small fooleries which other young gentlemen in my circumstances might have committed—because they came so very natural to me. But oh! when I <hi rend="italics">did</hi> find the house, and <hi rend="italics">did</hi> dismount at the garden gate, and drag those stoney-hearted boots across the lawn to Dora sitting on a garden seat under a lilac tree, what a spectacle she was, upon that beautiful morning, among the butterflies, in a white chip bonnet and a dress of celestial blue!</p><p >There was a young lady with her—comparatively stricken in years—almost twenty, I should say. Her name was Miss Mills, and Dora called her Julia. She was the bosom friend of Dora. Happy Miss Mills!</p><p >Jip was there, and Jip <hi rend="italics">would</hi> bark at me again. When I presented my bouquet, he gnashed his teeth with jealousy. Well he might. If he had the least idea how I adored his mistress, well he might!</p><p >“Oh, thank you, Mr. Copperfield! What dear flowers!” said Dora.</p><p >I had had an intention of saying (and had been studying the best form of words for three miles) that I thought them beautiful before I saw them so near <hi rend="italics">her.</hi> But I couldn't manage it. She was too bewildering. To see her lay the flowers against her little dimpled chin, was to lose all presence of mind and power of language in a feeble ecstacy. I wonder I didn't say, “Kill me, if you have a heart, Miss Mills. Let me die here!”</p><p >Then Dora held my flowers to Jip to smell. Then Jip growled, and wouldn't smell them. Then Dora laughed, and held them a little closer to Jip, to make him. Then Jip laid hold of a bit of geranium with his teeth, and worried imaginary cats in it. Then Dora beat him, and pouted, and said, “My poor beautiful flowers!” as compassionately, I thought, as if Jip and laid hold of me. I wished he had!</p><p >“You'll be so glad to hear, Mr. Copperfield,” said Dora, “that that cross Miss Murdstone is not here. She has gone to her brother's marriage, and will be away at least three weeks. Isn't that delightful?”</p><p >I said I was sure it must be delightful to her, and all that was delightful to her was delightful to me. Miss Mills, with an air of superior wisdom and benevolence, smiled upon us.</p><p >“She is the most disagreeable thing I ever saw,” said Dora. “You can't believe how ill-tempered and shocking she is, Julia.”</p><p >“Yes, I can, my dear!” said Julia.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">You</hi> can, perhaps, love,” returned Dora, with her hand on Julia's. “Forgive my not excepting you, my dear, at first.”</p><p >I learnt, from this, that Miss Mills had had her trials in the course of a chequered existence; and that to these, perhaps, I might refer that wise benignity of manner which I had already noticed. I found, in the course
<pb xml:id="p341"/>
of the day, that this was the case: Miss Mills having been unhappy in a misplaced affection, and being understood to have retired from the world on her awful stock of experience, but still to take a calm interest in the unblighted hopes and loves of youth.</p><p >But now Mr. Spenlow came out of the house, and Dora went to him, saying, “Look, papa, what beautiful flowers!” And Miss Mills smiled thoughtfully, as who should say, “Ye May-flies, enjoy your brief existence in the bright morning of life!” And we all walked from the lawn towards the carriage, which was getting ready.</p><p >I shall never have such a ride again. I have never had such another. There were only those three, their hamper, my hamper, and the guitarcase, in the phaeton; and, of course, the phaeton was open; and I rode behind it, and Dora sat with her back to the horses, looking towards me. She kept the bouquet close to her on the cushion, and wouldn't allow Jip to sit on that side of her at all, for fear he should crush it. She often carried it in her hand, often refreshed herself with its fragrance. Our eyes at those times often met; and my great astonishment is that I didn't go over the head of my gallant grey into the carriage.</p><p >There was dust, I believe. There was a good deal of dust, I believe. I have a faint impression that Mr. Spenlow remonstrated with me for riding in it; but I knew of none. I was sensible of a mist of love and beauty about Dora, but of nothing else. He stood up sometimes, and asked me what I thought of the prospect. I said it was delightful, and I daresay it was; but it was all Dora to me. The sun shone Dora, and the birds sang Dora. The south wind blew Dora, and the wild flowers in the hedges were all Doras, to a bud. My comfort is, Miss Mills understood me. Miss Mills alone could enter into my feelings thoroughly.</p><p >I don't know how long we were going, and to this hour I know as little where we went. Perhaps it was near Guildford. Perhaps some Arabian-night magician, opened up the place for the day, and shut it for ever when we came away. It was a green spot, on a hill, carpeted with soft turf. There were shady trees, and heather, and, as far as the eye could see, a rich landscape.</p><p >It was a trying thing to find people here, waiting for us; and my jealously, even of the ladies, knew no bounds. But all of my own sex—especially one impostor, three or four years my elder, with a red whisker, on which he established an amount of presumption not be endured—were my mortal foes.</p><p >We all unpacked our baskets, and employed ourselves in getting dinner ready. Red Whisker pretended he could make a salad (which I don't believe), and obtruded himself on public notice. Some of the young ladies washed the lettuces for him, and sliced them under his directions. Dora was among these. I felt that fate had pitted me against this man, and one of us must fall.</p><p >Red Whisker made his salad (I wondered how they could eat it. Nothing should have induced <hi rend="italics">me</hi> to touch it!) and voted himself into the charge of the wine-cellar, which he constructed, being an ingenious beast, in the hollow trunk of a tree. By-and-by I saw him, with the majority of a lobster on his plate, eating his dinner at the feet of Dora!</p><p >I have but an indistinct idea of what happened for some time after this
<pb xml:id="p342"/>
baleful object presented itself to my view. I was very merry, I know; but it was hollow merriment. I attached myself to a young creature in pink, with little eyes, and flirted with her desperately. She received my attentions with favour; but whether on my account solely, or because she had any designs on Red Whisker, I can't say. Dora's health was drunk. When I drank it, I affected to interrupt my conversation for that purpose, and to resume it immediately afterwards. I caught Dora's eye as I bowed to her, and I thought it looked appealing. But it looked at me over the head of Red Whisker, and I was adamant.</p><p >The young creature in pink had a mother in green; and I rather think the latter separated us from motives of policy. Howbeit, there was a general breaking up of the party, while the remnants of the dinner were being put away; and I strolled off by myself among the trees, in a raging and remorseful state. I was debating whether I should pretend that I was not well, and fly—I don't know where—upon my gallant grey, when Dora and Miss Mills met me.</p><p >“Mr. Copperfield,” said Miss Mills, “you are dull.”</p><p >I begged her pardon. Not at all.</p><p >“And, Dora,” said Miss Mills, “<hi rend="italics">you</hi> are dull.”</p><p >Oh dear no! Not in the least.</p><p >“Mr. Copperfield and Dora,” said Miss Mills, with an almost venerable air. “Enough of this. Do not allow a trivial misunderstanding to wither the blossoms of spring, which, once put forth and blighted, can not be renewed. I speak,” said Miss Mills, “from experience of the past—the remote irrevocable past. The gushing fountains which sparkle in the sun, must not be stopped in mere caprice; the oasis in the desert of Sahara, must not be plucked up idly.”</p><p >I hardly knew what I did, I was burning all over to that extraordinary extent; but I took Dora's little hand and kissed it—and she let me! I kissed Miss Mills's hand; and we all seemed, to my thinking, to go straight up to the seventh heaven.</p><p >We did not come down again. We stayed up there all the evening. At first we strayed to and fro among the trees: I with Dora's shy arm drawn through mine: and Heaven knows, folly as it all was, it would have been a happy fate to have been struck immortal with those foolish feelings, and have strayed among the trees for ever!</p><p >But, much too soon, we heard the others laughing and talking, and calling “where's Dora!” So we went back, and they wanted Dora to sing. Red Whisker would have got the guitar-case out of the carriage, but Dora told him nobody knew where it was, but I. So Red Whisker was done for in a moment; and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> got it, and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> unlocked it, and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> took the guitar out, and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> sat by her, and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> held her handkerchief and gloves, and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> drank in every note of her dear voice, and she sang to <hi rend="italics">me</hi> who loved her, and all the others might applaud as much as they liked, but they had nothing to do with it!</p><p >I was intoxicated with joy. I was afraid it was too happy to be real, and that I should wake in Buckingham Street presently, and hear Mrs. Crupp clinking the teacups in getting breakfast ready. But Dora sang, and others sang, and Miss Mills sang—about the slumbering echoes in the caverns of Memory; as if she were a hundred years old—and the
<pb xml:id="p343"/>
evening came on; and we had tea, with a kettle boiling gipsy-fashion; and I was stili as happy as ever.</p><p >I was happier than ever when the party broke up, and the other people, defeated Red Whisker and all, went their several ways, and we went ours through the still evening and the dying light, with sweet scents rising up around us. Mr. Spenlow being a little drowsy after the champagne—honour to the soil that grew the grape, to the grape that made the wine, to the sun that ripened it, and to the merchant who adulterated it!—and being fast asleep in a corner of the carriage, I rode by the side, and talked to Dora. She admired my horse and patted him—oh, what a dear little hand it looked upon a horse!—and her shawl would not keep right, and now and then I drew it round her with my arm; and I even fancied that Jip began to see how it was, and to understand that he must make up his mind to be friends with me.</p><p >That sagacious Miss Mills, too; that amiable, though quite used up, recluse; that little patriarch of something less than twenty, who had done with the world, and mustn't on any account have the slumbering echoes in the caverns of Memory awakened; what a kind thing <hi rend="italics">she</hi> did!</p><p >“Mr. Copperfield,” said Miss Mills, “come to this side of the carriage a moment—if you can spare a moment. I want to speak to you.”</p><p >Behold me, on my gallant grey, bending at the side of Miss Mills, with my hand upon the carriage-door!</p><p >“Dora is coming to stay with me. She is coming home with me the day after to-morrow. If you would like to call, I am sure papa would be happy to see you.”</p><p >What could I do but invoke a silent blessing on Miss Mills's head, and store Miss Mills's address in the securest corner of my memory! What could I do but tell Miss Mills, with grateful looks and fervent words, how much I appreciated her good offices, and what an inestimable value I set upon her friendship!</p><p >Then Miss Mills benignantly dismissed me, saying, “Go back to Dora!” and I went; and Dora leaned out of the carriage to talk to me, and we talked all the rest of the way; and I rode my gallant grey so close to the wheel that I grazed his near fore leg against it, and “took the bark off,” as his owner told me, “to the tune of three pun' sivin”—which I paid, and thought extremely cheap for so much joy. What time Miss Mills sat looking at the moon, murmuring verses and recalling, I suppose, the ancient days when she and earth had anything in common.</p><p >Norwood was many miles too near, and we reached it many hours too soon; but Mr. Spenlow came to himself a little short of it, and said, “You must come in, Copperfield, and rest!” and I consenting, we had sandwiches and wine-and-water. In the light room, Dora blushing looked so lovely, that I could not tear myself away, but sat there staring, in a dream, until the snoring of Mr. Spenlow inspired me with sufficient consciousness to take my leave. So we parted; I riding all the way to London with the farewell touch of Dora's hand still light on mine, recalling every incident and word ten thousand times; lying down in my own bed at last, as enraptured a young noodle as ever was carried out of his five wits by love.</p><p >When I awoke next morning, I was resolute to declare my passion
<pb xml:id="p344"/>
to Dora, and know my fate. Happiness or misery was now the question. There was no other question that I knew of in the world, and only Dora could give the answer to it. I passed three days in a luxury of wretchedness, torturing myself by putting every conceivable variety of discouraging construction on all that ever had taken place between Dora and me. At last, arrayed for the purpose at a vast expense, I went to Miss Mills's, fraught with a declaration.</p><p >How many times I went up and down the street, and round the square—painfully aware of being a much better answer to the old riddle than the original one—before I could persuade myself to go up the steps and knock, is no matter now. Even when, at last, I had knocked, and was waiting at the door, I had some flurried thought of asking if that were Mr. Blackboy's (in imitation of poor Barkis), begging pardon, and retreating. But I kept my ground.</p><p >Mr. Mills was not at home. I did not expect he would be. Nobody wanted <hi rend="italics">him.</hi> Miss Mills was at home. Miss Mills would do.</p><p >I was shown into a room upstairs, where Miss Mills and Dora were. Jip was there. Miss Mills was copying music (I recollect, it was a new song, called Affection's Dirge), and Dora was painting flowers. What were my feelings, when I recognised my own flowers; the identical Covent Garden Market purchase! I cannot say that they were very like, or that they particularly resembled any flowers that have ever come under my observation; but I knew from the paper round them, which was accurately copied, what the composition was.</p><p >Miss Mills was very glad to see me, and very sorry her Papa was not at home: though I thought we all bore that with fortitude. Miss Mills was conversational for a few minutes, and then, laying down her pen upon Affection's Dirge, got up, and left the room.</p><p >I began to think I would put it off till to-morrow.</p><p >“I hope your poor horse was not tired, when he got home at night,” said Dora, lifting up her beautiful eyes. “It was a long way for him.”</p><p >I began to think I would do it to-day.</p><p >“It was a long way for <hi rend="italics">him,</hi>” said I, “for <hi rend="italics">he</hi> had nothing to uphold him on the journey.”</p><p >“Wasn't he fed, poor thing?” asked Dora.</p><p >I began to think I would put it off till to-morrow.</p><p >“Ye—yes,” I said, “he was well taken care of. I mean he had not the unutterable happiness that I had in being so near you.”</p><p >Dora bent her head over her drawing, and said, after a little while—I had sat, in the interval, in a burning fever, and with my legs in a very rigid state—</p><p >“You didn't seem to be sensible of that happiness yourself, at one time of the day.”</p><p >I saw now that I was in for it, and it must be done on the spot.</p><p >“You didn't care for that happiness in the least,” said Dora, slightly raising her eyebrows, and shaking her head, “when you were sitting by Miss Kitt.”</p><p >Kitt, I should observe, was the name of the creature in pink, with the little eyes.</p><p >“Though certainly I don't know why you should,” said Dora, “or why
<pb xml:id="p345"/>
you should call it a happiness at all. But of course you don't mean what you say. And I am sure no one doubts your being at liberty to do whatever you like. Jip, you naughty boy, come here!”</p><p >I don't know how I did it. I did it in a moment. I intercepted Jip. I had Dora in my arms. I was full of eloquence. I never stopped for a word. I told her how I loved her. I told her I should die without her. I told her that I idolised and worshipped her. Jip barked madly all the time.</p><p >When Dora hung her head and cried, and trembled, my eloquence increased so much the more. If she would like me to die for her, she had but to say the word, and I was ready. Life without Dora's love was not a thing to have on any terms. I couldn't bear it, and I wouldn't. I had loved her every minute, day and night, since I first saw her. I loved her at that minute to distraction. I should always love her, every minute, to distraction. Lovers had loved before, and lovers would love again; but no lover had ever loved, might, could, would, or should ever love, as I loved Dora. The more I raved, the more Jip barked. Each of us, in his own way, got more mad every moment.</p><p >Well, well! Dora and I were sitting on the sofa by-and-by, quiet enough, and Jip was lying in her lap, winking peacefully at me. It was off my mind. I was in a state of perfect rapture. Dora and I were engaged.</p><p >I suppose we had some notion that this was to end in marriage. We must have had some, because Dora stipulated that we were never to be married without her papa's consent. But, in our youthful ecstacy, I don't think that we really looked before us or behind us; or had any aspiration beyond the ignorant present. We were to keep our secret from Mr. Spenlow; but I am sure the idea never entered my head, then, that there was anything dishonorable in that.</p><p >Miss Mills was more than usually pensive when Dora, going to find her, brought her back;—I apprehend, because there was a tendency in what had passed to awaken the slumbering echoes in the caverns of memory. But she gave us her blessing, and the assurance of her lasting friendship, and spoke to us, generally, as became a Voice from the Cloister.</p><p >What an idle time it was! What an unsubstantial, happy, foolish time it was!</p><p >When I measured Dora's finger for a ring that was to be made of Forget-me-nots, and when the jeweller, to whom I took the measure, found me out, and laughed over his order book, and charged me anything he liked, for the pretty little toy, with its blue stones—so associated in my remembrance with Dora's hand, that yesterday, when I saw such another, by chance, on the finger of my own daughter, there was a momentary stirring in my heart, like pain!</p><p >When I walked about, exalted with my secret, and full of my own interest, and felt the dignity of loving Dora, and of being beloved, so much, that if I had walked the air, I could not have been more above the people not so situated, who were creeping on the earth!</p><p >When we had those meetings in the garden of the square, and sat within the dingy summer-house, so happy, that I love the London sparrows to this hour, for nothing else, and see the plumage of the tropics in their smoky feathers!</p><pb  xml:id="p346"/><p >When we had our first great quarrel (within a week of our betrothal), and when Dora sent me back the ring, enclosed in a despairing cockedhat note, wherein she used the terrible expression that “our love had begun in folly, and ended in madness!” which dreadful words occasioned me to tear my hair, and cry that all was over!</p><p >When, under cover of the night, I flew to Miss Mills, whom I saw by stealth in a back kitchen where there was a mangle, and implored Miss Mills to interpose between us and avert insanity. When Miss Mills undertook the office and returned with Dora, exhorting us, from the pulpit of her own bitter youth, to mutual concession, and the avoidance of the Desert of Sahara!</p><p >When we cried, and made it up, and were so blest again, that the back-kitchen, mangle and all, changed to Love's own temple, where we arranged a plan of correspondence through Miss Mills, always to comprehend at least one letter on each side every day!</p><p >What an idle time! What an unsubstantial, happy, foolish time! Of all the times of mine that Time has in his grip, there is none that in one retrospection I can smile at half so much, and think of half so tenderly.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXIV. <lb/> MY AUNT ASTONISHES ME.</head><p >I WROTE to Agnes as soon as Dora and I were engaged. I wrote her a long letter, in which I tried to make her comprehend how blest I was, and what a darling Dora was. I entreated Agnes not to regard this as a thoughtless passion which could ever yield to any other, or had the least resemblance to the boyish fancies that we used to joke about. I assured her that its profundity was quite unfathomable, and expressed my belief that nothing like it had ever been known.</p><p >Somehow, as I wrote to Agnes on a fine evening by my open window, and the remembrance of her clear calm eyes and gentle face came stealing over me, it shed such a peaceful influence upon the hurry and agitation in which I had been living lately, and of which my very happiness partook in some degree, that it soothed me into tears. I remember that I sat resting my head upon my hand, when the letter was half done, cherishing a general fancy as if Agnes were one of the elements of my natural home. As if, in the retirement of the house made almost sacred to me by her presence, Dora and I must be happier than anywhere. As if, in love, joy, sorrow, hope, or disappointment; in all emotions; my heart turned naturally there, and found its refuge and best friend.</p><p >Of Steerforth, I said nothing. I only told her there had been sad grief at Yarmouth, on account of Emily's flight; and that on me it made a
<pb xml:id="p347"/>
double wound, by reason of the circumstances attending it. I knew how quick she always was to divine the truth, and that she would never be the first to breathe his name.</p><p >To this letter, I received an answer by return of post. As I read it, I seemed to hear Agnes speaking to me. It was like her cordial voice in my ears. What can I say more!</p><p >While I had been away from home lately, Traddles had called twice or thrice. Finding Peggotty within, and being informed by Peggotty (who always volunteered that information to whomsoever would receive it), that she was my old nurse, he had established a good-humoured acquaintance with her, and had stayed to have a little chat with her about me. So Peggotty said; but I am afraid the chat was all on her own side, and of immoderate length, as she was very difficult indeed to stop, God bless her! when she had me for her theme.</p><p >This reminds me, not only that I expected Traddles on a certain afternoon of his own appointing, which was now come, but that Mrs. Crupp had resigned everything appertaining to her office (the salary excepted) until Peggotty should cease to present herself. Mrs. Crupp, after holding divers conversations respecting Peggotty, in a very high pitched voice, on the staircase—with some invisible Familiar it would appear, for corporeally speaking she was quite alone at those times—addressed a letter to me, developing her views. Beginning it with that statement of universal application, which fitted every occurrence of her life, namely, that she was a mother herself, she went on to inform me that she had once seen very different days, but that at all periods of her existence she had had a constitutional objection to spies, intruders, and informers. She named no names, she said; let them the cap fitted, wear it; but spies, intruders, and informers, especially in widders' weeds (this clause was underlined), she had ever accustomed herself to look down upon. If a gentleman was the victim of spies, intruders, and informers (but still naming no names), that was his own pleasure. He had a right to please himself; so let him do. All that she, Mrs. Crupp, stipulated for, was, that she should not be “brought in contract” with such persons. Therefore she begged to be excused from any further attendance on the top set, until things was as they formerly was, and as they could be wished to be; and further mentioned that her little book would be found upon the breakfast-table every Saturday morning, when she requested an immediate settlement of the same, with the benevolent view of saving trouble, “and an ill-conwenience” to all parties.</p><p >After this, Mrs. Crupp confined herself to making pitfalls on the stairs, principally with pitchers, and endeavouring to delude Peggotty into breaking her legs. I found it rather harassing to live in this state of siege, but was too much afraid of Mrs. Crupp to see any way out of it.</p><p >“My dear Copperfield,” cried Traddles, punctually appearing at my door, in spite of all these obstacles, “how do you do?”</p><p >“My dear Traddles,” said I, “I am delighted to see you at last, and very sorry I have not been at home before. But I have been so much engaged—”</p><p >“Yes, yes, I know,” said Traddles, “of course. Your's lives in London, I think.”</p><pb  xml:id="p348"/><p >“What did you say?”</p><p >“She—excuse me—Miss D., you know,” said Traddles, colouring in his great delicacy, “lives in London, I believe?”</p><p >“Oh yes. Near London.”</p><p >“Mine, perhaps you recollect,” said Traddles, with a serious look, “lives down in Devonshire—one of ten. Consequently, I am not so much engaged as you—in that sense.”</p><p >“I wonder you can bear,” I returned, “to see her so seldom.”</p><p >“Hah!” said Traddles, thoughtfully. “It does seem a wonder. I suppose it is, Copperfield, because there's no help for it?”</p><p >“I suppose so,” I replied, with a smile, and not without a blush. “And because you have so much constancy and patience, Traddles.”</p><p >“Dear me!” said Traddles, considering about it, “do I strike you in that way, Copperfield? Really I didn't know that I had. But she is such an extraordinarily dear girl herself, that it's possible she may have imparted something of those virtues to me. Now you mention it, Copperfield, I shouldn't wonder at all. I assure you she is always forgetting herself, and taking care of the other nine.”</p><p >“Is she the eldest?” I inquired.</p><p >“Oh dear, no,” said Traddles. “The eldest is a Beauty.”</p><p >He saw, I suppose, that I could not help smiling at the simplicity of this reply; and added, with a smile upon his own ingenuous face:</p><p >“Not, of course, but that my Sophy—pretty name, Copperfield, I always think?”</p><p >“Very pretty!” said I.</p><p >“Not, of course, but that Sophy is beautiful too, in my eyes, and would be one of the dearest girls that ever was, in anybody's eyes (I should think). But when I say the eldest is a Beauty, I mean she really is a—” he seemed to be describing clouds about himself, with both hands: “Splendid, you know,” said Traddles, energetically.</p><p >“Indeed!” said I.</p><p >“Oh, I assure you,” said Traddles, “something very uncommon, indeed! Then, you know, being formed for society and admiration, and not being able to enjoy much of it, in consequence of their limited means, she naturally gets a little irritable and exacting, sometimes. Sophy puts her in good humour!”</p><p >“Is Sophy the youngest?” I hazarded.</p><p >“Oh dear, no!” said Traddles, stroking his chin. “The two youngest are only nine and ten. Sophy educates 'em.”</p><p >“The second daughter, perhaps?” I hazarded.</p><p >“No,” said Traddles. “Sarah's the second. Sarah has something the matter with her spine, poor girl. The malady will wear out by-and-by, the doctors say, but in the meantime she has to lie down for a twelvemonth. Sophy nurses her. Sophy's the fourth.”</p><p >“Is the mother living?” I inquired.</p><p >“Oh yes,” said Traddles, “she is alive. She is a very superior woman, indeed, but the damp country is not adapted to her constitution, and—in fact, she has lost the use of her limbs.”</p><p >“Dear me!” said I.</p><p >“Very sad, is it not?” returned Traddles. “But in a merely domestic
<pb xml:id="p349"/>
view it is not so bad as it might be, because Sophy takes her place. She is quite as much a mother <hi rend="italics">to</hi> her mother, as she is to the other nine.”</p><p >I felt the greatest admiration for the virtues of this young lady; and, honestly with the view of doing my best to prevent the good-nature of Traddles from being imposed upon, to the detriment of their joint prospects in life, inquired how Mr. Micawber was?</p><p >“He is quite well, Copperfield, thank you,” said Traddles. “I am not living with him at present.”</p><p >“No?”</p><p >“No. You see the truth is,” said Traddles, in a whisper, “he has changed his name to Mortimer, in consequence of his temporary embarrassments; and he don't come out till after dark—and then in spectacles. There was an execution put into our house, for rent. Mrs. Micawber was in such a dreadful state that I really couldn't resist giving my name to that second bill we spoke of here. You may imagine how delightful it was to my feelings, Copperfield, to see the matter settled with it, and Mrs. Micawber recover her spirits.”</p><p >“Hum!” said I.</p><p >“Not that her happiness was of long duration,” pursued Traddles, “for, unfortunately, within a week another execution came in. It broke up the establishment. I have been living in a furnished apartment since then, and the Mortimers have been very private indeed. I hope you won't think it selfish, Copperfield, if I mention that the broker carried off my little round table with the marble top, and Sophy's flower-pot and stand?”</p><p >“What a hard thing!” I exclaimed indignantly.</p><p >“It was a—it was a pull,” said Traddles, with his usual wince at that expression. “I don't mention it reproachfully, however, but with a motive. The fact is, Copperfield, I was unable to repurchase them at the time of their seizure; in the first place, because the broker, having an idea that I wanted them, ran the price up to an extravagant extent; and, in the second place, because I—hadn't any money. Now, I have kept my eye since, upon the broker's shop,” said Traddles, with a great enjoyment of his mystery, “which is up at the top of Tottenham Court Road, and, at last, to-day I find them put out for sale. I have only noticed them from over the way, because if the broker saw <hi rend="italics">me,</hi> bless you, he'd ask any price for them! What has occurred to me, having now the money, is, that perhaps you wouldn't object to ask that good nurse of yours to come with me to the shop—I can show it her from round the corner of the next street—and make the best bargain for them, as if they were for herself, that she can!”</p><p >The delight with which Traddles propounded this plan to me, and the sense he had of its uncommon artfulness, are among the freshest things in my remembrance.</p><p >I told him that my old nurse would be delighted to assist him, and that we would all three take the field together, but on one condition. That condition was, that he should make a solemn resolution to grant no more loans of his name, or anything else, to Mr. Micawber.</p><p >“My dear Copperfield,” said Traddles, “I have already done so, because I begin to feel that I have not only been inconsiderate, but that I have been positively unjust to Sophy. My word being passed to myself,
<pb xml:id="p350"/>
there is no longer any apprehension; but I pledge it to you, too, with the greatest readiness. That first unlucky obligation, I have paid. I have no doubt Mr. Micawber would have paid it if he could, but he could not. One thing I ought to mention, which I like very much in Mr. Micawber, Copperfield. It refers to the second obligation, which is not yet due. He don't tell me that it <hi rend="italics">is</hi> provided for, but he says it <hi rend="italics">will be.</hi> Now, I think there is something very fair and honest about that!”</p><p >I was unwilling to damp my good friend's confidence, and therefore assented. After a little further conversation, we went round to the chandler's shop, to enlist Peggotty; Traddles declining to pass the evening with me, both because he endured the liveliest apprehensions that his property would be bought by somebody else before he could re-purchase it, and because it was the evening he always devoted to writing to the dearest girl in the world.</p><p >I never shall forget him peeping round the corner of the street in Tottenham Court Road, while Peggotty was bargaining for the precious articles; or his agitation when she came slowly towards us after vainly offering a price, and was hailed by the relenting broker, and went back again. The end of the negotiation was, that she bought the property on tolerably easy terms, and Traddles was transported with pleasure.</p><p >“I am very much obliged to you, indeed,” said Traddles, on hearing it was to be sent to where he lived, that night. “If I might ask one other favor, I hope you wouldn't think it absurd, Copperfield?”</p><p >I said beforehand, certainly not.</p><p >“Then if you <hi rend="italics">would</hi> be good enough,” said Traddles to Peggotty, “to get the flower-pot now, I think I should like (it being Sophy's, Copperfield) to carry it home myself!”</p><p >Peggotty was glad to get it for him, and he overwhelmed her with thanks, and went his way up Tottenham Court Road, carrying the flowerpot affectionately in his arms, with one of the most delighted expressions of countenance I ever saw.</p><p >We then turned back towards my chambers. As the shops had charms for Peggotty which I never knew them possess in the same degree for anybody else, I sauntered easily along, amused by her staring in at the windows, and waiting for her as often as she chose. We were thus a good while in getting to the Adelphi.</p><p >On our way upstairs, I called her attention to the sudden disappearance of Mrs. Crupp's pitfalls, and also to the prints of recent footsteps. We were both very much surprised, coming higher up, to find my outer door standing open (which I had shut), and to hear voices inside.</p><p >We looked at one another, without knowing what to make of this, and went into the sitting-room. What was my amazement to find, of all people upon earth, my aunt there, and Mr. Dick! My aunt sitting on a quantity of luggage, with her two birds before her, and her cat on her knee, like a female Robinson Crusoe, drinking tea. Mr. Dick leaning thoughtfully on a great kite, such as we had often been out together to fly, with more luggage piled about him!</p><p >“My dear aunt!” cried I. “Why, what an unexpected pleasure!”</p><p >We cordially embraced; and Mr. Dick and I cordially shook hands; and Mrs. Crupp, who was busy making tea, and could not be too attentive,
<pb xml:id="p351"/>
cordially said she had knowed well as Mr. Copperfull would have his heart in his mouth, when he see his dear relations.</p><p >“Halloa!” said my aunt to Peggotty, who quailed before her awful presence. “How are <hi rend="italics">you?</hi>”</p><p >“You remember my aunt, Peggotty?” said I.</p><p >“For the love of goodness, child,” exclaimed my aunt, “don't call the woman by that South Sea Island name! If she married and got rid of it, which was the best thing she could do, why don't you give her the benefit of the change? What's your name now,—P?” said my aunt, as a compromise for the obnoxious appellation.</p><p >“Barkis, ma'am,” said Peggotty, with a curtsey.</p><p >“Well! that's human,” said my aunt. “It sounds less as if you wanted a Missionary. How d'ye do, Barkis? I hope you're well?”</p><p >Encouraged by these gracious words, and by my aunt's extending her hand, Barkis came forward, and took the hand, and curtseyed her acknowledgments.</p><p >“We are older than we were, I see,” said my aunt. “We have only met each other once before, you know. A nice business we made of it then! Trot, my dear, another cup.”</p><p >I handed it dutifully to my aunt, who was in her usual inflexible state of figure; and ventured a remonstrance with her on the subject of her sitting on a box.</p><p >“Let me draw the sofa here, or the easy chair, aunt,” said I. “Why should you be so uncomfortable?”</p><p >“Thank you, Trot,” replied my aunt, “I prefer to sit upon my property.” Here my aunt looked hard at Mrs. Crupp, and observed, “We needn't trouble you to wait, ma'am.”</p><p >“Shall I put a little more tea in the pot afore I go, ma'am?” said Mrs. Crupp.</p><p >“No, I thank you, ma'am,” replied my aunt.</p><p >“Would you let me fetch another pat of butter, ma'am?” said Mrs. Crupp. “Or would you be persuaded to try a new-laid hegg? or should I brile a rasher? Ain't there nothing I could do for your dear aunt, Mr. Copperfull?”</p><p >“Nothing, ma'am,” returned my aunt. “I shall do very well, I thank you.”</p><p >Mrs. Crupp, who had been incessantly smiling to express sweet temper, and incessantly holding her head on one side, to express a general feebleness of constitution, and incessantly rubbing her hands, to express a desire to be of service to all deserving objects, gradually smiled herself, one-sided herself, and rubbed herself, out of the room.</p><p >“Dick!” said my aunt. “You know what I told you about time-servers and wealth-worshippers?”</p><p >Mr. Dick—with rather a scared look, as if he had forgotten it—returned a hasty answer in the affirmative.</p><p >“Mrs. Crupp is one of them,” said my aunt. “Barkis, I'll trouble you to look after the tea, and let me have another cup, for I don't fancy that woman's pouring-out!”</p><p >I knew my aunt sufficiently well to know that she had something of importance on her mind, and that there was far more matter in this
<pb xml:id="p352"/>
arrival than a stranger might have supposed. I noticed how her eye lighted on me, when she thought my attention otherwise occupied; and what a curious process of hesitation appeared to be going on within her, while she preserved her outward stiffness and composure. I began to reflect whether I had done anything to offend her; and my conscience whispered me that I had not yet told her about Dora. Could it by any means be that, I wondered!</p><p >As I knew she would only speak in her own good time, I sat down near her, and spoke to the birds, and played with the cat, and was as easy as I could be. But I was very far from being really easy; and I should still have been so, even if Mr. Dick, leaning over the great kite behind my aunt, had not taken every secret opportunity of shaking his head darkly at me, and pointing at her.</p><p >“Trot,” said my aunt at last, when she had finished her tea, and carefully smoothed down her dress, and wiped her lips—“you needn't go, Barkis!—Trot, have you got to be firm, and self-reliant?”</p><p >“I hope so, aunt.”</p><p >“What do you think?” inquired Miss Betsey.</p><p >“I think so, aunt.”</p><p >“Then why, my love,” said my aunt, looking earnestly at me, “why do you think I prefer to sit upon this property of mine to-night?”</p><p >I shook my head, unable to guess.</p><p >“Because,” said my aunt, “it's all I have. Because I'm ruined, my dear!”</p><p >If the house, and every one of us, had tumbled out into the river together, I could hardly have received a greater shock.</p><p >“Dick knows it,” said my aunt, laying her hand calmly on my shoulder. “I am ruined, my dear Trot! All I have in the world is in this room, except the cottage; and that I have left Janet to let. Barkis, I want to get a bed for this gentleman to-night. To save expense, perhaps you can make up something here for myself. Anything will do. It's only for to-night. We'll talk about this, more, to-morrow.”</p><p >I was roused from my amazement, and concern for her—I am sure, for her—by her falling on my neck, for a moment, and crying that she only grieved for me. In another moment, she suppressed this emotion; and said with an aspect more triumphant than dejected:</p><p >“We must meet reverses boldly, and not suffer them to frighten us, my dear. We must learn to act the play out. We must live misfortune down, Trot!”</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><head >A SKETCH FOR <gap reason="illegible"/></head><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">How cheering is the dawn of Spring!</l><l part="N">What happy thoughts its moments bring;</l><l part="N">The balmy freshness of its breeze,</l><l part="N">The welcome budding of the trees,</l><l part="N">The sun beams peeping from the cloud</l><l part="N">Which lately formed a snowy shroud,</l><l part="N">The opening flower, the warbling bird,</l><l part="N">Are gladly seen and gladly heard.</l><l part="N">Not only in the country-scene</l><l part="N">Has spring its charms—where all is green—</l><l part="N">But in the town and City, too,</l><l part="N">A change in every thing we view.</l><l part="N">While all our hopes are on the wing</l><l part="N">To meet the welcome, smiling spring;</l><l part="N">But here a hint may be supplied,</l><l part="N">Cast not your winter dress aside.</l><l part="N">How often has the first fine day</l><l part="N">Caused people to be led astray!</l><l part="N">MOSES' will soon before you bring</l><l part="N">Their dresses for the coming spring.</l><l part="N">Meanwhile they'd have you not forget</l><l part="N">The clothing which they furnish yet.</l><l part="N">The cold March winds you all should shun</l><l part="N">With Wrappers made by M. &amp; SON.</l><l part="N">When next upon this printed sheet</l><l part="N">The name of MOSES' mart you meet,</l><l part="N">My muse will touch her trading lyre</l><l part="N">In praise of MOSES' spring attire,</l><l part="N">Which thousands buy and all admire.</l></lg></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><head>Ready Made.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Chesterfield, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome style of Overcoats </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Shooting Coat </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Lounging and Morning Coat </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Doeskin </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Vest </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Dress Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Frock </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Youth's and Boys' Overcoats in every style, from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Hussar and Tunic Suit </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Autumn and Winter Vests </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Made to Measure.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats, from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Black Cassimere Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Black Cloth </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Silk Velvet Best Black Cloth </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Dress Coats, from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Frock 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> H. and T. Suit, from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from £3 to £20.</p><p >NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p><p >MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The New Book, entitled “The Minion of the Million,” with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >NOTICE.—The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p><p >OBSERVE.—Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >E. MOSES &amp; SON,</head><p >TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p><p >ALL COMMUNICATING, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p><p >TAKE NOTICE.—This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2a"/><head >THE NICOLL PALETOT,</head><p >OR PATENT COAT; <lb/> And the original invention, the Registered Paletòt (6 and 7 Vic. cap. 65.) The West-end Warerooms for the sale of these graceful and useful articles of dress are in Regent-street, and extend from number 114 to number 120 inclusive; and those in the City are at 22, Cornhill, the shipping department being in the rear—viz., 'Change-alley. Many have assumed the use of the word paletòt, but H. J., and D. NICOLL are the sole Proprietors and Patentees of either design or material. The prices are one, two, and three guineas, and according to the climate or purpose for which they are required.</p><p >San Francisco from the south-west, sketched by <lb/> Willie &amp; Co., Agents in California for Messrs. NICOLL.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer></div></back></text></TEI>