<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XIII:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.   170K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XIII</title><author>Charles  Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> 50 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LONDON:BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher><date>1850</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p/></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords scheme="LCSH"><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-11-19"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-10-08">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_verso_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"> No.  XIII. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate> MAY.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docAuthor><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:—J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><epigraph ><p>Trouser Straps superseded by the DOUDNEY SPRING. 17, Old Bond Street, and 49, Lombard Street.</p></epigraph><head >FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS.</head><p >DOUDNEYS <lb/> Waterproofers, Habit Makers, and Tailors <lb/> TO QUEEN VICTORIA, QUEEN ADELAIDE, <lb/> H.R.H. Prince Albert, H.R.H. The Duchess of Kent, <lb/> KING LOUIS PHILIPPE, <lb/> And the ROYAL FAMILIES of ENGLAND and FRANCE.</p><p >The DOUDNEYS motto is “none but Good Articles can be cheap,” and with this ever in view, they have, by increasing efforts, established a Ready Money business of great extent among the strong holds of the old fashioned usurious Credit System. As to the character, and recommendatory influence of the approbation which has been bestowed upon their endeavours; let their Five Royal Appointments, and their Patronage Book filled with the Royal, Illustrious, and Noble names of their customers, testify.</p><p >The New Patterns for Spring and Summer wear are now ready for inspection at the Old Prices, so famous in seasons past, viz.:—Summer Waistcoats 7s. each, or 3 for 20s.—Summer Trousers 10s. 6d. per pair, or 3 for 30s.—Summer Coats, the beautiful light material 10s. 6d.—21s. and 30s.</p><p >The Queens Victoria and Adelaide, and the Royal and Noble Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge, Sutherland and Buccleuch, constantly wear Doudney's elegant Registered Cloak, in a variety of Waterproof, materials for Winter Wraps and the Promenade.—“Every Lady should see these graceful Garments.” <hi rend="italics">(Vide Morning Post, September</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">th.)</hi> They surpass all others for School Cloaks for the sons and daughters.</p><p >For Gentlemen.—The Royal Registered Cloak, as made for H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, the Nobility, the Army, and Navy, and all who study comfort, coupled with a truly Gentlemanly exterior. These cloaks are pronounced by those who understand the matter, “The most sensible Garment ever introduced,” at prices to suit all customers from the Superb down to the useful Guinea Cloak.</p><p >The New Patent Belt for Riding or general exercise, the only really effectual protection against rupture; the support commencing at the <hi rend="italics">bottom edge</hi> of the belt, and producing an uniform upward pressure. They may be enlarged or tightened to the extent of six inches at pleasure, and never produce indigestion either in Ladies or Gentlemen. They are attached to Drawers with excellent effect. The most eminent of the Faculty are recommending these in preference to all others.</p><p >LIVERIES. Three Guineas the Plain Suit of Best Quality. <hi rend="italics">Ready Money does it!!!</hi> and a very extensive practice among families of first distinction insures satisfactory results.</p><p >Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria and the Ladies of the Court. A Superfine Cloth Habit for 4 Guineas.</p><p >Waterproof Irish Poplin. The DOUDNEYS are the sole manufacturers of this beautiful article to HER MAJESTY AND THE PRINCE CONSORT. Gentlemen's Coats, Ladies Cloaks, and lengths for Dresses can be obtained only at their Establishment.</p><p >Country Gentlemen wishing to be Respectably Dressed at low Prices should send for a Book of detail, self-measurement and all the System of business, or if 3 or 4 Gentlemen unite, a Traveller will wait upon them.</p><closer >17, OLD BOND ST., 25, BURLINGTON ARCADE AND 49, LOMBARD STREET—Established 1784.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><head >New Illustrated Weekly Periodical for <lb/> Ladies.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Published every Thursday, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d., Stamped,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> AND IN MONTHLY PARTS, PRICE 1s. 2d.:</p><p >THE <lb/> LADIES' COMPANION, <lb/> EDITED <lb/> BY MRS. LOUDON.</p><p >THREE Parts of this Work are already published, and will form the best criterion of its merits. It may, however, be well to state that the literary portion contains papers on interesting subjects, by eminent writers, viz:—On Geology, by Professor ANSTED; On Household Chemistry, by Professor SOLLY; On Diet, by Dr. LANKESTER; On the Cultivation of the Voice, by Mr. FRANK ROMER; A Series of Papers by Professor TOM TAYLOR; Letters of the Ladies of England, by PETER CUNNINGHAM, &amp;c. &amp;c. Also, <lb/> A NEW TALE, <lb/> (Written expressly for the LADIES' COMPANION, and published weekly,) <lb/> LETTICE ARNOLD, <lb/> By the author of “Two Old Men's Tales,” “Emilia Wyndham,” &amp;c.; The Botany of Spring Flowers, with Illustrations,
<pb xml:id="p2"/>
by Mrs. LOUDON; Household Receipts, by Miss ACTON; the Emigrant, &amp;c. &amp;c., by DORA GRRENWELL; the Adventures of Carlo Franconi, by Mrs. J. WHITTLE; The Inexperienced Governess, by Mrs. TOMLINSON; the Business of the Garden, by Mrs. LOUDON; and numerous other Contributions on a variety of subjects incidental to in-door and out-door recreations for Ladies; together with much interesting Correspondence.</p><p >In addition to the higher character of Engravings occasionally given, it contains Illustrations of Work,—Berlin, Crochet, Embroidery, &amp;c. &amp;c.,—together with the Newest Fashions of every description.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Parts I., II. and III. are already published, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d. each.</hi></p><div type="advertisement"><head >Visit to the Exhibition of Ancient and <lb/> Mediæval Art.</head><p >With the Number for Saturday, April 13th, is published a SUPPLEMENT, containing upwards of <lb/> FIFTY ILLUSTRATIONS</p><p >Of the Rarest Specimens of Ancient and Mediæval Art.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d., Stamped,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><closer >Office, 11, Bouverie Street, and all Booksellers and Newsmen.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><opener >No. XIII.—MAY, 1850.</opener><head >COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head><div><head >WORKS BY MR. CHARLES DICKENS.</head><p >I. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In course of Publication in Monthly Parts, (to be completed in Twenty,) price One Shilling each.</hi></p><p >DAVID COPPERFIELD.</p><p >WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Thirteen Parts are now Published.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> Complete in One Thick Volume, 8vo, price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth, or 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> half bound in morocco, with Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE.</p><p >DOMBEY AND SON.</p><p >III. <lb/> In One Volume, demy 8vo. Price 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> uniform with “The Pickwick Papers,”</p><p >THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF OLIVER TWIST.</p><p >This Edition has been carefully corrected by the Author, throughout, and contains the whole of the Original Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p><p >IV. <lb/> PICTURES FROM ITALY.</p><p >SECOND EDITION. FCAP. 8vo. PRICE 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >In small 8vo. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, bound in cloth, with <lb/> gilt edges,</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Illustrations by D. Maclise, R.A., Clarkson Stanfield, R.A., Frank Stone, John Leech, John Tenniel, and Richard Doyle.</hi></p><p >A Christmas Carol. In Prose.</p><p >The Chimes. A Goblin Story of Some Bells that rang an Old Year Out, and a New Year In.</p><p >The Battle of Life. A Love Story.</p><p >The Cricket on the Hearth. A Fairy Tale of Home.</p><p >The Haunted Man and the Ghost's Bargain.</p><p >New Monthly Work on Gardening and Botany, Beautifully Illustrated.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">On the First of May was published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., No. III. of</hi>
<lb/> PAXTON'S FLOWER-GARDEN.</p><p >EDITED BY DR. LINDLEY AND JOSEPH PAXTON, <lb/> AND ILLUSTRATED BY HIGHLY FINISHED PLATES AND WOODCUTS.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div><p >Part IV. of THE LADIES' COMPANION, Edited by MRS. LOUDON, is published this day. This Part, having an extra Number, contains about ONE HUNDRED ILLUSTRATIONS, Fifty of which are DESIGNS IN ANCIENT AND MEDIÆVAL ART. Also, <lb/> A New Tale (“LETTICE ARNOLD”)</p><p >By the Author of “EMILIA WYNDHAM,” &amp;c. &amp;c.: and numerous Papers by eminent writers.</p><p >Price, with the Extra Number, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >THE LADIES' COMPANION is published in Weekly Numbers, price 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and in Monthly Parts, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Parts I., II., III., and IV., are now Ready.</p><closer >OFFICE, 11, <hi rend="italics">Bouverie Street.</hi></closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2a"/><head >A BIT OF MY MIND.</head><p >SEE PUNCH.</p><closer ><hi rend="italics">Office,</hi> 85, <hi rend="italics">Fleet Street.</hi></closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Second Edition, Enlarged, with Portrait of the Author; Cloth, Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >RUINS OF MANY LANDS.</head><p >A PILGRIMAGE. BY NICHOLAS MICHELL.</p><p >CONTENTS:—Babylon—Nineveh—Petra—Egypt—Ruined Cities of America—Rock-Temples of India—Athens—Rome—Pompeii—South of France—Carthage—Tyre—Baalbec—Palmyra—Persepolis—Jerusalem, &amp;c.</p><p >“This interesting and remarkable production must be deemed a standard composition wherever the English language is understood. It is an extraordinary volume.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser,</hi> Nov. 17, 1849.</p><p >“The author moves over all the celebrated ruins of the world. The volume evinces a profound acquaintance with ancient history; few will read the work without gleaning some new fact, and all will close it, determined to open it again.”—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Daily Mail,</hi> January 7, 1850.</p><p >“Ideas more refined, poetic beauties more richly developed, and classic knowledge more extensive, we scarcely remember to have seen. The work is most valuable.”—<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Independent Press,</hi> 24th Nov.</p><p >“Most heartily do we rejoice to see a second edition of Mr. Michell's remarkable work.”—<hi rend="italics">New Monthly Magazine.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG, and Co., 85, Queen Street, Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >On the 1st of May will be published, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><p >THE WHITE CHARGER, that cost me £200; lost me £70,000; drove me from society; eventually deprived me of my friends; and finally compelled me to quit the Service. By the author of “The Horse Guards,” “The Days when we had Tails on us,” &amp;c. With Two Coloured Illustrations, etched on Steel by ALFRED ASHLEY.</p><p >“Opportunities make us known to ourselves and others.”—<hi rend="italics">Rochefoucault.</hi></p><closer >London: J. &amp; D. A. DARLING, 126, Bishopsgate Street.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHEAP EDITION OF “JANE EYRE.”</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in One Vol. small Post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s. in embossed cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE FOURTH EDITION OF <lb/> JANE EYRE. BY CURRER BELL.</p><p >AUTHOR OF “SHIRLEY.”</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Nearly ready.</hi></p><p >THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF LEIGH HUNT.</p><p >In 3 Vols. Post 8vo, with Portraits.</p><closer >London: SMITH, ELDER &amp; CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Now ready, elegantly bound, in 1 vol., 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or free <lb/> by post, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >MISS BREMER'S EASTER OFFERING.</head><p >Comprising THE LIGHT HOUSE, a Domestic Story; and LIFE IN THE NORTH. Translated by MARY HOWITT. From the Unpublished Swedish Manuscript.</p><closer >HENRY COLBURN, Publisher, 13, Great Marlborough <lb/> Street.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BIBLES, PRAYER-BOOKS, &amp;c.</head><p >By Royal Letters Patent, LEIGHUON'S Herculeanised India Rubber binding, a peculiar preparation of caoutchoue used in place of glue, unites greatest flexibility with strength, opening with the greatest freedom and laying perfectly flat when open, the books used in the usual way. Sold by EYRE and SPOTTISWOODE. Fleet Street, and all booksellers and stationers. Manufactured by LEIGHTON and SON, Harp Alley, Shoe Lane, who apply this patent to all kinds of books; invaluable for music, ledgers, &amp;c. Please observe the names LEIGHTON &amp; SON inside each book, without which they are not genuine. Retail Agent, J. W. TURNER, 47, Rathbone Place, where gentlemen wishing to apply it to their private <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>sibraries</sic><corr>libraries</corr></choice> can see samples and obtain all information.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE FLORIFORM PARASOL.—</head><p >Registered Act 6 and 7 Vict., c. 65.—Some time ago a Number of the “Art-Union Journal” contained a letter from a lady on the shapes of Parasols, the writer of which tastefully suggested that a great improvement might be made in their appearance by adopting in their formation the configuration of flowers, instead of the antique mushroom shape.</p><p >This suggestion, as far as is mechanically practicable, is carried out by the invention of the FLORIFORM PARASOL, which exhibits, when open, the elegant outline of an expanded flower.</p><p >The FLORIFORM PARASOL may be purchased of all first-class mercers and Parasol dealers throughout the kingdom, and wholesale of JOHN MORELAND AND SON, manufacturers, 50, Eastcheap, London-bridge.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KNOW THYSELF.—</head><p >The art of describing persons' characters from their handwriting has long been practised by Dr. BLENKINSOP, with a success which is proved by innumerable Testimonials; pointing out gifts which modesty may be ignorant of, and defects which self-love may overlook. Address by letter, stating age, sex, and station, with 13 uncut postage-stamps to him, at No. 10, Lancaster Place, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><opener >A CERTAIN AND SPEEDY CURE FOR <lb/> Influenza, Coughs, Colds, Asthma, <lb/> INCIPIENT CONSUMPTIONS, <lb/> And all Disorders of the Chest and Lungs.</opener><head >SPENCER'S PULMONIC <lb/> ELIXIR,</head><p >CAREFULLY PREPARED FROM THE RECIPE <lb/> OF THE LATE C. SPENCER, SURGEON, &amp;C., SALFORD, <lb/> MANCHESTER; <lb/> DESERVEDLY CELEBRATED AS THE MOST <lb/> SUCCESSFUL PRACTITIONER IN ALL PULMONARY <lb/> AFFECTIONS.</p><p >Persons desirous of testing the efficacy of this medicine, must observe that on each bottle are the words “SPENCER'S PULMONIC ELIXIR,” and that each wrapper has a fac-simile of the Proprietors' signature, “T. ROBERTS &amp; Co.”</p><p >Prepared only by T. ROBERTS &amp; Co., Crane-court, Fleet-street, London. In Bottles at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p><p >The Bottles at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> contain nearly three small.</p><p >Sold by all medicine vendors in Town and Country. Wholesale London Agents:—Messrs. Barclay and Sons, Farringdon-street; Edwards, St. Paul's Churchyard; Sutton and Co., Bew Churchyard; Sanger, 151, Oxford-street; and Hannay and Co., Oxford-st.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p >and all other Medicines of a nauseous character, may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p><p >The recent discovery that the low priced Gelatine Capsules contain a compound of train and other oils, and in many cases no Copaiba whatever, renders it important that the public should be made aware that the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES are <hi rend="italics">guaranteed</hi> to contain <hi rend="italics">genuine Copaiba only.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BEAUTY.—</head><p >The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal—the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed “G. H. HOGARD” for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head><p >FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.—Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET of BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature.—“Robert Shaw, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Prices 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head><p >EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.—Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p><closer >21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY £1 10s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >PRICE ONE FLORIN EACH.</head><p >LADIES AND GENTLEMEN TRY MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT.—A new and elegant preparation for the Hair, compounded on rational principles, and which once used will at once supersede the filthy stuff sold as Bears' Grease, Circassian Cream, or various oils with nonsensical names, which possess not the slightest power to render a benefit.</p><p >MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT, used as directed in a Treatise on the Hair sold with each pot, will soon render the Hair clean, lustrous, and curly. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Medicine Vendors in town and country. Wholesale London Agents—Messrs. BARCLAY &amp; SONS, Farringdon-street; EDWARDS, St. Paul's Churchyard; SUTTON &amp; Co., Bow Churchyard; SANGAR, 151, Oxford-street; and HANNAY &amp; Co., Oxford-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p >In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p><p >HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10½<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p><p >INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p><p >An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >AN EXCELLENT cure of a DISORDER IN THE STOMACH effected by HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.—</head><p >A Lady, an intimate friend of the family of General Rosas, Governor of the Republic of La Plata, declares that she was lately cured of a disorder in the stomach, and restored to perfect health, by the use of this admirable remedy. She had consulted the most eminent physicians in the country, but had not been able to obtain any relief from the complaint that was killing her by inches, until she took Holloway's Pills. John Eastman, Esq., an eminent merchant of Buenos Ayres, communicated these particulars to Professor HOLLOWAY in a letter dated the 4th September, 1849.—Sold by all druggists, and at Professor HOLLOWAY'S Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><opener >Under Royal Patronage.<lb/>PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES, AND INSTANT RELIEF <lb/> AND A RAPID CURE OF ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, <lb/> COLDS, AND ALL DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS, <lb/> ARE INSURED BY</opener><head >DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated Testimonials, may be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">had from every Agent.</hi></p><div type="section"><head >Cure of a 14 years' Asthmatic Cough.</head><p >I, Thomas Carter, Egremont, Cheshire, had an asthmatic cough for fourteen years; nothing ever gave me relief until I commenced taking Dr. LOCOCK'S Pulmonic Wafers, three boxes of which have entirely cured me. (Signed) THOMAS CARTER.</p><p >Witness, Mr. Geo. H. Howell, <lb/> Chemist, Dale St., Liverpool.</p><p >Extract of a Letter from Mr. James Macarthy, Medical <lb/> Hall, 4, Essex Bridge, Dublin, <lb/> “Gentlemen,—I can bear testimony to the efficacy of DR. LOCOCK's Wafers, which act as a specific in affections of the Lungs, viz.: Influenza, Colds, Asthma, Irritation, Cough, &amp;c.</p><p >To many elderly persons who could not leave home on a damp or foggy day, they prove a complete boon, &amp;c. &amp;c. (Signed) JAMES MACARTHY.,</p></div><div><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >They have a pleasant taste. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per box.</p><p >AGENTS: DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors</p><p >Also, Protected by Royal Letters Patent.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS.</head><p >HAVE NO TASTE OF MEDICINE, and are the only remedy recommended to be taken by Ladies. They fortify the constitution at all periods of life, and in all Nervous Affections act like a Charm. They remove Heaviness, Fatigue on Slight Exertion, Palpitation of the Heart, Lowness of Spirits, Weakness, and Allay Pain.</p><p >They create Appetite, and remove Indigestion, Heart-burn, Wind, Head-aches, Giddiness, &amp;c.</p><p >In Hysterical Diseases, a proper perseverance in the use of this Medicine will be found to effect a Cure after all other means have failed.</p><p >Full Directions are given with every box.</p><p >NOTE.—These Wafers do not contain any Mineral, and may be taken either dissolved in water, or whole.</p><p >Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per Box.</p><p >The 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Boxes contain nearly three of the small size, and the 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Boxes five of those at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >BEWARE OF COUNTERFEITS IN THE FORM OF PILLS, &amp;c.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MECHI, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">4, Leadenhall Street,</hi>
<lb/> LONDON.</head><p >THE BEST &amp; CHEAPEST <lb/> CUTLERY, DESKS, DRESSING CASES <lb/> WORK BOXES, TEA TRAYS <lb/> &amp; PAPIER MACHÉ ELEGANCIES.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Bagatelle &amp; Backgammon Boards.</hi></p><p >EVERY THING FOR THE TOILET &amp; WORK TABLE.</p><p >Pocket Books, Card Cases, Portfolios &amp; Inkstands.</p><p >TRY MECHI'S MAGIC STROP</p><p >Mechi's Patent Castellated Silver Wire <lb/> Tooth Brushes,9d each.</p><p >LADIES IVORY HANDLED PENKNIVES 1s. EACH.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >PARASOLS.</head><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER, <lb/> Respectfully inform the Nobility and public that the Parasols they will have the honour of submitting to them this season are larger than usual, but owing to the peculiarity of their make are much lighter, a quality so much to be desired in a Parasol. They are chiefly plain, without fringe, and made of Glacé, and striped silks of perfectly new mixtures of colours of the most striking and elegant description.</p><p >W. and J. SANGSTER have also a large assortment of the Swiss or Alpaca Parasols which gave such universal satisfaction last year, 30,000 having been sold in the course of the season.</p><p >PATENTEES OF THE ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</p><closer >140, Regent-street; 94, Fleet-street; 10, Royal Exchange; <lb/> 75 Cheapside.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >THE ONLY RATIONAL REMEDY <lb/> IS</opener><head >PARR'S LIFE PILLS.</head><p >THOMAS PARR.<lb/>This Engraving is from a Portrait by Rubens, when at the age of 152 years. See his Life, to be had Gratis of all Agents.</p><p >IT is a clear indisputable fact that for cleansing, and enriching the human blood, restoring vigour and tone to the system, curing nervousness, indigestion, gout, rheumatism, and all bilious disorders, there is no remedy so certain, and safe, as that favourite and universal Medicine, <lb/> PARR'S LIFE PILLS.</p><list  type="simple"><head>THE ADVANTAGES DERIVED FROM TAKING PARR'S LIFE PILLS, ARE</head><item>1ST.—LONG LIFE, AND HAPPINESS!</item><item>2ND.—SOUND AND REFRESHING SLEEP!</item><item>3RD.—GOOD APPETITE!</item><item>4TH.—ENERGY OF MIND AND CLEARNESS OF PERCEPTION!</item><item>5TH.—GENERAL GOOD HEALTH AND COMFORT.</item><item>6TH.—THEY ARE FOUND, AFTER GIVING THEM A FAIR TRIAL FOR A FEW WEEKS, TO POSSESS THE MOST ASTONISHING AND INVIGORATING PROPERTIES.</item></list><div type="section"><head >TO PERSONS ABOUT TO EMIGRATE.</head><p >A most important appendage to an Emigrant's store is a good supply of PARR'S LIFE PILLS. On ship board these Pills will be found invaluable in keeping the stomach and bowels in a regular and healthful state, purifying the blood, and preventing cutaneous diseases, such as scurvy, &amp;c., incidental to long voyages. By attending to the directions given with each box, they may be safely taken by infants, adults, or persons in advanced age. When settled in distant climes, the emigrant will find in these Pills all he can require in the form of medicine. They will keep good in all climates; and any person proceeding to the Colonies will find it profitable to take out a supply.</p><p >None are genuine unless the words ‘PARR'S LIFE PILLS’ are in WHITE LETTERS on a RED GROUND, on the Government stamp, pasted round each box; also a fac-simile of the signature of the Proprietors “T. ROBERTS &amp; Co., Crane-court, Fleet-street, London,” on the directions.</p><p >Sold in Boxes at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and family packets at 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >Warren's Sketches of Character.</head><p >MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HANDWRITING.</p><p >Specimens of Writing, with an enclosure of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's age to be addressed as above.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PATENT LEVER COPYING PRESSES,</head><p >AT CONSIDERABLY REDUCED PRICES.</p><p >Lever Press.</p><p >Screw Press.</p><p >First Quality Screw.</p><p >Wrot. Iron Beam Screw.</p><p >These Presses, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged if any fault is discovered.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press, wrt.iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell></row><row><cell> Large 4to </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell></row><row><cell> Post Folio </cell><cell> — </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Copying Paper, very best quality, 2 reams for 17s.—5 reams for 37s. 6d.—10 reams for 65s.—Ditto French ditto, 2 reams for 16s.—5 reams for 35s.—10 reams for 60s. Copying Ink, per quart, 3s.; per dozen quarts, 30s.</p><closer >WATERLOW AND SONS, <lb/> WHOLESALE &amp; RETAIL MANUFACTURING STATIONERS, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, AND 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE INVISIBLE VENTILATING HEADS OF HAIR.</head><p >
<table><head>ROSS &amp; SONS' METHOD OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eights. </cell></row><row><cell> Round the Head </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From Ear to Ear </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From Forehead to Poll </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >These Inimitable works of art, for both Ladies and Gentlemen, from One Guinea-and-a-half.</p><closer >Address, ROSS &amp; SONS, 119 and 120, Bishopsgate Street, London.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >NUMBER ONE SAINT PAUL'S <lb/> CHURCH-YARD.</head><p >It may be well just to remind new comers that Number One St. Paul's Church-yard continues to stand prominent in its old spot, right in the very centre of England's metropolis, and that from this great centre of supply are sent out eastward, westward, northward, and southward, to all parts of London, and to the remotest districts in the country, the very best TEAS, and the choicest COFFEES, of the world's growth.</p><p >Excellent Congou Tea, that never fails to give great satisfaction, is now only 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> the pound, whilst true and fine-flavoured Coffee, of particularly choice quality, is sold at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> a pound, by</p><p >DAKIN AND COMPY, <lb/> TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> AND PATENTEES FOR ROASTING COFFEE IN SILVER <lb/> CYLINDERS,</p><closer >NUMBER ONE ST. PAUL'S CHURCH-YARD, <lb/> LONDON.</closer></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">The Wanderer.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Traddles Makes a figure in parliament and I report him.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="p1b"/><opener >To be Published Monthly, with the Magazines, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or Stamped,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE <lb/> OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS.</head><p >CONDUCTED BY <lb/> CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >BEING A <lb/> Monthly Supplement to “Household Words.”</p><p >WE take this opportunity of announcing a design, closely associated with our Household Words, which we have now matured, and which we hope will be acceptable to our readers.</p><p >We purpose publishing, at the end of each month as a Supplementary Number to the monthly part of Household Words, a comprehensive Abstract or History of all the occurrences of that month, native and foreign, under the title of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF CURRENT EVENTS.</p><p >The size and price of each of these numbers will be the same as the size and price of a single number of “HOUSEHOLD WORDS.” Twelve numbers will necessarily be published in the course of the year—one for each month—and on the completion of the Annual Volume, a copious Index will appear, and a title-page for the volume; which will then be called THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE of such a year. It will form a complete Chronicle of all that year's events, carefully compiled, thoroughly digested, and systematically arranged for easy reference; presenting a vast mass of information that must be interesting to all, at a price that will render it accessible to the humblest purchasers of books, and at which only our existing machinery in connexion with our Weekly Miscellany would enable us to produce it.</p><p >The first number of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE will appear as a Supplement to the first monthly part of “Household Words,” published at the end of the present month of APRIL. As the Volume for 1850 would be incomplete (in consequence of our not having commenced this publication at the beginning of a year) without a backward reference to the three
<pb xml:id="p2b"/>
months of JANUARY, FEBRUARY, and MARCH, a similar number of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE for each of those months will be published before the year is out.</p><p >It is scarcely necessary to explain that it is not proposed to render the purchase of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE compulsory on the purchasers of Household Words; and that the Supplementary Number, though always published at the same time as our Monthly Part, will therefore be detached from it, and published separately.</p><p >Nor is it necessary for us, we believe, to expatiate on our leading reasons for adding this new undertaking to our present enterprise. The intimate connexion between the facts and realities of the time, and the means by which we aim, in “HOUSEHOLD WORDS,” to soften what is hard in them, to exalt what is held in little consideration, and to show the latent hope there is in what may seem unpromising, needs not to be pointed out. All that we sought to express in our Preliminary Word, in reference to this work, applies, we think, to its proposed companion. As another humble means of enabling those who accept us for their friend, to bear the world's rough-cast events to the anvil of courageous duty, and there beat them into shape, we enter on the project, and confide in its success.</p><closer >
<dateline>OFFICE, 16, Wellington Street North. <lb/> April 12, 1850.</dateline>
</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >“Familiar in their Mouths as HOUSEHOLD WORDS.”—<hi rend="italics">Shakspeare.</hi><lb/><hi rend="italics">Publishing weekly, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d. also in Monthly Parts.</hi></opener><head >HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A WEEKLY JOURNAL.</p><p >Designed for the Instruction and Entertainment of all <lb/> Classes of Readers.</p><p >CONDUCTED BY <lb/> CHARLES DICKENS.</p><closer >OFFICE, 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH, STRAND; AND ALL BOOKSELLERS.</closer><trailer >[Bradbury &amp; Evans, Printers, Whitefriars.]</trailer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="narrative"><pb  xml:id="p385"/><head >[THE 
<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXVIII. <lb/> A DISSOLUTION OF PARTNERSHIP.</head><p >I DID not allow my resolution, with respect to the Parliamentary Debates, to cool. It was one of the irons I began to heat immediately, and one of the irons I kept hot, and hammered at, with a perseverance I may honestly admire. I bought an approved scheme of the noble art and mystery of stenography (which cost me ten and sixpence); and plunged into a sea of perplexity that brought me, in a few weeks, to the confines of distraction. The changes that were rung upon dots, which in such a position meant such a thing, and in such another position something else, entirely different; the wonderful vagaries that were played by circles; the unaccountable consequences that resulted from marks like flies' legs; the tremendous effects of a curve in a wrong place; not only troubled my waking hours, but reappeared before me in my sleep. When I had groped my way, blindly, through these difficulties, and had mastered the alphabet, which was an Egyptian Temple in itself, there then appeared a procession of new horrors, called arbitrary characters; the most despotic characters I have ever known; who insisted, for instance, that a thing like the beginning of a cobweb, meant expectation, and that a pen and ink sky-rocket stood for disadvantageous. When I had fixed these wretches in my mind, I found that they had driven everything else out of it; then, beginning again, I forgot them; while I was picking them up, I dropped the other fragments of the system; in short, it was almost heart-breaking.</p><p >It might have been quite heart-breaking, but for Dora, who was the stay and anchor of my tempest-driven bark. Every scratch in the scheme was a gnarled oak in the forest of difficulty, and I went on cutting them down, one after another, with such vigour, that in three or four months I was in a condition to make an experiment on one of our crack speakers in the Commons. Shall I ever forget how the crack speaker walked off from me before I began, and left my imbecile pencil staggering about the paper as if it were in a fit!</p><p >This would not do, it was quite clear. I was flying too high, and should never get on, so. I resorted to Traddles for advice; who suggested that he should dictate speeches to me, at a pace, and with occasional stoppages, adapted to my weakness. Very grateful for this friendly aid, I accepted the proposal; and night after night, almost every night, for a long time, we had a sort of private Parliament in Buckingham Street, after I came home from the Doctor's.</p><p >I should like to see such a Parliament anywhere else! My aunt and Mr. Dick represented the Government or the Opposition (as the case might be), and Traddles, with the assistance of Enfield's Speaker or a volume of parliamentary orations, thundered astonishing invectives against them. Standing by the table, with his finger in the page to keep the place,
<pb xml:id="p386"/>
and his right arm flourishing above his head, Traddles, as Mr. Pitt, Mr. Fox, Mr. Sheridan, Mr. Burke, Lord Castlereagh, Viscount Sidmouth, or Mr. Canning, would work himself into the most violent heats, and deliver the most withering denunciations of the profligacy and corruption of my aunt and Mr. Dick; while I used to sit, at a little distance, with my note-book on my knee, fagging after him with all my might and main. The inconsistency and recklessness of Traddles were not to be exceeded by any real politician. He was for any description of policy, in the compass of a week; and nailed all sorts of colours to every denomination of mast. My aunt, looking very like an immoveable Chancellor of the Exchequer, would occasionally throw in an interruption or two, as “Hear!” or “No!” or “Oh!” when the text seemed to require it: which was always a signal to Mr. Dick (a perfect country gentleman) to follow lustily with the same cry. But Mr. Dick got taxed with such things in the course of his Parliamentary career, and was made responsible for such awful consequences, that he became uncomfortable in his mind sometimes. I believe he actually began to be afraid he really had been doing something, tending to the annihilation of the British constitution, and the ruin of the country.</p><p >Often and often we pursued these debates until the clock pointed to midnight, and the candles were burning down. The result of so much good practice was, that by-and-by I began to keep pace with Traddles pretty well, and should have been quite triumphant if I had had the least idea what my notes were about. But, as to reading them after I had got them, I might as well have copied the Chinese inscriptions on an immense collection of tea-chests, or the golden characters on all the great red and green bottles in the chemists' shops!</p><p >There was nothing for it, but to turn back and begin all over again. It was very hard, but I turned back, though with a heavy heart, and began laboriously and methodically to plod over the same tedious ground at a snail's pace; stopping to examine minutely every speck in the way, on all sides, and making the most desperate efforts to know these elusive characters by sight wherever I met them. I was always punctual at the office; at the Doctor's too: and I really did work, as the common expression is, like a cart-horse.</p><p >One day, when I went to the Commons as usual, I found Mr. Spenlow in the doorway looking extremely grave, and talking to himself. As he was in the habit of complaining of pains in his head—he had naturally a short throat, and I do seriously believe he overstarched himself—I was at first alarmed by the idea that he was not quite right in that direction; but he soon relieved my uneasiness.</p><p >Instead of returning my “Good morning” with his usual affability, he looked at me in a distant, ceremonious manner, and coldly requested me to accompany him to a certain coffee-house, which, in those days, had a door opening into the Commons, just within the little archway in St. Paul's churchyard. I complied, in a very uncomfortable state, and with a warm shooting all over me, as if my apprehensions were breaking out into buds. When I allowed him to go on a little before, on account of the narrowness of the way, I observed that he carried his head with a lofty air that was particularly unpromising; and my mind misgave me that he had found out about my darling Dora.</p><pb  xml:id="p387"/><p >If I had not guessed this, on the way to the coffee-house, I could hardly have failed to know what was the matter when I followed him into an up-stairs room, and found Miss Murdstone there, supported by a background of sideboard, on which were several inverted tumblers sustaining lemons, and two of those extraordinary boxes, all corners and flutings, for sticking knives and forks in, which, happily for mankind, are now obsolete.</p><p >Miss Murdstone gave me her chilly finger-nails, and sat severely rigid. Mr. Spenlow shut the door, motioned me to a chair, and stood on the hearth-rug in front of the fireplace.</p><p >“Have the goodness to show Mr. Copperfield,” said Mr. Spenlow, “what you have in your reticule, Miss Murdstone.”</p><p >I believe it was the old identical steel-clasped reticule of my childhood, that shut up like a bite. Compressing her lips, in sympathy with the snap, Miss Murdstone opened it—opening her mouth a little at the same time—and produced my last letter to Dora, teeming with expressions of devoted affection.</p><p >“I believe that is your writing, Mr. Copperfield?” said Mr. Spenlow.</p><p >I was very hot, and the voice I heard was very unlike mine, when I said, “It is sir!”</p><p >“If I am not mistaken,” said Mr. Spenlow, as Miss Murdstone brought a parcel of letters out of her reticule, tied round with the dearest bit of blue ribbon, “those are also from your pen, Mr. Copperfield?”</p><p >I took them from her with a most desolate sensation; and, glancing at such phrases at the top, as “My ever dearest and own Dora,” “My best beloved angel,” “My blessed one for ever,” and the like, blushed deeply, and inclined my head.</p><p >“No, thank you!” said Mr. Spenlow coldly, as I mechanically offered them back to him. “I will not deprive you of them. Miss Murdstone, be so good as to proceed!”</p><p >That gentle creature, after a moment's thoughtful survey of the carpet, delivered herself with much dry unction as follows.</p><p >“I must confess to having entertained my suspicions of Miss Spenlow, in reference to David Copperfield, for some time. I observed Miss Spenlow and David Copperfield, when they first met; and the impression made upon me then was not agreeable. The depravity of the human heart is such—”</p><p >“You will oblige me, ma'am,” interrupted Mr. Spenlow, “by confining yourself to facts.”</p><p >Miss Murdstone cast down her eyes, shook her head as if protesting against this unseemly interruption, and with frowning dignity resumed:</p><p >“Since I am to confine myself to facts, I will state them as dryly as I can. Perhaps that will be considered an acceptable course of proceeding. I have already said, sir, that I have had my suspicions of Miss Spenlow, in reference to David Copperfield, for some time. I have frequently endeavoured to find decisive coroboration of those suspicions, but without effect. I have therefore forborne to mention them to Miss Spenlow's father;” looking severely at him; “knowing how little disposition there usually is in such cases, to acknowledge the conscientious discharge of duty.”</p><p >Mr. Spenlow seemed quite cowed by the gentlemanly sternness of Miss
<pb xml:id="p388"/>
Murdstone's manner, and deprecated her severity with a conciliatory little wave of his hand.</p><p >“On my return to Norwood, after the period of absence occasioned by my brother's marriage,” pursued Miss Murdstone in a disdainful voice, “and on the return of Miss Spenlow from her visit to her friend Miss Mills, I imagined that the manner of Miss Spenlow gave me greater occasion for suspicion than before. Therefore I watched Miss Spenlow closely.”</p><p >Dear, tender little Dora, so unconscious of this Dragon's eye!</p><p >“Still,” resumed Miss Murdstone, “I found no proof until last night. It appeared to me that Miss Spenlow received too many letters from her friend Miss Mills; but Miss Mills being her friend with her father's full concurrence,” another telling blow at Mr. Spenlow, “it was not for me to interfere. If I may not be permitted to allude to the natural depravity of the human heart, at least I may—I must—be permitted, so far to refer to misplaced confidence.”</p><p >Mr. Spenlow apologetically murmured his assent.</p><p >“Last evening after tea,” pursued Miss Murdstone, “I observed the little dog starting, rolling, and growling about the drawing-room, worrying something. I said to Miss Spenlow, ‘Dora, what is that the dog has in his mouth? It's paper.’ Miss Spenlow immediately put her hand to her frock, gave a sudden cry, and ran to the dog. I interposed, and said ‘Dora my love, you must permit me.’ ”</p><p >Oh Jip, miserable Spaniel, this wretchedness, then, was your work!</p><p >“Miss Spenlow endeavoured” said Miss Murdstone “to bribe me with kisses, work-boxes, and small articles of jewellery—that, of course, I pass over. The little dog retreated under the sofa on my approaching him, and was with great difficulty dislodged by the fire-irons. Even when dislodged, he still kept the letter in his mouth; and on my endeavouring to take it from him, at the imminent risk of being bitten, he kept it between his teeth so pertinaciously as to suffer himself to be held suspended in the air by means of the document. At length I obtained possession of it. After perusing it, I taxed Miss Spenlow with having many such letters in her possession; and ultimately obtained from her, the packet which is now in David Copperfield's hand.”</p><p >Here she ceased; and snapping her reticule again, and shutting her mouth, looked as if she might be broken, but could never be bent.</p><p >“You have heard Miss Murdstone,” said Mr. Spenlow, turning to me. “I beg to ask, Mr. Copperfield, if you have anything to say in reply?”</p><p >The picture I had before me, of the beautiful little treasure of my heart, sobbing and crying all night—of her being alone, frightened, and wretched, then—of her having so piteously begged and prayed that stony-hearted woman to forgive her—of her having vainly offered her those kisses, work-boxes, and trinkets—of her being in such grievous distress, and all for me—very much impaired the little dignity I had been able to muster. I am afraid I was in a tremulous state for a minute or so, though I did my best to disguise it.</p><p >“There is nothing I can say, sir,” I returned, “except that all the blame is mine. Dora—”</p><p >“Miss Spenlow, if you please,” said her father, majestically.</p><pb  xml:id="p389"/><p >“— was induced and persuaded by me,” I went on, swallowing that colder designation, “to consent to this concealment, and I bitterly regret it.”</p><p >“You are very much to blame, sir,” said Mr. Spenlow, walking to and fro upon the hearth-rug, and emphasizing what he said with his whole body instead of his head, on account of the stiffness of his cravat and spine. “You have done a stealthy and unbecoming action, Mr. Copperfield. When I take a gentleman to my house, no matter whether he is nineteen, twenty-nine, or ninety, I take him there in a spirit of confidence. If he abuses my confidence, he commits a dishonourable action, Mr. Copperfield.”</p><p >“I feel it, sir, I assure you,” I returned. “But I never thought so, before. Sincerely, honestly, indeed, Mr. Spenlow, I never thought so, before. I love Miss Spenlow to that extent—”</p><p >“Pooh! nonsense!” said Mr. Spenlow, reddening. “Pray don't tell me to my face that you love my daughter, Mr. Copperfield!”</p><p >“Could I defend my conduct if I did not, sir?” I returned, with all humility.</p><p >“Can you defend your conduct if you do, sir?” said Mr. Spenlow, stopping short upon the hearth-rug. “Have you considered your years, and my daughter's years, Mr. Copperfield? Have you considered what it is to undermine the confidence that should subsist between my daughter and myself? Have you considered my daughter's station in life, the projects I may contemplate for her advancement, the testamentary intentions I may have with reference to her? Have you considered anything, Mr. Copperfield?”</p><p >“Very little, sir, I am afraid;” I answered, speaking to him as respectfully and sorrowfully as I felt; “but pray believe me, I have considered my own worldly position. When I explained it to you, we were already engaged—”</p><p >“I BEG,” said Mr. Spenlow, more like Punch than I had ever seen him, as he energetically struck one hand upon the other—I could not help noticing that even in my despair; “that you will NOT talk to me of engagements, Mr. Copperfield!”</p><p >The otherwise immoveable Miss Murdstone laughed contemptuously in one short syllable.</p><p >“When I explained my altered position to you, sir,” I began again, substituting a new form of expression for what was so unpalatable to him, “this concealment, into which I am so unhappy as to have led Miss Spenlow, had begun. Since I have been in that altered position, I have strained every nerve, I have exerted every energy, to improve it. I am sure I shall improve it in time. Will you grant me time—any length of time? We are both so young, sir,—”</p><p >“You are right,” interrupted Mr. Spenlow, nodding his head a great many times, and frowning very much, “you are both very young. It's all nonsense. Let there be an end of the nonsense. Take away those letters, and throw them in the fire. Give me Miss Spenlow's letters to throw in the fire; and although our future intercourse must, you are aware, be restricted to the Commons here, we will agree to make no further mention of the past. Come, Mr. Copperfield, you don't want sense; and this is the sensible course.”</p><pb  xml:id="p390"/><p >No. I couldn't think of agreeing to it. I was very sorry, but there was a higher consideration than sense. Love was above all earthly considerations, and I loved Dora to idolatry, and Dora loved me. I didn't exactly say so; I softened it down as much as I could; but I implied it, and I was resolute upon it. I don't think I made myself very ridiculous, but I know I was resolute.</p><p >“Very well, Mr. Copperfield,” said Mr. Spenlow, “I must try my influence with my daughter.”</p><p >Miss Murdstone, by an expressive sound, a long drawn respiration, which was neither a sigh nor a moan, but was like both, gave it as her opinion that he should have done this at first.</p><p >“I must try,” said Mr. Spenlow, confirmed by this support, “my influence with my daughter. Do you decline to take those letters, Mr. Copperfield?” For I had laid them on the table.</p><p >Yes. I told him I hoped he would not think it wrong, but I couldn't possibly take them from Miss Murdstone.</p><p >“Nor from me?” said Mr. Spenlow.</p><p >No, I replied with the profoundest respect; nor from him.</p><p >“Very well!” said Mr. Spenlow.</p><p >A silence succeeding, I was undecided whether to go or stay. At length I was moving quietly towards the door, with the intention of saying that perhaps I should consult his feelings best by withdrawing: when he said, with his hands in his coat pockets, into which it was as much as he could do to get them; and with what I should call, upon the whole, a decidedly pious air:</p><p >“You are probably aware, Mr. Copperfield, that I am not altogether destitute of worldly possessions, and that my daughter is my nearest and dearest relative?”</p><p >I hurriedly made him a reply to the effect, that I hoped the error into which I had been betrayed by the desperate nature of my love, did not induce him to think me mercenary too?</p><p >“I don't allude to the matter in that light,” said Mr. Spenlow. “It would be better for yourself, and all of us, if you <hi rend="italics">were</hi> mercenary, Mr. Copperfield—I mean, if you were more discreet and less influenced by all this youthful nonsense. No. I merely say, with quite another view, you are probably aware I have some property to bequeath to my child?”</p><p >I certainly supposed so.</p><p >“And you can hardly think,” said Mr. Spenlow, “having experience of what we see, in the Commons here, every day, of the various unaccountable and negligent proceedings of men, in respect of their testamentary arrangements—of all subjects, the one on which perhaps the strangest revelations of human inconsistency are to be met with—but that mine are made?”</p><p >I inclined my head in acquiescence.</p><p >“I should not allow,” said Mr. Spenlow, with an evident increase of pious sentiment, and slowly shaking his head as he poised himself upon his toes and heels alternately, “my suitable provision for my child to be influenced by a piece of youthful folly like the present. It is mere folly. Mere nonsense. In a little while, it will weigh lighter than any feather. But I might—I might—if this silly business were not completely relinquished
<pb xml:id="p391"/>
altogether, be induced in some anxious moment to guard her from, and surround her with protections against, the consequences of, any foolish step in the way of marriage. Now, Mr. Copperfield, I hope that you will not render it necessary for me to open, even for a quarter of an hour, that closed page in the book of life, and unsettle, even for a quarter of an hour, grave affairs long since composed.”</p><p >There was a serenity, a tranquillity, a calm-sunset air about him, which quite affected me. He was so peaceful and resigned—clearly had his affairs in such perfect train, and so systematically wound up—that he was a man to feel touched in the contemplation of. I really think I saw tears rise to his eyes, from the depth of his own feeling of all this.</p><p >But what could I do? I could not deny Dora and my own heart. When he told me I had better take a week to consider of what he had said, how could I say I wouldn't take a week, yet how could I fail to know that no amount of weeks could influence such love as mine?</p><p >“In the meantime, confer with Miss Trotwood, or with any person with any knowledge of life,” said Mr. Spenlow, adjusting his cravat with both hands. “Take a week, Mr. Copperfield.”</p><p >I submitted; and, with a countenance as expressive as I was able to make it of dejected and despairing constancy, came out of the room. Miss Murdstone's heavy eyebrows followed me to the door—I say her eyebrows rather than her eyes, because they were much more important in her face—and she looked so exactly as she used to look, at about that hour of the morning, in our parlour at Blunderstone, that I could have fancied I had been breaking down in my lessons again, and that the dead weight on my mind was that horrible old spelling-book, with oval woodcuts, shaped, to my youthful fancy, like the glasses out of spectacles.</p><p >When I got to the office, and, shutting out old Tiffey and the rest of them with my hands, sat at my desk, in my own particular nook, thinking of this earthquake that had taken place so unexpectedly, and in the bitterness of my spirit cursing Jip, I fell into such a state of torment about Dora, that I wonder I did not take up my hat and rush insanely to Norwood. The idea of their frightening her, and making her cry, and of my not being there to comfort her, was so excruciating, that it impelled me to write a wild letter to Mr. Spenlow, beseeching him not to visit upon her the consequences of my awful destiny. I implored him to spare her gentle nature—not to crush a fragile flower—and addressed him generally, to the best of my remembrance, as if, instead of being her father, he had been an Ogre, or the Dragon of Wantley. This letter I sealed and laid upon his desk before he returned; and when he came in, I saw him, through the half-opened door of his room, take it up and read it.</p><p >He said nothing about it all the morning; but before he went away in the afternoon he called me in, and told me that I need not make myself at all uneasy about his daughter's happiness. He had assured her, he said, that it was all nonsense; and he had nothing more to say to her. He believed he was an indulgent father (as indeed he was), and I might spare myself any solicitude on her account.</p><p >“You may make it necessary, if you are foolish or obstinate, Mr. Copperfield,” he observed, “for me to send my daughter abroad again, for a term; but I have a better opinion of you. I hope you will be wiser than
<pb xml:id="p392"/>
that, in a few days. As to Miss Murdstone,” for I had alluded to her in the letter, “I respect that lady's vigilance, and feel obliged to her; but she has strict charge to avoid the subject. All I desire, Mr. Copperfield, is, that it should be forgotten. All you have got to do, Mr. Copperfield, is, to forget it.”</p><p >All! In the note I wrote to Miss Mills, I bitterly quoted this sentiment. All I had to do, I said, with gloomy sarcasm, was to forget Dora. That was all, and what was that! I entreated Miss Mills to see me, that evening. If it could not be done with Mr. Mills's sanction and concurrence, I besought a clandestine interview in the back kitchen where the Mangle was. I informed her that my reason was tottering on its throne, and only she, Miss Mills, could prevent its being deposed. I signed myself, hers distractedly; and I couldn't help feeling, when I read this composition over, before sending it by a porter, that it was something in the style of Mr. Micawber.</p><p >However, I sent it. At night I repaired to Miss Mills's street, and walked up and down, until I was stealthily fetched in by Miss Mills's maid, and taken the area way to the back kitchen. I have since seen reason to believe that there was nothing on earth to prevent my going in at the front door, and being shown up into the drawing-room, except Miss Mills's love of the romantic and mysterious.</p><p >In the back kitchen, I raved as became me. I went there, I suppose, to make a fool of myself, and I am quite sure I did it. Miss Mills had received a hasty note from Dora, telling her that all was discovered, and saying, “Oh pray come to me, Julia, do, do!” But Miss Mills, mistrusting the acceptability of her presence to the higher powers, had not yet gone; and we were all benighted in the Desert of Sahara.</p><p >Miss Mills had a wonderful flow of words, and liked to pour them out. I could not help feeling, though she mingled her tears with mine, that she had a dreadful luxury in our afflictions. She petted them, as I may say, and made the most of them. A deep gulf, she observed, had opened between Dora and me, and Love could only span it with its rainbow. Love must suffer in this stern world; it ever had been so, it ever would be so. No matter, Miss Mills remarked. Hearts confined by cobwebs would burst at last, and then Love was avenged.</p><p >This was small consolation, but Miss Mills wouldn't encourage fallacious hopes. She made me much more wretched than I was before, and I felt (and told her with the deepest gratitude) that she was indeed a friend. We resolved that she should go to Dora the first thing in the morning, and find some means of assuring her, either by looks or words, of my devotion and misery. We parted, overwhelmed with grief; and I think Miss Mills enjoyed herself completely.</p><p >I confided all to my aunt when I got home; and in spite of all she could say to me, went to bed despairing. I got up despairing, and went out despairing. It was Saturday morning, and I went straight to the Commons.</p><p >I was surprised, when I came within sight of our office-door, to see the ticket-porters standing outside talking together, and some half dozen stragglers gazing at the windows which were shut up. I quickened my pace, and, passing among them, wondering at their looks, went hurriedly in.</p><pb  xml:id="p393"/><p >The clerks were there, but nobody was doing anything. Old Tiffey, for the first time in his life I should think, was sitting on somebody else's stool, and had not hung up his hat.</p><p >“This is a dreadful calamity, Mr. Copperfield,” said he, as I entered.</p><p >“What is?” I exclaimed. “What's the matter?”</p><p >“Don't you know?” cried Tiffey, and all the rest of them, coming round me.</p><p >“No!” said I, looking from face to face.</p><p >“Mr. Spenlow,” said Tiffey.</p><p >“What about him!”</p><p >“Dead!”</p><p >I thought it was the office reeling, and not I, as one of the clerks caught hold of me. They sat me down in a chair, untied my neckcloth, and brought me some water. I have no idea whether this took any time.</p><p >“Dead?” said I.</p><p >“He dined in town yesterday, and drove down in the phaeton by himself,” said Tiffey, “having sent his own groom home by the coach, as he sometimes did, you know—”</p><p >“Well?”</p><p >“The phaeton went home without him. The horses stopped at the stable gate. The man went out with a lantern. Nobody in the carriage.”</p><p >“Had they run away?”</p><p >“They were not hot,” said Tiffey, putting on his glasses; “no hotter, I understand, than they would have been, going down at the usual pace. The reins were broken, but they had been dragging on the ground. The house was roused up directly, and three of them went out along the road. They found him a mile off.”</p><p >“More than a mile off, Mr. Tiffey,” interposed a junior.</p><p >“Was it? I believe you are right,” said Tiffey,—“<hi rend="italics">more</hi> than a mile off—not far from the church—lying partly on the road-side, and partly on the path, upon his face. Whether he fell out in a fit, or got out, feeling ill before the fit came on—or even whether he was quite dead then, though there is no doubt he was quite insensible—no one appears to know. If he breathed, certainly he never spoke. Medical assistance was got as soon as possible, but it was quite useless.”</p><p >I cannot describe the state of mind into which I was thrown by this intelligence. The shock of such an event happening so suddenly, and happening to one with whom I had been in any respect at variance—the appalling vacancy in the room he had occupied so lately, where his chair and table seemed to wait for him, and his handwriting of yesterday was like a ghost—the indefinable impossibility of separating him from the place, and feeling, when the door opened, as if he might come in—the lazy hush and rest there was in the office, and the insatiable relish with which our people talked about it, and other people came in and out all day, and gorged themselves with the subject—this is easily intelligible to any one. What I cannot describe is, how, in the innermost recesses of my own heart, I had a lurking jealousy even of Death. How I felt as if its might would push me from my ground in Dora's thoughts. How I was, in a grudging way I have no words for, envious of her grief. How it made me restless to think of her weeping to others, or being consoled by others. How I had
<pb xml:id="p394"/>
a grasping, avaricious wish to shut out everybody from her but myself, and to be all in all to her, at that unseasonable time of all times.</p><p >In the trouble of this state of mind—not exclusively my own, I hope, but known to others—I went down to Norwood that night; and finding from one of the servants, when I made my inquiries at the door, that Miss Mills was there, got my aunt to direct a letter to her, which I wrote. I deplored the untimely death of Mr. Spenlow most sincerely, and shed tears in doing so. I entreated her to tell Dora, if Dora were in a state to hear it, that he had spoken to me with the utmost kindness and consideration; and had coupled nothing but tenderness, not a single or reproachful word, with her name. I know I did this selfishly, to have my name brought before her; but I tried to believe it was an act of justice to his memory. Perhaps I did believe it.</p><p >My aunt received a few lines next day in reply; addressed, outside, to her; within, to me. Dora was overcome by grief; and when her friend had asked her should she send her love to me, had only cried, as she was always crying, “Oh, dear papa! oh, poor papa!” But she had not said No, and that I made the most of.</p><p >Mr. Jorkins, who had been at Norwood since the occurrence, came to the office a few days afterwards. He and Tiffey were closeted together for some few moments, and then Tiffey looked out at the door and beckoned me in.</p><p >“Oh!” said Mr. Jorkins. “Mr. Tiffey and myself, Mr. Copperfield, are about to examine the desk, the drawers, and other such repositories of the deceased, with the view of sealing up his private papers, and searching for a Will. There is no trace of any, elsewhere. It may be as well for you to assist us, if you please.”</p><p >I had been in agony to obtain some knowledge of the circumstances in which my Dora would be placed—as, in whose guardianship, and so forth—and this was something towards it. We began the search at once; Mr. Jorkins unlocking the drawers and desks, and we all taking out the papers. The office-papers we placed on one side, and the private papers (which were not numerous) on the other. We were very grave; and when we came to a stray seal, or pencil-case, or ring, or any little article of that kind which we associated personally with him, we spoke very low.</p><p >We had sealed up several packets; and were still going on dustily and quietly, when Mr. Jorkins said to us, applying exactly the same words to his late partner as his late partner had applied to him:</p><p >“Mr. Spenlow was very difficult to move from the beaten track. You know what he was! I am disposed to think he had made no will.”</p><p >“Oh, I know he had!” said I.</p><p >They both stopped and looked at me.</p><p >“On the very day when I last saw him,” said I, “he told me that he had, and that his affairs were long since settled.”</p><p >Mr. Jorkins and old Tiffey shook their heads with one accord.</p><p >“That looks unpromising,” said Tiffey.</p><p >“Very unpromising,” said Mr. Jorkins.</p><p >“Surely you don't doubt—” I began.</p><p >“My good Mr. Copperfield!” said Tiffey, laying his hand upon my arm,
<pb xml:id="p395"/>
and shutting up both his eyes as he shook his head: “if you had been in the Commons as long as I have, you would know that there is no subject on which men are so inconsistent, and so little to be trusted.”</p><p >“Why, bless my soul, he made that very remark!” I replied persistently.</p><p >“I should call that almost final,” observed Tiffey. “My opinion is—no will.”</p><p >It appeared a wonderful thing to me, but it turned out that there <hi rend="italics">was</hi> no will. He had never so much as thought of making one, so far as his papers afforded any evidence; for there was no kind of hint, sketch, or memorandum, of any testamentary intention whatever. What was scarcely less astonishing to me, was, that his affairs were in a most disordered state. It was extremely difficult, I heard, to make out what he owed, or what he had paid, or of what he died possessed. It was considered likely that for years he could have had no clear opinion on these subjects himself. By little and little it came out, that, in the competition on all points of appearance and gentility then running high in the Commons, he had spent more than his professional income, which was not a very large one, and had reduced his private means, if they ever had been great (which was exceedingly doubtful), to a very low ebb indeed. There was a sale of the furniture and lease, at Norwood; and Tiffey told me, little thinking how interested I was in the story, that, paying all the just debts of the deceased, and deducting his share of outstanding bad and doubtful debts due to the firm, he wouldn't give a thousand pounds for all the assets remaining.</p><p >This was at the expiration of about six weeks. I had suffered tortures all the time; and thought I really must have laid violent hands upon myself, when Miss Mills still reported to me, that my broken-hearted little Dora would say nothing, when I was mentioned, but “Oh, poor papa! Oh, dear papa!” Also, that she had no other relations than two aunts, maiden sisters of Mr. Spenlow, who lived at Putney, and who had not held any other than chance communication with their brother for many years. Not that they had ever quarrelled (Miss Mills informed me); but that having been, on the occasion of Dora's christening, invited to tea, when they considered themselves privileged to be invited to dinner, they had expressed their opinion in writing, that it was “better for the happiness of all parties” that they should stay away. Since which they had gone their road, and their brother had gone his.</p><p >These two ladies now emerged from their retirement, and proposed to take Dora to live at Putney. Dora, clinging to them both, and weeping, exclaimed, “O yes, aunts! Please take Julia Mills and me and Jip to Putney!” So they went, very soon after the funeral.</p><p >How I found time to haunt Putney, I am sure I don't know; but I contrived, by some means or other, to prowl about the neighbourhood pretty often. Miss Mills, for the more exact discharge of the duties of friendship, kept a journal; and she used to meet me sometimes, on the Common, and read it, or (if she had not time to do that) lend it to me. How I treasured up the entries, of which I subjoin a sample!</p><p >“Monday. My sweet D. still much depressed. Headache. Called attention to J. as being beautifully sleek. D. fondled J. Associations thus awakened, opened floodgates of sorrow. Rush of grief admitted. (Are tears the dewdrops of the heart? J.M.)</p><pb  xml:id="p396"/><p >“Tuesday. D. weak and nervous. Beautiful in pallor. (Do we not remark this in moon likewise? J. M.) D. J. M. and J. took airing in carriage. J. looking out of window, and barking violently at dustman, occasioned smile to overspread features of D. (Of such slight links is chain of life composed! J. M.)</p><p >“Wednesday. D. comparatively cheerful. Sang to her, as congenial melody, Evening Bells. Effect not soothing, but reverse. D. inexpressibly affected. Found sobbing afterwards, in own room. Quoted verses respecting self and young Gazelle. Ineffectually. Also referred to Patience on Monument. (Qy. Why on monument? J. M.)</p><p >“Thursday. D. certainly improved. Better night. Slight tinge of damask revisiting cheek. Resolved to mention name of D. C. Introduced same, cautiously, in course of airing. D. immediately overcome. ‘Oh, dear, dear Julia! Oh, I have been a naughty and undutiful child!’ Soothed and caressed. Drew ideal picture of D. C. on verge of tomb. D. again overcome. ‘Oh, what shall I do, what shall I do? Oh, take me somewhere!’ Much alarmed. Fainting of D. and glass of water from public-house. (Poetical affinity. Chequered sign on door-post; chequered human life. Alas! J. M.)</p><p >“Friday. Day of incident. Man appears in kitchen, with blue bag, ‘for lady's boots left out to heel.’ Cook replies, ‘No such orders.’ Man argues point. Cook withdraws to inquire, leaving man alone with J. On Cook's return, man still argues point, but ultimately goes. J. missing. D. distracted. Information sent to police. Man to be identified by broad nose, and legs like balustrades of bridge. Search made in every direction. No J. D. weeping bitterly, and inconsolable. Renewed reference to young Gazelle. Appropriate, but unavailing. Towards evening, strange boy calls. Brought into parlour. Broad nose, but no balustrades. Says he wants a pound, and knows a dog. Declines to explain further, though much pressed. Pound being produced by D. takes Cook to little house, where J. alone tied up to leg of table. Joy of D. who dances round J. while he eats his supper. Emboldened by this happy change, mention D. C. upstairs. D. weeps afresh, cries piteously. ‘Oh, don't, don't, don't. It is so wicked to think of anything but poor papa!’—embraces J. and sobs herself to sleep. (Must not D. C. confide himself to the broad pinions of Time? J. M.)”</p><p >Miss Mills and her journal were my sole consolation at this period. To see her, who had seen Dora but a little while before—to trace the initial letter of Dora's name through her sympathetic pages—to be made more and more miserable by her—were my only comforts. I felt as if I had been living in a palace of cards, which had tumbled down, leaving only Miss Mills and me among the ruins; as if some grim enchanter had drawn a magic circle round the innocent goddess of my heart, which nothing indeed but those same strong pinions, capable of carrying so many people over so much, would enable me to enter!</p></div><div type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p397"/><head >CHAPTER XXXIX. <lb/> WICKFIELD AND HEEP.</head><p >MY aunt, beginning, I imagine, to be made seriously uncomfortable by my prolonged dejection, made a pretence of being anxious that I should go to Dover, to see that all was working well at the cottage, which was let; and to conclude an agreement, with the same tenant, for a longer term of occupation. Janet was drafted into the service of Mrs. Strong, where I saw her every day. She had been undecided, on leaving Dover, whether or no to give the finishing touch to that renunciation of mankind in which she had been educated, by marrying a pilot; but she decided against that venture. Not so much for the sake of principle, I believe, as because she happened not to like him.</p><p >Although it required an effort to leave Miss Mills, I fell rather willingly into my aunt's pretence, as a means of enabling me to pass a few tranquil hours with Agnes. I consulted the good Doctor relative to an absence of three days; and the Doctor wishing me to take that relaxation,—he wished me to take more; but my energy could not bear that,—I made up my mind to go.</p><p >As to the Commons, I had no great occasion to be particular about my duties in that quarter. To say the truth, we were getting in no very good odour among the tip-top proctors, and were rapidly sliding down to but a doubtful position. The business had been indifferent under Mr. Jorkins, before Mr. Spenlow's time; and although it had been quickened by the infusion of new blood, and by the display which Mr. Spenlow made, still it was not established on a sufficiently strong basis to bear, without being shaken, such a blow as the sudden loss of its active manager. It fell off very much. Mr. Jorkins, notwithstanding his reputation in the firm, was an easy-going, incapable, sort of man, whose reputation out of doors was not calculated to back it up. I was turned over to him now, and when I saw him take <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>h i ssnuff</sic><corr>his snuff</corr></choice> and let the business go, I regretted my aunt's thousand pounds more than ever.</p><p >But this was not the worst of it. There were a number of hangers-on and outsiders about the Commons, who, without being proctors themselves, dabbled in common-form business, and got it done by real proctors, who lent their names in consideration of a share in the spoil;—and there were a good many of these too. As our house now wanted business on any terms, we joined this noble band; and threw out lures to the hangers-on and outsiders, to bring their business to us. Marriage licenses and small probates were what we all looked for, and what paid us best; and the competition for these, ran very high indeed. Kidnappers and inveiglers were planted in all the avenues of entrance to the Commons, with instructions to do their utmost to cut off all persons in mourning, and all gentlemen with anything bashful in their appearance, and entice them to
<pb xml:id="p398"/>
the offices in which their respective employers were interested; which instructions were so well observed, that I myself, before I was known by sight, was twice hustled into the premises of our principal opponent. The conflicting interests of these touting gentlemen being of a nature to irritate their feelings, personal collisions took place; and the Commons was even scandalised by our principal inveigler (who had formerly been in the wine trade, and afterwards in the sworn brokery line) walking about for some days with a black eye. Any one of these scouts used to think nothing of politely assisting an old lady in black out of a vehicle, killing any proctor whom she inquired for, representing his employer as the lawful successor and representative of that proctor, and bearing the old lady off (sometimes greatly affected) to his employer's office. Many captives were brought to me in this way. As to marriage licenses, the competition rose to such a pitch, that a shy gentleman in want of one, had nothing to do but submit himself to the first inveigler, or be fought for, and become the prey of the strongest. One of our clerks, who was an outsider, used, in the height of this contest, to sit with his hat on, that he might be ready to rush out and swear before a surrogate any victim who was brought in. The system of inveigling continues, I believe, to this day. The last time I was in the Commons, a civil able-bodied person in a white apron pounced out upon me from a doorway, and whispering the word “Marriage-license” in my ear, was with great difficulty prevented from taking me up in his arms and lifting me into a proctor's.</p><p >From this digression, let me proceed to Dover.</p><p >I found everything in a satisfactory state at the cottage; and was enabled to gratify my aunt exceedingly by reporting that the tenant inherited her feud, and waged incessant war against donkies. Having settled the little business I had to transact there, and slept there one night, I walked on to Canterbury early in the morning. It was now winter again; and the fresh, cold windy day, and the sweeping downland, brightened up my hopes a little.</p><p >Coming into Canterbury, I loitered through the old streets with a sober pleasure that calmed my spirits, and eased my heart. There were the old signs, the old names over the shops, the old people serving in them. It appeared so long, since I had been a schoolboy there, that I wondered the place was so little changed, until I reflected how little I was changed myself. Strange to say, that quiet influence which was inseparable in my mind from Agnes, seemed to pervade even the city where she dwelt. The venerable cathedral towers, and the old jackdaws and rooks whose airy voices made them more retired than perfect silence would have done; the battered gateways, once stuck full with statues, long thrown down, and crumbled away, like the reverential pilgrims who had gazed upon them; the still nooks, where the ivied growth of centuries crept over gabled ends and ruined walls; the ancient houses, the pastoral landscape of field, orchard, and garden; everywhere—on everything—I felt the same serener air, the same calm, thoughtful, softening spirit.</p><p >Arrived at Mr. Wickfield's house, I found, in the little lower-room on the ground floor, where Uriah Heep had been of old accustomed to sit, Mr. Micawber plying his pen with great assiduity. He was dressed in a legal-looking suit of black, and loomed, burly and large, in that small office.</p><pb  xml:id="p399"/><p >Mr. Micawber was extremely glad to see me, but a little confused too. He would have conducted me immediately into the presence of Uriah, but I declined.</p><p >“I know the house of old, you recollect,” said I, “and will find my way up stairs. How do you like the law, Mr. Micawber?”</p><p >“My dear Copperfield,” he replied. “To a man possessed of the higher imaginative powers, the objection to legal studies is the amount of detail which they involve. Even in our professional correspondence,” said Mr. Micawber, glancing at some letters he was writing, “the mind is not at liberty to soar to any exalted form of expression. Still, it is a great pursuit. A great pursuit!”</p><p >He then told me that he had become the tenant of Uriah Heep's old house; and that Mrs. Micawber would be delighted to receive me, once more, under her own roof.</p><p >“It is humble,” said Mr. Micawber, “—to quote a favourite expression of my friend Heep; but it may prove the stepping-stone to more ambitious domiciliary accommodation.”</p><p >I asked him whether he had reason, so far, to be satisfied with his friend Heep's treatment of him? He got up to ascertain if the door were close shut, before he replied, in a lower voice:</p><p >“My dear Copperfield, a man who labours under the pressure of pecuniary embarrassments, is, with the generality of people, at a disadvantage. That disadvantage is not diminished, when that pressure necessitates the drawing of stipendiary emoluments, before those emoluments are strictly due and payable. All I can say is, that my friend Heep has responded to appeals to which I need not more particularly refer, in a manner calculated to redound equally to the honour of his head, and of his heart.”</p><p >“I should not have supposed him to be very free with his money either,” I observed.</p><p >“Pardon me!” said Mr. Micawber, with an air of constraint, “I speak of my friend Heep as I have experience.”</p><p >“I am glad your experience is so favourable,” I returned.</p><p >“You are very obliging, my dear Copperfield,” said Mr. Micawber; and hummed a tune.</p><p >“Do you see much of Mr. Wickfield?” I asked, to change the subject.</p><p >“Not much,” said Mr. Micawber, slightingly. “Mr. Wickfield is, I dare say, a man of very excellent intentions; but he is—in short, he is obsolete.”</p><p >“I am afraid his partner seeks to make him so,” said I.</p><p >“My dear Copperfield!” returned Mr. Micawber, after some uneasy evolutions on his stool, “allow me to offer a remark! I am here, in a capacity of confidence. I am here, in a position of trust. The discussion of some topics, even with Mrs. Micawber herself (so long the partner of my various vicissitudes, and a woman of a remarkable lucidity of intellect), is, I am led to consider, incompatible with the functions now devolving on me. I would therefore take the liberty of suggesting that in our friendly intercourse—which I trust will never be disturbed!—we draw a line. On one side of this line,” said Mr. Micawber, representing it on the desk with the office ruler, “is the whole range of the human
<pb xml:id="p400"/>
intellect, with a trifling exception; on the other, <hi rend="italics">is</hi> that exception; that is to say, the affairs of Messrs. Wickfield and Heep, with all belonging and appertaining thereunto. I trust I give no offence to the companion of my youth, in submitting this proposition to his cooler judgment?”</p><p >Though I saw an uneasy change in Mr. Micawber, which sat tightly on him, as if his new duties were a misfit, I felt I had no right to be offended. My telling him so, appeared to relieve him; and he shook hands with me.</p><p >“I am charmed, Copperfield,” said Mr. Micawber, “let me assure you, with Miss Wickfield. She is a very superior young lady, of very remarkable attractions, graces, and virtues. Upon my honour,” said Mr. Micawber, indefinitely kissing his hand and bowing with his genteelest air, “I do Homage to Miss Wickfield! Hem!”</p><p >“I am glad of that, at least,” said I.</p><p >“If you had not assured us, my dear Copperfield, on the occasion of that agreeable afternoon we had the happiness of passing with you, that D was your favourite letter,” said Mr. Micawber, “I should unquestionably have supposed that A had been so.”</p><p >We have all some experience of a feeling, that comes over us occasionally, of what we are saying and doing having been said and done before, in a remote time—of our having been surrounded, dim ages ago, by the same faces, objects, and circumstances—of our knowing perfectly what will be said next, as if we suddenly remembered it! I never had this mysterious impression more strongly in my life, than before he uttered those words.</p><p >I took my leave of Mr. Micawber, for the time, charging him with my best remembrances to all at home. As I left him, resuming his stool and his pen, and rolling his head in his stock, to get it into easier writing order, I clearly perceived that there was something interposed between him and me, since he had come into his new functions which prevented our getting at each other as we used to do, and quite altered the character of our intercourse.</p><p >There was no one in the quaint old drawing-room, though it presented tokens of Mrs. Heep's whereabout. I looked into the room still belonging to Agnes, and saw her sitting by the fire, at a pretty old fashioned desk she had, writing.</p><p >My darkening the light made her look up. What a pleasure to be the cause of that bright change in her attentive face, and the object of that sweet regard and welcome!</p><p >“Ah, Agnes!” said I, when we were sitting together, side by side; “I have missed you so much, lately!”</p><p >“Indeed?” she replied. “Again! And so soon?”</p><p >I shook my head.</p><p >“I don't know how it is, Agnes; I seem to want some faculty of mind that I ought to have. You were so much in the habit of thinking for me, in the happy old days here, and I came so naturally to you for counsel and support, that I really think I have missed acquiring it?”</p><p >“And what is it?” said Agnes, cheerfully.</p><p >“I don't know what to call it,” I replied. “I think I am earnest and persevering?”</p><pb  xml:id="p401"/><p >“I am sure of it,” said Agnes.</p><p >“And patient, Agnes?” I enquired, with a little hesitation.</p><p >“Yes,” returned Agnes, laughing. “Pretty well.”</p><p >“And yet,” said I, “I get so miserable and worried, and am so unsteady and irresolute in my power of assuring myself, that I know I must want—shall I call it—reliance, of some kind?”</p><p >“Call it so, if you will,” said Agnes.</p><p >“Well!” I returned. “See here! You come to London, I rely on you, and I have an object and a course at once. I am driven out of it, I come here, and in a moment I feel an altered person. The circumstances that distressed me are not changed, since I came into this room; but an influence comes over me in that short interval that alters me, oh, how much for the better! What is it? What is your secret, Agnes?”</p><p >Her head was bent down, looking at the fire.</p><p >“It's the old story,” said I. “Don't laugh, when I say it was always the same in little things as it is in greater ones. My old troubles were nonsense, and now they are serious; but whenever I have gone away from my adopted sister—”</p><p >Agnes looked up—with such a Heavenly face!—and gave me her hand, which I kissed.</p><p >“Whenever I have not had you, Agnes, to advise and approve in the beginning, I have seemed to go wild, and to get into all sorts of difficulty. When I have come to you, at last (as I have always done), I have come to peace and happiness. I come home, now, like a tired traveller, and find such a blessed sense of rest!”</p><p >I felt so deeply what I said, it affected me so sincerely, that my voice failed, and I covered my face with my hand, and broke into tears. I write the truth. Whatever contradictions and inconsistencies there were within me, as there are within so many of us; whatever might have been so different, and so much better; whatever I had done, in which I had perversely wandered away from the voice of my own heart; I knew nothing of. I only knew that I was fervently in earnest, when I felt the rest and peace of having Agnes near me.</p><p >In her placid sisterly manner; with her beaming eyes; with her tender voice; and with that sweet composure, which had long ago made the house that held her quite a sacred place to me; she soon won me from this weakness, and led me on to tell all that had happened since our last meeting.</p><p >“And there is not another word to tell, Agnes,” said I, when I had made an end of my confidence. “Now, my reliance is on you.”</p><p >“But it must not be on me, Trotwood,” returned Agnes, with a pleasant smile. “It must be on some one else.”</p><p >“On Dora?” said I.</p><p >“Assuredly.”</p><p >“Why, I have not mentioned, Agnes,” said I, a little embarrassed, “that Dora is rather difficult to—I would not, for the world, say, to rely upon, because she is the soul of purity and truth—but rather difficult to—I hardly know how to express it, really, Agnes. She is a timid little thing, and easily disturbed and frightened. Some time ago, before her father's death, when I thought it right to mention to her—but I'll tell you, if you will bear with me, how it was.”</p><pb  xml:id="p402"/><p >Accordingly, I told Agnes about my declaration of poverty, about the cookery-book, the housekeeping accounts, and all the rest of it.</p><p >“Oh, Trotwood!” she remonstrated, with a smile. “Just your old headlong way! You might have been in earnest in striving to get on in the world, without being so very sudden with a timid, loving, inexperienced girl. Poor Dora!”</p><p >I never heard such sweet forbearing kindness expressed in a voice, as she expressed in making this reply. It was as if I had seen her admiringly and tenderly embracing Dora, and tacitly reproving me, by her considerate protection, for my hot haste in fluttering that little heart. It was as if I had seen Dora, in all her fascinating artlessness, caressing Agnes, and thanking her, and coaxingly appealing against me, and loving me with all her childish innocence.</p><p >I felt so grateful to Agnes, and admired her so! I saw those two together, in a bright perspective, such well-associated friends, each adorning the other so much!</p><p >“What ought I to do then, Agnes?” I inquired, after looking at the fire a little while. “What would it be right to do?”</p><p >“I think,” said Agnes, “that the honourable course to take, would be to write to those two ladies. Don't you think that any secret course is an unworthy one?”</p><p >“Yes. If <hi rend="italics">you</hi> think so,” said I.</p><p >“I am poorly qualified to judge of such matters,” replied Agnes, with a modest hesitation, “but I certainly feel—in short, I feel that your being secret and clandestine, is not being like yourself.”</p><p >“Like myself, in the too high opinion you have of me, Agnes, I am afraid,” said I.</p><p >“Like yourself in the candour of your nature,” she returned; “and therefore I would write to those two ladies. I would relate, as plainly and as openly as possible, all that has taken place; and I would ask their permission to visit sometimes, at their house. Considering that you are young, and striving for a place in life, I think it would be well to say that you would readily abide by any conditions they might impose upon you. I would entreat them not to dismiss your request, without a reference to Dora; and to discuss it with her when they should think the time suitable. I would not be too vehement,” said Agnes, gently, “or propose too much. I would trust to my fidelity and perseverance—and to Dora.”</p><p >“But if they were to frighten Dora again, Agnes, by speaking to her,” said I. “And if Dora were to cry, and say nothing about me!”</p><p >“Is that likely?” inquired Agnes, with the same sweet consideration in her face.</p><p >“God bless her, she is as easily scared as a bird,” said I. “It might be! Or if the two Miss Spenlows (elderly ladies of that sort are odd characters sometimes) should not be likely persons to address in that way!”</p><p >“I don't think, Trotwood,” returned Agnes, raising her soft eyes to mine, “I would consider that. Perhaps it would be better only to consider whether it is right to do this; and, if it is, to do it.”</p><p >I had no longer any doubt on the subject. With a lightened heart, though with a profound sense of the weighty importance of my task, I
<pb xml:id="p403"/>
devoted the whole afternoon to the composition of the draft of this letter; for which great purpose, Agnes relinquished her desk to me. But first I went down stairs to see Mr. Wickfield and Uriah Heep.</p><p >I found Uriah in possession of a new, plaster-smelling office, built out in the garden; looking extraordinarily mean, in the midst of a quantity of books and papers. He received me in his usual fawning way, and pretended not to have heard of my arrival from Mr. Micawber; a pretence I took the liberty of disbelieving. He accompanied me into Mr. Wickfield's room, which was the shadow of its former self—having been divested of a variety of conveniences, for the accommodation of the new partner—and stood before the fire, warming his back, and shaving his chin with his bony hand, while Mr. Wickfield and I exchanged greetings.</p><p >“You stay with us, Trotwood, while you remain in Canterbury?” said Mr. Wickfield, not without a glance at Uriah for his approval.</p><p >“Is there room for me?” said I.</p><p >“I am sure, Master Copperfield—I should say Mister, but the other comes so natural,” said Uriah,—“I would turn out of your old room with pleasure, if it would be agreeable.”</p><p >“No, no,” said Mr. Wickfield. “Why should <hi rend="italics">you</hi> be inconvenienced? There's another room. There's another room.”</p><p >“Oh, but you know,” returned Uriah, with a grin, “I should really be delighted!”</p><p >To cut the matter short, I said I would have the other room or none at all; so it was settled that I should have the other room: and, taking my leave of the firm until dinner, I went up stairs again.</p><p >I had hoped, to have no other companion than Agnes. But Mrs. Heep had asked permission to bring herself and her knitting near the fire, in that room; on pretence of its having an aspect more favourable for her rheumatics, as the wind then was, than the drawing-room or dining-parlour. Though I could almost have consigned her to the mercies of the wind on the topmost pinnacle of the Cathedral, without remorse, I made a virtue of necessity, and gave her a friendly salutation.</p><p >“I'm umbly thankful to you, sir,” said Mrs. Heep, in acknowledgment of my inquiries concerning her health, “but I'm only pretty well. I haven't much to boast of. If I could see my Uriah well settled in life, I couldn't expect much more I think. How do you think my Ury looking, sir?”</p><p >I thought him looking as villanous as ever, and I replied that I saw no change in him.</p><p >“Oh, don't you think he's changed?” said Mrs. Heep. “There I must umbly beg leave to differ from you. Don't you see a thinness in him?”</p><p >“Not more than usual,” I replied.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Don't</hi> you though!” said Mrs. Heep. “But you don't take notice of him with a mother's eye!”</p><p >His mother's eye was an evil eye to the rest of the world, I thought as it met mine, howsoever affectionate to him; and I believe she and her son were devoted to one another. It passed me, and went on to Agnes.</p><p >“Don't <hi rend="italics">you</hi> see a wasting and a wearing in him, Miss Wickfield?” inquired Mrs. Heep.</p><pb  xml:id="p404"/><p >“No,” said Agnes, quietly pursuing the work on which she was engaged. “You are too solicitous about him. He is very well.”</p><p >Mrs. Heep, with a prodigious sniff, resumed her knitting.</p><p >She never left off, or left us for a moment. I had arrived early in the day, and we had still three or four hours before dinner; but she sat there, plying her knitting-needles as monotonously as an hour-glass might have poured out its sands. She sat on one side of the fire; I sat at the desk in front of it; a little beyond me, on the other side, sat Agnes. Whensoever, slowly pondering over my letter, I lifted up my eyes, and meeting the thoughtful face of Agnes, saw it clear, and beam encouragement upon me, with its own angelic expression, I was conscious presently of the evil eye passing me, and going on to her, and coming back to me again, and dropping furtively upon the knitting. What the knitting was, I don't know, not being learned in that art; but it looked like a net; and as she worked away with those Chinese chopsticks of knitting-needles, she showed in the firelight like an ill-looking enchantress, baulked as yet by the radiant goodness opposite, but getting ready for a cast of her net by-and-by.</p><p >At dinner she maintained her watch, with the same unwinking eyes. After dinner, her son took his turn; and when Mr. Wickfield, himself, and I were left alone together, leered at me, and writhed until I could hardly bear it. In the drawing-room, there was the mother knitting and watching again. All the time that Agnes sang and played, the mother sat at the piano. Once she asked for a particular ballad, which she said her Ury (who was yawning in a great chair) doted on; and at intervals she looked round at him, and reported to Agnes that he was in raptures with the music. But she hardly ever spoke—I question if she ever did—without making some mention of him. It was evident to me that this was the duty assigned to her.</p><p >This lasted until bedtime. To have seen the mother and son, like two great bats hanging over the whole house, and darkening it with their ugly forms, made me so uncomfortable, that I would rather have remained down stairs, knitting and all, than gone to bed. I hardly got any sleep. Next day the knitting and watching began again, and lasted all day.</p><p >I had not an opportunity of speaking to Agnes, for ten minutes. I could barely show her my letter. I proposed to her to walk out with me; but Mrs. Heep repeatedly complaining that she was worse, Agnes charitably remained within, to bear her company. Towards the twilight I went out by myself, musing on what I ought to do, and whether I was justified in withholding from Agnes, any longer, what Uriah Heep had told me in London; for that began to trouble me again, very much.</p><p >I had not walked out far enough to be quite clear of the town, upon the Ramsgate road, where there was a good path, when I was hailed, through the dusk, by somebody behind me. The shambling figure, and the scanty great coat, were not to be mistaken. I stopped, and Uriah Heep came up.</p><p >“Well?” said I.</p><p >“How fast you walk!” said he. “My legs are pretty long, but you've given 'em quite a job.”</p><p >“Where are you going?” said I.</p><p >“I am coming with you, Master Copperfield, if you'll allow me the
<pb xml:id="p405"/>
pleasure of a walk with an old acquaintance.” Saying this, with a jerk of his body, which might have been either propitiatory or derisive, he fell into step beside me.</p><p >“Uriah!” said I, as civilly as I could, after a silence.</p><p >“Master Copperfield!” said Uriah.</p><p >“To tell you the truth (at which you will not be offended), I came out to walk alone, because I have had so much company.”</p><p >He looked at me sideways, and said with his hardest grin, “You mean mother?”</p><p >“Why yes, I do,” said I.</p><p >“Ah! But you know we're so very umble,” he returned. “And having such a knowledge of our own umbleness, we must really take care that we're not pushed to the wall by them as isn't umble. All stratagems are fair in love, sir.”</p><p >Raising his great hands until they touched his chin, he rubbed them softly, and softly chuckled; looking as like a malevolent baboon, I thought, as anything human could look.</p><p >“You see,” he said, still hugging himself in that unpleasant way, and shaking his head at me, “you're quite a dangerous rival, Master Copperfield. You always was, you know.”</p><p >“Do you set a watch upon Miss Wickfield, and make her home no home, because of me?” said I.</p><p >“Oh! Master Copperfield! Those are very arsh words,” he replied.</p><p >“Put my meaning into any words you like,” said I. “You know what it is, Uriah, as well as I do.”</p><p >“Oh no! You must put it into words,” he said. “Oh, really! I couldn't myself.”</p><p >“Do you suppose,” said I, constraining myself to be very temperate and quiet with him, on account of Agnes, “that I regard Miss Wickfield otherwise than as a very dear sister?”</p><p >“Well, Master Copperfield,” he replied, “you perceive I am not bound to answer that question. You may not, you know. But then, you see, you may!”</p><p >Anything to equal the low cunning of his visage, and of his shadowless eyes without the ghost of an eyelash, I never saw.</p><p >“Come, then!” said I. “For the sake of Miss Wickfield —”</p><p >“My Agnes!” he exclaimed, with a sickly, angular contortion of himself. “Would you be so good as call her Agnes, Master Copperfield!”</p><p >“For the sake of Agnes Wickfield—Heaven bless her!”</p><p >“Thank you for that blessing, Master Copperfield!” he interposed.</p><p >“I will tell you what I should, under any other circumstances, as soon have thought of telling to—Jack Ketch.”</p><p >“To who, sir?” said Uriah, stretching out his neck, and shading his ear with his hand.</p><p >“To the hangman,” I returned. “The most unlikely person I could think of,”—though his own face had suggested the allusion quite as a natural sequence. “I am engaged to another young lady. I hope that contents you.”</p><p >“Upon your soul?” said Uriah.</p><p >I was about indignantly to give my assertion the confirmation he required, when he caught hold of my hand, and gave it a squeeze.</p><pb  xml:id="p406"/><p >“Oh, Master Copperfield!” he said. “If you had only had the condescension to return my confidence when I poured out the fulness of my art, the night I put you so much out of the way by sleeping before your sitting-room fire, I never should have doubted you. As it is, I'm sure I'll take off mother directly, and only too appy. I know you'll excuse the precautions of affection, won't you? What a pity, Master Copperfield, that you didn't condescend to return my confidence! I'm sure I gave you every opportunity. But you never have condescended to me, as much as I could have wished. I know you have never liked me, as I have liked you!”</p><p >All this time he was squeezing my hand with his damp fishey fingers, while I made every effort I decently could to get it away. But I was quite unsuccessful. He drew it under the sleeve of his mulberry-colored great coat, and I walked on, almost upon compulsion, arm in arm with him.</p><p >“Shall we turn?” said Uriah, by-and-by wheeling me face about towards the town, on which the early moon was now shining, silvering the distant windows.</p><p >“Before we leave the subject, you ought to understand,” said I, breaking a pretty long silence, “that I believe Agnes Wickfield to be as far above <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> and as far removed from all <hi rend="italics">your</hi> aspirations, as that moon herself!”</p><p >“Peaceful! Ain't she!” said Uriah. “Very! Now confess, Master Copperfield, that you havn't liked me quite as I have liked you. All along you've thought me too umble now, I shouldn't wonder?”</p><p >“I am not fond of professions of humility,” I returned, “or professions of anything else.”</p><p >“There now!” said Uriah, looking flabby and lead-coloured in the moonlight. “Didn't I know it! But how little you think of the rightful umbleness of a person in my station, Master Copperfield! Father and me was both brought up at a foundation school for boys; and mother, she was likewise brought up at a public, sort of charitable, establishment. They taught us all a deal of umbleness—not much else that I know of, from morning to night. We was to be umble to this person, and umble to that; and to pull off our caps here, and to make bows there; and always to know our place, and abase ourselves before our betters. And we had such a lot of betters! Father got the monitor-medal by being umble. So did I. Father got made a sexton by being umble. He had the character, among the gentlefolks, of being such a well-behaved man, that they were determined to bring him in. ‘Be umble, Uriah,’ says father to me, ‘and you'll get on. It was what was always being dinned into you and me at school; it's what goes down best. Be umble,’ says father, ‘and you'll do!’ And really it ain't done bad!”</p><p >It was the first time it had ever occurred to me, that this detestable cant of false humility might have originated out of the Heep family. I had seen the harvest, but had never thought of the seed.</p><p >“When I was quite a young boy,” said Uriah, “I got to know what umbleness did, and I took to it. I ate umble pie with an appetite. I stopped at the umble point of my learning, and says I, ‘Hold heard!’ When you offered to teach me latin, I knew better. ‘People like to
<pb xml:id="p407"/>
be above you,’ says father, ‘keep yourself down.’ I am very umble to the present moment, Master Copperfield, but I've got a little power!”</p><p >And he said all this—I knew, as I saw his face in the moonlight—that I might understand he was resolved to recompense himself by using his power. I had never doubted his meanness, his craft and malice; but I fully comprehended now, for the first time, what a base, unrelenting, and revengeful spirit, must have been engendered by this early, and this long, suppression.</p><p >His account of himself was so far attended with an agreeable result, that it led to his withdrawing his hand in order that he might have another hug of himself under the chin. Once apart from him, I was determined to keep apart; and we walked back, side by side, saying very little more by the way.</p><p >Whether his spirits were elevated by the communication I had made to him, or by his having indulged in this retrospect, I don't know; but they were raised by some influence. He talked more at dinner than was usual with him; asked his mother (off duty, from the moment of our re-entering the house), whether he was not growing too old for a bachelor; and once looked at Agnes so, that I would have given all I had, for leave to knock him down.</p><p >When we three males were left alone after dinner, he got into a more adventurous state. He had taken little or no wine; and I presume it was the mere insolence of triumph that was upon him, flushed perhaps by the temptation my presence furnished to its exhibition.</p><p >I had observed yesterday, that he tried to entice Mr. Wickfield to drink; and, interpreting the look which Agnes had given me as she went out, had limited myself to one glass, and then proposed that we should follow her. I would have done so again to-day; but Uriah was too quick for me.</p><p >“We seldom see our present visitor, sir,” he said, addressing Mr. Wickfield, sitting, such a contrast to him, at the end of the table, “and I should propose to give him welcome in another glass or two of wine, if you have no objections. Mr. Copperfield, your elth and appiness!”</p><p >I was obliged to make a show of taking the hand the stretched across to me; and then, with very different emotions, I took the hand of the broken gentleman, his partner.</p><p >“Come, fellow partner,” said Uriah, “if I may take the liberty,—now suppose you give us something or another appropriate to Copperfield!”</p><p >I pass over Mr. Wickfield's proposing my aunt, his proposing Mr. Dick his proposing Doctor's Commons, his proposing Uriah, his drinking everything twice; his consciousness of his own weakness, the ineffectual effort that he made against it; the struggle between his shame in Uriah's deportment, and his desire to conciliate him; the manifest exultation with which Uriah twisted and turned, and held him up before me. It made me sick at heart to see, and my hand recoils from writing it.</p><p >“Come, fellow partner!” said Uriah, at last, “<hi rend="italics">I</hi>'ll give you another one, and I umbly ask for bumpers, seeing I intend to make it the divinest of her sex.”</p><p >Her father had his empty glass in his hand. I saw him set it down look at the picture she was so like, put his hand to his forehead, and shrink back in his elbow chair.</p><pb  xml:id="p408"/><p >“I'm an umble individual to give you her elth,” proceeded Uriah, “but I admire—adore her.”</p><p >No physical pain that her father's grey head could have borne, I think could have been more terrible to me, than the mental endurance I saw compressed now within both his hands.</p><p >“Agnes,” said Uriah, either not regarding him, or not knowing what the nature of his action was, “Agnes Wickfield is, I am safe to say, the divinest of her sex. May I speak out, among friends? To be her father is a proud distinction, but to be her <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>usband</sic><corr>husband</corr></choice>—”</p><p >Spare me from ever again hearing such a cry, as that with which her father rose up from the table!</p><p >“What's the matter?” said Uriah, turning of a deadly colour. “You are not gone mad, after all, Mr. Wickfield, I hope? If I say, I've an ambition to make your Agnes my Agnes, I have as good a right to it as another man. I have a better right to it than any other man!”</p><p >I had my arms round Mr. Wickfield, imploring him by everything that I could think of, oftenest of all by his love for Agnes, to calm himself a little. He was mad for the moment; tearing out his hair, beating his head, trying to force me from him and to force himself from me, not answering a word, not looking at or seeing any one; blindly striving for he knew not what, his face all staring and distorted—a frightful spectacle.</p><p >I conjured him, incoherently, but in the most impassioned manner, not to abandon himself to this wildness, but to hear me. I besought him to think of Agnes, to connect me with Agnes, to recollect how Agnes and I had grown up together, how I honored her and loved her, how she was his pride and joy. I tried to bring her idea before him in any form; I even reproached him with not having firmness to spare her the knowledge of such a scene as this. I may have effected something, or his wildness may have spent itself; but by degrees he struggled less, and began to look at me—strangely at first, then with recognition in his eyes. At length he said, “I know, Trotwood! My darling child and you—I know! But look at him!”</p><p >He pointed to Uriah, pale and glowering in a corner, evidently very much out in his calculations, and taken by surprise.</p><p >“Look at my torturer,” he replied. “Before him I have step by step abandoned name and reputation, peace and quiet, house and home.”</p><p >“I have kept your name and reputation for you, and your peace and quiet, and your house and home too,” said Uriah, with a sulky, hurried, defeated air of compromise. “Don't be foolish, Mr. Wickfield. If I have gone a little beyond what you were prepared for, I can go back I suppose? There's no harm done.”</p><p >“I looked for single motives in every one,” said Mr. Wickfield, “and I was satisfied I had bound him to me by motives of interest. But see what he is—oh, see what he is!”</p><p >“You had better stop him, Copperfield, if you can,” cried Uriah, with his long fore-finger pointing towards me. “He'll say something presently—mind you!—he'll be sorry to have said afterwards, and you'll be sorry to have heard!”</p><p >“I'll say anything!” cried Mr. Wickfield, with a desperate air. “Why should I not be in all the world's power if I am in yours!”</p><pb  xml:id="p409"/><p >“Mind! I tell you!” said Uriah, continuing to warn me. “If you don't stop his mouth, you're not his friend! Why shouldn't you be in all the world's power, Mr. Wickfield? Because you have got a daughter. You and me know what we know, don't we? Let sleeping dogs lie—who wants to rouse 'em? I don't. Can't you see I am as umble as I can be? I tell you, if I've gone too far, I'm sorry. What would you have, sir?”</p><p >“Oh, Trotwood, Trotwood!” exclaimed Mr. Wickfield, wringing his hands. “What I have come down to be, since I first saw you in this house! I was on my downward way then, but the dreary, dreary, road I have traversed since! Weak indulgence has ruined me. Indulgence in remembrance, and indulgence in forgetfulness. My natural grief for my child's mother turned to disease; my natural love for my child turned to disease. I have infected everything I touched. I have brought misery on what I dearly love, I know—<hi rend="italics">You</hi> know! I thought it possible that I could truly love one creature in the world, and not love the rest; I thought it possible that I could truly mourn for one creature gone out of the world, and not have some part in the grief of all who mourned. Thus the lessons of my life have been perverted! I have preyed on my own morbid coward heart, and it has preyed on me. Sordid in my grief, sordid in my love, sordid in my miserable escape from the darker side of both, oh see the ruin I am, and hate me, shun me!”</p><p >He dropped into a chair, and weakly sobbed. The excitement into which he had been roused was leaving him. Uriah came out of his corner.</p><p >“I don't know all I have done, in my fatuity,” said Mr. Wickfield, putting out his hands, as if to deprecate my condemnation. “<hi rend="italics">He</hi> knows best,” meaning Uriah Heep, “for he has always been at my elbow, whispering me. You see the millstone that he is about my neck. You find him in my house, you find him in my business. You heard him, but a little time ago. What need have I to say more!”</p><p >“You haven't need to say so much, nor half so much, nor anything at all,” observed Uriah, half defiant, and half fawning. “You wouldn't have took it up so, if it hadn't been for the wine. You'll think better of it to-morrow, sir. If I have said too much, or more than I meant, what of it? I haven't stood by it!”</p><p >The door opened, and Agnes, gliding in, without a vestige of colour in her face, put her arm round his neck, and steadily said, “Papa, you are not well. Come with me!” He laid his head upon her shoulder, as if he were oppressed with heavy shame, and went out with her. Her eyes met mine for but an instant, yet I saw how much she knew of what had passed.</p><p >“I didn't expect he'd cut up so rough, Master Copperfield,” said Uriah. “But it's nothing. I'll be friends with him to-morrow. It's for his good. I'm umbly anxious for his good.”</p><p >I gave him no answer, and went upstairs into the quiet room where Agnes had so often sat beside me at my books. Nobody came near me until late at night. I took up a book, and tried to read. I heard the clocks strike twelve, and was still reading, without knowing what I read, when Agnes touched me.</p><pb  xml:id="p410"/><p >“You will be going early in the morning, Trotwood. Let us say good bye, now!”</p><p >She had been weeping, but her face then was so calm and beautiful!</p><p >“Heaven bless you!” she said, giving me her hand.</p><p >“Dearest Agnes!” I returned, “I see you ask me not to speak of to-night—but is there nothing to be done?”</p><p >“There is God to trust in!” she replied.</p><p >“Can <hi rend="italics">I</hi> do nothing—<hi rend="italics">I,</hi> who come to you with <hi rend="italics">my</hi> poor sorrows?”</p><p >“And make mine so much lighter,” she replied. “Dear Trotwood, no!”</p><p >“Dear Agnes,” I said, “it is presumptuous for me, who am so poor in all in which you are so rich—goodness, resolution, all noble qualities—to doubt or direct you; but you know how much I love you, and how much I owe you. You will never sacrifice yourself to a mistaken sense of duty, Agnes?”</p><p >More agitated for a moment than I had ever seen her, she took her hand from me, and moved a step back.</p><p >“Say you have no such thought, dear Agnes! Much more than sister! Think of the priceless gift of such a heart as yours, of such a love as yours!”</p><p >Oh! long, long afterwards, I saw that face rise up before me, with its momentary look, not wondering, not accusing, not regretting. Oh, long, long afterwards, I saw that look subside, as it did now, into the lovely smile, with which she told me she had no fear for herself—I need have none for her—and parted from me by the name of Brother, and was gone!</p><p >It was dark in the morning, when I got upon the coach at the inn door. The day was just breaking when we were about to start, and then, as I sat thinking of her, came struggling up the coach side, through the mingled day and night, Uriah's head.</p><p >“Copperfield!” said he, in a croaking whisper, as he hung by the iron on the roof, “I thought you'd be glad to hear before you went off, that there are no squares broke between us. I've been into his room already, and we've made it all smooth. Why, though I'm umble, I'm useful to him, you know; and he understands his interest when he isn't in liquor! What an agreeable man he is, after all, Master Copperfield!”</p><p >I obliged myself to say that I was glad he had made his apology.</p><p >“Oh, to be sure!” said Uriah. “When a person's umble, you know, what's an apology? So easy! I say! I suppose,” with a jerk, “you have sometimes plucked a pear before it was ripe, Master Copperfield?”</p><p >“I suppose I have,” I replied.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">I</hi> did that last night,” said Uriah; “but it'll ripen yet! It only wants attending to. I can wait!”</p><p >Profuse in his farewells, he got down again as the coachman got up. For anything I know, he was eating something to keep the raw morning air out; but, he made motions with his mouth as if the pear were ripe already, and he were smacking his lips over it.</p></div><div type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p411"/><head >CHAPTER XL. <lb/> THE WANDERER.</head><p >WE had a very serious conversation in Buckingham Street that night, about the domestic occurrences I have detailed in the last chapter. My aunt was deeply interested in them, and walked up and down the room with her arms folded, for more than two hours afterwards. Whenever she was particularly discomposed, she always performed one of these pedestrian feats; and the amount of her discomposure might always be estimated by the duration of her walk. On this occasion she was so much disturbed in mind as to find it necessary to open the bed-room door, and make a course for herself, comprising the full extent of the bed-rooms from wall to wall; and while Mr. Dick and I sat quietly by the fire, she kept passing in and out, along this measured track, at an unchanging pace, with the regularity of a clock-pendulum.</p><p >When my aunt and I were left to ourselves by Mr. Dick's going out to bed, I sat down to write my letter to the two old ladies. By that time she was tired of walking, and sat by the fire with her dress tucked up as usual. But instead of sitting in her usual manner, holding her glass upon her knee, she suffered it to stand neglected on the chimney-piece; and, resting her left elbow on her right arm, and her chin on her left hand, looked thoughtfully at me. As often as I raised my eyes from what I was about, I met hers. “I am in the lovingest of tempers, my dear,” she would assure me with a nod, “but I am fidgetted and sorry!”</p><p >I had been too busy to observe, until after she was gone to bed, that she had left her night-mixture, as she always called it, untasted on the chimney-piece. She came to her door, with even more than her usual affection of manner, when I knocked to acquaint her with this discovery; but only said, “I have not the heart to take it, Trot, to-night,” and shook her head, and went in again.</p><p >She read my letter to the two old ladies, in the morning, and approved of it. I posted it, and had nothing to do then, but wait, as patiently as I could, for the reply. I was still in this state of expectation, and had been, for nearly a week; when I left the Doctor's one snowy night, to walk home.</p><p >It had been a bitter day, and a cutting north-east wind had blown for some time. The wind had gone down with the light, and so the snow had come on. It was a heavy, settled fall, I recollect, in great flakes; and it lay thick. The noise of wheels and tread of people were as hushed, as if the streets had been strewn that depth with feathers.</p><p >My shortest way home,—and I naturally took the shortest way on such a night—was through Saint Martin's Lane. Now, the church which gives its name to the lane, stood in a less free situation at that time; there being no open space before it, and the lane winding down to the
<pb xml:id="p412"/>
Strand. As I passed the steps of the portico, I encountered, at the corner, a woman's face. It looked in mine, passed across the narrow lane, and disappeared. I knew it. I had seen it somewhere. But I could not remember where. I had some association with it, that struck upon my heart directly; but I was thinking of anything else when it came upon me, and was confused.</p><p >On the steps of the church, there was the stooping figure of a man, who had put down some burden on the smooth snow, to adjust it; my seeing the face, and my seeing him, were simultaneous. I don't think I had stopped in my surprise; but, in any case, as I went on, he rose, turned, and came down towards me. I stood face to face with Mr. Peggotty!</p><p >Then I remembered the woman. It was Martha, to whom Emily had given the money that night in the kitchen. Martha Endell—side by side with whom, he would not have seen his dear niece, Ham had told me, for all the treasures wrecked in the sea.</p><p >We shook hands heartily. At first neither of us could speak a word.</p><p >“Mas'r Davy!” he said, griping me tight, “it do my art good to see you, sir. Well met, well met!”</p><p >“Well met, my dear old friend!” said I.</p><p >“I had my thowts o' coming to make inquiration for you, sir, to-night,” he said, “but knowing as your aunt was living along wi' you—for I've been down yonder—Yarmouth way—I was afeerd it was too late. I should have come early in the morning, sir, afore going away.”</p><p >“Again?” said I.</p><p >“Yes, sir,” he replied, patiently shaking his head, “I'm away to-morrow.”</p><p >“Where were you going now?” I asked.</p><p >“Well!” he replied, shaking the snow out of his long hair, “I was a going to turn in somewheers.”</p><p >In those days there was a side-entrance to the stable-yard of the Golden Cross, the inn so memorable to me in connexion with his misfortune, nearly opposite to where we stood. I pointed out the gateway, put my arm through his, and we went across. Two or three public-rooms opened out of the stable-yard; and looking into one of them, and finding it empty, and a good fire burning, I took him in there.</p><p >When I saw him in the light, I observed, not only that his hair was long and ragged, but that his face was burnt dark by the sun. He was greyer, the lines in his face and forehead were deeper, and he had every appearance of having toiled and wandered through all varieties of weather; but he looked very strong, and like a man upheld by stedfastness of purpose, whom nothing could tire out. He shook the snow from his hat and clothes, and brushed it away from his face, while I was inwardly making these remarks. As he sate down opposite to me at a table, with his back to the door by which we had entered, he put out his rough hand again, and grasped mine warmly.</p><p >“I'll tell you, Mas'r Davy,” he said,—“wheer all I've been, and what-all we've heerd. I've been fur, and we've heerd little; but I'll tell you!”</p><p >I rang the bell for something hot to drink. He would have nothing younger than ale; and while it was being brought, and being warmed at
<pb xml:id="p413"/>
the fire, he sat thinking. There was a fine, massive gravity in his face, I did not venture to disturb.</p><p >“When she was a child,” he said, lifting up his head soon after we were left alone, “she used to talk to me a deal about the sea, and about them coasts where the sea got to be dark blue, and to lay a shining and a shining in the sun. I thowt, odd times, as her father being drownded made her think on it so much. I doen't know, you see, but maybe she believed—or hoped—he had drifted out to them parts, where the flowers is always a blowing, and the country bright.”</p><p >“It is likely to have been a childish fancy,” I replied.</p><p >“When she was—lost,” said Mr. Peggotty, “I know'd in my mind, as he would take her to them countries. I know'd in my mind, as he'd have told her wonders of 'em, and how she was to be a lady theer, and how he got her listen to him first, along o'sech like. When we see his mother, I know'd quite well as I was right. I went across-channel to France, and landed theer, as if I'd fell down from the sky.”</p><p >I saw the door move, and the snow drift in. I saw it move a little more, and a hand softly interpose to keep it open.</p><p >“I found out a English gentleman as was in authority,” said Mr. Peggotty, “and told him I was a going to seek my niece. He got me them papers as I wanted fur to carry me through—I doen't rightly know how they're called—and he would have give me money, but that I was thankful to have no need on. I thank him kind, for all he done, I'm sure! ‘I've wrote afore you,’ he says to me, ‘and I shall speak to many as will come that way, and many will know you, fur distant from here, when you're a travelling alone.’ I told him, best as I was able, what my gratitoode was, and went away through France.”</p><p >“Alone, and on foot?” said I.</p><p >“Mostly a-foot,” he rejoined; “sometimes in carts along with people going to market; sometimes in empty coaches. Many mile a day a-foot, and often with some poor soldier or another, travelling to see his friends. I couldn't talk to him,” said Mr. <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Peggoty</sic><corr>Peggotty</corr></choice>, “nor he to me; but we was company for one another, too, along the dusty roads.”</p><p >I should have known that by his friendly tone.</p><p >“When I come to any town,” he pursued, “I found the inn, and waited about the yard till some one turned up (some one mostly did) as know'd English. Then I told how that I was on my way to seek my niece, and they told me what manner of gentlefolks was in the house, and I waited to see any as seemed like her, going in or out. When it warn't Em'ly, I went on agen. By little and little, when I come to a new village or that, among the poor people, I found they know'd about me. They would set me down at their cottage doors, and give me what-not fur to eat and drink, and show me where to sleep; and many a woman, Mas'r Davy, as has had a daughter of about Em'ly's age, I've found a-waiting for me, at Our Saviour's Cross outside the village, fur to do me sim'lar kindnesses. Some has had daughters as was dead. And God only knows how good them mothers was to me!”</p><p >It was Martha at the door. I saw her haggard, listening face distinctly. My dread was lest he should turn his head, and see her too.</p><p >“They would often put their children—partic'lar their little girls,” said Mr. Peggotty, “upon my knee; and many a time you might have seen
<pb xml:id="p414"/>
me sitting at their doors, when night was coming on, a'most as if they'd been my Darling's children. Oh, my Darling!”</p><p >Overpowered by sudden grief, he sobbed aloud. I laid my trembling hand upon the hand he put before his face. “Thankee, sir,” he said, “don't take no notice.”</p><p >In a very little while he took his hand away and put it in his breast, and went on with his story.</p><p >“They often walked with me,” he said, “in the morning, maybe a mile or two upon my road; and when we parted, and I said, ‘I'm very thankful to you! God bless you!’ they always seemed to understand, and answered pleasant. At last I come to the sea. It warn't hard, you may suppose, for a seafaring man like me to work his way over to Italy. When I got theer, I wandered on as I had done afore. The people was just as good to me, and I should have gone from town to town, maybe the country through, but that I got news of her being seen among them Swiss mountains yonder. One as know'd his servant see 'em there, all three, and told me how they travelled, and where they was. I made for them mountains, Mas'r Davy, day and night. Ever so fur as I went, ever so fur the mountains seemed to shift away from me. But I come up with 'em, and I crossed 'em. When I got nigh the place as I had been told of, I began to think within my own self, ‘What shall I do when I see her?’ ”</p><p >The listening face, insensible to the inclement night, still drooped at the door, and the hands begged me—prayed me—not to cast it forth.</p><p >“I never doubted her,” said Mr. Peggotty. “No! not a bit! On'y let her see my face—on'y let her heer my voice—on'y let my stanning still afore her bring to her thoughts the home she had fled away from, and the child she had been—and if she had growed to be a royal lady, she'd have fell down at my feet! I know'd it well! Many a time in my sleep had I heerd her cry out, ‘Uncle!’ and seen her fall like death afore me. Many a time in my sleep had I raised her up, and whispered to her, ‘Em'ly my dear, I am come fur to bring forgiveness, and to take you home!’ ”</p><p >He stopped and shook his head, and went on with a sigh.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">He</hi> was nowt to me now. Em'ly was all. I bought a country dress to put upon her; and I know'd that, once found, she would walk beside me over them stony roads, go where I would, and never, never, leave me more. To put that dress upon her, and to cast off what she wore—to take her on my arm again, and wander towards home—to stop sometimes upon the road, and heal her bruised feet and her worse-bruised heart—was all that I thowt of now. I doen't believe I should have done so much as look at him. But, Mas'r Davy, it warn't to be—not yet! I was too late, and they was gone. Wheer, I couldn't learn. Some said heer, some said theer. I travelled heer, and I travelled theer, but I found no Em'ly, and I travelled home.”</p><p >“How long ago?” I asked.</p><p >“A matter o' fower days,” said Mr. Peggotty. “I sighted the old boat arter dark, and the light a shining in the winder. When I come nigh and looked in through the glass, I see the faithful creetur Missis Gummidge sittin' by the fire, as we had fixed upon, alone. I called out, ‘Doen't be afeerd! It's Dan'l!’ and I went in. I never could have thowt the old boat would have been so strange!”</p><p >From some pocket in his breast, he took out, with a very careful hand,
<pb xml:id="p415"/>
a small paper bundle containing two or three letters or little packets, which he laid upon the table.</p><p >“This first one come,” he said, selecting it from the rest, “afore I had been gone a week. A fifty pound Bank note, in a sheet of paper, directed to me, and put underneath the door in the night. She tried to hide her writing, but she couldn't hide it from Me!”</p><p >He folded up the note again, with great patience and care, in exactly the same form, and laid it on one side.</p><p >“This come to Missis Gummidge,” he said, opening another, “two or three months ago.” After looking at it for some moments, he gave it to me, and added in a low voice, “Be so good as read it, sir.”</p><p >I read as follows:</p><q ><p>“Oh what will you feel when you see this writing, and know it comes from my wicked hand! But try, try—not for my sake, but for uncle's goodness, try to let your heart soften to me, only for a little little time! Try, pray do, to relent towards a miserable girl, and write down on a bit of paper whether he is well, and what he said about me before you left off ever naming me among yourselves—and whether, of a night, when it is my old time of coming home, you ever see him look as if he thought of one he used to love so dear. Oh, my heart is breaking when I think about it! I am kneeling down to you, begging and praying you not to be as hard with me as I deserve — as I well, well, know I deserve — but to be so gentle and so good, as to write down something of him, and to send it to me. You need not call me Little, you need not call me by the name I have disgraced; but oh, listen to my agony, and have mercy on me so far as to write me some word of uncle, never, never to be seen in this world by my eyes again!</p><p>“Dear, if your heart is hard towards me—justly hard, I know—but, Listen, if it is hard, dear, ask him I have wronged the most—him whose wife I was to have been—before you quite decide against my poor poor prayer! If he should be so compassionate as to say that you might write something for me to read—I think he would, oh, I think he would, if you would only ask him, for he always was so brave and so forgiving—tell him then (but not else), that when I hear the wind blowing at night, I feel as if it was passing angrily from seeing him and uncle, and was going up to God against me. Tell him that if I was to die to-morrow (and oh, if I was fit, I would be so glad to die!) I would bless him and uncle with my last words, and pray for his happy home with my last breath!”</p></q><p >Some money was inclosed in this letter also. Five pounds. It was untouched like the previous sum, and he refolded it in the same way. Detailed instructions were added relative to the address of a reply, which, although they betrayed the intervention of several hands, and made it difficult to arrive at any very probable conclusion in reference to her place of concealment, made it at least not unlikely that she had written from that spot where she was stated to have been seen.</p><p >“What answer was sent?” I inquired of Mr. Peggotty.</p><p >“Missis Gummidge,” he returned, “not being a good scholar, sir, Ham kindly drawed it out, and she made a copy on it. They told her I was gone to seek her, and what my parting words was.”</p><p >“Is that another letter in your hand?” said I.</p><p >“It's money, sir,” said Mr. Peggotty, unfolding it a little way. “Ten pound, you see. And wrote inside, ‘From a true friend,’ like the first. But the first was put underneath the door, and this come by the post, day afore yesterday. I'm a going to seek her at the post-mark.”</p><p >He showed it to me. It was a town on the Upper Rhine. He had
<pb xml:id="p416"/>
found out, at Yarmouth, some foreign dealers who knew that country, and they had drawn him a rude map on paper, which he could very well understand. He laid it between us on the table; and, with his chin resting on one hand, tracked his course upon it with the other.</p><p >I asked him how Ham was? He shook his head.</p><p >“He works,” he said, “as bold as a man can. His name's as good, in all that part, as any man's is, anywheres in the wureld. Anyone's hand is ready to help him, you understand, and his is ready to help them. He's never been heerd fur to complain. But my sister's belief is ('twixt ourselves) as it has cut him deep.”</p><p >“Poor fellow, I can believe it!”</p><p >“He ain't no care, Mas'r Davy,” said Mr. Peggotty in a solemn whisper—“keinder no care no-how for his life. When a man's wanted for rough service in rough weather, he's theer. When there's hard duty to be done with danger in it, he steps forward afore all his mates. And yet he's as gentle as any child. There ain't a child in Yarmouth that doen't know him.”</p><p >He gathered up the letters thoughtfully, smoothing them with his hand; put them into their little bundle; and placed it tenderly in his breast again. The face was gone from the door. I still saw the snow drifting in; but nothing else was there.</p><p >“Well!” he said, looking to his bag, “having seen you to-night, Mas'r Davy (and that doos me good!) I shall away betimes to-morrow morning. You have seen what I've got heer;” putting his hand on where the little packet lay; “all that troubles me is, to think that any harm might come to me, afore that money was give back. If I was to die, and it was lost, or stole, or elseways made away with, and it was never knowed by him but what I'd took it, I believe the t'other wureld wouldn't hold me! I believe I must come back!”</p><p >He rose, and I rose too; we grasped each other by the hand again, before going out.</p><p >“I'd go ten thousand mile,” he said, “I'd go till I dropped dead, to lay that money down afore him. If I do that, and find my Em'ly, I'm content. If I doen't find her, maybe she'll come to hear, sometime, as her loving uncle only ended his search for her when he ended his life; and if I know her, even that will turn her home at last!”</p><p >As we went out into the rigorous night, I saw the lonely figure flit away before us. I turned him hastily on some pretence, and held him in conversation until it was gone.</p><p >He spoke of a traveller's house on the Dover road, where he knew he could find a clean, plain lodging for the night. I went with him over Westminster Bridge, and parted from him on the Surrey shore. Everything seemed, to my imagination, to be hushed in reverence for him, as he resumed his solitary journey through the snow.</p><p >I returned to the inn yard, and, impressed by my remembrance of the face, looked awfully around for it. It was not there. The snow had covered our late footprints; my new track was the only one to be seen; and even that began to die away (it snowed so fast) as I looked back over my shoulder.</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1c"/><head >“SO-SO.”</head><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">THOUSANDS to MOSES' Warehouse press;</l><l part="N">And pray what makes them go so?</l><l part="N">Because the articles of dress</l><l part="N">Are any thing but “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">The dress is good—the dress is smart—</l><l part="N">And all the buyers know so;</l><l part="N">And not a thing at MOSES' mart</l><l part="N">Is ever viewed as “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">No one in reason can suppose</l><l part="N">That public aid would flow so,</l><l part="N">If Messrs. MOSES in their clothes</l><l part="N">Were any thing like “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">MOSES and SON are cheap as well,</l><l part="N">And all their prices show so,</l><l part="N">Although the articles they sell</l><l part="N">Are any thing but “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Monopoly they thus attack,</l><l part="N">And while they face the foe so,</l><l part="N">Ile feels constrain'd to turn his back,</l><l part="N">And own himself but “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Come, then, and swell the list of those</l><l part="N">Who aid the vast Depot so;</l><l part="N">And purchase MOSES' new Spring clothes,</l><l part="N">So opposite to “So-so.”</l></lg><lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">If you, in point of dress, are one</l><l part="N">That's called a virtuoso,</l><l part="N">Right pleased you'll be with M. and SON,</l><l part="N">Whose dress is never “So-so.”</l></lg></lg></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><head>Ready Made.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Paletot, Ditto. </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Chesterfield, Ditto. </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome Style of Overcoats </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Shooting Coat </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Lounging and Morning Coat </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Doeskin </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Vest </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Dress Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Frock </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Youths' and Boys' Overcoats in every style, from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Hussar and Tunic Suit </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Autumn and Winter Vests </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Made to Measure.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats, from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Black Cassimere Ditto. </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Black Cloth </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Silk Velvet Ditto </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Dress Coats, from </cell><cell> 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Frock </cell><cell> 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> H. and T. Suit, from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from </cell><cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from £3 to £20.</p><p >NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p><p >MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The New Book, entitled “The Minion of the Million,” with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >NOTICE.—The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p><p >OBSERVE.—Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >E. MOSES &amp; SON,</head><p >TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p><p >ALL COMMUNICATING, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p><p >TAKE NOTICE.—This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2c"/><head >MESSRS. NICOLL'S WAREROOMS,</head><p >Through the purchase of adjoining premises, now extend over a space hitherto occupied by four large Establishments, viz, 114, 116, 118, and 120, REGENT STREET, thus forming, with their several suites of Show Rooms on the First Floor, not only the largest, but also the most elegant, Magazine for Gentlemen's Clothing to be met with in Europe.</p><p >The Entrance to the WHOLESALE AND SHIPPING DEPARTMENTS, for the sale of Woollen Cloths, &amp;c., will, for the future, be in Warwick-street, No. 41 (immediately at the rear of the Retail Warerooms in Regent-street), where the counting-house is also placed, and to which address all applications for agencies, &amp;c., are referred, as also those who may desire interviews with the Principals, or Heads of Departments; but Manufacturers, or others, having novelties to submit to the above firm, are requested to make an appointment by writing.</p><p >Those who are desirous of becoming Messrs. NICOLL'S Agents for the sale of their Patented and other Goods, in such towns of the United Kingdom or Colonies, where Messrs. N. are at present unrepresented, are informed that the Goods in question may be sold by them at the same price as they are retailed in Regent street; at the same time affording to the Agent a better profit than if attempts be made to copy, or otherwise pirate, the several articles.</p><p >Merchants, Shippers, and others, will find the class of goods sold by Messrs. NICOLL peculiarly well adapted, through their excellence of quality and finish, for the wants of the now numerous respectable residents in the Colonies, as the Goods are such as are required by the wealthy and middle classes of the Mother Country. Indeed, a safer or more profitable venture cannot be made by Shippers, seeing that the Market has been hitherto almost exclusively supplied with garments calculated, in material and appearance, for the use of labourers, &amp;c., only.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >THE NICOLL PALETOT, OR PATENT COAT,</head><p >As also the original Invention, the REGISTERED PALETOT (6 and 7 Vic., Cap. 65), and NICOLL'S MORNING COAT, adapted for Spring and Summer Wear, and, notwithstanding all the recent Improvements, making these Garments not only the most Gentlemanly, but also the most durable and inexpensive articles of Dress extant, the prices for the above seasons will yet remain at ONE and TWO GUINEAS each.</p><p >114, 116, 118, 120, REGENT STREET, and 22, Cornhill.</p><div type="section"><head >114, REGENT STREET.</head><p >The above will, as heretofore, form the principal entrance to NICOLL'S PALETOT WAREROOMS, as also where Gentlemen are respectfully invited to inspect all the NOVELTIES, as well as all the established articles of Costume, that capital can collect, or skill can form.</p></div><div type="section"><head >116, REGENT STREET.</head><p >Much ingenuity of design may be here witnessed in Embroidered and other materials intended for WAISTCOATS, in WEDDING, BALL, or MORNING WEAR, all moderate in cost.</p><p >UNIFORMS, either DIPLOMATIC, NAVAL, or MILITARY, are produced at fair prices. Clever and efficient persons are employed by Messrs. NICOLL to attend to each department.</p></div><div type="section"><head >118, REGENT STREET.</head><p >ROBES, whether intended for the PEER, the CLERGYMAN, the BARRISTER, or YOUTH AT COLLEGE, may be here obtained at the same moderate scale of prices as have served to distinguish NICOLL'S PALETOT.</p></div><div type="section"><head >120, REGENT STREET,</head><p >Forms a Department for YOUTH'S CLOTHING, which, hitherto, has not been contemplated as an adjunct to Messrs. NICOLL'S Trade, but, increased space now affording the convenience, the same moderate prices and excellence will be here developed, as may be observed in the Paletot, &amp;c.</p><p >Parents and Guardians are respectfully invited to inspect the cost of the COLLEGE CAP and GOWN, with all other Items necessary for the Universities, Public and Private Schools, &amp;c.</p></div><div type="section"><head >22, CORNHILL,</head><p >(OPPOSITE THE ROYAL EXCHANGE)</p><p >This is the address of Messrs. NICOLL'S CITY ESTABLISHMENT, where the PALETOT, with Materials and skill, as in Regent-street, are submitted for inspection and use.</p><p >Many of late have used the word “Paletot,” but H. J. and D. NICOLL are the Sole Proprietors and Patentees of both design and material.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS WHITEFRIARS.</closer></div></div></back></text></TEI>