<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>Bleak House. No. I:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882. </name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of his title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Maura McKee</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca. 280K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_pageBleak House</title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>  70 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LondonBradbury &amp; Evans, Bouverie Street</publisher><date>[1852]</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number Dickens 21 c. 2 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi>
</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-27"> Jill Kuhn Sexton finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-14">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><titlePage><titlePart type="main"> No. I. </titlePart><docDate>MARCH.</docDate><docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE 
</titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docEdition>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docEdition><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
<lb/>AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
<lb/></docImprint><docImprint>NOTICE is hereby given that the Author of “BLEAK HOUSE”, reserves to <lb/> himself the right of publishing a Translation in France.
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><head >TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</head><p >EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>WATERFROOF</sic><corr>WATERPROOF</corr></choice> OVERCOAT. <lb/> WEIGHT 10 oz.</p><p >Sole Manufacturers of the celebrated Pocket Siphonin, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on Saddle; the most <hi rend="italics">important</hi> feature in this <hi rend="italics">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.—Price according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat.</p><p >NOTICE.—NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p><p >EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, <lb/> Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p><div type="section"><head >OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head><p >WATERPROOF—“The lightest and most effectual, is the SIPHONIA, made by EDMISTON &amp; SON, of 69, Strand; they can be carried in the hat or pocket; and for the summer we hear they are about to have light coloured Siphonies.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life, April</hi> 20<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><p >“NEW INVENTION—A newly invented waterproof garment has been manufactured by EDMISTON &amp; SON, 69 Strand, and its lightness and softness of texture exceeds all other fabrics that have been brought before the notice of the public; on that account well adapted for riding or walking; can easily be carried in the pocket or hat, and the most important feature respecting it is the process of mineralisation, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun—a desideratum so much required, to prevent the unpleasant smell, and sticking observable in all hitherto waterproof garments.”—<hi rend="italics">British Army Despatch, May</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><p >“A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable weather of the season, has been manufactured by EDMISTON &amp; SON. It is remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome umbrella.”—<hi rend="italics">Home News, May</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><list  type="simple"><item>Leggings or Overalls.</item><item>Yacht Jackets.</item><item>Fishing and Shooting Hats or Caps.</item><item>Driving Gloves.</item><item>Cricketing Gloves.</item><item>Gun Covers.</item><item>Gig Aprons.</item><item>Sou-Westers.</item><item>Goloshes.</item><item>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods.</item><item>Ladies' Capes, Paletots.</item><item>Air Cushions.</item><item>Air Pillows.</item><item>Air Beds.</item><item>India Rubber Portable Folding Baths.</item><item>Nursing Aprons.</item><item>Crib Sheets.</item><item>The newly invented Swimming Gloves.</item></list><p >FISHING AND SHOOTING BOOTS, soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every description of India Rabber and Gutta Percha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c.</p><p >AGENTS APPOINTED.</p><p >LONDON: EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, near the Adelphi.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><head >BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head><p >No. I.—MARCH, 1852.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><div type="section"><head >CHEAP EDITION OF THE <lb/> Works of Mr. Charles Dickens.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces by the Author, and Frontispieces to each volume, handsomely bound in cloth.</hi></p><p >THE PICKWICK PAPERS. Price 5s.</p><p >NICHOLAS NICKLEBY. Price 5s.</p><p >THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP. Price 4s.</p><p >BARNABY RUDGE. Price 4s.</p><p >MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT. Price 5s.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >SKETCHES BY BOZ. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >AMERICAN NOTES. Price 2s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><head >CHEAP EDITION OF THE <lb/> Novels &amp; Tales of Sir E. Bulwer <lb/> Lytton.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces by the Author, and Frontispiece to each volume, handsomely bound in cloth.</hi></p><p >RIENZI; the Last of the Tribunes. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >PAUL CLIFFORD. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >PELHAM; or, The Adventures of a Gentleman. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >EUGENE ARAM. A Tale. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >THE LAST OF THE BARONS. Price 5s.</p><p >THE LAST DAYS OF POMPEII. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >PILGRIMS OF THE RHINE. Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >GODOLPHIN. Price 3s.</p><p >NIGHT AND MORNING. Price 4s.</p><p >ERNEST MALTRAVERS. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p >ERNEST MALTRAVERS. Part II. (ALICE.) Price 3s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><p >I. <lb/> THE HISTORY OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE, from the Accession of James the First. To which is prefixed a Review of the Progress of England from the Saxon Period to the Last Year of the Reign of Queen Elizabeth, 1603. By JOHN MAC-GREGOR, M.P. 2 vols. 8vo, cloth, 36s.</p><p >II. <lb/> THE LIFE AND LETTERS OF BARTHOLD GEORGE NIEBUHR. From the German. With Essays on his Character and Influence. By the Chevalier BUNSEN and Professors BRANDIS and LOEBELL. 2 vols. 8vo, 32s.</p><p >III. <lb/> THE POETICAL and DRAMATIC WORKS OF SIR E. BULWER LYTTON, Bart. 8vo. Vol. I., with a Portrait and Vignette, 8s.</p><p >IV. <lb/> ALICE LEARMONT. A Fairy Tale. By the Author of “Olive,” &amp;c. Illustrated by J. GODWIN. Fcap., elegantly bound, 5s.</p><p >V. <lb/> THE LIFE OF JOHN STERLING. By THOMAS CARLYLE. Second Edition. Post 8vo, 10s. 6d.</p><p >VI. <lb/> WILLIAM PENN. An Historical Biography. From New Sources. By HEPWORTH DIXON. Second Edition. Small 8vo, cloth, 7s., with a Portrait.</p><p >VII. <lb/> THE PASSIONS OF ANIMALS. By EDWARD P. THOMPSON, Author of “Note-Book of a Naturalist,” &amp;c. Post 8vo, 10s. 6d.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> EXCURSION TO CALIFORNIA, OVER THE PRAIRIE, ROCKY MOUNTAINS, AND GREAT SIEREA NEVADA; with a Stroll through the Diggings and Ranches of that Country. By WILLIAM KELLY, J.P. 2 vols. 8vo, 21s.</p><p >IX. <lb/> THE ERNE, ITS LEGENDS AND ITS FLY-FISHING. By Rev. H. NEWLAND. Post 8vo, cloth, with Plates and Map, 12s.</p><p >X. <lb/> ROMANCE OF THE PEERAGE; OR, CURIOSITIES OF FAMILY HISTORY. By GEORGE LILLIE CRAIK, Esq., Professor of History in Queen's College, Belfast. 4 vols., with Portraits, post 8vo, 10s. 6d. each</p><p >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >NEW AND POPULAR BOOKS FOR THE YOUNG.</head><p >PUBLISHED BY <lb/> GRANT &amp; GRIFFITH, <lb/> SUCCESSORS TO <lb/> NEWBERY &amp; HARRIS, <lb/> CORNER OF <lb/> SAINT PAUL'S CHURCH-YARD.</p><p >MARK SEAWORTH: a Tale of the Indian Ocean. By the Author of “Peter the Whaler.” With Illustrations. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >ANECDOTES OF THE HABITS AND INSTINCT OF ANIMALS. By Mrs. LEE. With Illustrations by H. WEIR. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >THE DOLL AND HER FRIENDS. By the Author of “Letters from Madras.” With Illustrations by PHIZ. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. cloth; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >GOOD IN EVERYTHING; or, the Early History of Gilbert Harland. By Mrs. BARWELL. With Illustrations. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. cloth; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >STORIES OF JULIAN AND HIS PLAY-FELLOW. With Illustrations. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. plain; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >TALES FROM CATLAND. Written for Young Kittens. By an OLD TABBY. With Illustrations by H. WEIR. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. plain; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >ADVENTURES IN AUSTRALIA; or, The Wanderings of Captain Spencer in the Bush and the Wilds. By Mrs. R. LEE, Author of “The African Wanderers.” With Illustrations by J. S. PROUT. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >PETER THE WHALER: his Early Life and Adventures in the Arctic Regions. By W. H. G. KINGSTON, Esq. With Illustrations. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >TALES OF SCHOOL LIFE. By AGNES LOUDON. Illustrated by J. ABSOLON. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. plain; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >THE WONDERS OF HOME; in Eleven Stories. By GRANDFATHER GREY, Second Edition. With Engravings. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. plain; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >THE MODERN BRITISH PLUTARCH; or, Lives of Men distinguished in the recent History of our Country. By the late Dr. W. C. TAYLOR. Second Thousand, with a new Steel Fron-tispiece. 12mo, price 6s. cloth.</p><p >THE AFRICAN WANDERERS: or, The Adventures of Carlos and Antonio among the Western Tribes. By Mrs. R. LEE (formerly Mrs. T. E. BOWDICH). Second Edition. Fcap. 8vo, with Engravings, price 6s. cloth.</p><p >THE WONDER-SEEKER; or, The History of Charles Douglas. By M. F. TYTLER. Illustrated by ABSOLON. Second Edition. Fcap. 8vo, 4s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >FACTS FROM THE WORLD OF NATURE, Animate and Inanimate. By Mrs. LOUDON. With numerous Engravings. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth, gilt edges.</p><p >HANS ANDERSEN'S TALES FROM DENMARK. Translated by C. BONER. With 50 Illustrations by COUNT POCCI. Small 4to, 6s. plain; 7s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >“We prophesy for these Tales an immortality in the nursery.”—<hi rend="italics">Blackwood.</hi></p><p >TRUE STORIES FROM ANCIENT HISTORY, chronologically arranged from the Creation of the World to the Death of Charlemagne. Tenth Edition, with 24 Steel Engravings. 5s. cloth.</p><p >TRUE STORIES FROM MODERN HISTORY, from the Death of Charlemagne to the Year 1849. 7th Edition, with 24 Steel Engravings. 5s. cloth.</p><p >TRUE STORIES FROM ENGLISH HISTORY, from the Invasion of the Romans to the Close of the Great Exhibition. Sixth Edition, 36 Steel Engravings. 5s. cloth.</p><p >EARLY DAYS OF ENGLISH PRINCES. By Mrs. RUSSELL GRAY. Illustrated by JOHN FRANKLIN. Royal 16mo, 4s. plain; 5s. coloured.</p><p >GLIMPSES OF NATURE AND OBJECTS OF INTEREST, described during a Visit to the Isle of Wight. By Mrs. LOUDON. Second Edition, with 41 Illustrations. Square 16mo, 3s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >THE MINE; or, Subterranean Wonders: an Account of the Operations of the Miner, and the Products of his Labour. Sixth Edition, With 45 new Woodcuts, and 16 Steel Engravings. Price 4s. cloth.</p><p >THE SHIP: a Description of various kinds of Vessels, the origin of Ship-building, Steamboats, &amp;c. With numerous Illustrative Engravings. Fifth Edition, revised by M. H. BARKER, Esq., “The Old Sailor.” Price 4s. cloth.</p><div type="section"><head >THE FAVOURITE LIBRARY.</head><p >A Series of Works for the Young, each with an Illustration by a Well-known Artist. Complete in 12 Volumes, 1s. each; fancy boards or in Six double Volumes, cloth, gilt edges, at 2s. 6d.</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. THE ESKDALE HERD-BOY. By Lady STODDART.</item><item>2. MRS. LEICESTER'S SCHOOL. By CHARLES and MARY LAMS.</item><item>3. THE HISTORY OF THE ROBINS. By Mrs. TRIMMER.</item><item>4. MEMOIRS OF BOB, THE SPOTTED TERRIER.</item><item>5. KEEPER'S TRAVELS IN SEARCH OF HIS MASTER.</item><item>6. THE SCOTTISH ORPHANS. By Lady STODDART.</item><item>7. NEVER WRONG; or, The Young Disputant.</item><item>8. THE LIFE AND PERAMBULATIONS OF A MOUSE.</item><item>9. TRIMMER'S INTRODUCTION TO THE KNOWLEDGE OF NATURE.</item><item>10. RIGHT AND WRONG. By the Author of “Always Happy.”</item><item>11. HARRY'S HOLIDAY. By JEFFERYS TAYLOR.</item><item>12. SHORT POEMS AND HYMNS.</item></list></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><head >GROOMBRIDGE AND SONS' NEW WORKS.</head><p >THE LATE GRACE AGUILAR.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In the press, in 1 vol., uniform with the Author's other works,</hi>
<lb/> THE DAYS OF BRUCE.</p><p >A Story from Scottish history.</p><p >BY GRACE AGUILAR, <lb/> Author of “Home Influence,” “The Mother's Recompense,” “The Vale of Cedars,” <lb/> “Woman's Friendship,” &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >Fourth Edition, price 6s. 6d., <lb/> HOME INFLUENCE. <lb/> A TALE FOR MOTHERS AND DAUGHTERS.</p><p >Second Edition, price 7s., <lb/> THE MOTHER'S RECOMPENSE. <lb/> A SEQUEL TO “HOME INFLUENCE.”</p><p >Second Edition, price 6s. 6d., <lb/> WOMAN'S FRIENDSHIP. <lb/> A STORY OF DOMESTIC LIFE.</p><p >Second Edition, price 6s., <lb/> THE VALE OF CEDARS.</p><p >A STORY OF SPAIN IN THE FIFTEENTH CENTURY.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In the press, in a cheap and attractive form,</hi>
<lb/> LABOUR STANDS ON GOLDEN FEET; <lb/> OR, <lb/> The Life of a Foreign Workman.</p><p >A HOLIDAY STORY FOR SENSIBLE APPRENTICES, JOURNEYMEN, AND MASTERS.</p><p >REID ON THE STEAM ENGINE.</p><p >Third Edition, with 40 Illustrations, price 4s. 6d., <lb/> THE STEAM ENGINE; <lb/> A Popular Account of its Construction, Action, and History; a Description of its various forms; with a Sketch of the Laws of Heat and Pneumatics, and a Critique on M. Arago's “Eloge of Watt.”</p><p >BY HUGO REID.</p><p >Illustrated with 240 Engravings, price 7s., <lb/> DRAWING FROM OBJECTS.</p><p >BY HANNAH BOLTON.</p><p >A Handbook upon Drawing, equally adapted for the Teacher, the Parent, and the Artisan.</p><p >Illustrated by WHIMPER, price 2s. 6d., <lb/> SOMETHING NEW FROM THE <lb/> STORY-GARDEN, <lb/> BROUGHT BY SISTER FOR IDA, AGNES, AND ERNIE.</p><p >Illustrated with Frontispiece, price 3s., <lb/> THE AMYOTTS' HOME.</p><p >A DOMESTIC STORY.</p><p >By the Author of “Tales that might be True,” &amp;c.</p><p >Illustrated with Frontispiece, price 1s., <lb/> THE GOOD BOY HENRY; <lb/> OR, <lb/> The Young Child's Book of Manners.</p><p >LONDON: GROOMBRIDGE AND SONS, PUBLISHERS, 5, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >MR. MURRAY'S LIST.</head><div type="section"><head >Nearly Ready.</head><p >I. <lb/> JOURNAL OF A WINTER'S TOUR IN INDIA; with a VISIT to NEPAUL. By the Honourable Captain FRANCIS EGERTON, R. N. Woodcuts. 2 vols. Post 8vo.</p><p >II. <lb/> FARINI'S HISTORY OF THE ROMAN STATE, Vol. 3. Translated by the Right Honourable W. E. GLADSTONE, M.P. 8vo.</p><p >III. <lb/> A BOTANIST'S JOURNEY TO THE BOHEA MOUNTAINS AND THE TEA DISTRICTS OF CHINA AND INDIA. By ROBERT FORTUNE, author of “Wanderings in China.” Wooducts. 8vo.</p><p >IV. <lb/> STRIFE FOR THE MASTERY. Two Allegories. With Illustrations. Crown 8vo.</p><p >V. <lb/> HANDBOOK OF FAMILIAR QUOTATIONS FROM ENGLISH AUTHORS. Fcap. 8vo.</p><p >VI. <lb/> A MILITARY MANUAL OF FIELD OPERATIONS. By LIEUT. JERVIS, R.A. Post 8vo.</p><p >VII. <lb/> NOTES ON PUBLIC SUBJECTS, made during a Tour in the UNITED STATES and CANADA, 1851. By HUGH SEYMOUR TREMENHEERE. Post 8vo.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Now Ready.</head><p >VIII. <lb/> MODERN INDIA. A SKETCH OF THE CIVIL ADMINISTRATION OF INDIA. With some Account of the Natives and Native Institutions. By GEORGE CAMPBELL, Esq., Bengal Civil Service. 8vo.</p><p >IX. <lb/> KING GUSTAVUS VASA; HIS ADVENTURES AND EXPLOITS. With Extracts from his Correspondence and Chronicles of his Reign. Portrait. 8vo.</p><p >X. <lb/> THE GRENVILLE PAPERS. From the Archives at Stowe; including Mr. GRENVILLE'S POLITICAL DIARY. Edited by WM. JAS. SMITH, formerly Librarian at Stowe. 2 vols. 8vo. 32s.</p><p >XI. <lb/> THE POLITICAL EXPERIENCE OF THE ANCIENTS, in its bearing upon Modern Times. By H. SEYMOUR TREMENHEERE. Fcap. 8vo.</p><p >XII. <lb/> LIVES OF THE FRIENDS AND CONTEMPORARIES OF LORD CHANCELLOR CLARENDON. By LADY THERESA LEWIS. Portraits. 3 Vols. 8vo. 42s.</p><p >XIII. <lb/> HISTORY OF GREECE. Vols. 9 and 10. Continued to the Accession of Philip of Macedon, B.C. 403—359. By GEORGE GROTE. Maps. 2 vols. 8vo. 32s.</p><p >XIV. <lb/> HISTORY OF ENGLAND AND FRANCE UNDER THE HOUSE OF LANCASTER. With an Introductory View of the Early Reformation. 8vo. 15s.</p><p >XV. <lb/> THE HAND; ITS MECHANISM AND ENDOWMENTS, as evincing Design. By SIR CHARLES BELL. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> Woodcuts. Post 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p><p >XVI. <lb/> MARLBOROUGH COLLEGE SCHOOL SERMONS. By Rev. Dr. WILKINSON, Master. 8vo.</p><p >XVII. <lb/> THE FIRST YEARS OF THE AMERICAN WAR. By LORD MAHON. Forming VOLS. 5 and 6 of his HISTORY OF ENGLAND. 8vo. 30s.</p><p >XVIII. <lb/> PARIS, 1851. A FAGGOT OF FRENCH STICKS. By the AUTHOR of “BUBBLES.” 2 Vols. Post 8vo. 24s.</p><p >XIX. <lb/> AN ACCOUNT OF THE DANES AND NORWEGIANS IN ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, AND IRELAND. By J. J. A. WORSAAE, Woodcuts. Post 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p><p >XX. <lb/> LIFE OF THOMAS STOTHARD, R.A. With Personal Reminiscences. By MRS. BRAY. Illustrated in a novel style of Art. Fcap. 4to. 21s.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">In Preparation.</hi></opener><head >THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF WILLIAM JERDAN, <lb/> WITH HIS LITERARY, POLITICAL, AND SOCIAL REMINISCENCES AND CORRESPONDENCE, <lb/> DURING THE LAST FORTY YEARS, <lb/> AS EDITOR OF THE SUN NEWSPAPER (1812—17), AND OF THE LITERARY <lb/> GAZETTE (1817—50),</head><p > In connection with most of the Eminent Persons who have been distinguished in the past <lb/> half century as Statesmen, Poets, Authors, Men of Science and Artists.</p><p >The First Volume, price 5s., with a Portrait of the Author engraved by Robinson, from a Painting by Harlowe, will appear on the First of May, and it is proposed to complete the work in 4 or 6 volumes, to be published Quarterly.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Subscribers' Names received by all Booksellers.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Second Edition, with Twenty-three Engravings on Steel, price 14s. cloth, gilt edges, or 26s. morocco elegant,</opener><head >FOOTSTEPS OF OUR LORD AND HIS APOSTLES <lb/> IN SYRIA, GREECE, AND ITALY, <lb/> A Succession of Visits to the Scenes of New Testament Narrative.</head><p >BY W. H. BARTLETT.</p><p >“If beauty of design and execution, combined with elegance of narrative and trustworthy description, can be any recommendation to a book, it is sufficient to say that this excellent volume possesses every one of these features, and establishes its own character without the need of any further praise.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> THE NILE BOAT. Second Edition.</p><p >Price 16s. cloth gilt, 28s. morocco gilt.</p><p >III. <lb/> GLEANINGS ON THE OVERLAND</p><p >ROUTE. Second Edition, price 16s. cloth gilt, 28s. morocco elegant.</p><p >IV. <lb/> FORTY DAYS IN THE DESERT.</p><p >Fourth Edition, 12s. cloth, 21s. morocco.</p><p >V. <lb/> WALKS ABOUT JERUSALEM. New</p><p >Edition, cloth gilt, 12s., morocco gilt, 21s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Dr. Cumming's New Series of Lectures.</head><p >Fifth Thousand, in 2 vols., uniformly printed, price 9s. each, bound and gilt, <lb/> FORESHADOWS; <lb/> OR, LECTURES ON OUR LORD'S MIRACLES AND PARABLES AS EARNESTS OF <lb/> THE AGE TO COME.</p><p >Third Thousand.</p><p >ROMISH MIRACLES. Foolscap, price 1s.</p><p >Eleventh Thousand.</p><p >APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES. 3 vols., price 9s. each, cloth gilt.</p><p >Fourth Edition.</p><p >A MESSAGE FROM GOD. Price 2s. with gilt edges.</p><p >Sixth Thousand.</p><p >PROPHETIC STUDIES. Price 9s. cloth gilt; 13s. morocco elegant.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Second Edition, revised, price 1s. 6d., in a neat pocket Volume,</opener><head >WOMAN,—Her Mission and Her Life, from the French of MONOD, by Rev. W. G. BARRETT.</head><p >Just published, with Portrait, &amp;c., price 7s. 6d., in post 8vo., cloth antique,</p><p >Y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> HOUSEHOLD OF SIR THO<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> MORE. Libellus à Margareta More, quindecim annos nata, Chelseiæ inceptus.</p><p >“Clever and agreeable reading. . . . . . We can give the book unqualified praise for the pleasant and tolerably accurate pictures which it affords of the domestic manners of the period; and the characters of some of the personages represented are drawn with distinctness, and with the features of nature.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >“It ends with musical melancholy, a strain of exquisitely simple beauty, referring to the judicial slaying of one of England's worthiest sons. There are some fine portraits ably <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>limned</sic><corr>lined</corr></choice> herein. There are family pictures so graphically described that they possess the mind for ever.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just published, handsomely bound and gilt,</opener><head >QUEENE PHILIPPA'S GOLDEN BOOKE. With Illuminations.</head><p >Y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> MAIDEN and MARRIED LIFE of MARY POWELL, afterwards MISTRESS MILTON. New Edition.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; Co., 25, PATEROSTER-ROW; <lb/> SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; AND J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >NEW AND POPULAR BOOKS.</head><div type="section"><head >Dr. W. Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Geography.</head><p >By various Writers. Illustrated with Coins, Plans of Cities, Districts, and Battles, &amp;c. By WILLIAM SMITH, LL. D., Editor of the Dictionaries of “Greek and Roman Antiquities,” and of “Biography and Mythology.”</p><p >To appear in Quarterly Parts, and to form 1 vol., medium 8vo. (<hi rend="italics">Part I. price</hi> 4s. <hi rend="italics">is now ready.</hi>)</p></div><div type="section"><head >Liebig's Familiar Letters on Chemistry.</head><p >New and Cheap Edition, containing the Author's latest Researches on Food, Dietetics, Physiology, Agriculture, &amp;c. Fcap. 8vo. 6s. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Buff's Familiar Letters on the Physics of the Earth.</head><p >Teaching of the Chief Movements of the Land, the Waters, and the Air. By Dr. HOFMANN. Foolscap 8vo. 5s.</p><p >CONTENTS.—Introduction—Gravity and its Effects.—Tides.—Heat within the Earth.—Warm Springs.—Hot Springs and Jets of Steam.—Jets of Gas and Mud Volcanoes.—Volcanoes and Earthquakes.—Temperature of the Outermost Crust of the Earth.—Temperature of the Lowest Layer of the Atmosphere.—Lines of Equal Heat.—Temperature of the Upper Layers of the Atmosphere.—The Snow Limits.—Glaciers.—Temperature of the Waters, and their Influence on Climate.—Currente of the Sea—Winds.—Moisture of the Air and Atmospheric Precipitation.—Electricity of the Air, Lightning and Thunder.</p></div><div type="section"><head >De Morgan's Book of Almanacs:</head><p >By which the Almanac belonging to any year preceding A.D. 2000 can be found; with means of finding New and Full Moons from B.C. 2000, to A.D. 2000. Oblong 8vo. 5s. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. Wm. Gregory's Letters to a Candid Enquirer on Animal</head><p >MAGNETISM. 12mo. 9s. 6d. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Baron Von Reichenbach's Researches,</head><p >On Magnetism, Electricity, Heat, Light, Crystallisation, and Chemical Attraction in their relation to the Vital Force. Translated and Edited (at the express desire of the author), by DR. GREGORY, of the University of Edinburgh, 8vo, cloth, 12s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Niebuhr's Lectures on Ancient History:</head><p >Comprising the History of the Asiatic Nations, the Egyptians, Greeks, Carthaginians, and Macedonians Translated from the German by DR. SCHMITZ. With Additions from MSS. in the exclusive possession of the Editor. 3 vols. 8vo. (<hi rend="italics">In April.</hi>)</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. Lardner on the Steam Engine, Steam Navigation,</head><p > ROADS AND RAILWAYS. New and Cheap Edition. Large 12mo. 8s. 6d. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. R. G. Latham's Handbook of the English Language.</head><p >For the Use of Students of the Universities and Higher Classes of Schools. Large 8vo. 8s. 6d. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. Lardner's Handbook of Natural Philosophy and</head><p >ASTRONOMY. FIRST COURSE: MECHANICS, HYDROSTATICS, PNEUMATICS, SOUND, AND OPTICS. Large 12mo. 400 Woodcuts. 12s. 6d. cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Guesses at Truth. By TWO Brothers.</head><p >New Edition. 2 vols. Fcap. 13s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. W. Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography</head><p >AND MYTHOLOGY, By VARIOUS WRITERS. 560 Woodcuts. 3 vols. Medium 8vo. £5 15s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Dr. W. Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities.</head><p >By VARIOUS WRITERS. Second Edition. 500 Woodcuts. Medium 8vo. £2 2s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Niebuhr's Lectures on the History of Rome.</head><p >By DR. SCHMITZ. Cheap Edition. 3 vols. 8vo. £1 4s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >A Descriptive Catalogue of School and College Books,</head><p > published by TAYLOR, WALTON, AND MABERLY. 4to.</p><p >The object of this descriptive Catalogue of Books for the Use of Schools and Colleges, is to convey a more satisfactory notion of their contents than can be drawn from reading the titles. Instead of laudatory extracts from reviews, general notices are given of the chief subjects and most prominent peculiarities of the books. The publication is designed to put the reader, as far as possible, in the same position as if he had inspected for himself, at least cursorily, the works described; and with this view, care has been taken in drawing up the notices, merely to state facts, with but little comment and no exaggeration whatever.</p><p >TAYLOR, WALTON, AND MABERLY, UPPER GOWER STREET.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >Smith, Elder, &amp; Co.'s New Publications.</head><p >1. <lb/> THE SCHOOL FOR FATHERS.</p><p >AN OLD ENGLISH STORY. In One Volume.</p><p >2. <lb/> THE LILY OF ST. PAUL'S; <lb/> A ROMANCE OF OLD LONDON.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “TREVETHLAN.” In Three Volumes.</p><p >3. <lb/> LENA; THE SILENT WOMAN.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “KING'S COPE,” &amp;c. In Three Volumes.</p><p >4. <lb/> THE TWO FAMILIES: <lb/> AN EPISODE IN THE HISTORY OF CHAPELTON.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “ROSE DOUGLAS.” Two Volumes post 8vo.</p><p >5. <lb/> WOMEN OF CHRISTIANITY, EXEMPLARY <lb/> FOR PIETY AND CHARITY.</p><p >BY MISS JULIA KAVANAGH, Author of “Woman in France,” “Nathalie,” &amp;c. One Volume post 8vo. with Portraits, price 12s. in embossed cloth, gilt edges.</p><p >6. <lb/> PICTURES OF LIFE IN MEXICO.</p><p >BY R. H. MASON, Esq. Two Volumes post 8vo, with Etchings, price 24s. cloth.</p><p >7. <lb/> THE LIFE OF TAOU-KWANG, <lb/> LATE EMPEROR OF CHINA; WITH MEMOIRS OF THE COURT OF PEKING.</p><p >BY THE LATE REV. CHARLES GUTZLAFF. Post 8vo, 10s.</p><p >8. <lb/> FLORENCE SACKVILLE; <lb/> OR, SELF-DEPENDENCE, BY MRS. BURBURY, Three Volumes post 8vo.</p><p >9. <lb/> AGATHA BEAUFORT; <lb/> OR, FAMILY PRIDE. BY THE AUTHOR OF “PIQUE.” Three Volumes post 8vo.</p><p >10. <lb/> THE FAIR CAREW; <lb/> OR, HUSBANDS AND WIVES. Three Volumes post 8vo.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >PREPARING FOR PUBLICATION,</head><p >1. <lb/> A NOVEL, BY W. M. THACKERAY, ESQ., <lb/> Author of “Pendennis,” “Vanity Fair,” &amp;c. In Three Volumes.</p><p >2. <lb/> THE PRESENT STATE OF PARTIES: <lb/> A SERIES OF ETCHINGS, WITH DESCRIPTIONS. BY RICHARD DOYLE, Esq.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >THE TRAVELLER'S LIBRARY, <lb/> PUBLISHING MONTHLY AND SOLD AT <lb/> ONE SHILLING EACH PART,</head><p > Is intended to comprise Books of valuable information and acknowledged merit, in a form adapted for reading while Travelling, and at the same time of a character that will render them worthy of preservation; but the <hi rend="italics">price</hi> of which has hitherto confined them within a comparatively narrow circle of readers.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >The first Seventeen Parts comprise—</head><p >1. WARREN HASTINGS. BY THOMAS BABINGTON MACAULAY.</p><p >2. LORD CLIVE. BY THOMAS BABINGTON MACAULAY.</p><p >3. LONDON IN 1850-51. BY J. R. M'CULLOCH, ESQ.</p><p >4. SIR ROGER DE COVERLEY. From the “Spectator.”</p><p >5. WILLIAM PITT, EARL OF CHATHAM. BY T. B. MACAULAY.</p><p >6—7. LAING'S JOURNAL OF A RESIDENCE IN NORWAY.</p><p >8. “RANKE'S HISTORY OF THE POPES.” And, “GLADSTONE ON CHURCH AND STATE.” BY THOMAS BABINGTON MACAULAY.</p><p >9—10. PFEIFFER'S LADY'S VOYAGE ROUND THE WORLD.</p><p >11—12. EÖTHEN, OR TRACES OF TRAVEL FROM THE EAST.</p><p >13. “THE LIFE AND WRITINGS OF ADDISON.” And, HORACE WALPOLE. BY THOMAS BABINGTON MACAULAY.</p><p >14—15. HUC'S TRAVELS IN TARTARY, THIBET, AND CHINA. A CONDENSED TRANSLATION, by MRS. PERCY SINNETT.</p><p >16—17. HOLCROFT'S MEMOIRS, WRITTEN BY HIMSELF, AND CONTINUED TO HIS DEATH, FROM HIS DIARY, NOTES, AND OTHER PAPERS.</p><p >To be followed by—</p><p >AFRICAN WANDERINGS; or, An Expedition from Sennaar to Taka, Basa, and Beni-Amer; with a particular glance at the Races of Bellad Sudan. By FERDINAND WERNE, Author of “Expedition in search of Sources of the White Nile.” Translated from the German by J. R. JOHNSTON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head ><hi rend="italics">The following</hi> Fourteen Parts <hi rend="italics">may be had in</hi> Seven Volumes, <hi rend="italics">bound in Cloth,</hi></head><p ><hi rend="italics">price</hi> Half-a-Crown <hi rend="italics">each</hi>:—</p><p >EÖTHEN. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >LAING'S NORWAY. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >A LADY'S VOYAGE ROUND THE WORLD. BY IDA PFEIFFER. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >HUC'S TRAVELS IN TARTARY, THIBET, AND CHINA. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >MR. MACAULAY'S ESSAYS ON WARREN HASTINGS AND LORD CLIVE. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >MR. MACAULAY'S ESSAYS ON THE EARL OF CHATHAM, ON RANKE'S HISTORY OF THE POPES, AND ON GLADSTONE ON CHURCH AND STATE. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >HOLCROFT'S MEMOIRS. Two Parts, One Shilling each; or One Volume, Half-a-Crown.</p><p >LONDON: LONGMAN, BROWN, GREEN, AND LONGMANS.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.: in Monthly Parts,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">and in Half-yearly Volumes,</hi></opener><head >HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A WEEKLY JOURNAL, <lb/> Conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST IN <lb/> THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p><p >Volumes I., II., and III., price 5s. 6d. each, in cloth boards, are always on sale, and the Fourth Volume will be published on the 22nd of March, price 5s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Also, published at the end of every month, at the same Office, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head >THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE <lb/> OF CURRENT EVENTS;</head><p > Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Exchequer, a Legal Publication not coming <lb/> within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The First and Second Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of</hi> 1850—51, <hi rend="italics">are always</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">on sale, price 3s. each, neatly bound in cloth.</hi></p><p >OFFICE, No. 16, Wellington Street North. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Works by Mr. Charles Dickens.</head><div type="section"><p >THE FIRST VOLUME OF <lb/> A CHILD'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND. With a Frontispiece from a Drawing by F. W. TOPHAM. Corrected and revised from “Household Words,” with a Table of Dates. Price 3s. 6d., neatly bound in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The History will be completed in Three Volumes of the same size and price.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><p >THE PERSONAL HISTORY OF DAVID COPPERFIELD. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21s., in cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><p >DOMBEY AND SON. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21s., in cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><p >THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF OLIVER TWIST. In demy 8vo., price 11s., in cloth.</p><p >This Edition has been carefully corrected by the Author throughout, and contains the whole of the Original Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p></div><div type="section"><p >PICTURES FROM ITALY. In fcap. 8vo., price 6s., in cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><head ><hi rend="italics">In small 8vo, price 5s., each, bound in cloth, with <lb/> gilt edges,</hi></head><p >The Illustrations by D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, JOHN TENNIEL, and RICHARD DOYLE.</p><div type="section"><p >THE HAUNTED MAN AND THE GHOST'S BARGAIN. A Fancy for Christmas Time.</p></div><div type="section"><p >THE CHIMES. A Goblin Story of some Bells that rang an Old Year out and a New Year in.</p></div><div type="section"><p >A CHRISTMAS CAROL, IN PROSE.</p></div><div type="section"><p >THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH. A Fairy Tale of Home.</p></div><div type="section"><p >THE BATTLE OF LIFE. A Love Story.</p></div></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW WORKS.</head><div type="section"><p >PROSE AND VERSE. By MARK LEMON. Price 4s., in cloth boards.</p></div><div type="section"><p ><hi rend="italics">By the same Author,</hi>
<lb/> THE ENCHANTED DOLL. A Fairy Tale for Young People. Illustrated by RICHARD DOYLE. Price 3s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><p >HOW TO SEE THE BRITISH MUSEUM. In FOUR VISITS. By WILLIAM BLANCHARD JERROLD. Price 6d, each, or bound in cloth, complete in One Vol., 2s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><p >WHAT SHALL WE HAVE FOR DINNER? By LADY MARIA CLUTTERBUCK. Price 1s., a New Edition, Enlarged and Improved.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >THE COMIC HISTORY OF ROME. By G. A. A'BECKETT. Illustrated with ten large coloured Engravings and numerous Woodcuts by JOHN LEECH. In one vol. 8vo, price 11s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >MEN OF CHARACTER. By DOUGLAS JERROLD.</p></div><div type="section"><p ><hi rend="italics">By the same Author, price 4s. in cloth,</hi>
<lb/> ST. GILES AND ST. JAMES.</p><p > These Works form the FIRST and SECOND Volumes of a COLLECTED EDITION of Mr. JERROLD'S WORKS, now publishing in Weekly Numbers, price 1½d., in Monthly Parts, price 7d.; and in Volumes.</p><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><head >COLBURN &amp; CO.'S NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</p><p >TO BE HAD OF ALL BOOKSELLERS.</p><p >Fourth Edition of Mr. D'Israeli's Political Biography of <lb/> LORD GEORGE BENTINCK.</p><p >Revised, in 1 vol. 8vo, 15s. bound.</p><p >Mr. WARBURTON'S DARIEN; or, the Merchant Prince.</p><p >3 vols.</p><p >LORD PALMERSTON'S OPINIONS and POLICY, as MINISTER, DIPLOMATIST, and STATESMAN, during more than Forty Years of Public Life. With a Memoir by G. H. FRANCIS, Esq. 1 large vol., 8vo, with Portrait. 12s.</p><p >THE LITERATURE AND ROMANCE OF NORTHERN EUROPE, constituting a complete History of the Literature of Sweden, Denmark, Norway, and Iceland, with Copious Specimens of the most celebrated Histories, Romances, Popular Legends and Tales, old Chivalrous Ballads, Tragic and Comic Dramas, National Songs, Novels, and Scenes from the Life of the Present Day. By WILLIAM and MARY HOWITT. 2 vols., post 8vo.</p><p >CANADA AS IT WAS, IS, AND MAY BE. By the late Lieut-Col. SIR R. BONNYCASTLE. With considerable Additions, and an Account of Recent Transactions. By SIR JAMES E. ALEXANDER, K.L.S., &amp;c. 2 vols., with Maps. (<hi rend="italics">Just Ready.</hi>)</p><p >HISTORY OF CORFU; AND OF THE REPUBLIC OF THE IONIAN ISLANDS. By LIEUT. H. J. W. JERVIS, Royal Artillery 1 vol., with Illustrations.</p><p >RULE AND MISRULE OF THE ENGLISH IN AMERICA. By the Author of “Sam Slick,” “The Old Judge,” &amp;c. 2 vols 21s.</p><p >ARCTIC MISCELLANIES, A SOUVENIR OF THE LATE POLAR SEARCH. By the Officers and Seamen of the Expedition. Dedicated by permission to the Lords of the Admiralty. Second and cheaper Edition, with a new Preface. With numerous Illustrations, 10s. 6d.</p><p >TRAVELS IN EUROPEAN TURKEY, with a Tour through Hungary and the Slavonian Provinces of Austria. &amp;c., in 1850. By EDMUND SPENCER, Esq., Author of “Travels in Circassia,” &amp;c. 2 vols., 8vo, with a valuable Map and Illustrations, 28s.</p><p >FIVE YEARS IN THE WEST INDIES. By CHARLES WILLIAM DAY, ESQ. 2 vols., post 8vo, with Illustrations. (<hi rend="italics">Just Ready.</hi>)</p><p >SAM SLICK'S TRAITS OF AMERICAN HUMOUR. 3 vols. “Superlatively entertaining volumes.” — <hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p><p >EIGHT YEARS IN PALES-TINE, SYRIA, AND ASIA MINOR, from 1842 to 1850. By F. A. NEALE, ESQ. Second Edition. Two vols., with Illustrations. 21s.</p><p >KHARTOUM AND THE NILES. By GEORGE MELLY, ESQ. Second Edition. 2 vols., with Illustrations, 21s.</p><div type="section"><head >THE NEW AND POPULAR NOVELS.</head><p >ADVENTURES OF A BEAUTY, By MRS. CROWE, Author of “Susan HOPLEY,” &amp;c. 3 vols.</p><p >HEARTS AND ALTARS. By ROBERT BELL, Esq., Author of “The Ladder of Gold,” &amp;c. 3 vols.</p><p >RAVENSCLIFFE. By the Author of “Emilia Wyndham,” &amp;c. 3 vols.</p><p >JACOB BENDIXEN, THE JEW. By MARY HOWITT. 3 vols.</p><p >THE HEIR OF ARDENNAN, A STORY OF DOMESTIC LIFE IN SCOTLAND. By the Author of “Anne Dysart.” 3 vols.</p><p >EMILY HOWARD. By Mrs. DUNLOP. 3 vols. “A most fascinating work.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p><p >FALKENBURG. By the Author of “Mildred Vernon.” 3 vols.</p><p >RUTH GARNETT. An Historical Romance. 3 vols.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><head >VALUABLE AND INTERESTING WORKS, <lb/> PUBLISHED BY COLBURN AND CO.</head><p >13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</p><p >THE NEW EDITION OF BURKE'S PEERAGE AND <lb/> BARONETAGE FOR 1852.</p><p >Revised and corrected throughout, from the Personal Communications of the Nobility, &amp;c. In 1 vol. royal 8vo, <lb/> with 1500 accurate Engravings of Arms, 38s. bound.</p><p >BURKE'S HISTORY OF THE LANDED GENTRY <lb/> FOR 1852.</p><p >Corrected to the present time: a Genealogical Dictionary of the Untitled Aristocracy of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and comprising particulars of 100,000 persons connected with them. 2 vols, royal 8vo, including the SUPPLEMENT, AND A SEPARATE INDEX, GRATIS, £2 2s. bound.</p><p >LIVES OF THE QUEENS OF ENGLAND.</p><p >BY AGNES STRICKLAND.</p><p >New, Revisèd, and Cheaper Edition, embellished with Portraits of every Queen. Vol. VI. is now ready.</p><p >To be completed in 8 vols., price 12s, each.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >Memoirs of Horace Walpole AND HIS CONTEMPORARIES. Edited by FLIOT WARBURTON, Esq. 2 vols. 8vo, with Portraits, 28s.</p><p >Burke's Romantic Records OF DISTINGUISHED FAMILIES. A Second Series of Anecdotes of the Aristocracy. 2 vols., 21s.</p><p >Evelyn's Diary.</p><p >New and Cheaper Edition. 2 vols., 21s. bound.</p><p >Lives of the Princesses of ENGLAND. By Mrs. EVERETT GREEN. 2 vols., Portraits, 10s. 6d. each.</p><p >Thiers' History of the Con-SULATE AND EMPIRE OF FRANCE UNDER NAPOLEON. Colburn's English Translation. Vol. XI., 7s.</p><p >Germany, its Courts and PEOPLE. By the Author of “Mildred Vernon.” 2 vols., 21s.</p><p >Captain Crawford's Remi-NISCENCES OF ADMIRALS SIR E. OWEN, SIR B. HALLOWELL CAREW, &amp;c. 2 vols., Portraits, 21s.</p><p >Howitt's Year-Book of the COUNTRY; or, THE FIELD, THE FOREST, AND THE FIRE-SIDE. New and Cheap Edition. With Illustrations. 6s. bound.</p><p >Zoological Recreations. By W. J. BRODERIP, Esq., F.R.S. Cheaper Edition, 1 vol., 6s.</p><p >Lights and Shades of Mili-TARY LIFE. Edited by Lieut.-General Sir CHARLES NAPIER, G.C.B. 1 vol., 10s. 6d.</p><p >Lord Lindsay's Letters from THE HOLY LAND. Fourth Edition. 1 vol., 6s.</p><p >Revelations of Prince Tal-LEYRAND. By M. COLMACHE, Private Secretary to the Prince. Cheap Edition. 1 vol., 10s. 6d.</p><p >Hochelaga; or, England in THE NEW WORLD. Edited by ELIOT WARBURTON. Fourth and Cheaper Edition. 10s. 6d.</p><p >Passages in the Life of MRS. MARGARET MAITLAND, of Sunnyside. Cheap Edition. 1 vol., 10s. 6d.</p><p >Mr. Warburton's Reginald HASTINGS. AN AUTOBIOGRAPHY. Third and Cheaper Edition. 1 vol, 10s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >POPULAR NOVELS.—CHEAP <lb/> EDITIONS.</head><p >ADAPTED FOR COUNTRY LIBRARIES.</p><p >Price only 5s. per Volume.</p><p >Time the Avenger.</p><p >By the Author of “Emilia Wyndham.” 3 vols.</p><p >Lady Ponsonby's Pride and IRRESOLUTION. 3 vols.</p><p >Mrs. Trollope's Beauty and INTELLECT. 3 vols.</p><p >Miss Kavanagh's Nathalie. 3 vols.</p><p >Mr. Howitt's Madam Dor-RINGTON. 3 vols.</p><p >The Dreamer &amp; the Worker. By R. H. HORNE, Esq. 2 vols.</p><p >Madame Pulszky's Tales of HUNGARY. 3 vols.</p><p >Mr. Cobbold's Freston TOWER; or, DAYS OF WOLSEY. 3 vols.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p12"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">On</hi> 31<hi rend="italics">st March,</hi>
<lb/> In Two Volumes, demy octavo, with Portrait after <lb/> Colvin Smith,</opener><head > THE LIFE OF LORD JEFFREY.</head><p >With a Selection from his Correspondence.</p><p >By LORD COCKBURN, <lb/> One of the Judges of the Court of Session in Scotland.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">On</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st May,</hi>
<lb/> With Frontispiece and Vignette, designed and engraved expressly for this Edition, Vol. I. of a New Library Edition, uniform with the Standard English Authors, of <lb/> THE WAVERLEY NOVELS.</p><p >By SIR WALTER SCOTT, BART.</p><p >To be completed in Twenty-five Monthly Volumes, <lb/> demy 8vo, price 9s. each.</p><p >ADAM &amp; CHARLES BLACK, Edinburgh.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >LE FOLLET, Journal du Grand Monde, Fashion, <lb/> Polite Literature, Beaux Arts, &amp;c.</head><p >THE piracies of the Designs of this esteemed Magazine, which have been for so long carried on by contemporaneous works, will be effectually prevented by the new LAW of INTERNATIONAL COPYRIGHT, and henceforth it will be the only work in which the original French Plates can appear.—LE FOLLET is universally recognised throughout the COURTS OF EUROPE as the Oracle of Fashion, and is quoted by the leading journal as affording a more correct account of “La Mode Parisienne” than can be obtained from any other source.—Each number contains three exquisitely coloured Steel Plate Engravings executed in the first style of art. Description of Fashion translated from the French and original contributions in Prose and Verse. Single copies, 1s. 6d. each; subscription, 16s. per year.</p><p >Office, 8, Argyle-place, Regent-street; SIMPKIN, <lb/> MARSHALL, &amp; Co.; and all Booksellers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >DEDICATED BY PERMISSION TO THE PROVOST <lb/> OF ETON.<lb/>
Now ready in 8vo, price 9s. 6d.</opener><head >THE POPES; an Historical Summary, from LINUS to PIUS IX.</head><p > By G. A. F. WILKS, M.D.</p><p >“In this single volume of moderate size are condensed nearly all the materials requisite for a complete history of the Papacy.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >“An admirably arranged historical summary.”—<hi rend="italics">Britanniu.</hi></p><p >“Useful as a book of reference, and conveys a vast deal of information.”—<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p><p >“Fair and impartial.”—<hi rend="italics">Guardian.</hi></p><p >RIVINGTON'S, St. Paul's Churchyard, and <lb/> Waterloo-place.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >The best Edition of <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Shakspere</sic><corr>Shakespeare</corr></choice> in one Volume.—Price 13s. cloth, or in Twelve Shilling Parts.</head><p >THE WORKS of WILLIAM <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>SHAKSPERE</sic><corr>SHAKESPEARE</corr></choice>; containing his Plays and Poems, from the text of the editions by Charles Knight; with Explanatory Notes and Facts connected with his Life and Writings abridged from “William <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Shakespere</sic><corr>Shakespeare</corr></choice>, a Biography.” Illustrated by W. Harvey.</p><p >C. COX, 12, King William-street, Strand.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOUTH'S HINTS ON EMERGENCIES.</head><p >Third Edition of 3000 copies each, with an additional Chapter on Poisons by Dr. Gladstone, price 3s. cloth.</p><p >HOUSEHOLD SURGERY; or, Hints on Emergencies. By JOHN F. SOUTH, Surgeon to St. Thomas's Hospital. The object of this work is to afford some useful hints as to the means which people have in their own power to employ when accidents happen which require immediate attention, and no medical man is at hand, and often cannot be obtained for hours. Such cases are neither few nor unimportant, and many serious consequences—nay, even death—may be prevented if a judicious person, having been put on the track, make use of the simple remedies almost every house affords.</p><p >C. COX, 12, King William-street, Strand.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE DUBLIN UNIVERSITY MAGAZINE.</head><p >For March, price 2s. 6d., contains</p><list  type="simple"><item>I. Ireland under Lord Clarendon, Part 2, “The Rebellion” in the city and the field.</item><item>II. The Celto-Scythic progresses.</item><item>III. The Last Life in the Lease.</item><item>IV. The Birds of Ireland.</item><item>V. Stray Leaves from Greece.</item><item>VI. The Bath of Badamar.</item><item>VII. Lord Palmerston, and our policy in the Mediterranean.</item><item>VIII. The Heirs of Randolph Abbey.</item><item>IX. The Bursting of the Bud, by Jonathan Treke Slingsby.</item><item>X. The Administration of Scinde.</item></list><p >Dublin: JAMES M'GLASHAN, Sackville Street; WILLIAM S. ORR, &amp; Co., 2 Amen Corner, London, and all Booksellers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Just published by <lb/> PARTRIDGE &amp; OAKEY.</head><p >Fcap. 8vo, bds. 1s. 6d.; per post, 2s.</p><p >LOUIS NAPOLEON: the Patriot or the Conspirator? including a Biography and a History of the <hi rend="italics">Coup d'Etat;</hi> the Results and Prospects estimated; with Reflections on the probable chances of War. By TRUMAN SLATER, Esq.</p><p >Crown 8vo, cloth, with Engravings, price 5s., <lb/> A SEQUEL TO THE FEMALE JESUIT, containing her Previous History, and Recent Discovery. By the Author of “The Female Jesuit.’, <lb/> Post 8vo., price 5s. cloth, <lb/> THE PERVERTER IN HIGH LIFE: a True Narrative of Jesuit Duplicity.</p><p >Post 8vo, price 6s., <lb/> TALES OF THE BRAGANZA: or Reminiscences of a Voyage with the late Captain Simmons, of the Amazon. By T. H. USBORNE, Esq.</p><p >London: PARTRIDGE &amp; OAKEY, Paternosterrow; and 70, Edgware-road.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >EVERY MAN HIS OWN BUTLER.</head><p >Second Edition, just published, bound in cloth, <lb/> price 3s.,</p><p >EVERY MAN his own BUTLER. By CYRUS REDDING, Author of “The History and Description of Modern Wines.”</p><p >London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co., 85, Queen- <lb/> street, Cheapside.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NORMA AND SONNAMBULA,</head><p >4s. each, complete. BOOSEY'S new editions of these Operas for the Pianoforte Solo perfect and complete, beautifully engraved and printed, are just published, price 4s. each in wrappers, or 5s. each in illuminated covers, gilt edges.</p><p >T. BOOSEY &amp; Co., 28, Holles-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just published, crown 8vo, price 5s., with 6 Engravings <lb/> and numerous Woodcuts, elegantly bound.</opener><head >MEMORIALS FROM BEN RHYDDING, CONCERNING THE PLACE, ITS PEOPLE, and ITS CURES.</head><p >“This is the most handsome and well-embellished volume ever laid upon our table. * * * Besides much that is entertaining, it gives the only real scientific view of the water cure that we have met with, and presents it in a light that cannot fail to commend it to every unprejudiced mind. The work is published from a sense of benefits received, and a desire to enlighten the community.”—<hi rend="italics">British Friend.</hi></p><p >London: CHARLES GILPIN, 5, Bishopsgate <lb/> Without.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HUSBANDS, FATHERS, BROTHERS, </head><p >YOU know how dull they are at Home when <hi rend="italics">you</hi> are out; therefore before you leave home of an Evening to <hi rend="italics">hear the news,</hi> have a <hi rend="italics">quiet rubber,</hi> or play <hi rend="italics">just one game at chess,</hi> don't forget to leave some amusement at home. The cheapest and best is READING. Try <lb/> MOUNTCASTLE'S LIBRARY, <lb/> Bedford-court, Covent-Garden.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13"/><head >IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT.</head><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">With the Magazines for April will appear, as the First Volume of the</hi></opener><head > ILLUSTRATED LONDON LIBRARY, </head><p >Illustrated with above Two Hundred Engravings, <lb/> NINEVEH AND ITS PALACES: <lb/> THE DISCOVERIES OF BOTTA AND LAYARD APPLIED TO THE ELUCIDATION <lb/> OF HOLY WRIT.</p><p >“For the stones shall cry out of the wall, and the beams out of the timber shall answer it.”—HAB. ii. 11.</p><p >BY JOSEPH BONOMI.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PROSPECTUS OF THE ILLUSTRATED LONDON LIBRARY.</head><p >PRICE SIX SHILLINGS EACH VOLUME.</p><p >ILLUSTRATED WORKS are every day becoming more popular. The aid which Art can afford to Literature is beginning to be more thoroughly appreciated by the reading public, and the education of the mind through the eye is felt to be not only of advantage as a source of refined amusement for the passing hour, but of more positive and permanent instruction. To meet the demand for works of this kind which has in consequence arisen, the Proprietors of the</p><p >NATIONAL ILLUSTRATED LIBRARY <lb/> have the honour to announce a NEW SERIES, of larger and more copiously illustrated volumes, under the title of the <lb/> ILLUSTRATED LONDON LIBRARY.</p><p >Each volume will contain upwards of 400 pages, full-sized demy octavo, printed on superior paper, and in a new and elegant type. The Landscape Illustrations will invariably be derived either from original sketches or from other authentic sources; the Portraits will be as accurate and faithful as it is possible to make them; while the Architectural and Archæological subjects will in all cases be entrusted to the most competent Artists and Engravers. Each Volume will be handsomely and substantially bound, and will form an elegant ornament to the drawing-room table, as well as a useful addition to the shelves of the book-case. The Series will include Works of History. <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Blography</sic><corr>Biography</corr></choice> and Travels, and the general progress of Art, Science and Literature; and will in all respects be as varied in the subjects selected as the intellect and the wants of the present time demand.</p><p >227, STRAND, <hi rend="italics">February,</hi> 1852.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >New and Important Works just published at 227, Strand.</head><p >LOUIS NAPOLEON BONAPARTE</p><p >This day is published, in two vols. demy 8vo, price One Guinea, or elegantly bound in calf, <lb/> hf.-extra, marble edges, £1 11s. 6d.,</p><p > THE POLITICAL WORKS OF LOUIS NAPOLEON <lb/> BONAPARTE:</p><p > With an Original Memoir of his Life, brought down to the present date, drawn from authentic sources.</p><p >These volumes possess great interest. Among the most important works of the Prince which they comprise are his “Political Reveries,” with the Scheme of a Constitution, published in 1832; “Ideas of Napoleonism,” “On the Extinction of Pauperism,” “Historical Parallels between 1688 and 1830,” &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >In 2 vols. post 8vo, cloth, price 7s.; or handsomely bound in calf, price 14s., Second Edition, <lb/> THE LIFE OF GENERAL WASHINGTON.</p><p >WRITTEN BY HIMSELF.</p><p >With highly finished Engravings, and elegantly bound in cloth, price 5s., <lb/> THE PATHWAY OF THE FAWN.</p><p >A Cale of the New Year.</p><p >Bound in blue and silver, price 5s.</p><p >LADY FELICIA; A NEW NOVEL.</p><p >By HENRY COCKTON, author of “Valentine Vox,” “Sylvester Sound,” &amp;c.</p><p >This day, March 1, Volumes I. and II., fcp. 8vo, cloth, price 2s. 6d. each Volume, Unabridged Edition.</p><p >HUC'S TRAVELS IN TARTARY, THIBET, AND <lb/> CHINA, IN 1844, 1845, AND 1846.</p><p >OFFICE, 227, STRAND.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14"/><head >AMERICAN AND CONTINENTAL LITERARY AGENCY,</head><p > (ESTABLISHED IN 1837, BY WILEY AND PUTNAM,) <lb/> 12, PATERNOSTER-ROW, LONDON, <lb/> FOR THE IMPORTATION OF <lb/> Foreign Books, Periodicals, Newspapers, Maps, &amp;c.</p><p >IN addition to a well-selected Stock of the Works of American Authors in every department of Literature, the Agency is supplied by every Steamer from the United States with copies of all the New Publications of interest and value. By the facilities afforded through the great increase and rapidity of steam communication between the two countries, orders for Books can be executed in about thirty-five days.</p><p >“The American Almanac,” “Silliman's Journal of Science and Arts,” “Bibliotheca Sacra,” “North American Review,” &amp;c. &amp;c., regularly received as soon as published.</p><p >Catalogues and every information relating to American and Continental Literature will be supplied to Correspondents.</p><p >DELF &amp; TRUBNER, IMPORTERS OF AMERICAN BOOKS, &amp;c. 12, PATERNOSTER-ROW.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SURE GUIDE TO MATRIMONIAL HAPPINESS.</head><p >New and improved Edition.—This day, in a neat volume, in cloth gilt, price 3s. 6d., <lb/> HOME TRUTHS FOR HOME PEACE.</p><p >A PRACTICAL INQUIRY INTO WHAT CHIEFLY MARS OR MAKES THE COMFORTS OF <lb/> DOMESTIC LIFE. ESPECIALLY ADDRESSED TO YOUNG HOUSEWIVES.</p><p >“We cannot too strongly recommend this volume to our female readers; by attention to its contents they cannot fail to become efficient housekeepers and exemplary wives and mothers.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Times.</hi></p><p >LONDON: EFFINGHAM WILSON, PUBLISHER, 11, ROYAL EXCHANGE.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >READABLE BOOKS,</head><p >
<table><row><cell>IN VOLUMES, CONTAINING 260 PAGES</cell><cell>ONE SHILLING.</cell></row><row><cell>IN MONTHLY PARTS, OF 160 PAGES</cell><cell>SIXPENCE.</cell></row><row><cell>IN WEEKLY NUMBERS, OF 32 PAGES</cell><cell>ONE PENNY.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Handsomely printed on good paper, with Frontispieces, &amp; numerous other Illustrations, <lb/> FORMING A LIBRARY, SUITED AS REGARDS PRICE TO THE PURSE, AND <lb/> AS REGARDS PORTABILITY TO THE POCKET.</p><p >CHARLES LAMB, in one of his admirable essays, told the public that he could read anything which he called <hi rend="italics">a book,</hi> but intimated that there were things in that shape which he could not allow to be such. “In this catalogue,” says he, “of <hi rend="italics">books which are no books—biblia-a-biblia</hi>—I reckon Court Calendars, Directories, Pocket-books, Draught-boards bound and lettered on the back, Scientific Treatises, Almanacks, Statutes at Large, the Works of Hume, Gibbon, Robertson, Beattie, Soame Jenyns, and generally all those volumes which ‘no gentleman's library should be without.’ With these exceptions, I can read almost anything. I bless my stars for a taste so catholic, so unexcluding.”</p><p >Had the essayist lived to the present day, when the printing-press sends forth library after library, until their very names are legion, he would have found it necessary to modify his self-congratulation, and to chronicle a few additional exceptions. It is a known fact that more than half of the books now published which escape the trunk-maker and the butterman, are never read at all; for the greater portion of that large section of the community who do read books, are too overworked to have much leisure for reading recreation beyond that bestowed on the Englishman's necessity—his newspaper; and of the little time that remains, it is idle to expect that it should be spent in poring over treatises on popular science, dull translated histories, dreary voyages and travels, or dry standard authors,—in short, those books which, as Charles Lamb says, “no gentleman's library should be without.”</p><p >If we are to believe the Chancellor of the Exchequer, who recently described to a gaping audience at the Halifax Mechanics' Institute, the contents of one of the railway book-stalls that engaged his attention, even those great patrons of cheap literature, the railway travellers, are but indifferently catered for,—for the Chancellor seems to have stumbled upon a volume of Thucydides and a Treatise on Logarithms, side by side with Shilling Novels, of the usual soporific character.</p><p >It is true, that Dr. Johnson, on his Tour to the Hebrides, bought a Cocker's Arithmetic to beguile the tedium of the journey, and when Boswell expressed surprise at his choice, the sage silenced him with this ready reply: “Why, sir, if you are to have but one book with you upon a journey, it should be a book of science. When you have read through a book of entertainment, you know it, and it can do no more for you, but a book of science is inexhaustible.” In the belief, however, that most people are not Dr. Johnsons, and that they require a somewhat lighter literary fare to suit their mental digestion, it is proposed to publish, at the lowest possible price, a series of READABLE BOOKS, the distinguishing feature of which will be a certain vivacity of style or subject, suitable alike to the family circle, and the solitary student—to the idler suffering from <hi rend="italics">ennui,</hi> and the man weary with work—to the sedentary stayer at home, and the more mercurial traveller on river, road, and rail.</p><p >The First Volume, the First Part, and the First Number are published this day, and may be obtained of all Booksellers.</p><p >LONDON: HENRY VIZETELLY, GOUGH SQUARE, FLEET STREET.</p><p >JOHN MENZIES, EDINBURGH. JAMES M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >A SOVEREIGN REMEDY FOR BAD TEA.</head><p >ALEADEN PACKAGE, containing FIVE POUNDS of FINE, TRUE, RICH, RIPE, RARE SOUCHONG TEA (which will please everybody), sent, CARRIAGE FREE, to any part of England, on receipt of a Post-office Order for ONE SOVEREIGN, by</p><p >PHILLIPS AND COMPANY, TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> No. 8, KING WILLIAM-STREET, CITY, LONDON.</p><p >And will prove indeed a Sovereign Remedy for Bad Tea.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15"/><head >Newspaper for the Farming and Gardening Interest.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Published every Saturday, price Sixpence, free by post, each Volume complete in itself,</hi>
<lb/> ENLARGED TO TWENTY-FOUR FOLIO PAGES, <lb/> THE GARDENERS' CHRONICLE <lb/> AND <lb/> AGRICULTURAL GAZETTE; <lb/> A Weekly Record of Rural Economy and General News.</p><p >THE HORTICULTURAL PART EDITED BY PROFESSOR LINDLEY.</p><p >The Farming Part under the Editorship of a practical Farmer.</p><p >Reports are regularly given of the English, Scotch, and Irish Agricultural Societies and Farmers' Clubs—London Market Prices of Corn, Hay, Cattle, Seeds, Hops, Potatoes, Wool, Coal, Timber, Bark, &amp;c., and the Weekly Averages.</p><p >As regards the Gardening Part (under the Editorship of Dr. Lindley), the principle is to make it a weekly record of everything that bears upon Horticulture, Floriculture, Arboriculture, or Garden Botany, and such Natural History as has a relation to Gardening, with Notices and Criticisms of all Works on such subjects. Connected with this part are <lb/> WEEKLY CALENDARS OF GARDENING OPERATIONS.</p><p >Replies to Questions connected with the object of the Paper are also furnished weekly.</p><p >Lastly, that description of Domestic and Political News is introduced which is usually found in a Weekly Newspaper.</p><p >A PROSPECTUS, WITH LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS, may be had on application, or by letter, at the Office, 5, Upper Wellington Street, Covent Garden, London.</p><p >Parties intending to Commence with the New Volume had better give their <lb/> Orders at once to any Newsvender.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Every Saturday Price Fourpence of any Bookseller, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Twenty-four and occasionally Thirty-two Large Quarto Pages.</hi></opener><head >THE ATHENÆUM, <lb/> JOURNAL OF LITERATURE, SCIENCE, AND ART.</head><p >(Stamped to go free by post, 5d.)</p><p >CONTAINS:—</p><p >Reviews, with copious extracts, of every important New English Book, and of the more important Foreign Works.</p><p >List of Works published each week.</p><p >Reports of the Proceedings of the Learned and Scientific Societies, with Abstracts of all Papers of Interest.</p><p >Authentic Accounts of all Scientific Voyages and Expeditions.</p><p >Foreign Correspondence on Subjects relating to Literature, Science, and Art.</p><p >Criticisms on Art, with Critical Notices of Exhibitions, Picture Collections, New Prints, &amp;c.</p><p >Music and Drama, including Reports on the Opera, Concerts, Theatres, New Music, &amp;c.</p><p >Biographical Notices of Men distinguished in Literature, Science and Art.</p><p >Original Papers and Poems.</p><p >Weekly Gossip.</p><p >Miscellanea, including all that is likely to interest the informed and intelligent.</p><p >THE ATHENÆUM <lb/> is so conducted that the reader, however far distant, is, in respect to Literature, Science, and the Arts, on an equality in point of information with the best-informed circles of the <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Metropoils</sic><corr>Metropolis</corr></choice>.</p><p >The ATHENÆUM is published every SATURDAY, but is re-issued each Month, stitched in a wrapper.</p><p >Wholesale Agents: for SCOTLAND, Messrs. Bell &amp; Bradfute, Edinburgh; for IRELAND, Messrs.</p><p >Robertson, Dublin; for France, M. Baudry, 3, Quai Malaquais, Paris.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16"/><opener >THE PUBLISHERS of “THE PARLOUR LIBRARY,” encouraged by the striking success which has attended their efforts to popularise works of the highest merit in the department of Fiction, beg to announce, that they have now completed their arrangements for the issue of a New Series, to be entitled,</opener><head >THE BOOKCASE, <lb/> and to consist of the most valuable and attractive works of <lb/> TRAVELS, HISTORY, BIOGRAPHY, ETC., ETC.</head><p >THE FIRST VOLUME IS NOW READY.</p><p >In post 8vo, price 1s. 6d., with Enamelled Cover, <lb/> ACROSS THE ROCKY MOUNTAINS, <lb/> FROM NEW YORK TO CALIFORNIA, WITH A VISIT TO THE CELEBRATED MORMON <lb/> COLONY, AT THE GREAT SALT LAKE.</p><p >BY WILLIAM KELLY, ESQ.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A Volume will appear on the 1st of each month with the Parlour Library.</hi></p><p >Also Just Published, <lb/> MARGARET CATCHPOLE.</p><p >BY THE REV. R. COBBOLD.</p><p >FORMING THE 74TH VOLUME OF THE PARLOUR LIBRARY.</p><p >Price 1s. 6d. boards, 2s. cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Lists free by post on application.</hi></p><p >SIMMS AND M`INTYRE, <lb/> 13, Paternoster Row, London, and Belfast.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NISSEN AND PARKER, <lb/> STATIONERS, ENGRAVERS, PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS, ACCOUNT-BOOK <lb/> MANUFACTURERS, &amp;c.</head><p >No. 43, MARK LANE, GREAT TOWER STREET, LONDON.</p><p >RESPECTFULLY direct the attention of Bankers, Merchants, and Public Companies to their Establishment for the supply of <lb/> EVERY ARTICLE FOR THE COUNTING-HOUSE.</p><p >Experience, extending over twenty years, enables them to offer many advantages in quality and price. In large Mercantile, Establishments, the Stationery Department, whilst it involves a considerable outlay, seldom receives the attention which its importance demands, from the fact of few Stationers having combined under one Establishment, Printing in LETTER-PRESS, LITHOGRAPHY and COPPER-PLATE, the Manufacture of ACCOUNT-BOOKS, and the supply of the more minute articles for the office, in addition to the various descriptions of Paper.</p><p >NISSEN &amp; PARKER, executing every branch on the Premises, beg to state, that all business entrusted to their care will receive (for the smallest order) the most strict attention; any article not thoroughly approved is immediately exchanged, and in all cases the utmost exertion used to give satisfaction. The extraordinary fact, that upwards of <hi rend="italics">Two Thousand Banking and Mercantile Firms have opened accounts with this Establishment in the short space of seven years,</hi> is submitted as a guarantee for the mode in which the business is carried out.</p><div type="section"><head >ACCOUNT-BOOKS</head><p >of the finest PAPERS, bound with loose backs, in forril, calf, vellum, and russia, with bands for extra strength, with or without brass edging, locks or bolt clasps, upon a NEW AND IMPROVED PRINCIPLE, UNITING EVERY SHEET OF PAPER MORE CLOSELY AND PERMANENTLY TOGETHER THAN COULD POSSIBLY BE EFFECTED BY THE OLD SYSTEM OF ACCOUNT-BOOK BINDING.</p><p >An extensive assortment of Account-Books, always ready for immediate despatch, ruled to all the usual mercantile patterns.</p><p >Books for the East Indies, prepared especially for protection from the destructiveness of the <hi rend="italics">White Ant.</hi></p><p >BANKERS, MERCHANTS, MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT, AND OTHERS, REQUIRING STATIONERY, <lb/> WILL FIND AT THIS ADDRESS, <lb/> EVERY ARTICLE FOR THE COUNTING HOUSE OR LIBRARY, <lb/> Of the finest quality.—Letter and Note Papers, Envelopes (with or without stamped addresses), Foreign Copying Papers, India Letter Papers, Despatch and Deed Boxes, Cloth Envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >SHIPPING ORDERS TO ANY EXTENT, ON THE SHORTEST NOTICE.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p17"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">Crown 8vo., price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></opener><head > THE FRENCH IN ENGLAND;</head><p > OR, BOTH SIDES OF THE QUESTION ON BOTH SIDES OF THE CHANNEL.</p><p >BEING THE STORY OF THE EMPEROR NAPOLEON'S PROJECTED INVASION.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Numbers I. to III. (to be completed in Twelve Monthly Parts, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. each) of</hi></opener><head > MR. SPONGE'S SPORTING TOUR.</head><p >By the Author of “Handley Cross,” “Jorrocks's Jaunts,” &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >EACH NUMBER CONTAINS ONE COLOURED ENGRAVING AND NUMEROUS WOODCUTS, BY JOHN LEECH.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Works on Gardening and Botany.</head><p >PAXTON'S FLOWER-GARDEN.</p><p >Edited by SIR JOSEPH PAXTON and Dr. LINDLEY. Each Volume is Illustrated by 36 highly-finished Plates, and more than 200 beautiful Wood Engravings. Volumes I. and II. Price 33<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, elegantly bound in cloth.</p><p >Numbers 1 to 24 may be procured by order of any Bookseller, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p><p >PAXTON'S BOTANICAL DICTIONARY. Comprising the Names, History, and Culture of all Plants known in Britain; with a full Explanation of Technical Terms. Crown 8vo, 16s.</p><p >THE SUPPLEMENT, containing all the New Plants since the First Edition, may be had separately, price 5s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Works by Professor Lindley.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Preparing for Publication, a New Edition, Enlarged</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">and Improved, of</hi></p><p >THE VEGETABLE KINGDOM; OR, THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS. Illustrated upon the Natural System.</p><p >THE ELEMENTS OF BOTANY, STRUCTURAL AND PHYSIOLOGICAL. With a Glossary of Technical Terms, and Numerous Illustrations, 12s. cl.<hi rend="italics">The</hi> GLOSSARY <hi rend="italics">may be had separately, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. cloth.</hi></p><p >THE ELEMENTS OF MEDICAL AND ECONOMICAL BOTANY. With Numerous Illustrations. 8vo, price 14s. cloth.</p><p >SCHOOL BOTANY; OR, THE RUDIMENTS OF BOTANICAL SCIENCE. With nearly 400 Illustrations. New Edition. 8vo, price 5s. 6d. half-bound.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Price 7s. cloth, with numerous Woodcuts representing the Processes of Grafting, Budding, Layering, &amp;c.</hi></opener><head >THE FIFTH EDITION OF <lb/> THE LADIES' COMPANION TO THE FLOWER GARDEN.</head><p >BEING AN ALPHABETICAL ARRANGEMENT OF ALL THE ORNAMENTAL PLANTS GROWN IN GARDENS AND <lb/> SHRUBBERIES; WITH FULL DIRECTIONS FOR THEIR CULTURE.</p><p >BY MRS. LOUDON.</p><p >BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MUDIE'S SELECT LIBRARY </head><p > is removed from No. 28, Upper King-street, <lb/> Bloomsbury, to <lb/> 510, NEW OXFORD-STREET, <lb/> AND 20, MUSEUM-STREET.</p><p >AN ample supply is provided at this Library of all the principal New Works as they appear. The preference is given to works of History, Biography, Religion, Philosophy, and Travel. The <hi rend="italics">best</hi> works of Fiction are also freely added.</p><p >Single Subscription one guinea per annum. First Class Country Subscription two guineas and upwards, according to the number of volumes required.</p><p >Literary Institutions and Book Societies supplied on liberal terms.</p><p >The Addenda for 1850—1 is now ready, and will be sent in answer to all applications inclosing 12 stamps.</p><p >CHARLES EDWARD MUDIE, 510, New Oxford-st.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHARACTER FROM HAND WRITING.</head><p >MR. WARREN, of 9, Great College-street, Westminster, continues with great success to <hi rend="italics">delineate the Character of Individuals from their Handwriting.</hi>—All persons desirous of testing his art are invited to forward a specimen of their ordinary writing, together with 13 postage-stamps, and a mention of their sex and age, to the above address.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned. `Robert Shaw, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Prices, 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >WRITING RAPIDLY IMPROVED.</head><p >MR. CARSTAIRS (Son of the inventor of the celebrated System of Writing), continues to give LESSONS to LADIES and GENTLEMEN of all ages, in his highly improved method, which will impart a command and fluency of the hand and pen seldom, if ever, equalled, in every size and variety of penmanship, even to the worst writer, in the shortest possible time. Arithmetic and Book-keeping taught practically.—PROSPECTUSES of terms, &amp;c., may be had at his establishment, 81, LOMBARD-STREET, CITY.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SIR JAMES MURRAY'S FLUID <lb/> MAGNESIA.</head><p >PREPARED under the immediate care of the Inventor, and established for upwards of thirty years, by the PROFESSION, for removing BILE, ACIDITIES, and INDIGESTION, restoring APPETITE, preserving a moderate state of the bowels, and dissolving uric acid in GRAVEL and GOUT; also as an easy remedy for SEA SICKNESS, and for the febrile affection incident to childhood it is invaluable.—On the value of Magnesia as a remedial agent it is unnecessary to enlarge; but the Fluid Preparation of Sir James Murray is now the most valued by the profession as it entirely avoids the possibility of those dangerous concretions usually resulting from the use of the article in powder.</p><p >Sold by the sole consignee, Mr. WILLIAM BAILEY, of Wolverhampton; and by all wholesale and retail Druggists and Medicine Agents throughout the British Empire, in bottles, 1s., 2s.6d., 3s.6d., 5s.6d., 11s., and 21s. each.</p><p >The Acidulated Syrup, in Bottles 2s. each. N.B.—Be sure to ask for “Sir James Murray's Preparation,” and to see that his name is stamped on each label <hi rend="italics">in green ink,</hi> as follows:—“James Murray, Physician to the Lord Lieutenant.”</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p18"/><head >THE HUMAN HAIR.</head><p >ROWLANDS' MACASSAR OIL.</p><p >THIS ELEGANT, FRAGRANT, and PELLUCID OIL, in its <hi rend="italics">preservative, restorative,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">beautifying</hi> qualities for the Human Hair, is unequalled over the whole world. It <hi rend="italics">preserves</hi> and <hi rend="italics">reproduces</hi> the <hi rend="italics">hair,</hi> even at a late period of life: prevents it from <hi rend="italics">turning grey.</hi> or if so changed, <hi rend="italics">restores it to its original colour;</hi> frees it from <hi rend="italics">scurf</hi> and <hi rend="italics">impurity,</hi> and renders it <hi rend="italics">soft, silky, curly, glossy.</hi></p><p >CAUTION.—A. R. and Sons have complaints repeatedly from parties who have materially suffered from the use of spurious imitations; and to frustrate to some extent such impositions, they here add a small copy in outline of their genuine label from the burin of MESSRS. PERKINS, BACON &amp; PETCH, the eminent engravers of London, on which will be seen the names and address of the Proprietors in full (these are in red ink on the label), any deviation from which will always prove a spurious article.</p><p >The prices are 3s. 6d.; 7s.; family bottles (equal to four small) 10s. 6d.; and double that size 21s. Sold by the Proprietors, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Rodger's Improved Shirts, 26s., 31s. 6d., <lb/> and 37s. 6d. the half dozen,</head><p >ARE cut upon a New and Improved Principle, which insures the most perfect fit, and combines the highest degree of excellence at the smallest cost.—Satisfaction is (as usual) guaranteed or the money returned.</p><p >Printed priced lists, with full particulars and directions for self-measurement, and, if required, patterns of the New <hi rend="italics">Coloured</hi> Shirts for 1852 at 26s. the half-dozen, gratis and post free to all parts of the Kingdom.</p><p >RODGER'S &amp; Co., Improved Shirt Makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing-cross, and 29, New-street, Covent-garden, London. (Established 60 years.)—N.B. Boys' Shirts in all sizes at exceedingly moderate prices.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT and PILLS have AGAIN been MOST EFFICACIOUS in CURING a SORE LEG.—</head><p >John Thomas, a labourer, far advanced in years, residing at Pemaen Back, near Conway, had suffered for a very considerable time from a dreadfully sore leg, and was for many months under the care of most eminent medical men, but their remedies appeared perfectly useless. He then commenced using Holloway's Ointment and Pills, and after giving them a fair trial, his leg was completely cured, and the wounds soundly healed. These medicines excel all others in the cure of scrofula or king's evil, glandular and other unnatural swellings, scurvy, leprosy, and all diseases of the skin.—Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p >In all the new Materials and prevailing styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON, (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1s. 11d., 2s. 6d., 3s. 6d.; medium, 5s. 6d., 7s. 6d., 10s. 6d., 12s. 6d.; handsome, 15s. 6d., 18s. 6d., 21s. 6d., up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p><p >HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10½d,; Frocks, 1s. 6d., 1s. 9d.; ditto, long sleeves, 2s. 9d., 3s. 6d.; Blouses, 3s. 6d., 4s. 6d., 5s. 6d.</p><p >MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two <lb/> years and upwards.</p><p >INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY; thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p><p >An illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >STRAKER'S NEW &amp; IMPROVED SIDE &amp; UPRIGHT LEVER PRESSES,</head><p > which for every character of work stands unrivalled; in sizes from 15 by 20 inches upwards.</p><p >IMPORTER OF LITHOGRAPHIC STONES, <lb/> The most extensive Stocks of which are constantly on hand and at the lowest current rates.</p><p >DETAILED PRICE LISTS <lb/> Of Presses, and every Material and Instrument in the art, together with Designs, forwarded on application.</p><p >Instruction in the Art afforded to Amateurs and Public Institutions.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p19"/><head >PRIZE MEDAL.</head><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN, Manufacturing Goldsmiths, Established A.D. 1798, beg to announce to the Nobility, Gentry, and Public in general, that in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them since the Great Exhibition, they have resolved to throw open their Manufactory to the public at <hi rend="italics">Manufacturers' Prices,</hi> a closer connexion than has hitherto existed between the real worker in the precious metals and the Public, being obviously an advantage to both parties.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S dealings will be principally to establish confidence in the gold employed in the manufacture of chains, where at present the greatest uncertainty exists, owing to the prevalence of electro-gilt articles, and weighing chains, frequently as low as 11 carats fine=38s. 11¼d., against sovereigns of 22 carats fine=77s. 10½. per oz., when there is no analogy between one and the other; a chain weighing 5 sovereigns being intrinsically worth only 50s. The object of the vendor is wholly to conceal the remaining 50s.</p><p >Gold is capable of being alloyed to any extent, and in order to protect the public, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN will make the Mint. price of 77s. 10½d. per oz. for British standard, the basis of all their operations, and making their profit on the workmanship alone, will charge the bullion in their chains at its intrinsic value, undertaking to repurchase it at any time at the same price: thus—</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>per oz.</cell></row><row><cell>15 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell><cell>53s. 1d.</cell></row><row><cell>18 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell><cell>63s. 8⅛d.</cell></row><row><cell>22 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise the Mint price of</cell><cell>77s. 10½d.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >The price for workmanship will be charged according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern. For example—</p><p >A Chain weighing 2 oz. of 15 Carat</p><p >Gold is worth, at 53s. 1d. per oz. 5£ 6<hi rend="ITALICS">s.</hi>  2 <hi rend="ITALICS">d.</hi> intrinsic value.</p><p >Supposing the Workmanship to be 2£ 0<hi rend="ITALICS">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="ITALICS">d.</hi></p><p >Total £7£ 6<hi rend="ITALICS">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="ITALICS">d.</hi></p><p >By this arrangement the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">bullion</hi> in a gold chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S Stock consists of Gold Guard Chains, Albert Chains, Seals, Keys, Rings, Brooches, Bracelets, Diamond Setting, and every description of Goldsmith's and Jeweller's Work, all made on the premises.</p><p >MANUFACTORY, No. 16, Henrietta-street, Covent-garden, London; where the processes of manipulation may be seen by those who are interested in the subject.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >TESTIMONIAL.</head><p >From Mr. JOHN HEATON, Agent, Leeds.</p><p >7, Briggate, Leeds, Aug. 15, 1851.</p><p >DEAR SIRS,—I some time since forwarded you a Testimonial as to the efficacy of PARR'S LIFE PILLS in this neighbourhood. I am happy to be able now to inform you that my opinion of their excellence continues unaltered, and the unvarying testimony of my customers assures me that they are a great boon to the working classes; their use having, in a great number of cases which have come under my notice, been attended by the most beneficial results in the removal or abatement of the most distressing maladies—in many instances amongst persons whose circumstances rendered it utterly impossible for them to avail themselves of medical treatment, and in many others where medical treatment had been resorted to without avail. It is always satisfactory to know that what one is the means of introducing or circulating is likely to serve the desired purpose; and there is no medicine I sell with greater satisfaction or confidence, on account of their excellence and efficacy in all respects, than PARR'S LIFE PILLS.—I am, dear Sirs, yours faithfully, <lb/> JOHN HEATON.</p><p >Messrs. T. Roberts &amp; Co., Crane-court, Fleet-street, London.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >TO LADIES.</head><p >PARR'S LIFE PILLS are especially efficacious in all the variety of ailments incident to the Fair Sex. Ladies even of the most delicate constitutions will find them particularly beneficial both before and after confinement; and for general use in SCHOOLS they cannot be too strongly recommended. They mildly and speedily remove all Skin Eruptions, Sallowness of Complexion, Nervous Irritability, Sick Head-ache, Depression of Spirits, Irregularity, or general derangement of the system.</p><p >Sole Proprietors, T. ROBERTS &amp; Co., Crane-court, Fleet-street, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PARR'S LIFE PILLS</head><p >SOLD <lb/> WHOLESALE AND <lb/> RETAIL</p><p >BY <lb/> APPOINTMENT <lb/> BY</p><p >E. EDWARDS, 67, St. Paul's Churchyard; BARCLAY &amp; SONS, Farringdon-street; SUTTON &amp; Co., Bow Churchyard, London; J. and R. RAIMES &amp; Co., Edinburgh; MOTTERSHEAD &amp; Co., Manchester; RAIMES &amp; Co., Liverpool; APOTHECARIES' COMPANY, Glasgow; MANDER &amp; Co., Wolverhampton; DAGLISH &amp; ISMAY, Newcastle; and BOLTON &amp; Co., York. Also Retail by our Agents in every Town in the United Kingdom; and by most respectable Medicine Vendors, in boxes at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p20"/><head >THOS. HARRIS &amp; SON'S <lb/> CHRYSTAL SPECTACLES.</head><p >THE BEST FOR PRESERVING THE SIGHT.</p><p >By Using HARRIS &amp; SON's Spectacles, the many painful sensations in the eyes so frequently complained of by ladies when at Needlework, Music, &amp;c., are removed: they are very beneficial by candle-light, and enable the wearer to continue reading a much longer time, without fatigue, or the risk of injuring the sight.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Best blued Steel Crystal Spectacles and Case,</cell><cell>15s. 0d.</cell></row><row><cell>Steel Glass Spectacles from</cell><cell>2s. 6d.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >OPERA GLASSES <lb/> Made on a new principle, at very low prices.</p><p >RACE GLASSES, <lb/> The most powerful that can be, with case, £4 10s.</p><p >THO<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. HARRIS &amp; SON'S</p><p >Improved Achromatic Telescopes.</p><p >Most amusing for Tourists and Seaside Visitors. For eight miles, 18s.; twelve ditto, 30s.; sixteen ditto, 42s.; twenty ditto, £4. Game-keepers' Telescopes, 20s.</p><p >THOMAS HARRIS &amp; SON, Opticians to the Royal Family, 141, OXFORD STREET, corner of Old Cavendish-street; and 52, GREAT RUSSELL STREET, opposite the British Museum Entrance, London.</p><p >ESTABLISHED SEVENTY YEARS.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >COUGH JUJUBE LOZENGES.—</head><p >These Jujubes are composed of the most approved expectorants, with pure gum, which, by relieving the irritation in the air passages, present a safe, agreeable, and efficacious Medicine in all cases of Asthma, Bronchitis, Difficult Respiration, Consumptive Complaints, and all other affections of the Chest and Lungs.</p><p >Prepared and sold by WARWICK BROTHERS, 3, GARLICK-HILL, LONDON; and by all Chemists and Druggists throughout the Country. Price 1s. 1½d. and 2s. 9d. per box, with directions.</p><p >Also Proprietors of the <lb/> Acidulated Cayenne Jujube Lozenges.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.</head><p >A CERTAIN REMEDY for disorders of the <hi rend="italics">Pulmonary Organs</hi>—in Difficulty of Breathing—in Redundancy of Phlegm—in Incipient CONSUMPTION (of which COUGH is the most positive indication) they are of unerring efficacy. In ASTHMA, and in WINTER COUGH, they have <hi rend="italics">never</hi> been known to fall.</p><p >Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1s. 1½d., and Tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Church Yard, London.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >IMPORTANT TESTIMONIAL.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Copy of a Letter from COLONEL HAWKER, (the well known Author on “GUNS AND SHOOTING.”)</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">Longparish House, near Whitchurch, Hants,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">October 21st,</hi> 1846.</p><p >SIR.—I cannot resist informing you of the extraordinary effect I have experienced by taking only a few of your LOZENGES. I had a cough for several weeks, that defied all that had been prescribed for me; and yet 1 got completely rid of it by taking about half a small box of your Lozenges, which I find are the only ones that relieve the cough without deranging the stomach or digestive organs.</p><p >I am, Sir, your humble servant, <lb/> P. HAWKER.</p><p >To Mr. KEATING, 79, St. Paul's Churchyard.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NATIONAL PROVIDENT INSTITUTION FOR MUTUAL LIFE ASSURANCE, ANNUITIES, &amp;c.,</head><p >48, GRACECHURCH-STREET, LONDON.</p><p >SAMUEL HAYHURST LUCAS, Esq., CHAIRMAN.</p><p >CHARLES LUSHINGTON, Esq., M.P., <lb/> DEPUTY-CHAIRMAN.</p><p >CONSULTING ACTUARY.—Charles Ansell, Esq., F.R.S.</p><p >EXTRACT FROM THE REPORT FOR 1851:—</p><p >“In the year ending the 20th November, 1851, 1231 Policies have been issued: the Annual Premiums on which amount to £18,498 8s. 6d.</p><p >“Since the establishment of the institution in December, 1835, 13,729 Policies have been effected, and the Annual Income is £189,240 2s.</p><p >“The balance of receipts over the disbursements in 1851, is £114,623 3s. 9d.; and the capital is now £738,492 18s. 4d.”</p><p >The next Quinquennial Division of Profits will be made up to the 20th November, 1852, and all who effect assurances before that time will participate in the profits which may accrue to such Policies.</p><p >The Report is now ready, and may be had on application at the Office, or of the Agents in the country.</p><p >Feb. 5, 1852.</p><p >JOSEPH MARSH, <hi rend="italics">Secretary.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >LOANS IN CONNECTION WITH LIFE ASSURANCE.—PELICAN LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY, Established in 1797.</head><p >NOTICE.—The Directors are prepared to receive proposals for LOANS ON APPROVED SECURITY in Sums of not less than £500, coupled with one or more Policies of Insurance to be effected in the Pelican office.</p><p >Applications to be made to the Secretary at the chief office of the Company, No. 70, Lombard street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Garden Engines, Syringes, &amp;c.,</head><p > upon the last improved principle, manufactured <hi rend="italics">only</hi>
<lb/> by <lb/> RICHARD READ, <lb/> Instrument Maker (by special Appointment) to Her <lb/> Majesty, <lb/> 35, REGENT CIRCUS, PICCADILLY.</p><p >CAUTION.—As Instruments of the commonest description are extensively circulated throughout the Kingdom, and sold as “READ'S,” please observe the Royal Arms, and the words, “Read's Patent,” without which none are genuine.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p >(as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Disinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous, useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p><p >Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p><p >RIMMEL'S Hair Dye imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.—Price 5s. 6d.</p><p >RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended—Beware of counterfeits.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39, Gerard-street, Soho, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >STOOPING of the SHOULDERS and CONTRACTION of the CHEST PREVENTED and CURED, in Children and Adults, by BINYON'S PATENT CHEST EXPANDER,</head><p > which produces an immediate improvement in the figure, and where one shoulder has grown out, speedily restores it to its natural position. Can be forwarded by post. Full particulars and price sent on receipt of a stamped envelope, by Mr. A. BINYON, 3, Great Marlborough-street, Regent-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p21"/><head >THE HAIR.</head><p >Beware of Acids! All oils have a powerful acid in them. This truth may be rendered apparent by putting a drop upon copper, a green cankerous rust will soon appear. This acid is, of all things, the most injurious to the skin of the head, upon the healthiness of which mainly depends the existence of a fine head of Hair.</p><p >MILTON'S <lb/> HAIR LUBRICANT</p><p >is not oil or grease, strictly, but is an exact resemblance of the peculiar matter with which nature supplies the Hair, and which will, if applied as directed in a Treatise on the Hair sold with each pot, restore the Hair from any injury it may have received from improper treatment, and speedily render it vigorous, abundant, and beautiful. In an elegant pot, price 2s.</p><p >Sold by all perfumers and medicine vendors in town and country. Wholesale London Agents:—Messrs. Barclay &amp; Sons, Farringdon-street; Edwards, St. Paul's Church-yard; Sutton &amp; Co., Bow Church-yard; Sangar, 151, Oxford-street; and Hannay &amp; Co., Oxford-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Under Royal Patronage</opener><head >PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES.</head><p >And Instant Relief and Rapid Cure of ASTHMA, and CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, COLDS, and all <lb/> DISORDERS of the BREATH and LUNGS, are insured by</p><p >D<hi rend="superscript">R</hi> LOCOCK'S <lb/> PULMONIC WAFERS</p><p >The extraordinary powers of this invaluable medicine are now proved by a mass of evidence and testimonials which must convince the most sceptical that for all disorders of the breath and lungs it is the most effectual remedy ever discovered.</p><p >Cure of Cough.</p><p >Glasgow, No. 2, Trongate, November 20, 1851.</p><p >Sir,—Miss JEMIMA LIVINGSTONE, aged 18 years, residing at the Calton Hill, Edinburgh, was for a long time afflicted with a very severe cough and irritation of the air passages. Both external and internal medicines were used, but with little effect, until, as a last resource, Dr. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS were tried, and we are happy to say with best results. We may mention, as further recommendation, that the young lady's father is a medical man, and administered the wafers to her himself.</p><p >Yours, &amp;c., J. R. &amp; M. ALLEN.</p><p >Another Cure of a Thirty-nine Years' Asthma.</p><p >17, Church-lane, Hull.</p><p >Sir,—I have suffered more than I can describe from the effects of an asthma, which has for years rendered my days irksome, and my nights sleepless. It was brought on by cold while accompanying the retreat of Sir John Moore. I have had the ablest advice, but nothing has given me one-tenth part of the benefit which your Dr. Locock's Wafers have.</p><p >(Signed) WALTER ERRINGTON; <lb/> Late Grenadler Guards,</p><p >Witness—Mr. J. C. Reinhardt, Chemist, Market-place, Hull.</p><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness' and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >THEY HAVE A PLEASANT TASTE. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box, or free by post for 1s. 3d., 3s., and 11s. 6d.</p><p >By DA SILVA &amp; CO., Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors. Also may be had</p><p >DR. LOCOCK'S FAMILY APERIENT AND ANTIBILIOUS WAFERS.</p><p >A mild and gentle Aperient and Stomach Medicine, having a most agreeable taste, and of great efficacy for regulating the Secretions and correcting the Action of the Stomach and Liver. Sold at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box. Also, <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS, <lb/> The best Medicine for Females. They have a pleasant taste. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box. Full directions are given with every box. BEWARE OF COUNTERFEITS.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p22"/><head >MESSRS. J. HOLMES &amp; CO., <lb/> SHAWL MANUFACTURERS,</head><p > BY APPOINTMENT, <lb/> TO <lb/> HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN &amp; ROYAL FAMILY, <lb/> Have constantly on Sale an immense variety of <lb/> FOREIGN SHAWLS, <lb/> Which, combined with their vast and superb Productions in HOME MANUFACTURES, have justly <lb/> rendered their magnificent Establishment the most eminent and attractive in the Metropolis.</p><p >171, 173, &amp; 175, REGENT STREET.</p><p >AN ADDITIONAL WARE-ROOM IS ARRANGED EXCLUSIVELY FOR THE DISPLAY OF <lb/> MANTLES.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >USE <lb/> KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Co.'s. <lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES.</p><p >Sold by every Draper, &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MECHI, <lb/> 4, Leadenhall Street, <lb/> LONDON.</head><p >THE BEST &amp; CHEAPEST <lb/> CUTLERY, DESKS, DRESSING CASES <lb/> WORK BOXES, TEA TRAYS <lb/> &amp; PAPIER MACHÉ ELEGANCIES.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Bagatelle &amp; Backgammon Boards.</hi></p><p >EVERY THING FOR THE TOILET &amp; WORK TABLE.</p><p >Pocket Books, Card Cases, Portfolios &amp; Inkstands</p><p >TRY MECHI'S MACIC STROP</p><p >Mechi's Patent Castellated Silver Wire <lb/> Tooth Brushes, 9d. each.</p><p >LADIES IVORY HANDLED PENKNIVES 1s.EACH</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p23"/><head >MOURNING:—COURT, FAMILY, &amp; COMPLIMENTARY.</head><p >THE PROPRIETOR OF <lb/> THE LONDON GENERAL MOURNING WAREHOUSE <lb/> Begs respectfully to remind Families whose bereavements compel them to adopt Mourning attire, that every article, of the very best description, requisite for a complete outfit of Mourning, may be had at this Establishment at a moment's notice.</p><div type="section"><head >ESTIMATES FOR SERVANTS' MOURNING</head><p >Affording a great saving to Families, are furnished; whilst the habitual attendance of experienced assistants (including dressmakers and milliners) enables them to suggest or supply every necessary for the occasion, and suited to any grade or condition of the community.</p></div><div type="section"><head >WIDOWS' AND FAMILY MOURNING</head><p >Is always kept made up, and a note, descriptive of the Mourning required, will insure its being sent forthwith either in Town or into the Country, and on the most Reasonable Terms.</p></div><div type="section"><p >W. C. JAY, 247-249, REGENT STREET.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NOVELTY IN SMOKING.</head><p >INDERWICK'S NEW SELF-ACTING PIPE TUBE, <lb/> By which excellent invention the Pipe may be kept burning during conversation without applying it to the lips, superseding the annoyance of frequent lighting; and it is also recommended to persons afflicted with Asthma or other respiratory disorders, as the irritation produced by inhaling the smoke is entirely a voided, it being conveyed to the lips without drawing the breath. Price Four Shillings, sent free to any part of the Kingdom, on receipt of Postage Stamps to that amount.</p><p >Wholesale and Retail at J. INDERWICK'S Meerschaum Pipe Warehouse, 58, Princes-street, Leicestersquare, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMEN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.—</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell>Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose</cell><cell>As dotted 1 to 1.</cell><cell>Inches.</cell><cell>Eighths.</cell></row><row><cell>From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required</cell><cell>As dotted 2 to 2.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows</cell><cell>As marked 3 to 3.</cell><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p24"/><head >Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'S REGISTERED PARDESSUS, <lb/> (6 &amp; 7 VIC. CAP. 65), <lb/> OF AMALGAMATED AUSTRALIAN &amp; LLAMA WOOLS.</head><p >The immense patronage bestowed upon this really economical and truly elegant <lb/> LIGHT SPRING AND SUMMER WALKING OVER-COAT, (which can also be worn without another), has had but few precedents. It is made of an extremely fine though durable cloth, which, from its peculiarly soft and silky nature, produces a sensation of the most complete ease and comfort, is now ready, and can be had ready for immediate use in all sizes and colours, at the very moderate charge of TWO GUINEAS.</p><p >In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s. Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94, REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PARASOLS.</head><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER <lb/> Beg respectfully to announce that they will be prepared this season to submit to the notice of the Nobility ad Gentry an assortment of <lb/> PARASOLS MADE OF CHINA CRAPE, a quantity of this material having been embroidered in China to their order, expressly for this purpose. They will be made of various colours, and will form a perfectly novel and elegant article, the rich effect of embroidered China Crape, as well as the known strength of the material, rendering it peculiarly adapted for a Parasol.</p><p >Their Stock will also comprise a variety of Parasols of Glaçé, Moirée, and French figure silks, as well as Alpaca, so much approved of for the country or sea-side.</p><list  type="simple"><item>140, Regent Street.</item><item>94, Fleet Street.</item><item>10, Royal Exchange.</item><item>75, Cheapside.</item></list><p ><hi rend="italics">March</hi> 1, 1852.</p></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="milos1"/><pb  xml:id="pia"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill29"><p>Miss Jellyby</p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piia"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill30"><p>The little old Lady.</p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="text"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><head >BLEAK HOUSE.</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER I. <lb/> IN CHANCERY.</head><p >LONDON. MichaeImas Term lately over, and the Lord Chancellor sitting in Lincoln's Inn Hall. Implacable November weather. As much mud in the streets, as if the waters had but newly retired from the face of the earth, and it would not be wonderful to meet a Megalosaurus, forty feet long or so, waddling like an elephantine lizard up Holborn-hill. Smoke lowering down from chimney-pots, making a soft black drizzle, with flakes of soot in it as big as full-grown snow-flakes—gone into mourning, one might imagine, for the death of the sun. Dogs, undistinguishable in mire. Horses, scarcely better; splashed to their very blinkers. Foot passengers, jostling one another's umbrellas, in a general infection of ill-temper, and losing their foot-hold at street-corners, where tens of thousands of other foot passengers have been slipping and sliding since the day broke (if the day ever broke), adding new deposits to the crust upon crust of mud, sticking at those points tenaciously to the pavement, and accumulating at compound interest.</p><p >Fog everywhere. Fog up the river, where it flows among green aits and meadows; fog down the river, where it rolls defiled among the tiers of shipping, and the waterside pollutions of a great (and dirty) city. Fog on the Essex marshes, fog on the Kentish heights. Fog creeping into the cabooses of collier-brigs; fog lying out on the yards, and hovering in the rigging of great ships; fog drooping on the gunwales of barges and small boats. Fog in the eyes and throats of ancient Greenwich pensioners, wheezing by the firesides of their wards; fog in the stem and bowl of the afternoon pipe of the wrathful skipper, down in his close cabin; fog cruelly pinching the toes and fingers of his shivering little 'prentice boy on deck. Chance people on the bridges peeping over the parapets into a nether sky of fog, with fog all round them, as if they were up in a balloon, and hanging in the misty clouds.</p><p >Gas looming through the fog in divers places in the streets, much as the sun may, from the spongey fields, be seen to loom by husbandman and ploughboy. Most of the shops lighted two hours before their time—as the gas seems to know, for it has a haggard and unwilling look.</p><p >The raw afternoon is rawest, and the dense fog is densest, and the
<pb xml:id="p2a"/>
muddy streets are muddiest, near that leaden-headed old obstruction, appropriate ornament for the threshold of a leaden-headed old corporation: Temple Bar. And hard by Temple Bar, in Lincoln's Inn Hall, at the very heart of the fog, sits the Lord High Chancellor in his High Court of Chancery.</p><p >Never can there come fog too thick, never can there come mud and mire too deep, to assort with the groping and floundering condition which this High Court of Chancery, most pestilent of hoary sinners, holds, this day, in the sight of heaven and earth.</p><p >On such an afternoon, if ever, the Lord High Chancellor ought to be sitting here—as here he is—with a foggy glory round his head, softly fenced in with crimson cloth and curtains, addressed by a large advocate with great whiskers, a little voice, and an interminable brief, and outwardly directing his contemplation to the lantern in the roof, where he can see nothing but fog. On such an afternoon, some score of members of the High Court of Chancery bar ought to be—as here they are—mistily engaged in one of the ten thousand stages of an endless cause, tripping one another up on slippery precedents, groping knee-deep in technicalities, running their goat-hair and horse-hair warded heads against walls of words, and making a pretence of equity with serious faces, as players might. On such an afternoon, the various solicitors in the cause, some two or three of whom have inherited it from their fathers, who made a fortune by it, ought to be—as are they not?—ranged in a line, in a long matted well (but you might look in vain for Truth at the bottom of it), between the registrar's red table and the silk gowns, with bills, cross-bills, answers, rejoinders, injunctions, affidavits, issues, references to masters, masters' reports, mountains of costly nonsense, piled before them. Well may the court be dim, with wasting candles here and there; well may the fog hang heavy in it, as if it would never get out; well may the stained glass windows lose their color, and admit no light of day into the place; well may the uninitiated from the streets, who peep in through the glass panes in the door, be deterred from entrance by its owlish aspect, and by the drawl languidly echoing to the roof from the padded dais where the Lord High Chancellor looks into the lantern that has no light in it, and where the attendant wigs are all stuck in a fog-bank! This is the Court of Chancery; which has its decaying houses and its blighted lands in every shire; which has its worn-out lunatic in every madhouse, and its dead in every churchyard; which has its ruined suitor, with his slipshod heels and threadbare dress, borrowing and begging through the round of every man's acquaintance; which gives to monied might the means abundantly of wearying out the right; which so exhausts finances, patience, courage, hope; so overthrows the brain and breaks the heart; that there is not an honorable man among its practitioners who would not give—who does not often give—the warning, “Suffer any wrong that can be done you, rather than come here!”</p><p >Who happen to be in the Lord Chancellor's court this murky afternoon besides the Lord Chancellor, the counsel in the cause, two or three counsel who are never in any cause, and the well of solicitors before mentioned? There is the registrar below the Judge, in wig and gown; and there are two or three maces, or petty-bags, or privy-purses, or whatever they may be, in legal court suits. These are all yawning; for no crumb of amusement ever falls from JARNDYCE AND JARNDYCE (the cause in hand), which was squeezed dry years upon years ago. The short-hand writers,
<pb xml:id="p3a"/>
the reporters of the court, and the reporters of the newspapers, invariably decamp with the rest of the regulars when Jarndyce and Jarndyce comes on. Their places are a blank. Standing on a seat at the side of the hall, the better to peer into the curtained sanctuary, is a little mad old woman in a squeezed bonnet, who is always in court, from its sitting to its rising, and always expecting some incomprehensible judgment to be given in her favor. Some say she really is, or was, a party to a suit; but no one knows for certain, because no one cares. She carries some small litter in a reticule which she calls her documents; principally consisting of paper matches and dry lavender. A sallow prisoner has come up, in custody, for the half-dozenth time, to make a personal application “to purge himself of his contempt;” which, being a solitary surviving executor who has fallen into a state of conglomeration about accounts of which it is not pretended that he had ever any knowledge, he is not at all likely ever to do. In the meantime his prospects in life are ended. Another ruined suitor, who periodically appears from Shropshire, and breaks out into efforts to address the Chancellor at the close of the day's business, and who can by no means be made to understand that the Chancellor is legally ignorant of his existence after making it desolate for a quarter of a century, plants himself in a good place and keeps an eye on the Judge, ready to call out “My lord!” in a voice of sonorous complaint, on the instant of his rising. A few lawyers' clerks and others who know this suitor by sight, linger, on the chance of his furnishing some fun, and enlivening the dismal weather a little.</p><p >Jarndyce and Jarndyce drones on. This scarecrow of a suit has, in course of time, become so complicated, that no man alive knows what it means. The parties to it understand it least; but it has been observed that no two Chancery lawyers can talk about it for five minutes, without coming to a total disagreement as to all the premises. Innumerable children have been born into the cause; innumerable young people have married into it; innumerable old people have died out of it. Scores of persons have deliriously found themselves made parties in Jarndyce and Jarndyce, without knowing how or why; whole families have inherited legendary hatreds with the suit. The little plaintiff or defendant, who was promised a new rocking-horse when Jarndyce and Jarndyce should be settled, has grown up, possessed himself of a real horse, and trotted away into the other world. Fair wards of court have faded into mothers and grandmothers; a long procession of Chancellors has come in and gone out; the legion of bills in the suit have been transformed into mere bills of mortality; there are not three Jarndyces left upon the earth perhaps, since old Tom Jarndyce in despair blew his brains out at a coffee-house in Chancery-lane; but Jarndyce and Jarndyce still drags its dreary length before the Court, perennially hopeless.</p><p >Jarndyce and Jarndyce has passed into a joke. That is the only good that has ever come of it. It has been death to many, but it is a joke in the profession. Every master in Chancery has had a reference out of it. Every Chancellor was “in it,” for somebody or other, when he was counsel at the bar. Good things have been said about it by blue-nosed, bulbous-shoed old benchers, in select port-wine committee after dinner in hall. Articled clerks have been in the habit of fleshing their legal wit upon it. The last Lord Chancellor handled it neatly, when, correcting Mr. Blowers the eminent silk gown who said that such a
<pb xml:id="p4a"/>
thing might happen when the sky rained potatoes, he observed, “or when we get through Jarndyce and Jarndyce, Mr. Blowers;”—a pleasantry that particularly tickled the maces, bags, and purses.</p><p >How many people out of the suit, Jarndyce and Jarndyce has stretched forth its unwholesome hand to spoil and corrupt, would be a very wide question. From the master, upon whose impaling files reams of dusty warrants in Jarndyce and Jarndyce have grimly writhed into many shapes; down to the copying clerk in the Six Clerks' Office, who has copied his tens of thousands of Chancery-folio-pages under that eternal heading; no man's nature has been made the better by it. In trickery, evasion, procrastination, spoliation, botheration, under false pretences of all sorts, there are influences that can never come to good. The very solicitors' boys who have kept the wretched suitors at bay, by protesting time out of mind that Mr. Chizzle, Mizzle, or otherwise, was particularly engaged and had appointments until dinner, may have got an extra moral twist and shuffle into themselves out of Jarndyce and Jarndyce. The receiver in the cause has acquired a goodly sum of money by it, but has acquired too a distrust of his own mother, and a contempt for his own kind. Chizzle, Mizzle, and otherwise, have lapsed into a habit of vaguely promising themselves that they will look into that outstanding little matter, and see what can be done for Drizzle—who was not well used—when Jarndyce and Jarndyce shall be got out of the office. Shirking and sharking, in all their many varieties, have been sown broadcast by the ill-fated cause; and even those who have contemplated its history from the outermost circle of such evil, have been insensibly tempted into a loose way of letting bad things alone to take their own bad course, and a loose belief that if the world go wrong, it was, in some off-hand manner, never meant to go right.</p><p >Thus, in the midst of the mud and at the heart of the fog, sits the Lord High Chancellor in his High Court of Chancery.</p><p >“Mr. Tangle,” says the Lord High Chancellor, latterly something restless under the eloquence of that learned gentleman.</p><p >“Mlud,” says Mr. Tangle. Mr. Tangle knows more of Jarndyce and Jarndyce than anybody. He is famous for it—supposed never to have read anything else since he left school.</p><p >“Have you nearly concluded your argument?”</p><p >“Mlud, no—variety of points—feel it my duty tsubmit—ludship,” is the reply that slides out of Mr. Tangle.</p><p >“Several members of the bar are still to be heard, I believe?” says the Chancellor, with a slight smile.</p><p >Eighteen of Mr. Tangle's learned friends, each armed with a little summary of eighteen hundred sheets, bob up like eighteen hammers in a piano-forte, make eighteen bows, and drop into their eighteen places of obscurity.</p><p >“We will proceed with the hearing on Wednesday fortnight,” says the Chancellor. For, the question at issue is only a question of costs, a mere bud on the forest tree of the parent suit, and really will come to a settlement one of these days.</p><p >The Chancellor rises; the bar rises; the prisoner is brought forward in a hurry; the man from Shropshire cries, “My lord!” Maces, bags, and purses, indignantly proclaim silence, and frown at the man from Shropshire.</p><pb  xml:id="p5a"/><p >“In reference,” proceeds the Chancellor, still on Jarndyce and Jarndyce, “to the young girl—”</p><p >“Begludship's pardon—boy,” says Mr. Tangle, prematurely.</p><p >“In reference,” proceeds the Chancellor, with extra distinctness, “to the young girl and boy, the two young people,”</p><p >(Mr. Tangle crushed.)</p><p >“Whom I directed to be in attendance to-day, and who are now in my private room, I will see them and satisfy myself as to the expediency of making the order for their residing with their uncle.”</p><p >Mr. Tangle on his legs again.</p><p >“Begludship's pardon—dead.”</p><p >“With their,” Chancellor looking through his double eye-glass at the papers on his desk, “grandfather.”</p><p >“Begludship's pardon—victim of rash action—brains.”</p><p >Suddenly a very little counsel, with a terrific bass voice, arises, fully inflated, in the back settlements of the fog, and says, “Will your lordship allow me? I appear for him. He is a cousin, several times removed. I am not at the moment prepared to inform the Court in what exact remove he is a cousin; but he <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a cousin.”</p><p >Leaving this address (delivered like a sepulchral message) ringing in the rafters of the roof, the very little counsel drops, and the fog knows him no more. Everybody looks for him. Nobody can see him.</p><p >“I will speak with both the young people,” says the Chancellor anew, “and satisfy myself on the subject of their residing with their cousin. I will mention the matter to-morrow morning when I take my seat.”</p><p >The Chancellor is about to bow to the bar, when the prisoner is presented. Nothing can possibly come of the prisoner's conglomeration, but his being sent back to prison; which is soon done. The man from Shropshire ventures another remonstrative “My lord!” but the Chancellor, being aware of him, has dexterously vanished. Everybody else quickly vanishes too. A battery of blue bags is loaded with heavy charges of papers and carried off by clerks; the little mad old woman marches off with her documents; the empty court is locked up. If all the injustice it has committed, and all the misery it has caused, could only be locked up with it, and the whole burnt away in a great funeral pyre,—why, so much the better for other parties than the parties in Jarndyce and Jarndyce!</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER II. <lb/> IN FASHION.</head><p >IT is but a glimpse of the world of fashion that we want on this same miry afternoon. It is not so unlike the Court of Chancery, but that we may pass from the one scene to the other, as the crow flies. Both the world of fashion and the Court of Chancery are things of precedent and usage; over-sleeping Rip Van Winkles, who have played at strange games through a deal of thundery weather; sleeping beauties, whom the Knight will
<pb xml:id="p6a"/>
wake one day, when all the stopped spits in the kitchen shall begin to turn prodigiously!</p><p >It is not a large world. Relatively even to this world of ours, which has its limits too (as your Highness shall find when you have made the tour of it, and are come to the brink of the void beyond), it is a very little speck. There is much good in it; there are many good and true people in it; it has its appointed place. But the evil of it is, that it is a world wrapped up in too much jeweller's cotton and fine wool, and cannot hear the rushing of the larger worlds, and cannot see them as they circle round the sun. It is a deadened world, and its growth is sometimes unhealthy for want of air.</p><p >My Lady Dedlock has returned to her house in town for a few days previous to her departure for Paris, where her ladyship intends to stay some weeks; after which her movements are uncertain. The fashionable intelligence says so, for the comfort of the Parisians, and it knows all fashionable things. To know things otherwise, were to be unfashionable. My Lady Dedlock has been down at what she calls, in familiar conversation, her “place” in Lincolnshire. The waters are out in Lincolnshire. An arch of the bridge in the park has been sapped and sopped away. The adjacent low-lying ground, for half a mile in breadth, is a stagnant river, with melancholy trees for islands in it, and a surface punctured all over, all day long, with falling rain. My Lady Dedlock's “place” has been extremely dreary. The weather, for many a day and night, has been so wet that the trees seem wet through, and the soft loppings and prunings of the woodman's axe can make no crash or crackle as they fall. The deer, looking soaked, leave quagmires, where they pass. The shot of a rifle loses its sharpness in the moist air, and its smoke moves in a tardy little cloud towards the green rise, coppice-topped, that makes a back-ground for the falling rain. The view from my Lady Dedlock's own windows is alternately a lead-colored view, and a view in Indian ink. The vases on the stone terrace in the foreground catch the rain all day; and the heavy drops fall, drip, drip, drip, upon the broad flagged pavement, called, from old time, the Ghost's Walk, all night. On Sundays, the little church in the park is mouldy; the oaken pulpit breaks out into a cold sweat; and there is a general smell and taste as of the ancient Dedlocks in their graves. My Lady Dedlock (who is childless), looking out in the early twilight from her boudoir at a keeper's lodge, and seeing the light of a fire upon the latticed panes, and smoke rising from the chimney, and a child, chased by a woman, running out into the rain to meet the shining figure of a wrapped-up man coming through the gate, has been put quite out of temper. My Lady Dedlock says she has been “bored to death.”</p><p >Therefore my Lady Dedlock has come away from the place in Lincolnshire, and has left it to the rain, and the crows, and the rabbits, and the deer, and the partridges and pheasants. The pictures of the Dedlocks past and gone have seemed to vanish into the damp walls in mere lowness of spirits, as the housekeeper has passed along the old rooms, shutting up the shutters. And when they will next come forth again, the fashionable intelligence—which, like the fiend, is omniscient of the past and present, but not the future—cannot yet undertake to say.</p><p >Sir Leicester Dedlock is only a baronet, but there is no mightier baronet than he. His family is as old as the hills, and infinitely more
<pb xml:id="p7a"/>
respectable. He has a general opinion that the world might get on without hills, but would be done up without Dedlocks. He would on the whole admit Nature to be a good idea (a little low, perhaps, when not enclosed with a park-fence), but an idea dependent for its execution on your great county families. He is a gentleman of strict conscience, disdainful of all littleness and meanness, and ready, on the shortest notice, to die any death you may please to mention rather than give occasion for the least impeachment of his integrity. He is an honorable, obstinate, truthful, high-spirited, intensely prejudiced, perfectly unreasonable man.</p><p >Sir Leicester is twenty years, full measure, older than my Lady. He will never see sixty-five again, nor perhaps sixty-six, nor yet sixty-seven. He has a twist of the gout now and then, and walks a little stiffly. He is of a worthy presence, with his light grey hair and whiskers, his fine shirt-frill, his pure white waistcoat, and his blue coat with bright buttons always buttoned. He is ceremonious, stately, most polite on every occasion to my Lady, and holds her personal attractions in the highest estimation. His gallantry to my Lady, which has never changed since he courted her, is the one little touch of romantic fancy in him.</p><p >Indeed, he married her for love. A whisper still goes about, that she had not even family; howbeit, Sir Leicester had so much family that perhaps he had enough, and could dispense with any more. But she had beauty, pride, ambition, insolent resolve, and sense enough to portion out a legion of fine ladies. Wealth and station, added to these, soon floated her upward; and for years, now, my Lady Dedlock has been at the centre of the fashionable intelligence, and at the top of the fashionable tree.</p><p >How Alexander wept when he had no more worlds to conquer, everybody knows—or has some reason to know by this time, the matter having been rather frequently mentioned. My Lady Dedlock, having conquered <hi rend="italics">her</hi> world, fell, not into the melting but rather into the freezing mood. An exhausted composure, a worn-out placidity, an equanimity of fatigue not to be ruffled by interest or satisfaction, are the trophies of her victory. She is perfectly well bred. If she could be translated to Heaven to-morrow, she might be expected to ascend without any rapture.</p><p >She has beauty still, and, if it be not in its heyday, it is not yet in its autumn. She has a fine face—originally of a character that would be rather called very pretty than handsome, but improved into classicality by the acquired expression of her fashionable state. Her figure is elegant, and has the effect of being tall. Not that she is so, but that “the most is made,” as the Honorable Bob Stables has frequently asserted upon oath, “of all her points.” The same authority observes, that she is perfectly got up; and remarks, in commendation of her hair especially, that she is the best-groomed woman in the whole stud.</p><p >With all her perfections on her head, my Lady Dedlock has come up from her place in Lincolnshire (hotly pursued by the fashionable intelligence), to pass a few days at her house in town previous to her departure for Paris, where her ladyship intends to stay some weeks, after which her movements are uncertain. And at her house in town, upon this muddy, murky afternoon, presents himself an old-fashioned old gentleman, attorney-at-law, and eke solicitor of the High Court of Chancery, who has the honor of acting as legal adviser of the Dedlocks, and has as many cast-iron boxes in his office with that name outside, as if the present
<pb xml:id="p8a"/>
baronet were the coin of the conjuror's trick, and were constantly being juggled through the whole set. Across the hall, and up the stairs, and along the passages, and through the rooms, which are very brilliant in the season and very dismal out of it—Fairy-land to visit, but a desert to live in—the old gentleman is conducted, by a Mercury in powder, to my Lady's presence.</p><p >The old gentleman is rusty to look at, but is reputed to have made good thrift out of aristocratic marriage settlements and aristocratic wills, and to be very rich. He is surrounded by a mysterious halo of family confidences; of which he is known to be the silent depository. There are noble Mausoleums rooted for centuries in retired glades of parks, among the growing timber and the fern, which perhaps hold fewer noble secrets than walk abroad among men, shut up in the breast of Mr. Tulkinghorn. He is of what is called the old school—a phrase generally meaning any school that seems never to have been young—and wears knee breeches tied with ribbons, and gaiters or stockings. One preculiarity of his black clothes, and of his black stockings, be they silk or worsted, is, that they never shine. Mute, close, irresponsive to any glancing light, his dress is like himself. He never converses, when not professionally consulted. He is found sometimes, speechless but quite at home, at corners of dinnertables in great country houses, and near doors of drawing-rooms, concerning which the fashionable intelligence is eloquent: where everybody knows him, and where half the Peerage stops to say “How do you do, Mr. Tulkinghorn?” He receives these salutations with gravity, and buries them along with the rest of his knowledge.</p><p >Sir Leicester Dedlock is with my Lady, and is happy to see Mr. Tulkinghorn. There is an air of prescription about him which is always agreeable to Sir Leicester; he receives it as a kind of tribute. He likes Mr. Tulkinghorn's dress; there is a kind of tribute in that too. It is eminently respectable, and likewise, in a general way, retainer-like. It expresses, as it were, the steward of the legal mysteries, the butler of the legal cellar, of the Dedlocks.</p><p >Has Mr. Tulkinghorn any idea of this himself? It may be so, or it may not; but there is this remarkable circumstance to be noted in everything associated with my Lady Dedlock as one of a class—as one of the leaders and representatives of her little world. She supposes herself to be an inscrutable Being, quite out of the reach and ken of ordinary mortals—seeing herself in her glass, where indeed she looks so. Yet, every dim little star revolving about her, from her maid to the manager of the Italian Opera, knows her weaknesses, prejudices, follies, haughtinesses, and caprices; and lives upon as accurate a calculation and as nice a measure of her moral nature, as her dress-maker takes of her physical proportions. Is a new dress, a new custom, a new singer, a new dancer, a new form of jewellery, a new dwarf or giant, a new chapel, a new anything, to be set up? There are deferential people, in a dozen callings, whom my Lady Dedlock suspects of nothing but prostration before her, who can tell you how to manage her as if she were a baby; who do nothing but nurse her all their lives; who, humbly affecting to follow with profound subservience, lead her and her whole troop after them; who, in hooking one, hook all and bear them off, as Lemuel Gulliver bore away the stately fleet of the majestic Lilliput. “If you want to address our people, sir,” say Blaze and Sparkle the jewellers—meaning by our people, Lady Dedlock and
<pb xml:id="p9a"/>
the rest—“you must remember that you are not dealing with the general public; you must hit our people in their weakest place, and their weakest place is such a place.” “To make this article go down, gentlemen,” say Sheen and Gloss the mercers, to their friends the manufacturers, “you must come to us, because we know where to have the fashionable people, and we can make it fashionable.” “If you want to get this print upon the tables of my high connexion, sir,” says Mr. Sladdery the librarian, “or if you want to get this dwarf or giant into the houses of my high connexion, sir, or if you want to secure to this entertainment the patronage of my high connexion, sir, you must leave it, if you please, to me; for I have been accustomed to study the leaders of my high connexion, sir; and I may tell you, without vanity, that I can turn them round my finger,”—in which Mr. Sladdery, who is an honest man, does not exaggerate at all.</p><p >Therefore, while Mr. Tulkinghorn may not know what is passing in the Dedlock mind at present, it is very possible that he may.</p><p >“My Lady's cause has been again before the Chancellor, has it, Mr. Tulkinghorn?” says Sir Leicester, giving him his hand.</p><p >“Yes. It has been on again to-day,” Mr. Tulkinghorn replies; making one of his quiet bows to my Lady who is on a sofa near the fire, shading her face with a hand-screen.</p><p >“It would be useless to ask,” says my Lady, with the dreariness of the place in Lincolnshire still upon her, “whether anything has been done.”</p><p >“Nothing that <hi rend="italics">you</hi> would call anything, has been done to-day,” replies Mr. Tulkinghorn.</p><p >“Nor ever will be,” says my Lady.</p><p >Sir Leicester has no objection to an interminable Chancery suit. It is a slow, expensive, British, constitutional kind of thing. To be sure, he has not a vital interest in the suit in question, her part in which was the only property my Lady brought him; and he has a shadowy impression that for his name—the name of Dedlock—to be in a cause, and not in the title of that cause, is a most ridiculous accident. But he regards the Court of Chancery, even if it should involve an occasional delay of justice and a trifling amount of confusion, as a something, devised in conjunction with a variety of other somethings, by the perfection of human wisdom, for the eternal settlement (humanly speaking) of every thing. And he is upon the whole of a fixed opinion, that to give the sanction of his countenance to any complaints respecting it, would be to encourage some person in the lower classes to rise up somewhere—like Wat Tyler.</p><p >“As a few fresh affidavits have been put upon the file,” says Mr. Tulkinghorn, “and as they are short, and as I proceed upon the troublesome principle of begging leave to possess my clients with any new proceedings in a cause;” cautious man, Mr. Tulkinghorn, taking no more responsibility than necessary; “and further, as I see you are going to Paris; I have brought them in my pocket.”</p><p >(Sir Leicester was going to Paris too, by-the-bye, but the delight of the fashionable intelligence was in his Lady.)</p><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn takes out his papers, asks permission to place them on a golden talisman of a table at my Lady's elbow, puts on his spectacles, and begins to read by the light of a shaded lamp.</p><p >“ ‘In Chancery. Between John Jarndyce—’ ”</p><p >My Lady interrupts, requesting him to miss as many of the formal horrors as he can.</p><pb  xml:id="p10a"/><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn glances over his spectacles, and begins again lower down. My Lady carelessly and scornfully abstracts her attention. Sir Leicester in a great chair looks at the fire, and appears to have a stately liking for the legal repetitions and prolixities, as ranging among the national bulwarks. It happens that the fire is hot, where my Lady sits; and that the hand-screen is more beautiful than useful, being priceless, but small. My Lady, changing her position, sees the papers on the table—looks at them nearer—looks at them nearer still—asks impulsively:</p><p >“Who copied that?”</p><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn stops short, surprised by my Lady's animation and her unusual tone.</p><p >“Is it what you people call law-hand?” she asks, looking full at him in her careless way again, and toying with her screen.</p><p >“Not quite. Probably”—Mr. Tulkinghorn examines it as he speaks—“the legal character it has, was acquired after the original hand was formed. Why do you ask?”</p><p >“Anything to vary this detestable monotony. O, go on, do!”</p><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn reads again. The heat is greater, my Lady screens her face. Sir Leicester doses, starts up suddenly, and cries “Eh? what do you say?”</p><p >“I say I am afraid,” says Mr. Tulkinghorn, who has risen hastily, “that Lady Dedlock is ill.”</p><p >“Faint,” my Lady murmurs, with white lips, “only that; but it is like the faintness of death. Don't speak to me. Ring, and take me to my room!”</p><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn retires into another chamber; bells ring, feet shuffle and patter, silence ensues. Mercury at last begs Mr. Tulkinghorn to return.</p><p >“Better now,” quoth Sir Leicester, motioning the lawyer to sit down and read to him alone. “I have been quite alarmed. I never knew my Lady swoon before. But the weather is extremely trying—and she really has been bored to death down at our place in Lincolnshire.”</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER III. <lb/> A PROGRESS.</head><p >I HAVE a great deal of difficulty in beginning to write my portion of these pages, for I know I am not clever. I always knew that. I can remember, when I was a very little girl indeed, I used to say to my doll, when we were alone together, “Now, Dolly, I am not clever, you know very well, and you must be patient with me, like a dear!” And so she used to sit propped up in a great arm-chair, with her beautiful complexion and rosy lips, staring at me—or not so much at me, I think, as at nothing—while I busily stitched away, and told her every one of my secrets.</p><p >My dear old doll! I was such a shy little thing that I seldom dared to open my lips, and never dared to open my heart, to anybody else. It almost makes me cry to think what a relief it used to be to me, when I
<pb xml:id="p11a"/>
came home from school of a day, to run upstairs to my room, and say, “O you dear faithful Dolly, I knew you would be expecting me!” and then to sit down on the floor, leaning on the elbow of her great chair, and tell her all I had noticed since we parted. I had always rather a noticing way—not a quick way, O no!—a silent way of noticing what passed before me, and thinking I should like to understand it better. I have not by any means a quick understanding. When I love a person very tenderly indeed, it seems to brighten. But even that may be my vanity.</p><p >I was brought up, from my earliest remembrance—like some of the princesses in the fairy stories, only I was not charming—by my godmother. At least I only knew her as such. She was a good, good woman! She went to church three times every Sunday, and to morning prayers on Wednesdays and Fridays, and to lectures whenever there were lectures; and never missed. She was handsome; and if she had ever smiled, would have been (I used to think) like an angel—but she never smiled. She was always grave, and strict. She was so very good herself, I thought, that the badness of other people made her frown all her life. I felt so different from her, even making every allowance for the differences between a child and a woman; I felt so poor, so trifling, and so far off; that I never could be unrestrained with her—no, could never even love her as I wished. It made me very sorry to consider how good she was, and how unworthy of her I was; and I used ardently to hope that I might have a better heart; and I talked it over very often with the dear old doll; but I never loved my godmother as I ought to have loved her, and as I felt I must have loved her if I had been a better girl.</p><p >This made me, I dare say, more timid and retiring than I naturally was, and cast me upon Dolly as the only friend with whom I felt at ease. But something happened when I was still quite a little thing, that helped it very much.</p><p >I had never heard my mama spoken of. I had never heard of my papa either, but I felt more interested about my mama. I had never worn a black frock, that I could recollect. I had never been shown my mama's grave. I had never been told where it was. Yet I had never been taught to pray for any relation but my godmother. I had more than once approached this subject of my thoughts with Mrs. Rachael, our only servant, who took my light away when I was in bed (another very good woman, but austere to me), and she had only said, “Esther, good night!” and gone away and left me.</p><p >Although there were seven girls at the neighbouring school where I was a day boarder, and although they called me little Esther Summerson, I knew none of them at home. All of them were older than I, to be sure (I was the youngest there by a good deal), but there seemed to be some other separation between us besides that, and besides their being far more clever than I was, and knowing much more than I did. One of them, in the first week of my going to the school (I remember it very well), invited me home to a little party, to my great joy. But my godmother wrote a stiff letter declining for me, and I never went. I never went out at all.</p><p >It was my birthday. There were holidays at school on other birthdays—none on mine. There were rejoicings at home on other birthdays, as I knew from what I heard the girls relate to one another—there were none
<pb xml:id="p12a"/>
on mine. My birthday was the most melancholy day at home, in the whole year.</p><p >I have mentioned, that, unless my vanity should deceive me (as I know it may, for I may be very vain, without suspecting it—though indeed I don't), my comprehension is quickened when my affection is. My disposition is very affectionate; and perhaps I might still feel such a wound, if such a wound could be received more than once, with the quickness of that birthday.</p><p >Dinner was over, and my godmother and I were sitting at the table before the fire. The clock ticked, the fire clicked; not another sound had been heard in the room, or in the house, for I don't know how long. I happened to look timidly up from my stitching, across the table, at my godmother, and I saw in her face, looking gloomily at me, “It would have been far better, little Esther, that you had had no birthday; that you had never been born!”</p><p >I broke out crying and sobbing, and I said, “O, dear godmother, tell me, pray do tell me, did mama die on my birthday?”</p><p >“No,” she returned. “Ask me no more, child!”</p><p >“O, do pray tell me something of her. Do now, at last, dear godmother, if you please! What did I do to her? How did I lose her? Why am I so different from other children, and why is it my fault, dear godmother? No, no, no, don't go away. O, speak to me!”</p><p >I was in a kind of fright beyond my grief; and I had caught hold of her dress, and was kneeling to her. She had been saying all the while, “Let me go!” But now she stood still.</p><p >Her darkened face had such power over me, that it stopped me in the midst of my vehemence. I put up my trembling little hand to clasp hers, or to beg her pardon with what earnestness I might, but withdrew it as she looked at me, and laid it on my fluttering heart. She raised me, sat in her chair, and standing me before her, said, slowly, in a cold, low voice—I see her knitted brow, and pointed finger:</p><p >“Your mother, Esther, is your disgrace, and you were hers. The time will come—and soon enough—when you will understand this better, and will feel it too, as no one save a woman can. I have forgiven her;” but her face did not relent; “the wrong she did to me, and I say no more of it, though it was greater than you will ever know—than any one will ever know, but I, the sufferer. For yourself, unfortunate girl, orphaned and degraded from the first of these evil anniversaries, pray daily that the sins of others be not visited upon your head, according to what is written. Forget your mother, and leave all other people to forget her who will do her unhappy child that greatest kindness. Now, go!”</p><p >She checked me, however, as I was about to depart from her—so frozen as I was!—and added this:</p><p >“Submission, self-denial, diligent work, are the preparations for a life begun with such a shadow on it. You are different from other children, Esther, because you were not born, like them, in common sinfulness and wrath. You are set apart.”</p><p >I went up to my room, and crept to bed, and laid my doll's cheek against mine wet with tears; and holding that solitary friend upon my bosom, cried myself to sleep. Imperfect as my understanding of my sorrow was, I knew that I had brought no joy, at any time, to anybody's heart, and that I was to no one upon earth what Dolly was to me.</p><pb  xml:id="p13a"/><p >Dear, dear, to think how much time we passed alone together afterwards, and how often I repeated to the doll the story of my birthday, and confided to her that I would try, as hard as ever I could, to repair the fault I had been born with (of which I confusedly felt guilty and yet innocent), and would strive as I grew up to be industrious, contented and kind-hearted, and to do some good to some one, and win some love to myself if I could. I hope it is not self-indulgent to shed these tears as I think of it. I am very thankful, I am very cheerful, but I cannot quite help their coming to my eyes.</p><p >There! I have wiped them away now, and can go on again properly.</p><p >I felt the distance between my godmother and myself so much more after the birthday, and felt so sensible of filling a place in her house which ought to have been empty, that I found her more difficult of approach, though I was fervently grateful to her in my heart, than ever. I felt in the same way towards my school companions; I felt in the same way towards Mrs. Rachael, who was a widow; and O, towards her daughter, of whom she was proud, who came to see her once a fortnight! I was very retired and quiet, and tried to be very diligent.</p><p >One sunny afternoon, when I had come home from school with my books and portfolio, watching my long shadow at my side, and as I was gliding up stairs to my room as usual, my godmother looked out of the parlor door, and called me back. Sitting with her, I found—which was very unusual indeed—a stranger. A portly important-looking gentleman, dressed all in black, with a white cravat, large gold watch seals, a pair of gold eyeglasses, and a large seal-ring upon his little finger.</p><p >“This,” said my godmother in an under tone, “is the child.” Then she said, in her naturally stern way of speaking, “This is Esther, sir.”</p><p >The gentleman put up his eye-glasses to look at me, and said, “Come here, my dear!” He shook hands with me, and asked me to take off my bonnet—looking at me all the while. When I had complied, he said, “Ah!” and afterwards “Yes!” And then, taking off his eye-glasses and folding them in a red case, and leaning back in his arm-chair, turning the case about in his two hands he gave my godmother a nod. Upon that, my godmother said, “You may go upstairs, Esther!” and I made him my curtsey and left him.</p><p >It must have been two years afterwards, and I was almost fourteen, when one dreadful night my godmother and I sat at the fireside. I was reading aloud, and she was listening. I had come down at nine o'clock, as I always did, to read the Bible to her; and was reading, from St. John, how our Saviour stooped down, writing with his finger in the dust, when they brought the sinful woman to him.</p><p >“‘So when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself and said unto them, He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her!’”</p><p >I was stopped by my godmother's rising, putting her hand to her head, and crying out, in an awful voice, from quite another part of the book:</p><p >“‘Watch ye therefore! lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping. And what I say unto you, I say unto all, Watch!’”</p><p >In an instant, while she stood before me repeating these words, she fell down on the floor. I had no need to cry out; her voice had sounded through the house, and been heard in the street.</p><p >She was laid upon her bed. For more than a week she lay there, little
<pb xml:id="p14a"/>
altered outwardly; with her old handsome resolute frown that I so well knew, carved upon her face. Many and many a time, in the day and in the night, with my head upon the pillow by her that my whispers might be plainer to her, I kissed her, thanked her, prayed for her, asked her for her blessing and forgiveness, entreated her to give me the least sign that she knew or heard me. No, no, no. Her face was immoveable. To the very last, and even afterwards, her frown remained unsoftened.</p><p >On the day after my poor good godmother was buried, the gentleman in black with the white neckcloth reappeared. I was sent for by Mrs. Rachael, and found him in the same place, as if he had never gone away.</p><p >“My name is Kenge,” he said; “you may remember it, my child; Kenge and Carboy, Lincoln's Inn.”</p><p >I replied, that I remembered to have seen him once before.</p><p >“Pray be seated—here, near me. Don't distress yourself; it's of no use. Mrs. Rachael, I needn't inform you who were acquainted with the late Miss Barbary's affairs, that her means die with her; and that this young lady, now her aunt is dead—”</p><p >“My aunt, sir!”</p><p >“It really is of no use carrying on a deception when no object is to be gained by it,” said Mr. Kenge, smoothly. “Aunt in fact, though not in law. Don't distress yourself! Don't weep! Don't tremble! Mrs. Rachael, our young friend has no doubt heard of—the—a—Jarndyce and Jarndyce.”</p><p >“Never,” said Mrs. Rachael.</p><p >“Is it possible,” pursued Mr Kenge, putting up his eye-glasses, “that our young friend—I <hi rend="italics">beg</hi> you won't distress yourself!—never heard of Jarndyce and Jarndyce!”</p><p >I shook my head, wondering even what it was.</p><p >“Not of Jarndyce and Jarndyce?” said Mr. Kenge, looking over his glasses at me, and softly turning the case about and about, as if he were petting something. “Not of one of the greatest Chancery suits known? Not of Jarndyce and Jarndyce—the—a—in itself a monument of Chancery practice? In which (I would say) every difficulty, every contingency, every masterly fiction, every form of procedure known in that court, is represented over and over again? It is a cause that could not exist, out of this free and great country. I should say that the aggregate of costs in Jarndyce and Jarndyce, Mrs. Rachael;” I was afraid he addressed himself to her, because I appeared inattentive; “amounts at the present hour to from SIX-ty to SEVEN-ty THOUSAND POUNDS!” said Mr. Kenge, leaning back in his chair.</p><p >I felt very ignorant, but what could I do? I was so entirely unacquainted with the subject, that I understood nothing about it even then.</p><p >“And she really never heard of the cause!” said Mr. Kenge. “Surprising!”</p><p >“Miss Barbary, sir,” returned Mrs. Rachael, “who is now among the Seraphim—”</p><p >(“I hope so, I am sure,” said Mr. Kenge, politely.)</p><p >“—Wished Esther only to know what would be serviceable to her. And she knows, from any teaching she has had here, nothing more.”</p><p >“Well!” said Mr. Kenge. “Upon the whole, very proper. Now to the point,” addressing me. “Miss Barbary, your sole relation (in fact,
<pb xml:id="p15a"/>
that is; for I am bound to observe that in law you had none), being deceased, and it naturally not being to be expected that Mrs. Rachael—”</p><p >“O dear no!” said Mrs. Rachael, quickly.</p><p >“Quite so,” assented Mr. Kenge;—“that Mrs. Rachael should charge herself with your maintenance and support (I beg you won't distress yourself), you are in a position to receive the renewal of an offer which I was instructed to make to Miss Barbary some two years ago, and which, though rejected then, was understood to be renewable under the lamentable circumstances that have since occurred. Now, if I avow that I represent, in Jarndyce and Jarndyce, and otherwise, a highly humane, but at the same time singular man, shall I compromise myself by any stretch of my professional caution?” said Mr. Kenge, leaning back in his chair again, and looking calmly at us both.</p><p >He appeared to enjoy beyond everything the sound of his own voice. I couldn't wonder at that, for it was mellow and full, and gave great importance to every word he uttered. He listened to himself with obvious satisfaction, and sometimes gently beat time to his own music with his head, or rounded a sentence with his hand. I was very much impressed by him—even then, before I knew that he formed himself on the model of a great lord who was his client, and that he was generally called Conversation Kenge.</p><p >“Mr. Jarndyce,” he pursued, “being aware of the—I would say, desolate—position of our young friend, offers to place her at a first-rate establishment; where her education shall be completed, where her comfort shall be secured, where her reasonable wants shall be anticipated, where she shall be eminently qualified to discharge her duty in that station of life unto which it has pleased—shall I say Providence?—to call her.”</p><p >My heart was filled so full, both by what he said, and by his affecting manner of saying it, that I was not able to speak, though I tried.</p><p >“Mr. Jarndyce,” he went on, “makes no condition, beyond expressing his expectation, that our young friend will not at any time remove herself from the establishment in question without his knowledge and concurrence. That she will faithfully apply herself to the acquisition of those accomplishments, upon the exercise of which she will be ultimately dependent. That she will tread in the paths of virtue and honor, and—the—a—so forth.”</p><p >I was still less able to speak, than before.</p><p >“Now, what does our young friend say?” proceeded Mr. Kenge. “Take time, take time! I pause for her reply. But take time!”</p><p >What the destitute subject of such an offer tried to say, I need not repeat. What she did say, I could more easily tell, if it were worth the telling. What she felt, and will feel to her dying hour, I could never relate.</p><p >This interview took place at Windsor, where I had passed (as far as I knew) my whole life. On that day week, amply provided with all necessaries, I left it, inside the stage-coach, for Reading.</p><p >Mrs. Rachael was too good to feel any emotion at parting, but I was not so good, and wept bitterly. I thought that I ought to have known her better after so many years, and ought to have made myself enough of a favorite with her to make her sorry then. When she gave me one cold parting kiss upon my forehead, like a thaw-drop from the stone
<pb xml:id="p16a"/>
porch—it was a very frosty day—I felt so miserable and self-reproachful, that I clung to her and told her it was my fault, I knew, that she could say good bye so easily!</p><p >“No, Esther!” she returned. “It is your misfortune!”</p><p >The coach was at the little lawn gate—we had not come out until we heard the wheels—and thus I left her, with a sorrowful heart. She went in before my boxes were lifted to the coach-roof, and shut the door. As long as I could see the house, I looked back at it from the window, through my tears. My godmother had left Mrs. Rachael all the little property she possessed; and there was to be a sale; and an old hearth-rug with roses on it, which always seemed to me the first thing in the world I had ever seen, was hanging outside in the frost and snow. A day or two before, I had wrapped the dear old doll in her own shawl, and quietly laid her—I am half ashamed to tell it—in the gardenearth, under the tree that shaded my old window. I had no companion left but my bird, and him I carried with me in his cage.</p><p >When the house was out of sight, I sat, with my bird-cage in the straw at my feet, forward on the low seat, to look out of the high window; watching the frosty trees, that were like beautiful pieces of spar; and the fields all smooth and white with last night's snow; and the sun, so red but yielding so little heat; and the ice, dark like metal, where the skaters and sliders had brushed the snow away. There was a gentleman in the coach who sat on the opposite seat, and looked very large in a quantity of wrappings; but he sat gazing out of the other window, and took no notice of me.</p><p >I thought of my dead godmother; of the night when I read to her; of her frowning so fixedly and sternly in her bed; of the strange place I was going to; of the people I should find there, and what they would be like, and what they would say to me; when a voice in the coach gave me a terrible start.</p><p >It said, “What the de-vil are you crying for?”</p><p >I was so frightened that I lost my voice, and could only answer in a whisper. “Me, sir?” For of course I knew it must have been the gentleman in the quantity of wrappings, though he was still looking out of his window.</p><p >“Yes, you,” he said, turning round.</p><p >“I didn't know I was crying, sir,” I faltered.</p><p >“But you are!” said the gentleman. “Look here!” He came quite opposite to me from the other corner of the coach, brushed one of his large furry cuffs across my eyes (but without hurting me), and showed me that it was wet.</p><p >“There! Now you know you are,” he said. “Don't you?”</p><p >“Yes, sir,” I said.</p><p >“And what are you crying for?” said the gentleman. “Don't you want to go there?”</p><p >“Where, sir?”</p><p >“Where? Why, wherever you are going,” said the gentleman.</p><p >“I am very glad to go there, sir,” I answered.</p><p >“Well, then! Look glad!” said the gentleman.</p><p >I thought he was very strange; or at least that what I could see of him was very strange, for he was wrapped up to the chin, and his face was almost hidden in a fur cap, with broad fur straps at the side
<pb xml:id="p17a"/>
of his head, fastened under his chin; but I was composed again, and not afraid of him. So I told him that I thought I must have been crying, because of my godmother's death, and because of Mrs. Rachael's not being sorry to part with me.</p><p >“Con-found Mrs. Rachael!” said the gentleman. “Let her fly away in a high wind on a broomstick!”</p><p >I began to be really afraid of him now, and looked at him with the greatest astonishment. But I thought that he had pleasant eyes, although he kept on muttering to himself in an angry manner, and calling Mrs. Rachael names.</p><p >After a little while, he opened his outer wrapper, which appeared to me large enough to wrap up the whole coach, and put his arm down into a deep pocket in the side.</p><p >“Now, look here!” he said. “In this paper,” which was nicely folded, “is a piece of the best plum-cake that can be got for money—sugar on the outside an inch thick, like fat on mutton chops. Here's a little pie (a gem this is, both for size and quality), made in France. And what do you suppose it's made of? Livers of fat geese. There's a pie! Now let's see you eat 'em.”</p><p >“Thank you, sir,” I replied, “thank you very much indeed, but I hope you won't be offended; they are too rich for me.”</p><p >“Floored again!” said the gentleman, which I didn't at all understand; and threw them both out of window.</p><p >He did not speak to me any more, until he got out of the coach a little way short of Reading, when he advised me to be a good girl, and to be studious; and shook hands with me. I must say I was relieved by his departure. We left him at a milestone. I often walked past it afterwards, and never, for a long time, without thinking of him, and half expecting to meet him. But I never did; and so, as time went on, he passed out of my mind.</p><p >When the coach stopped, a very neat lady looked up at the window, and said:</p><p >“Miss Donny.”</p><p >“No, ma'am, Esther Summerson.”</p><p >“That is quite right,” said the lady, “Miss Donny.”</p><p >I now understood that she introduced herself by that name, and begged Miss Donny's pardon for my mistake, and pointed out my boxes at her request. Under the direction of a very neat maid, they were put outside a very small green carriage; and then Miss Donny, the maid, and I, got inside, and were driven away.</p><p >“Everything is ready for you, Esther,” said Miss Donny; “and the scheme of your pursuits has been arranged in exact accordance with the wishes of your guardian, Mr. Jarndyce.”</p><p >“Of — did you say, ma'am?”</p><p >“Of your guardian, Mr. Jarndyce,” said Miss Donny.</p><p >I was so bewildered that Miss Donny thought the cold had been too severe for me, and lent me her smelling-bottle.</p><p >“Do you know my—guardian, Mr. Jarndyce, ma'am?” I asked after a good deal of hesitation.</p><p >“Not personally, Esther,” said Miss Donny; “merely through his solicitors, Messrs. Kenge and Carboy, of London. A very superior gentleman, Mr. Kenge. Truly eloquent indeed. Some of his periods quite majestic!”</p><pb  xml:id="p18a"/><p >I felt this to be very true, but was too confused to attend to it. Our speedy arrival at our destination, before I had time to recover myself, increased my confusion; and I never shall forget the uncertain and unreal air of every thing at Greenleaf (Miss Donuy's house), that afternoon!</p><p >But I soon became used to it. I was so adapted to the routine of Greenleaf before long, that I seemed to have been there a great while; and almost to have dreamed, rather than to have really lived, my old life at my godmother's. Nothing could be more precise, exact, and orderly, than Greenleaf. There was a time for everything all round the dial of the clock, and everything was done at its appointed moment.</p><p >We were twelve boarders, and there were two Miss Donnys, twins. It was understood that I would have to depend, by-and-by, on my qualifications as a governess; and I was not only instructed in everything that was taught at Greenleaf, but was very soon engaged in helping to instruct others. Although I was treated in every other respect like the rest of the school, this single difference was made in my case from the first. As I began to know more, I taught more, and so in course of time I had plenty to do, which I was very fond of doing, because it made the dear girls fond of me. At last, whenever a new pupil came who was a little downcast and unhappy, she was so sure—indeed I don't know why—to make a friend of me, that all new comers were confided to my care. They said I was so gentle; but I am sure <hi rend="italics">they</hi> were! I often thought of the resolution I had made on my birthday, to try to be industrious, contented, and true-hearted, and to do some good to some one, and win some love if I could; and indeed, indeed, I felt almost ashamed to have done so little and have won so much.</p><p >I passed at Greenleaf six happy, quiet years. I never saw in any face there, thank Heaven, on my birthday, that it would have been better if I had never been born. When the day came round, it brought me so many tokens of affectionate remembrance that my room was beautiful with them from New Year's Day to Christmas.</p><p >In those six years I had never been away, except on visits at holiday time in the neighbourhood. After the first six months or so, I had taken Miss Donny's advice in reference to the propriety of writing to Mr. Kenge, to say that I was happy and grateful; and with her approval I had written such a letter. I had received a formal answer acknowledging its receipt, and saying, “We note the contents thereof, which shall be duly communicated to our client.” After that, I sometimes heard Miss Donny and her sister mention how regularly my accounts were paid; and about twice a year I ventured to write a similar letter. I always received by return of post exactly the same answer, in the same round hand; with the signature of Kenge and Carboy in another writing, which I supposed to be Mr. Kenge's.</p><p >It seems so curious to me to be obliged to write all this about myself! As if this narrative were the narrative of <hi rend="italics">my</hi> life! But my little body will soon fall into the back-ground now.</p><p >Six quiet years (I find I am saying it for the second time) I had passed at Greenleaf, seeing in those around me, as it might be in a looking-glass, every stage of my own growth and change there, when, one November morning, I received this letter. I omit the date.</p><pb  xml:id="p19a"/><quote><floatingText><body ><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="letter"><opener >
<dateline>Old Square, Lincoln's Inn.</dateline>
<salute>Madam,</salute>
</opener><p >Jarndyce and Jarndyce.</p><p >Our clt Mr. Jarndyce being abt to rece into his house, under an Order of the Ct of Chy, a Ward of the Ct in this cause, for whom he wishes to secure an elgble compu, directs us to inform you that he will be glad of your serces in the afsd capacity.</p><p >We have arrngd for your being forded, carriage free, p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> eight o'clock coach from Reading, on Monday morning next, to White Horse Cellar, Piccadilly, London, where one of our clks will be in waiting to convey you to our offe as above.</p><closer >
<salute>We are, Madam, <lb/> Your obed<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> serv<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>,</salute>
<signed>Kenge and Carboy.</signed>
<signed>Miss Esther Summerson.</signed>
</closer></div></body></floatingText></quote><p >O, never, never, never shall I forget the emotion this letter caused in the house! It was so tender in them to care so much for me; it was so gracious in that Father who had not forgotten me, to have made my orphan way so smooth and easy, and to have inclined so many youthful natures towards me; that I could hardly bear it. Not that I would have had them less sorry—I am afraid not; but the pleasure of it, and the pain of it, and the pride and joy of it, and the humble regret of it, were so blended, that my heart seemed almost breaking while it was full of rapture.</p><p >The letter gave me only five days' notice of my removal. When every minute added to the proofs of love and kindness that were given me in those five days; and when at last the morning came, and when they took me through all the rooms that I might see them for the last time; and when some cried, “Esther, dear, say good-bye to me here, at my bedside, where you first spoke so kindly to me!” and when others asked me only to write their names, “With Esther's love;” and when they all surrounded me with their parting presents, and clung to me weeping, and cried, “What shall we do when dear, dear Esther's gone!” and when I tried to tell them how forbearing, and how good they had all been to me, and how I blessed, and thanked them every one; what a heart I had!</p><p >And when the two Miss Donnys grieved as much to part with me, as the least among them; and when the maids said, “Bless you, miss, wherever you go!” and when the ugly lame old gardener, who I thought
<pb xml:id="p20a"/>
had hardly noticed me in all those years, came panting after the coach to give me a little nosegay of geraniums, and told me I had been the light of his eyes—indeed the old man said so!—what a heart I had then!</p><p >And could I help it, if with all this, and the coming to the little school, and the unexpected sight of the poor children outside waving their hats and bonnets to me, and of a grey-haired gentleman and lady, whose daughter I had helped to teach and at whose house I had visited (who were said to be the proudest people in all that country), caring for nothing but calling out, “Good bye, Esther. May you be very happy!”—could I help it if I was quite bowed down in the coach by myself, and said “O, I am so thankful, I am so thankful!” many times over!</p><p >But of course I soon considered that I must not take tears where I was going, after all that had been done for me. Therefore, of course, I made myself sob less, and persuaded myself to be quiet by saying very often, “Esther, now, you really must! This <hi rend="italics">will not</hi> do!” I cheered myself up pretty well at last, though I am afraid I was longer about it than I ought to have been; and when I had cooled my eyes with lavender water, it was time to watch for London.</p><p >I was quite persuaded that we were there, when we were ten miles off; and when we really were there, that we should never get there. However, when we began to jolt upon a stone pavement, and particularly when every other conveyance seemed to be running into us and we seemed to be running into every other conveyance, I began to believe that we really were approaching the end of our journey. Very soon afterwards we stopped.</p><p >A young gentleman who had inked himself by accident, addressed me from the pavement, and said “I am from Kenge and Carboy's, miss, of Lincoln's Inn.”</p><p >“If you please, sir,” said I.</p><p >He was very obliging; and as he handed me into a fly, after superintending the removal of my boxes, I asked him whether there was a great fire anywhere? For the streets were so full of dense brown smoke that scarcely anything was to be seen.</p><p >“O dear no, miss,” he said. “This is a London particular.”</p><p >I had never heard of such a thing.</p><p >“A fog, miss,” said the young gentleman.</p><p >“O indeed!” said I.</p><p >We drove slowly through the dirtiest and darkest streets that ever were seen in the world (I thought), and in such a distracting state of confusion that I wondered how the people kept their senses, until we passed into sudden quietude under an old gateway, and drove on through a silent square until we came to an odd nook in a corner, where there was an entrance up a steep broad flight of stairs, like an entrance to a church. And there really was a churchyard, outside under some cloisters, for I saw the gravestones from the staircase window.</p><p >This was Kenge and Carboy's. The young gentleman showed me through an outer office into Mr. Kenge's room—there was no one in it—and politely put an arm-chair for me by the fire. He then called my attention to a little looking-glass, hanging from a nail on one side of the chimney-piece.</p><p >“In case you should wish to look at yourself, miss, after the journey, as you're going before the Chancellor. Not that it's requisite, I am sure,” said the young gentleman civilly.</p><pb  xml:id="p21a"/><p >“Going before the Chancellor?” I said, startled for a moment.</p><p >“Only a matter of form, miss,” returned the young gentleman.</p><p >“Mr. Kenge is in court now. He left his compliments, and would you partake of some refreshment;” there were biscuits and a decanter of wine on a small table; “and look over the paper;” which the young gentleman gave me as he spoke. He then stirred the fire, and left me.</p><p >Everything was so strange—the stranger for its being night in the day-time, and the candles burning with a white flame, and looking raw and cold—that I read the words in the newspaper without knowing what they meant, and found myself reading the same words repeatedly. As it was of no use going on in that way, I put the paper down, took a peep at my bonnet in the glass to see if it was neat, and looked at the room which was not half lighted, and at the shabby dusty tables, and at the piles of writings, and at a bookcase full of the most inexpressive-looking books that ever had anything to say for themselves. Then I went on, thinking, thinking, thinking; and the fire went on, burning, burning, burning; and the candles went on flickering and guttering, and there were no snuffers—until the young gentleman by-and-by brought a very dirty pair; for two hours.</p><p >At last Mr. Kenge came. <hi rend="italics">He</hi> was not altered; but he was surprised to see how altered I was, and appeared quite pleased. “As you are going to be the companion of the young lady who is now in the Chancellor's private room, Miss Summerson,” he said, “we thought it well that you should be in attendance also. You will not be discomposed by the Lord Chancellor, I dare say?”</p><p >“No, sir,” I said, “I don't think I shall.” Really not seeing, on consideration, why I should be.</p><p >So Mr. Kenge gave me his arm, and we went round the corner, under a colonnade, and in at a side door. And so we came, along a passage, into a comfortable sort of room, where a young lady and a young gentleman were standing near a great, loud-roaring fire. A screen was interposed between them and it, and they were leaning on the screen, talking.</p><p >They both looked up when I came in, and I saw in the young lady, with the fire shining upon her, such a beautiful girl! With such rich golden hair, such soft blue eyes, and such a bright, innocent, trusting face!</p><p >“Miss Ada,” said Mr. Kenge, “this is Miss Summerson.”</p><p >She came to meet me with a smile of welcome and her hand extended, but seemed to change her mind in a moment, and kissed me. In short, she had such a natural, captivating, winning manner, that in a few minutes we were sitting in the window-seat, with the light of the fire upon us, talking together, as free and happy as could be.</p><p >What a load off my mind! It was so delightful to know that she could confide in me, and like me! It was so good of her, and so encouraging to me!</p><p >The young gentleman was her distant cousin, she told me, and his name Richard Carstone. He was a handsome youth, with an ingenuous face, and a most engaging laugh; and after she had called him up to where we sat, he stood by us, in the light of the fire too, talking gaily, like a light-hearted boy. He was very young; not more than nineteen then, if quite so much, but nearly two years older than she was. They were both orphans, and (what was very unexpected and curious to me) had never met before that day. Our all three coming together for the first
<pb xml:id="p22a"/>
time, in such an unusual place, was a thing to talk about; and we talked about it; and the fire, which had left off roaring, winked its red eyes at us—as Richard said—like a drowsy old Chancery lion.</p><p >We conversed in a low tone, because a full-dressed gentleman in a bag wig frequently came in and out, and when he did so, we could hear a drawling sound in the distance, which he said was one of the counsel in our case addressing the Lord Chancellor. He told Mr. Kenge that the Chancellor would be up in five minutes; and presently we heard a bustle, and a tread of feet, and Mr. Kenge said that the Court had risen, and his lordship was in the next room.</p><p >The gentleman in the bag wig opened the door almost directly, and requested Mr. Kenge to come in. Upon that, we all went into the next room; Mr. Kenge first, with my darling—it is so natural to me now, that I can't help writing it; and there, plainly dressed in black, and sitting in an arm-chair at a table near the fire, was his lordship, whose robe, trimmed with beautiful gold lace, was thrown upon another chair. He gave us a searching look as we entered, but his manner was both courtly and kind.</p><p >The gentleman in the bag wig laid bundles of papers on his lordship's table, and his lordship silently selected one, and turned over the leaves.</p><p >“Miss Clare,” said the Lord Chancellor. “Miss Ada Clare?”</p><p >Mr. Kenge presented her, and his lordship begged her to sit down near him. That he admired her, and was interested by her, even <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could see in a moment. It touched me, that the home of such a beautiful young creature should be represented by that dry official place. The Lord High Chancellor, at his best, appeared so poor a substitute for the love and pride of parents.</p><p >“The Jarndyce in question,” said the Lord Chancellor, still turning over leaves, “is Jarndyce of Bleak House.”</p><p >“Jarndyce of Bleak House, my lord,” said Mr. Kenge.</p><p >“A dreary name,” said the Lord Chancellor.</p><p >“But not a dreary place at present, my lord,” said Mr. Kenge.</p><p >“And Bleak House,” said his lordship, “is in—”</p><p >“Hertfordshire, my lord.”</p><p >“Mr. Jarndyce of Bleak House is not married?” said his lordship.</p><p >“He is not, my lord,” said Mr. Kenge.</p><p >A pause.</p><p >“Young Mr. Richard Carstone is present?” said the Lord Chancellor, glancing towards him.</p><p >Richard bowed and stepped forward.</p><p >“Hum!” said the Lord Chancellor, turning over more leaves.</p><p >“Mr. Jarndyce of Bleak House, my lord,” Mr. Kenge observed, in a low voice, “if I may venture to remind your lordship, provides a suitable companion for—”</p><p >“For Mr. Richard Carstone?” I thought (but I am not quite sure) I heard his lordship say, in an equally low voice, and with a smile.</p><p >“For Miss Ada Clare. This is the young lady. Miss Summerson.”</p><p >His lordship gave me an indulgent look, and acknowledged my curtsey very graciously.</p><p >“Miss Summerson is not related to any party in the cause, I think?”</p><p >“No, my lord.”</p><p >Mr. Kenge leant over before it was quite said, and whispered. His lordship, with his eyes upon his papers, listened, nodded twice or thrice,
<pb xml:id="p23a"/>
turned over more leaves, and did not look towards me again, until we were going away.</p><p >Mr. Kenge now retired, and Richard with him, to where I was, near the door, leaving my pet (it is so natural to me that again I can't help it!) sitting near the Lord Chancellor; with whom his lordship spoke a little apart; asking her, as she told me afterwards, whether she had well reflected on the proposed arrangement, and if she thought she would be happy under the roof of Mr. Jarndyce of Bleak House, and why she thought so? Presently he rose courteously, and released her, and then he spoke for a minute or two with Richard Carstone; not seated, but standing, and altogether with more ease and less ceremony—as if he still knew, though he <hi rend="italics">was</hi> Lord Chancellor, how to go straight to the candor of a boy.</p><p >“Very well!” said his lordship aloud. “I shall make the order. Mr. Jarndyce of Bleak House has chosen, so far as I may judge,” and this was when he looked at me, “a very good companion for the young lady, and the arrangement altogether seems the best of which the circumstances admit.”</p><p >He dismissed us pleasantly, and we all went out, very much obliged to him for being so affable and polite; by which he had certainly lost no dignity, but seemed to us to have gained some.</p><p >When we got under the colonnade, Mr. Kenge remembered that he must go back for a moment to ask a question; and left us in the fog, with the Lord Chancellor's carriage and servants waiting for him to come out.</p><p >“Well!” said Richard Carstone, “<hi rend="italics">that's</hi> over! And where do we go next, Miss Summerson?”</p><p >“Don't you know?” I said.</p><p >“Not in the least,” said he.</p><p >“And don't <hi rend="italics">you</hi> know, my love?” I asked Ada.</p><p >“No!” said she. “Don't you?”</p><p >“Not at all!” said I.</p><p >We looked at one another, half laughing at our being like the children in the wood, when a curious little old woman in a squeezed bonnet, and carrying a reticule, came curtseying and smiling up to us, with an air of great ceremony.</p><p >“O!” said she. “The wards in Jarndyce! Ve-ry happy, I am sure, to have the honor! It is a good omen for youth, and hope, and beauty, when they find themselves in this place, and don't know what's to come of it.”</p><p >“Mad!” whispered Richard, not thinking she could hear him.</p><p >“Right! Mad, young gentleman,” she returned so quickly that he was quite abashed. “I was a ward myself. I was not mad at that time,” curtseying low, and smiling between every little sentence. “I had youth, and hope. I believe, beauty. It matters very little now. Neither of the three served, or saved me. I have the honor to attend court regularly. With my documents. I expect a judgment. Shortly. On the Day of Judgment. I have discovered that the sixth seal mentioned in the Revelations is the Great Seal. It has been open a long time! Pray accept my blessing.”</p><p >As Ada was a little frightened, I said, to humor the poor old lady that we were much obliged to her.</p><pb  xml:id="p24a"/><p >“Ye-es!” she said mincingly. “I imagine so. And here is Conversation Kenge. With <hi rend="italics">his</hi> documents! How does your honorable worship do?”</p><p >“Quite well, quite well! Now don't be troublesome, that's a good soul!” said Mr. Kenge, leading the way back.</p><p >“By no means,” said the poor old lady, keeping up with Ada and me. “Anything but troublesome. I shall confer estates on both,—which is not being troublesome, I trust? I expect a judgment. Shortly. On the Day of Judgment. This is a good omen for you. Accept my blessing!”</p><p >She stopped at the bottom of the steep, broad flight of stairs; but we looked back as we went up, and she was still there, saying, still with a curtsey and a smile between every little sentence, “Youth. And hope. And beauty. And Chancery. And Conversation Kenge! Ha! Pray accept my blessing!”</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER IV. <lb/> TELESCOPIC PHILANTHROPY.</head><p >WE were to pass the night, Mr. Kenge told us when we arrived in his room, at Mrs. Jellyby's; and then he turned to me, and said he took it for granted I knew who Mrs. Jellyby was?</p><p >“I really don't, sir,” I returned. “Perhaps Mr. Carstone—or Miss Clare—”</p><p >But no, they knew nothing whatever about Mrs. Jellyby.</p><p >“In-deed! Mrs. Jellyby,” said Mr. Kenge, standing with his back to the fire, and casting his eyes over the dusty hearth-rug as if it were Mrs. Jellyby's biography, “is a lady of very remarkable strength of character, who devotes herself entirely to the public. She has devoted herself to an extensive variety of public subjects, at various times, and is at present (until something else attracts her) devoted to the subject of Africa; with a view to the general cultivation of the coffee berry—<hi rend="italics">and</hi> the natives—and the happy settlement, on the banks of the African rivers, of our superabundant home population. Mr. Jarndyce, who is desirous to aid in any work that is considered likely to be a good work, and who is much sought after by philanthropists, has, I believe, a very high opinion of Mrs. Jellyby.”</p><p >Mr. Kenge, adjusting his cravat, then looked at us.</p><p >“And Mr. Jellyby, sir?” suggested Richard.</p><p >“Ah! Mr. Jellyby,” said Mr. Kenge, “is—a—I don't know that I can describe him to you better than by saying that he is the husband of Mrs. Jellyby.”</p><p >“A nonentity, sir?” said Richard with a droll look.</p><p >“I don't say that,” returned Mr. Kenge, gravely. “I can't say that, indeed, for I know nothing whatever <hi rend="italics">of</hi> Mr. Jellyby. I never, to my knowledge, had the pleasure of seeing Mr. Jellyby. He may be a very superior man; but he is, so to speak, merged—Merged—in the more shining qualities of his wife.” Mr. Kenge proceeded to tell us that as
<pb xml:id="p25a"/>
the road to Bleak House would have been very long, dark, and tedious, on such an evening, and as we had been travelling already, Mr. Jarndyce had himself proposed this arrangement. A carriage would be at Mrs. Jellyby's to convey us out of town, early in the forenoon of to-morrow.</p><p >He then rang a little bell, and the young gentleman came in. Addressing him by the name of Guppy, Mr. Kenge inquired whether Miss Summerson's boxes and the rest of the baggage had been “sent round.” Mr. Guppy said yes, they had been sent round, and a coach was waiting to take us round too, as soon as we pleased.</p><p >“Then it only remains,” said Mr. Kenge, shaking hands with us, “for me to express my lively satisfaction in (good day, Miss Clare!) the arrangement this day concluded, and my (<hi rend="italics">good</hi> bye to you, Miss Summerson!) lively hope that it will conduce to the happiness, the (glad to have had the honor of making your acquaintance, Mr. Carstone!) welfare, the advantage in all points of view, of all concerned! Guppy, see the party safely there.”</p><p >“Where <hi rend="italics">is</hi> ‘there,’ Mr. Guppy?” said Richard, as we went down stairs.</p><p >“No distance,” said Mr. Guppy; “round in Thavies' Inn, you know.”</p><p >“I can't say I know where it is, for I come from Winchester, and am strange in London.”</p><p >“Only round the corner,” said Mr. Guppy. “We just twist up Chancery-lane, and cut along Holborn, and there we are in four minutes time, as near as a toucher. This is about a London particular <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> ain't it, miss?” He seemed quite delighted with it on my account.</p><p >“The fog is very dense indeed!” said I.</p><p >“Not that it affects you, though, I am sure,” said Mr. Guppy, putting up the steps. “On the contrary, it seems to do you good, miss, judging from your appearance.”</p><p >I knew he meant well in paying me this compliment, so I laughed at myself for blushing at it, when he had shut the door and got upon the box; and we all three laughed, and chatted about our inexperience, and the strangeness of London, until we turned up under an archway, to our destination: a narrow street of high houses, like an oblong cistern to hold the fog. There was a confused little crowd of people, principally children, gathered about the house at which we stopped, which had a tarnished brass plate on the door, with the inscription, JELLYBY.</p><p >“Don't be frightened!” said Mr. Guppy, looking in at the coach-window. “One of the young Jellybys been and got his head through the area railings!”</p><p >“O poor child,” said I, “let me out, if you please!”</p><p >“Pray be careful of yourself, miss. The young Jellybys are always up to something,” said Mr. Guppy.</p><p >I made my way to the poor child, who was one of the dirtiest little unfortunates I ever saw, and found him very hot and frightened, and crying loudly, fixed by the neck between two iron railings, while a milk-man and a beadle, with the kindest intentions possible, were endeavouring to drag him back by the legs, under a general impression that his skull was compressible by those means. As I found (after pacifying him), that he was a little boy, with a naturally large head, I thought that, perhaps, where his head could go, his body could follow, and mentioned that the
<pb xml:id="p26a"/>
best mode of extrication might be to push him forward. This was so favorably received by the milkman and beadle, that he would immediately have been pushed into the area, if I had not held his pinafore, while Richard and Mr. Guppy ran down through the kitchen, to catch him when he should be released. At last he was happily got down without any accident, and then he began to beat Mr. Guppy with a hoop-stick in quite a frantic manner.</p><p >Nobody had appeared belonging to the house, except a person in pattens, who had been poking at the child from below with a broom; I don't know with what object, and I don't think she did. I therefore supposed that Mrs. Jellyby was not at home; and was quite surprised when the person appeared in the passage without the pattens, and going up to the back room on the first floor, before Ada and me, announced us as, “Them two young ladies, Missis Jellyby!” We passed several more children on the way up, whom it was difficult to avoid treading on in the dark; and as we came into Mrs. Jellyby's presence, one of the poor little things fell down stairs—down a whole flight (as it sounded to me), with a great noise.</p><p >Mrs. Jellyby, whose face reflected none of the uneasiness which we could not help showing in our own faces, as the dear child's head recorded its passage with a bump on every stair—Richard afterwards said he counted seven, besides one for the landing—received us with perfect equanimity. She was a pretty, very diminutive, plump woman, of from forty to fifty, with handsome eyes, though they had a curious habit of seeming to look a long way off. As if—I am quoting Richard again—they could see nothing nearer than Africa!</p><p >“I am very glad indeed,” said Mrs. Jellyby, in an agreeable voice, “to have the pleasure of receiving you. I have a great respect for Mr. Jarndyce; and no one in whom he is interested can be an object of indifference to me.”</p><p >We expressed our acknowledgments, and sat down behind the door where there was a lame invalid of a sofa. Mrs. Jellyby had very good hair, but was too much occupied with her African duties to brush it. The shawl in which she had been loosely muffled, dropped on to her chair when she advanced to us; and as she turned to resume her seat, we could not help noticing that her dress didn't nearly meet up the back, and that the open space was railed across with a lattice-work of stay-lace—like a summer-house.</p><p >The room, which was strewn with papers and nearly filled by a great writing-table covered with similar litter, was, I must say, not only very untidy, but very dirty. We were obliged to take notice of that with our sense of sight, even while, with our sense of hearing, we followed the poor child who had tumbled down stairs: I think into the back kitchen, where somebody seemed to stifle him.</p><p >But what principally struck us was a jaded, and unhealthy-looking, though by no means plain girl, at the writing-table, who sat biting the feather of her pen, and staring at us. I suppose nobody ever was in such a state of ink. And, from her tumbled hair to her pretty feet, which were disfigured with frayed and broken satin slippers trodden down at heel, she really seemed to have no article of dress upon her, from a pin upwards, that was in its proper condition or its right place.</p><p >“You find me, my dears,” said Mrs. Jellyby, snuffing the two great
<pb xml:id="p27a"/>
office candles in tin candlesticks which made the room taste strongly of hot tallow (the fire had gone out, and there was nothing in the grate but ashes, a bundle of wood, and a poker), “you find me, my dears, as usual, very busy; but that you will excuse. The African project at present employs my whole time. It involves me in correspondence with public bodies, and with private individuals anxious for the welfare of their species all over the country. I am happy to say it is advancing. We hope by this time next year to have from a hundred and fifty to two hundred healthy families cultivating coffee and educating the natives of Borrioboola-Gha, on the left bank of the Niger.</p><p >As Ada said nothing, but looked at me, I said it must be very gratifying.</p><p >“It <hi rend="italics">is</hi> gratifying,” said Mrs. Jellyby. “It involves the devotion of all my energies, such as they are; but that is nothing, so that it succeeds; and I am more confident of success every day. Do you know, Miss Summerson, I almost wonder that <hi rend="italics">you</hi> never turned your thoughts to Africa?”</p><p >This application of the subject was really so unexpected to me, that I was quite at a loss how to receive it. I hinted that the climate—</p><p >“The finest climate in the world!” said Mrs. Jellyby.</p><p >“Indeed, ma'am?”</p><p >Certainly. With precaution,” said Mrs. Jellyby. “You may go into Holborn, without precaution, and be run over. You may go into Holborn, with precaution, and never be run over. Just so with Africa.”</p><p >I said, “No doubt.”—I meant as to Holborn.</p><p >“If you would like,” said Mrs. Jellyby, putting a number of papers towards us, “to look over some remarks on that head, and on the general subject (which have been extensively circulated), while I finish a letter I am now dictating—to my eldest daughter, who is my amanuensis—”</p><p >The girl at the table left off biting her pen, and made a return to our recognition, which was half bashful and half sulky.</p><p >“—I shall then have finished for the present,” proceeded Mrs. Jellyby, with a sweet smile; “though my work is never done. Where are you, Caddy?”</p><p >“ ‘Presents her compliments to Mr. Swallow, and begs—’ ” said Caddy.</p><p >“‘—And begs,’” said Mrs. Jellyby, dictating, “‘to inform him, in reference to his letter of inquiry on the African project.’—No, Peepy! Not on any account!”</p><p >Peepy (so self-named) was the unfortunate child who had fallen down stairs, who now interrupted the correspondence by presenting himself, with a strip of plaister on his forehead, to exhibit his wounded knees, in which Ada and I did not know which to pity most—the bruises or the dirt. Mrs. Jellyby merely added, with the serene composure with which she said everything, “Go along, you naughty Peepy!” and fixed her fine eyes on Africa again.</p><p >However, as she at once proceeded with her dictation, and as I interrupted nothing by doing it, I ventured quietly to stop poor Peepy as he was going out, and to take him up to nurse. He looked very much astonished at it, and at Ada's kissing him; but soon fell fast asleep in my arms, sobbing at longer and longer intervals, until he was quiet. I was so occupied with Peepy that I lost the letter in detail, though I derived
<pb xml:id="p28a"/>
such a general impression from it of the momentous importance of Africa, and the utter insignificance of all other places and things, that I felt quite ashamed to have thought so little about it.</p><p >“Six o'clock!” said Mrs. Jellyby. “And our dinner hour is nominally (for we dine at all hours) five! Caddy, show Miss Clare and Miss Summerson their rooms. You will like to make some change, perhaps? You will excuse me, I know, being so much occupied. O, that very bad child! Pray put him down, Miss Summerson!”</p><p >I begged permission to retain him, truly saying that he was not at all troublesome; and carried him upstairs and laid him on my bed. Ada and I had two upper rooms, with a door of communication between. They were excessively bare and disorderly, and the curtain to my window was fastened up with a fork.</p><p >“You would like some hot water, wouldn't you?” said Miss Jellyby, looking round for a jug with a handle to it, but looking in vain.</p><p >“If it is not being troublesome,” said we.</p><p >“O, it's not the trouble,” returned Miss Jellyby; “the question is, if there <hi rend="italics">is</hi> any.”</p><p >The evening was so very cold, and the rooms had such a marshy smell, that I must confess it was a little miserable; and Ada was half crying. We soon laughed, however, and were busily unpacking, when Miss Jellyby came back to say, that she was sorry there was no hot water; but they couldn't find the kettle, and the boiler was out of order.</p><p >We begged her not to mention it, and made all the haste we could to get down to the fire again. But all the little children had come up to the landing outside, to look at the phenomenon of Peepy lying on my bed; and our attention was distracted by the constant apparition of noses and fingers, in situations of danger between the hinges of the doors. It was impossible to shut the door of either room; for my lock, with no knob to it, looked as if it wanted to be wound up; and though the handle of Ada's went round and round with the greatest smoothness, it was attended with no effect whatever on the door. Therefore I proposed to the children that they should come in and be very good at my table, and I would tell them the story of little Red Riding Hood while I dressed; which they did, and were as quiet as mice, including Peepy, who awoke opportunely before the appearance of the wolf.</p><p >When we went downstairs we found a mug, with “A Present from Tunbridge Wells” on it, lighted up in the staircase window with a floating wick; and a young woman, with a swelled face bound up in a flannel bandage, blowing the fire of the drawing-room (now connected by an open door with Mrs. Jellyby's room), and choaking dreadfully. It smoked to that degree in short, that we all sat coughing and crying with the windows open for half an hour; during which Mrs. Jellyby, with the same sweetness of temper, directed letters about Africa. Her being so employed was, I must say, a great relief to me; for Richard told us that he had washed his hands in a pie-dish, and that they had found the kettle on his dressing-table; and he made Ada laugh so, that they made me laugh in the most ridiculous manner.</p><p >Soon after seven o'clock we went down to dinner; carefully, by Mrs. Jellyby's advice; for the stair-carpets, besides being very deficient in stairwires, were so torn as to be absolute traps. We had a fine cod-fish, a piece of roast beef, a dish of cutlets, and a pudding; an excellent
<pb xml:id="p29a"/>
dinner, if it had any cooking to speak of, but it was almost raw. The young woman with the flannel bandage waited, and dropped everything on the table wherever it happened to go, and never moved it again until she put it on the stairs. The person I had seen in pattens (who I suppose to have been the cook), frequently came and skirmished with her at the door, and there appeared to be ill-will between them.</p><p >All through dinner; which was long, in consequence of such accidents as the dish of potatoes being mislaid in the coal skuttle, and the handle of the corkscrew coming off, and striking the young woman in the chin; Mrs. Jellyby preserved the evenness of her disposition. She told us a great deal that was interesting about Borrioboola-Gha and the natives; and received so many letters that Richard, who sat by her, saw four envelopes in the gravy at once. Some of the letters were proceedings of ladies' committees, or resolutions of ladies' meetings, which she read to us; others were applications from people excited in various ways about the cultivation of coffee, and natives; others required answers, and these she sent her eldest daughter from the table three or four times to write. She was full of business, and undoubtedly was, as she had told us, devoted to the cause.</p><p >I was a little curious to know who a mild bald gentleman in spectacles was, who dropped into a vacant chair (there was no top or bottom in particular) after the fish was taken away, and seemed passively to submit himself to Borrioboola-Gha, but not to be actively interested in that settlement. As he never spoke a word, he might have been a native, but for his complexion. It was not until we left the table, and he remained alone with Richard, that the possibility of his being Mr. Jellyby ever entered my head. But he <hi rend="italics">was</hi> Mr. Jellyby; and a loquacious young man called Mr. Quale, with large shining knobs for temples, and his hair all brushed to the back of his head, who came in the evening, and told Ada he was a philanthropist, also informed her that he called the matrimonial alliance of Mrs. Jellyby with Mr. Jellyby the union of mind and matter.</p><p >This young man, besides having a great deal to say for himself about Africa, and a project of his for teaching the coffee colonists to teach the natives to turn piano-forte legs and establish an export trade, delighted in drawing Mrs. Jellyby out by saying, “I believe now, Mrs. Jellyby, you have received as many as from one hundred and fifty to two hundred letters respecting Africa in a single day, have you not?” or, “If my memory does not deceive me, Mrs. Jellyby, you once mentioned that you had sent off five thousand circulars from one post-office at one time?”—always repeating Mrs. Jellyby's answer to us like an interpreter. During the whole evening, Mr. Jellyby sat in a corner with his head against the wall, as if he were subject to low spirits. It seemed that he had several times opened his mouth when alone with Richard, after dinner, as if he had something on his mind; but had always shut it again, to Richard's extreme confusion, without saying anything.</p><p >Mrs. Jellyby, sitting in quite a nest of waste paper, drank coffee all the evening, and dictated at intervals to her eldest daughter. She also held a discussion with Mr. Quale; of which the subject seemed to be—if I understood it—the Brotherhood of Humanity; and gave utterance to some beautiful sentiments. I was not so attentive an auditor as I might have wished to be, however, for Peepy and the other children came flocking about Ada and me in a corner of the drawing-room to ask for another
<pb xml:id="p30a"/>
story: so we sat down among them, and told them in whispers Puss in Boots and I don't know what else, until Mrs. Jellyby, accidentally remembering them, sent them to bed. As Peepy cried for me to take him to bed, I carried him upstairs; where the young woman with the flannel bandage charged into the midst of the little family like a dragoon, and overturned them into cribs.</p><p >After that, I occupied myself in making our room a little tidy, and in coaxing a very cross fire that had been lighted, to burn; which at last it did, quite brightly. On my return downstairs, I felt that Mrs. Jellyby looked down upon me rather, for being so frivolous; and I was sorry for it; though at the same time I knew that I had no higher pretensions.</p><p >It was nearly midnight before we found an opportunity of going to bed; and even then we left Mrs. Jellyby among her papers drinking coffee, and Miss Jellyby biting the feather of her pen.</p><p >“What a strange house!” said Ada, when we got upstairs. “How curious of my cousin Jarndyce to send us here!”</p><p >“My love,” said I, “it quite confuses me. I want to understand it, and I can't understand it at all.”</p><p >“What?” asked Ada, with her pretty smile.</p><p >“All this, my dear,” said I. “It <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be very good of Mrs. Jellyby to take such pains about a scheme for the benefit of Natives—and yet—Peepy and the housekeeping!”</p><p >Ada laughed; and put her arm about my neck, as I stood looking at the fire; and told me I was a quiet, dear, good creature, and had won her heart. “You are so thoughtful, Esther,“ she said, “and yet so cheerful! and you do so much, so unpretendingly! You would make a home out of even this house.”</p><p >My simple darling! She was quite unconscious that she only praised herself, and that it was in the goodness of her own heart that she made so much of me!</p><p >“May I ask you a question?” said I, when we had sat before the fire a little while.</p><p >“Five hundred,” said Ada.</p><p >“Your cousin, Mr. Jarndyce. I owe so much to him. Would you mind describing him to me?”</p><p >Shaking back her golden hair, Ada turned her eyes upon me with such laughing wonder, that I was full of wonder too—partly at her beauty, partly at her surprise.</p><p >“Esther!” she cried.</p><p >“My dear!”</p><p >“You want a description of my cousin Jarndyce?”</p><p >“My dear, I never saw him.”</p><p >“And <hi rend="italics">I</hi> never saw him!” returned Ada.</p><p >Well, to be sure!</p><p >No, she had never seen him. Young as she was when her mama died, she remembered how the tears would come into her eyes when she spoke of him, and of the noble generosity of his character, which she had said was to be trusted above all earthly things; and Ada trusted it. Her cousin Jarndyce had written to her a few months ago,—“a plain, honest letter,” Ada said—proposing the arrangement we were now to enter on, and telling her that, “in time it might heal some of the wounds made by the miserable Chancery suit.” She had replied, gratefully accepting his
<pb xml:id="p31a"/>
proposal. Richard had received a similar letter, and had made a similar response. He <hi rend="italics">had</hi> seen Mr. Jarndyce once, but only once, five years ago, at Winchester school. He had told Ada, when they were leaning on the screen before the fire where I found them, that he recollected him as “a bluff, rosy fellow.” This was the utmost description Ada could give me.</p><p >It set me thinking so, that when Ada was asleep, I still remained before the fire, wondering and wondering about Bleak House, and wondering and wondering that yesterday morning should seem so long ago. I don't know where my thoughts had wandered, when they were recalled by a tap at the door.</p><p >I opened it softly, and found Miss Jellyby shivering there, with a broken candle in a broken candlestick in one hand, and an egg-cup in the other.</p><p >“Good night!” she said, very sulkily.</p><p >“Good night!” said I.</p><p >“May I come in?” she shortly and unexpectedly asked me in the same sulky way.</p><p >“Certainly,” said I. “Don't wake Miss Clare.”</p><p >She would not sit down, but stood by the fire, dipping her inky middle finger in the egg-cup, which contained vinegar, and smearing it over the ink stains on her face; frowning, the whole time, and looking very gloomy.</p><p >“I wish Africa was dead!” she said, on a sudden.</p><p >I was going to remonstrate.</p><p >“I do!” she said. “Don't talk to me, Miss Summerson. I hate it and detest it. It's a beast!”</p><p >I told her she was tired, and I was sorry. I put my hand upon her head, and touched her forehead, and said it was hot now, but would be cool to-morrow. She still stood, pouting and frowning at me; but presently put down her egg-cup, and turned softly towards the bed where Ada lay.</p><p >“She is very pretty!” she said, with the same knitted brow, and in the same uncivil manner.</p><p >I assented with a smile.</p><p >“An orphan. Ain't she?”</p><p >“Yes.”</p><p >“But knows a quantity, I suppose? Can dance, and play music, and sing? She can talk French, I suppose, and do geography, and globes, and needlework, and every thing?”</p><p >“No doubt,” said I.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">I</hi> can't,” she returned. “I can't do anything hardly, except write. I'm always writing for Ma. I wonder you two were not ashamed of yourselves to come in this afternoon, and see me able to do nothing else. It was like your ill-nature. Yet you think yourselves very fine, I dare say!”</p><p >I could see that the poor girl was near crying, and I resumed my chair without speaking, and looked at her (I hope), as mildly as I felt towards her.</p><p >“It's disgraceful,” she said. “You know it is. The whole house is disgraceful. The children are disgraceful. <hi rend="italics">I</hi>'m disgraceful. Pa's miserable, and no wonder! Priscilla drinks—she's always drinking. It's a great shame and a great story, of you, if you say you didn't smell her
<pb xml:id="p32a"/>
to-day. It was as bad as a public-house, waiting at dinner; you know it was!”</p><p >“My dear, I don't know it,” said I.</p><p >“You do,” she said, very shortly. “You sha'n't say you don't. You do!”</p><p >“O, my dear!” said I, “if you won't let me speak —”</p><p >“You're speaking now. You know you are. Don't tell stories, Miss Summerson.”</p><p >“My dear,” said I, “as long as you won't hear me out—”</p><p >“I don't want to hear you out.”</p><p >“O yes, I think you do,” said I, “because that would be so very unreasonable. I did not know what you tell me, because the servant did not come near me at dinner; but I don't doubt what you tell me, and I am sorry to hear it.”</p><p >“You needn't make a merit of that,” said she.</p><p >“No, my dear,” said I. “That would be very foolish.”</p><p >She was still standing by the bed, and now stooped down (but still with the same discontented face) and kissed Ada. That done, she came softly back, and stood by the side of my chair. Her bosom was heaving in a distressful manner that I greatly pitied; but I thought it better not to speak.</p><p >“I wish I was dead!” she broke out. “I wish we were all dead. It would be a great deal better for us.”</p><p >In a moment afterwards, she knelt on the ground at my side, hid her face in my dress, passionately begged my pardon, and wept. I comforted her, and would have raised her, but she cried, No, no; she wanted to stay there!</p><p >“You used to teach girls,” she said. “If you could only have taught me, I could have learnt from you! I am so very miserable, and I like you so much!”</p><p >I could not persuade her to sit by me, or to do anything but move a ragged stool to where she was kneeling, and take that, and still hold my dress in the same manner. By degrees, the poor tired girl fell asleep; and then I contrived to raise her head so that it should rest on my lap, and to cover us both with shawls. The fire went out, and all night long she slumbered thus before the ashy grate. At first I was painfully awake, and vainly tried to lose myself, with my eyes closed, among the scenes of the day. At length, by slow degrees, they became indistinct and mingled. I began to lose the identity of the sleeper resting on me. Now, it was Ada; now, one of my old Reading friends from whom I could not believe I had so recently parted. Now, it was the little mad woman worn out with curtseying and smiling; now, some one in authority at Bleak House. Lastly, it was no one, and I was no one.</p><p >The purblind day was feebly struggling with the fog, when I opened my eyes to encounter those of a dirty-faced little spectre fixed upon me. Peepy had scaled his crib, and crept down in his bedgown and cap, and was so cold that his teeth were chattering as if he had cut them all.</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1b"/><head >WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> 65 to 68, and Carpenters' Hall, LONDON WALL, <lb/> 49, PARLIAMENT STREET, <lb/> AND <lb/> 24, BIRCHIN LANE, CORNHILL, <lb/> LONDON, <lb/> WHOLESALE AND RETAIL STATIONERS, <lb/> MANUFACTURERS OF <lb/> PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS, <lb/> ENGRAVERS OF BANKERS' CHEQUES, &amp;c., <lb/> Printers and Lithographers,</head><p >RESPECTFULLY direct the attention of MANAGERS OF JOINT STOCK AND PRIVATE BANKS to their Establishments as above.</p><p >By concentrating in every article manufactured, all that is of the highest excellence in quality of material and finish, but with all due regard to economy; by guaranteeing all their goods, and immediately exchanging all that may in the least degree produce dissatisfaction; by carrying out their originally adopted principle of excluding every practice which is not compatible with the highest principles of fair trading; by giving to their customers every advantage in reduction of prices which fluctuation of markets, large purchases, or other causes may bring about, and with a full determination to use all the means in their power to give the utmost satisfaction, and produce the greatest good will between themselves and their customers, W. and SONS trust that they may still be honoured by that increased confidence and patronage, which has been bestowed on them for so long a period.</p><p >Patentees of the <lb/> AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, OR COUNTING-HOUSE PRINTING MACHINE, <lb/> AND <lb/> COPYING APPARATUS.</p><pb  xml:id="p2b"/><div type="section"><head >WRITING PAPERS,</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Of all qualities, Glazed or Hotpressed. Note Paper, half the price of Letter.</hi></p><p >WATERLOW AND SONS can offer considerable advantages in this department. Their Machine-papers are finished to suit all consumers, and being made from the best linen rags, possess soundness and strength, together with a purity in colour, rarely to be met with. A few only of the many varieties of paper are quoted; but W. and Sons, in addition to their own stock, are supplied from all the best makers, and can therefore furnish paper to any sample.</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>Per Ream.</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Large Blue Wove Post</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large Blue Wove Superfine</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large thin Blue Wove or Blue or Cream laid, extra superfine</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large middle extra superfine</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Large thick extra superfine</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Large B. Laid or Wove Foreign Post</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Large Cream wove Wove Foreign Post</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fine Blue Laid Foolscap 10s. 6d. and</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine Laid Foolscap 15s. and</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Extra Superfine Blue or Cream Laid Foolscap 19s. and</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Letter and Note Paper headed from plate, @ 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per ream, without any charge for engraving if two or more reams are ordered. Ruled Papers of every description.</p><p >
<table><head>BLOTTINGS.</head><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Cream Wove per ream</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>White or Pink Wove</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>White or Pink Laid</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Patent White Wove, of considerable strength and durability, per quire 2s. 6d.</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Patent Salmon Wove per quire 3s. 6d.</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>WRAPPING PAPERS.</head><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Brown Papers of various sizes per cwt.</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Strong Cartridge, demy per ream</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Strong Cartridge, demy royal per ream</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Strong Cartridge, demy imperial per ream 33s.</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Hand Paper (white brown) 2s. 6d and</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Tough Double Imperial Brown, glazed both sides per ream</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >FOR BANKERS' PARCELS, <lb/> Imperial (29¾ by 21½) Cloth Paper, pr. quire, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Royal (25 by 16) Cloth Paper, per quire, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><p >ACCOUNT BOOKS, <lb/> FOR BANKERS AND MERCHANTS, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Warranted of the very best materials, and finished by the most experienced workmen.</hi></p><p >These Account Books are manufactured of first-class paper, bound with <hi rend="italics">Patent Flexible Backs,</hi> in Russia, calf, vellum, white or green forel, basil (plain or grained), and <hi rend="italics">warranted to open perfectly flat,</hi> so that the inner columns may be used with comfort, and <hi rend="italics">without danger of the joints or sections giving way.</hi> They are also made with bands, iron backs, brass corners, with or without printed or lithographed headings, and paged or folio'd in type (without any extra charge) by a machine of ingenious and novel construction, worked by STEAM POWER, which produces a clear and bold figure, of an unequalled regularity impossible to be obtained by the ordinary machines.</p><list  type="simple"><item>General ledger</item><item>Bankers' ledger</item><item>Bought ledger</item><item>Private ledger with locks</item><item>Pocket ledger with clasps</item><item>Travelling with clasps</item><item>Insurance with clasps</item><item>Journals</item><item>Day books</item><item>Bought day books</item><item>Waste books</item><item>Cash books</item><item>Petty cash books</item><item>Invoice books</item><item>Guard books for letters, &amp;c.</item><item>Letter books</item><item>Letter for copying machine</item><item>Order books</item><item>Bill books</item><item>Contract books</item><item>Policy books</item><item>Postage books</item><item>Diaries</item><item>Manuscript books</item><item>Account current books</item><item>Account sale books</item><item>Ciphering books</item><item>Copy books</item><item>Memorandum books</item><item>Metallic books</item></list><p >An Extensive Stock of Account Books, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Of various Rulings and Bindings, always ready for immediate use.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p3b"/><head >ACCOUNT BOOKS</head><p >Of every description made to Order, for the use of <lb/> JOINT-STOCK AND PRIVATE BANKS, SAVINGS' BANKS, &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">No extra Charge for Type Paging or Folioing.</hi></p><p >Price List of Account Books, whole bound extra.</p><p >The following price list is intended as a guide for books termed extra, the very best that can be manufactured, and whole-bound. Contracts taken for the supply of large establishments and exporters; or tenders given for any particular book or set of books that may be required.</p><p >
<table><head>FOOLSCAP.—<hi rend="italics">Broad Folio,</hi> 12½ <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 8; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 15½ <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 6.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>2 q. or 176 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Extras. <lb/>If in Russia, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> if in Russia Bands, viz., 3 straps over the back, 8<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> if Double Bands or Russia along the Top and Bottom and one Band in the centre, 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>7 q. or 656 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 752 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>DEMY.—<hi rend="italics">Broad Folio,</hi> 14½ <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 9½; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 7¼.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>2 q. or 176 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Extras.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If in Russia</cell><cell>6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Russia Bands</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 752 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>If Double Bands</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>9 q. or 848 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>10 q. or 944 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>6</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MEDIUM.—16 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 10¼.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>2 q. or 176 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>Extras.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>If in Russia</cell><cell>8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Russia Bands</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 752 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Double Bands</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>9 q. or 848 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>10 q. or 944 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>ROYAL.—18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 11.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>3 q. or 272 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Extras.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If in Russia</cell><cell>8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Russia Bands</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 750 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>If Double Bands</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>10 q. or 944 pp.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SUPER ROYAL.—18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 13.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>Extras.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If in Russia</cell><cell>10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 752 pp.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Russia Bands</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>10 q. or 944 pp.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>If Double Bands</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>IMPERIAL.—20¼ <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 14¼.—(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row><cell>Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Basil, with or without Iron Back</cell><cell>4 q. or 368 pp.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Extras.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>6 q. or 560 pp.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If in Russia</cell><cell>11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>8 q. or 752 pp.</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>If Russia Bands</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>10 q. or 944 pp.</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>If Double Bands</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >BANKERS' PASS BOOKS—8vo Vellum Tuck.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>Fcap 8vo, 6 × 4.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Demy 8vo, 7 × 4½.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>6 Sheets or 92 pages per doz.</cell><cell>£0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>£0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>9 Sheets or 142 pages per doz.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>12 Sheets or 188 pages per doz.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Pass Books in basil, roan, sheep, or any other bindings, at equally reasonable charges.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p4b"/><head >PRINTING AND LITHOGRAPHY.</head><p >WATERLOW &amp; SONS beg to inform Proprietors and Managers of Banks that they continue to execute every kind of Printing and Lithography for Banking Houses, on the lowest terms consistent with workmanship and materials of the first quality.</p><p >CONTRACTS FOR PRINTING entered into, or Estimates furnished.</p><p >REPORTS of JOINT STOCK BANKS will be printed on the lowest terms; and any order from the Country, will be completed and forwarded, if required, on <hi rend="italics">Twelve Hours'</hi> notice.</p><p >FORMS ordinarily used in Banks, printed 20 per cent. under the usual charge. The following may be referred to as examples.</p><p >LODGEMENT RECEIPTS; REQUISITION SLIPS; CURRENT ACCOUNT RECEIPTS; DEPOSIT <lb/> ACCOUNT RECEIPTS;—7s. per 1000.</p><p >Letters of Credit: half sheet, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per 1000; fly, 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per 1000.</p><p >WEEKLY AND OTHER RETURNS, <lb/> From the Branches of Joint Stock Banks to the Head Office, at equally low rates.</p><p >BALANCE BOOKS LITHOGRAPHED,</p><p >In a superior manner, and with the greatest accuracy, at One Fourth, or (in cases where only a few copies are required) at One Tenth the price usually charged for printing them in Letter-press.</p><p >The following forms, Lithographed and Published by Waterlow and Sons, are always kept on sale:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>The Form of DAILY and WEEKLY RETURNS to be transmitted to the Stamp Office; on fscap. paper, fly-leaf, with the Certificate annexed to be signed by the manager, pursuant to the provisions of the Act per quire</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The MONTHLY RETURN, to be transmitted to the Stamp Office; on fscap. paper, fly-leaf, with the Certificate annexed to be signed by the manager, pursuant to the provisions of the Act per quire</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The HALF-YEARLY RETURN, to be transmitted to the Stamp Office; on fscap. paper, fly-leaf, with the Certificate annexed to be signed by the manager, pursuant to the provisions of the Act per quire</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The BANKS' CIRCULATION REGISTER, containing blank Daily, Weekly, and Monthly Return Accounts; medium Svo., neatly half-bound</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>PROXY FORMS for Voting at Bank Meetings, under 8 &amp; 9 Vic., cap. 21, per quire, 2<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> or ready stamped each</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>New Form of Notice of Dishonoured Bill per quire</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>New Form of Notice of Dishonoured Bill with Counterpart, bound in books of 250 each (to order)</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Acknowledgment on deposit of Deeds as Security, foolscap (3 different forms), per quire</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Acknowledgment on deposit of Deeds at Security, foolscap (3 different forms), post 4to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Special Forms of the above Lithographed, to order.</p><p >CIRCULAR LETTERS, NOTICES, &amp;c.—The attention of applicants for public situations, or persons desirous to address a large constituency, or body of shareholders in a public company, is requested to the facilities this establishment offers for accomplishing, at a few hours' notice, the printing of 4,000 or 5,000 copies of a circular, folding same, addressing envelopes, and dispatching them.</p><p >Drawings, Maps, Plaus, Share Certificates, Fac-Similes, and Writings of every description, <lb/> Lithographed by the first Artists.</p></div><div type="section"><head >ENGRAVING &amp; COPPER-PLATE PRINTING, <lb/> BANKERS' CHEQUES.</head><p >WATERLOW AND SONS beg to call the attention of Bankers to their prices for cheques, on paper of all tints, warranted secure from forgery. They trust that their long experience in this department, and their connexion with some of the first banks in the country, will be sufficient guarantee that the strictest attention is paid to the quality of the work and the excellence of the material.</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Cheques, in black ink, on white or tinted paper, per ream of 4,800, including engraving</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Cheques, in colour, on white or tinted paper, per ream of 4,800, including Binding in slip books, 1<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Credit Letters, per 1000, in black ink, on white or tinted paper, ½ sheets</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Credit Letters, per 1000, fly black ink</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Credit Letters, per 1000, in colour, ½ sheets</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Credit Letters, per 1000, fly ½ sheets</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Credit, Letters, per 1000, lithographed on white or tinted paper</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Engraving for Notes, Cheques, Drafts, Receipts, Certificates, Bonds, Bills of Exchange and Lading Invoices, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., in the first style of the art.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p5b"/><head >PATENT LETTER COPYING PRESSES,</head><p >These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>Lever Press.</cell><cell>Screw Press.</cell><cell>1st quality, Screw.</cell><cell>Screw Press, wrt.iron beam.</cell><cell>Mahogany Tables.</cell><cell>Damping Boxes.</cell></row><row><cell>Large 4to</cell><cell>£1 10</cell><cell>£2 10</cell><cell>£3 3</cell><cell>£3 15</cell><cell>£1 5</cell><cell>11s.</cell></row><row><cell>Foolscap Folio</cell><cell>2 0</cell><cell>3 3</cell><cell>4 10</cell><cell>5 5</cell><cell>2 2</cell><cell>12s</cell></row><row><cell>Post Folio</cell><cell>—</cell><cell>4 4</cell><cell>6 0</cell><cell>6 6</cell><cell>3 10</cell><cell>14s.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Fittings for Quarto Machine.</head><row><cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell><cell>2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Damping Brush</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Drying Book or Sheets</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Fittings for Foolscap Machine.</head><row><cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell><cell>3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Damping Brush</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Drying Book or Sheets</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>Fittings for Folio Machine.</head><row><cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell><cell>4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Damping Brush</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Drying Books or Sheets</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>COPYING BOOKS, <lb/>OF BLUE OR CREAM-WOVE COPYING PAPER, OF FIRST QUALITY, TYPE-PAGED BY STEAM POWER.</head><row><cell/><cell>QUARTER BOUND.</cell><cell>Each.</cell><cell>per Doz.</cell><cell/><cell>HALF BOUND.</cell><cell>Each.</cell><cell>per Doz.</cell></row><row><cell>500</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>8s.</cell><cell>84s.</cell><cell>500</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>10s.</cell><cell>102s.</cell></row><row><cell>750</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>10s.</cell><cell>105s.</cell><cell>750</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>13s.</cell><cell>138s.</cell></row><row><cell>1000</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>126s.</cell><cell>1000</cell><cell>LEAVES</cell><cell>15s.</cell><cell>156s.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >COPYING PAPER.</p><p >
<table><head>BEST FRENCH MAKE.</head><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Two Reams for</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Five Reams for</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Ten Reams for</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>BEST ENGLISH MAKE.</head><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Two Reams for</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Five Reams for</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Ten Reams for</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink,</head><p >FOR COPYING LETTERS, <lb/> The only <hi rend="italics">really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="italics">used</hi> in many of the <hi rend="italics">Principal Establishments in the City,’</hi>
<lb/> and is universally admitted the best yet produced.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Per PINT, 2s.</cell><cell>Per QUART, 3s.</cell><cell>Per DOZEN QUARTS, 30s.</cell><cell>Per GALLON, 10s.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Per HALF-GALLON, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per GALLON, do., do., 12s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >LINEN-LINED ENVELOPES, <lb/> AT GREATLY REDUCED PRICES.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>No. 1</cell><cell>4¾ by 2¾</cell><cell>at 1 9</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>5⅛ by 3⅛</cell><cell>at 2 0</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>5¾ by 3¾</cell><cell>at 2 9</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>7 by 4</cell><cell>at 4 0</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>No. 5</cell><cell>8¾ by 3½</cell><cell>at 5 6</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>8¾ by 4 </cell><cell>at 6 3</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>10¼ by 4½</cell><cell>at 8 0</cell><cell>per 100</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Extra for Printing or Lithographing Addresses on fronts, or Advice on flap, 7s. 6d. per 1000.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p6b"/><head >ENVELOPES.</head><p >THE extraordinary increase in the demand for Envelopes, now become an article of universal consumption, has led to the introduction of machinery, which Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS have secured, and by these means, in addition to their extensive connexion with the principal paper manufacturers, they are enabled not only to make a considerable reduction in the prices of all descriptions of Envelopes, but to offer better qualities than heretofore.</p><p >The following is a list of their Stock Envelopes, but they will be happy to make any size or pattern, and to contract for large quantities.</p><p >
<table><head>PRICE LIST OF STOCK ENVELOPES.</head><row><cell/><cell>At per 1000.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>DESCRIPTION.</cell><cell>No. 1. 4 × 2⅜</cell><cell/><cell>No. 2. 4⅛ × 2⅜</cell><cell/><cell>No. 3. 4⅜ × 2¾</cell><cell/><cell>No. 4. 4⅞ × 3</cell><cell/><cell>No. 5. 5⅛ × 3⅛</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Commercial</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fine</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Extra Superfine</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Fine Cream or Blue Laid</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Thick Cream or Blue Laid</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Extra Thick Cream Laid</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Vellum Laid (Substitute for Linen Lined)</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >IMPROVED ADHESIVE ENVELOPES.</head><p >EMBOSSED BY STEAM POWER.</p><p >WATERLOW &amp; SONS have also machinery for embossing the flaps of adhesive envelopes with plain or colored grounds, (Cameo). The utility of stamping the name and address on the flaps of envelopes, is very great to all engaged in business, as any letter misdirected is immediately returned to the writer, unopened by the Post-Office authorities.</p><p >The expense of sinking a special die for embossing the flaps with name and address, or coat of arms, crest, and device, is small (from 3s. 6d. upwards), and it may also be used for embossing note paper to correspond with the envelopes; and by affixing a handle, it forms a desk seal.</p><p >A great variety of dies are kept with initials and commercial devices, for the use of which no charge is made. Samples will be sent free to those about to order.</p><p >
<table><head>PRICE LIST OF ADHESIVE ENVELOPES — TO ORDERS.</head><row><cell/><cell>At per 1000.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>DESCRIPTION.</cell><cell>No. 1.</cell><cell/><cell>No. 2.</cell><cell/><cell>No. 3.</cell><cell/><cell>No. 4.</cell><cell/><cell>No. 5.</cell><cell/><cell>If Cameo.</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Commercial</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fine</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Extra-Superfine</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Fine Cream, or Blue-laid</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Thick Cream, or Blue-laid</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Extra Thick Cream-laid</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Vellum-laid</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >COMMERCIAL ADHESIVE ENVELOPES ALWAYS READY, <lb/> AT 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> PER 1,000, OR 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> PER 100.</p><p >CREAM LAID INITIAL DO., 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> PER 1,000, or 10<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> PER 100.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p7b"/><head >OFFICIAL ENVELOPES.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>Per 1000.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell>Per 100.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>DESCRIPTION.</cell><cell>W. 5⅜ × 3½</cell><cell/><cell>No. 1 Offil. 8¾ × 3⅜</cell><cell/><cell>No. 2 Offil. 8¾ × 4</cell><cell/><cell>Draft 11 × 4¾</cell><cell/><cell>Brief 13⅛ × 5</cell><cell/><cell>Deed 11¾ × 9⅝</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Fine Blue Laid</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell></row><row><cell>Thick Blue or Cream Laid</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell></row><row><cell>Vellum Laid</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell></row><row><cell>Cartridge</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Extra for Adhesive and Embossing</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >LINEN LINED ENVELOPES OF ALL SIZES.</p></div><div type="section"><head >METALLIC PENS, <lb/> Manufactured with all the LATEST IMPROVEMENTS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">A Sample Card of</hi> 13 <hi rend="italics">sorts of these Pens will be forwarded by post, free, upon receipt of Eight Postage Stamps.</hi></p><p >QUILL PENS, at 4s., 6s., 8s., 12s., and 14s. per 100. Turkey Quills, 8s. <hi rend="italics">Postage Stamps.</hi></p><p >The Patent Expanding Pen Holder will fit any pen, in Cedar, at 6d. and 1s per dozen; Ebony and <lb/> German Silver, 3s. 6d. per dozen. Ivory and German Silver Pen Holders, 5s. and 7s. per dozen.</p><p >PORCUPINE HOLDERS, mounted and tipped, 6d. each, or 5s. per dozen.</p><p >Superior Black Ink, adapted for Steel Pens, warranted not to change colour, or corrode the pen, gallons, <lb/> 5s.; quarts, 2s.; pints, 1s. 3d.; half-pints, 9d.; and gallon bottles, in baskets for the country, 6s. 6d.</p><p >The Glass Cone Inkstand is the most economical ever offered to the public. It presents so small a surface of ink to the atmosphere, that no evaporation takes place, and the ink is always fresh to the last.</p><p >Price 3s., 2s. 9d., 2s. 6d., 2s., 1s. 9d., 1s. 6d., and 1s. 3d.</p></div><div type="section"><head >SUNDRIES.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Extra Superfine Wax, red or black, per 1b.</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine red or black, per 1b.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Parcel red or black, per 1b.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Wafers, best mixed per 1b.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Wafers, patent mixed per 1b.</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Wafers, Vermilion Chequered, for affixing to paper deeds per box</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Foolscap</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Post 4to.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Foolscap 4to.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Letter and Invoice Clips each 8d. to</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Office Bags, large blue, lined each</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Office Bags, small blue, lined each</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Office Bags, large crimson, lined each</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Office Bags, small crimson, lined each</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Black Ebony Office Rules per inch</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1½</cell></row><row><cell>Patent Endorsement Boxes, supplied with liquid ink, dampers, cleaning brushes, &amp;c., for the better use of brass stamps each</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Wax Vesta Lights per 1,000</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Vermilion Fluid, for red lining skins</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Vermilion Powders</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Red Tape, 16 per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Red Tape, 24 per dozen</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Red Tape, 32 per dozen</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>China Grass, 32 per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Union Cord, 32 per reel</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Green Silk Tags for files per dozen</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Pounce Boxes, japanned, with rubber each</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Desk Knives, cocoa handles each</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Erasers cocoa handles each</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Office Hones, in mahogany case each</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Indian Rubber Bottle, prime thick per 1b.</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Indian Rubber Patent per 1b.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Bodkins Rubber, with or without eyes per 1b.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Tin Pens, for ruling Parchment per 1b.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Skinholders per 1b.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Parchment Knives per 1b.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Paper Pounce per 1b.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Parchment Pounce per 1b.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Solid Writing Pads, demy folio each</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Wafer Seals, ebony each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Indian Ink per stick, 6d., 1s., and</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Drawing Pins per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Drawing, Albata</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Ivory Folders, or Paper Knives each</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Outsides Writing Paper per 1b.</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>String and Twine per 1b.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Letter Cages 5s.</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Cash Boxes 7s. 6d.</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Deed Boxes 11s. 6d., 18s.</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Pen Trays, in ebony and gutta percha</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Tape Winders 5s. 6d.</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>String Boxes 2s., 3s.</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Taper Stands</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Pen Racks</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Date Boxes 1s. 6d.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Paper Weights 1s., 2s.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Waterlow's Original Office and Commercial Pencil, French polished per dozen</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Second quality, Original Office and Commercial Pencil, French polished per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >LEVER EMBOSSING AND SEALING PRESS <lb/> WITH STEEL DIE AND COUNTER-DIE COMPLETE, £2 2s.</p><p >POSTAGE SCALES AND BALANCES.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Beam Scales, to weigh 8 oz.</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>per pair.</cell></row><row><cell>Beam Scales, to weigh 16 oz.</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>per pair.</cell></row><row><cell>Beam Scales, to weigh 2 lbs.</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>per pair.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Improved Balances, to weigh 16 oz.</cell><cell>17s. 6d</cell></row><row><cell>Improved, for deeds and Parcels, to weight 2 lbs.</cell><cell>£1 10</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8b"/><head >BY ROYAL LETTERS PATENT.</head><p >PATRONIZED BY H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT.</p><p >WATERLOWS' <lb/> PATENT <lb/> AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, <lb/> OR PORTABLE <lb/> PRINTING MACHINE, <lb/> FOR THE COUNTING HOUSE, OFFICE, OR LIBRARY, <lb/> BY MEANS OF WHICH <lb/> EVERY PERSON MAY BECOME HIS OWN PRINTER.</p><p >The Process is extremely simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing, piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.</p><p >The Press is manufactured in three sizes, and the whole Apparatus is contained in neat boxes, French polished. It is now in use in some of the first establishments in this country and abroad, and may be seen at work at the Establishment of the Patentees, where also may be seen testimonials from various firms having the press constantly in use. It will be found a great desideratum in all Bankers' Establishments in multiplying copies of their letters to branches, with despatch and secrecy. Among the many notices of this useful invention in the leading Journals of the day, it is deemed sufficient to quote but one, explaining its merits:—</p><div type="section"><head >From the City Article of “The TIMES,” Sept. 6, 1850.</head><p >“A very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, which will be productive of great convenience to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared paper with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly valuable.”</p></div><div type="section"><p >Feeling convinced of the great utility of this invention, and anticipating a large sale, the Patentees have determined upon offering them at the following low prices, which include everything pertaining to the Press, and full instructions for using it.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>To print a subject 14 × 9</cell><cell>£5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>complete</cell></row><row><cell>To print a subject 16 × 10</cell><cell>£6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>complete</cell></row><row><cell>To print a subject 18 × 13</cell><cell>£7</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>complete</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >STATIONERY CASES, OF POLISHED MAHOGANY OR OAK.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>No. 1, with secret drawer, lock, and key, &amp;c., to hold foolscap and letter papers, envelopes, wax, &amp;c., and fitted with pen-tray and inkstand</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>No. 2, for large letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c.</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>No. 3, for small letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c.</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Sufficient paper, envelopes, &amp;c., to fill the above cases, of the best quality, would be respectively about 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >These Stationery Cases are admirably adapted for <lb/> presents.</p><p >65 to 68, London Wall, <lb/> 49, PARLIAMENT ST., &amp; 24, BIRCHIN LANE, CORNHILL, <lb/> LONDON.</p></div></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9b"/><head >ANTI-BLEAK HOUSE</head><p >A BLEAK HOUSE that is indeed, where the north winds meet to howl an ignoble concert, and bitter blasts mourn like tortured spirits of rebels, who, though prisoners, are unsubdued; where the whirlwind and the hurricane vow their vengeance; and the walls and timbers creak resistance, and, like wounded gladiators, rise again boldly to defy the antagonist. Woe to the inhabitant of the Bleak House if he is not armed with the weapons of an OVERCOAT and a SUIT of FASHIONABLE and substantial Clothing, such as can only be obtained at E. MOSES &amp; SON'S Establishments, Aldgate and Minories, New Oxford-street, and Hart-street, London; or 36, Fargate, Sheffield, or 19, Bridge-street, Bradford, Yorkshire. Who would covet a Bleak House in the month of March, when the old winds take out a fresh license, and to celebrate their re-commencement in a roaring trade, toss over a few houses, and as if churches were not good enough, but must be punished by their harmless spires being blown down,—or tear up a tree or two to save the boys the trouble of stealing the fruit next autumn, then becoming more mischievous, they toss over an unprotected traveller, and after that blow him up in grand style. But the Anti-Bleak House, the establishment whose inventions can annihilate the effects of biting, pinching, screwing, and driving bleak winds, is E. MOSES &amp; SON'S; they are determined their garments shall be proof against bleak winds and heavy showers, against cold blasts and sweeping hurricane: for this purpose they have invented garments which no wind can penetrate, which fit so exactly to the person of the wearer, that they render him secure as if he occupied an Anti-Bleak House, where the March winds having received due notice to quit, dare not remain for fear of having double rent to pay, by spending their fury without any recompense. E. MOSES AND SON are perfectly satisfied of the resistance their dress will offer to wind or water, being prepared specially for <hi rend="italics">March,</hi> strong, but neat, fine, but substantial, warm, but light, comfortable, but fashionable, the designs of artists, whose fame is identified with the success of E. MOSES &amp; SON for manufacturing the only elegant and Anti-Bleak garments in the kingdom, these are characterised by interminable variety, intrinsic excellence, superb quality, and unprecedented in the lowness of the charge—they are the quintessence of fashion, the emblems of true taste, the unrivalled embodiments of grace and neatness, and the approved essentials of gentility and durability.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><head>WINTER OVERCOATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>The new Bequeme Overcoat, designed by E. MOSES &amp; SON £1 5s. to</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Pea Coats, from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Coloured and Plain Witney Overcoats, in all shapes, from 15s. to</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The Bulwer</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The Premier, expressly made for this establishment 12s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The Albert Cape, made in the most approved waterproof materials, including the Devonshire Kersey, lined throughout, and velvet collar £1 5s. to</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>BOYS WINTER OVERCOATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Chesterfield, from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>The Byron Jacket and Overcoat, in all materials</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Prince of Wales' Wrapper, elegantly trimmed, and in various materials</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Dress Coats</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super Coats</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Best manufactured</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Frock Coats</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super Coats</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Best manufactured</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>WAISTCOATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Fancy Vests, from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Witney and plain cloth</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Satin, plain and figure</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Black cloth</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black cloth, best manufactured</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>White Marcella 4s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>TROUSERS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Fancy Trousers, from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Buckskin</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black cloth</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black and Fancy Doeskin</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Best Black Cassimere Trousers</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Boys' Hussar and Tunic Suits 18s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Summer cloth, with <unclear/> train</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Superior cloth</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine cloth</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LIVERIES.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Page's suit</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Footman's</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Groom's</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Coachman's</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MOURNING.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Ready made at Five Minutes' Notice.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Suit complete</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Boy's complete</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Made to Measure in Five Hours.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >NOTICE.—The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the season.</p><p >The “Universal Guide” a newspaper, containing daily events, &amp;c., and full directions for self-measurement, can be had gratis on application or forwarded post free to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >OBSERVE.—Any article purchased either ready made or made to measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged or the money returned.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON have no connection with any other house, in or out of London, except the following:—</p><p >London City Establishments:—154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, 86, Aldgate, opposite the Church, all communicating.</p><p >London West End Branch:—506, 507, 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, 3, Hart-street, all communicating.</p><p >Bradford, Yorkshire Branch, 19, Bridge-street.</p><p >Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p><p >TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT &amp; SHOE MAKERS, <lb/> AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed from sunset, on Friday, till sunset, on Saturday, when business is</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">resumed till</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10b"/><head >HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS,</head><p >Sent free by post.</p><p >It contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One Hundred <lb/> Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, Mahogany, <lb/> Rosewood, and Walnut Tree Woods;</p><p >Also their <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Their New Warerooms enable them to keep one of each design fixed for inspection.</hi></p><p >They have also, in addition to their usual stock, a great variety of the best designs of <lb/> PARISIAN BEDSTEADS, <lb/> BOTH IN WOOD AND IRON, WHICH THEY HAVE JUST IMPORTED.</p><p >HEAL &amp; SON, <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTURERS, <lb/> 196, (opposite the Chapel), Tottenham Court Road.</p><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</p></div></back></text></TEI>