<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>Bleak House, No. VI:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882.</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Maura McKee</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca. 220K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_pageBleak House</title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> 62 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LondonBradbury &amp; Evans</publisher><date>1852</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number RBC Dickens 21 c. 2 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-21"> Jill Kuhn Sexton finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-29">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><titlePage><titlePart type="main"> No. VI. </titlePart><docDate> AUGUST.</docDate><docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
<lb/>AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.<lb/>
The Author of this Work notifies that it is his intention to reserve the <lb/> right of translating it.
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><head >TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</head><p >EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT.</p><p >WEIGHT 10 oz.</p><p >Sole Manufacturers of the celebrated Pocket Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on Saddle; the most <hi rend="italics">important</hi> feature in this <hi rend="italics">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.—Price according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat.</p><p >NOTICE.—NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p><p >EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, <lb/> Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head><p >WATERPROOF—“The lightest and most effectual, is the SIPHONIA, made by EDMISTON &amp; SON, of 69, Strand; they can be carried in the hat or pocket.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life, April</hi> 20<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><p >“A new waterproof garment adapted to the vary changeable weather of the season, has been manufactured by EDMISTON &amp; SON. It is remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome umbrella.”—<hi rend="italics">Home News, May</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><list  type="simple"><item>Leggings or Overalls.</item><item>Yacht Jackets.</item><item>Fishing and Shooting Hats or Caps.</item><item>Driving Gloves.</item><item>Cricketing Gloves.</item><item>Gun Covers.</item><item>Gig Aprons.</item><item>Sou-Westers.</item><item>Goloshes.</item><item>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods.</item><item>Ladies' Paletots.</item><item>Air Cushions.</item><item>Air Pillows.</item><item>Air Beds.</item><item>India Rubber Portable Folding Baths.</item><item>Nursing Aprons.</item><item>Crib Sheets.</item><item>The newly invented Swimming Gloves, <lb/> Of great propelling power.</item></list><p >EDMISTON'S LIFE-BELTS NONE SHOULD BE WITHOUT.</p><p >FISHING AND SHOOTING BOOTS, soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every description of India Rubber and Gutta Pereha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c.</p><p >BELFAST—ALBION CLOTH COMPANY. EDINBURGH—GRIEVE &amp; OLIVER, Princes-street. LIVERPOOL—J. H. SMITH, 22, Lord-street. SHAFTESBURY—JAS. WHITE. GUISBORO'—ROBINSON. HANLEY—THED SMITH. LERWICK—HICKS. PORTSMOUTH—SEAGROVE, BROTHERS. SOUTHAMPTON—BATTEN &amp; SOUTHAMPTON.</p><p >LONDON, EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, near the Adelphi.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. VI—AUGUST 1852.</opener><head >BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head><div><head >DAKIN &amp; COMPANY</head><p >Even in the midst of the excitement of a general election, and of anxiety felt with regard to future fiscal arrangements, the domestic tea-table cannot be altogether forgotten. It must always be a matter of importance to consumers to know where to obtain Teas and Coffees of the finest qualities at the most moderate prices, and hence it must be necessary always to bear in mind the Establishment at the corner of <hi rend="italics">Saint Paul's Churchyard,</hi> where <lb/> DAKIN AND COMPY.</p><p >continue to supply Teas and Coffees of the best kinds and of the finest growths at <lb/> Merchants' prices.</p><p >All Orders from any part of the Metropolitan districts, within Eight Miles of Saint Paul's, will be delivered by DAKIN &amp; Compy's Vans, on the day after such Orders are received.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><opener >MR. HOGARTH has the honour to announce for Publication, a Portrait-subject, by Mr. MACLISE, R.A., from <lb/> LORD BYRON'S TRAGEDY OF “WERNER,” <lb/> REPRESENTING</opener><head >W. C. MACREADY, ESQ.,</head><p >IN HIS CELEBRATED PERSONATION OF THAT CHARACTER.</p><p >Engraved in the highest style of Line, by W. C. SHARPE, from the picture by D. MACLISE, Esq., R.A., in the possession of JOHN FORSTER, Esq. Artist's Proofs, £5 5s.; Autograph Proofs, £3 3s.; Prints, £1 1ls. 6d.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >ETON MONTEM.</head><p >THE SCHOOL-YARD, <lb/> AND <lb/> THE PLAYING-FIELDS, <lb/> TWO VIEWS ILLUSTRATIVE OF ETON MONTEM.</p><p >PAINTED BY WILLIAM EVANS, ESQ., ENGRAVED BY CHARLES LEWIS.</p><p >The time chosen is “The Halt” in the School-yard in the morning, before the march to Salt-Hill, at the moment of flourishing the Flag by the Ensign before Her Majesty; and the “Playing-fields,” at the time of the Evening Absence. The Drawings were made on the spot by Mr. EVANS, of Eton, for J. H. SMYTH PIGOTT, Esq., of Brockley. The Prices to Subscribers will be, for—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Artist's Proofs</cell><cell>£12</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0 the pair.</cell></row><row><cell>Proofs on India Paper</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0 the pair.</cell></row><row><cell>Proofs with Letters</cell><cell>£5 </cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0 the pair.</cell></row><row><cell>Prints</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0 the pair.</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >TWO VIEWS OF <lb/> SALISBURY CATHEDRAL,</head><p >FROM THE GARDEN AND THE CLOISTERS.</p><p >FROM ORIGINAL DRAWINGS BY OWEN B. CARTER, ARCHITECT, WINCHESTER.</p><p >Mr. HOGARTH has made arrangements with Mr. OWEN CARTER for the production of a large and important SET OF DRAWINGS, exhibiting the Beauties of our PRINCIPAL CATHEDRALS, upon a scale calculated to do justice to the magnificent variety which they individually and collectively present. Two Views of SALISBURY CATHEDRAL for the Series are now ready, and will be published uniform with the other DRAWINGS IN TINTED LITHOGRAPHY, executed in the best style of Art. The Drawings will be published in succession as they are completed.</p><p >Subscribers' Names are now received by the Publisher, and by the principal Printsellers, either for single Prints or the whole Work, which is limited to Twenty Subjects.</p><p >
<table><head>Size of the Prints, 27¼ by 24½ inches, exclusive of margin. PRICE.</head><row><cell>Prints</cell><cell>£1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Prints, Coloured</cell><cell>£2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >London: Published by J. HOGARTH, 5, HAYMARKET; and G. BROWN, Bookseller, SALISBURY.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >This day is published, Second Edition, 2 vols. crown 8vo., 12s. cloth.</opener><head >THE WIDE, WIDE WORLD.</head><p >BY ELIZABETH WETHERELL.</p><p >“This work has attained a popularity which we may safely say is unprecedented in the annals of our literature. It has been published little more than a year, and is new verging towards its <hi rend="italics">fourteenth</hi> edition.”—<hi rend="italics">New York Home Journal.</hi></p><p >JAMES NISBET &amp; CO., 21, Berners-street; HAMILTON, ADAMS, &amp; CO., Paternoster-row.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just published, in 2 vols. crown 8vo., 12s. cloth,</opener><head >QUEECHY.</head><p >BY ELIZABETH WETHERELL.</p><p >Author of “THE WIDE, WIDE WORLD.”</p><p >JAMES NISBET &amp; CO., 21, Berners-street; HAMILTON, ADAMS, &amp; CO., Paternoster-row.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE <lb/> LETTERS of a VAGABOND</head><p >will appear Next Month in <lb/> THE “LEADER” NEWSPAPER, <lb/> Published every Saturday, price Sixpence.</p><p >OFFICE, 7, WELLINGTON STREET, STRAND.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BEAUTIES OF ALL THE POETS.</head><p >Published on August 1st., 1852, in Foolscape 8vo, Part 1, price 6d.; to be completed in Ten Monthly Parts.</p><p >A CYCLOPÆDIA OF POETICAL QUOTATIONS; consisting of Choice Passages from the Poets of Every Age and Country, classified under distinct Heads, and Alphabetically arranged for Ready Reference. With a Copious Index of Subjects and Authors' Names. Edited by H. G. ADAMS, Author of “Favourite Song Birds,” &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >London: GROOMBRIDGE &amp; SONS, 5, Paternoster-row.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALBANY LAMP AND CANDLE-MANUFACTORY —</head><p >CLARKE'S Russian Wax Candles, 1s. per lb., burn superior to all others. Best Albany Composite Candles, 8d. per lb., do not require snuffing: for ordinary purposes the Cheapest Candles that can be used, Moulds, 6d., Store Candles, 5d. per lb.; Express Pale Soap, very old and dry, 548. per cwt.; Good Yellow, 50s, and 44s.; Best Mottled, 56s.; Honey Soap, 1s.; Old Brown Windsor, 2s.; all other Scented Soaps, 1s. 6d. per lb.; Patent Albany Oil, 5s. 6d per gallon, superior to Sperm; CLARKE'S Refined Oil for French Lamps, 4s. 6d. per gallon; Solar, 3s. 6d. Italian goods of the finest quality at the Wholesale Price; Lamps of every description manufactured on the premises, for cash only.</p><p >SAMUEL CLARKE, Albany Lamp and Candle Manufactory, 55, Albany street, Regent's-park, London, within two minutes' walk of the Colosseum.</p><p >N.B. Country Orders, amounting to £10 or upwards, Carriage Free.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><p >AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF WILLIAM JERDAN; with his Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences and Correspondence, during the last Forty Years. 2nd Volume, with Portrait of George Canning, and View of Gloucester Lodge. Price 5s. Post 8vo. cloth gilt. [<hi rend="italics">Published this day.</hi></p><p >THE CELT, THE ROMAN, AND THE SAXON. A History of the Early Inhabitants of Britain down to the Conversion of the Anglo-Saxons to Christianity. By THOMAS WRIGHT, Esq., M.A., F.S.A. With numerous Illustrations. Price 8s., post 8vo. cloth.</p><p >NINEVEH AND PERSEPOLIS, By W. S. W. Vaux, M.A. Third Edition, revised and enlarged, in post 8vo., with numerous Illustrations. Price 8s. bound in cloth; or 17s. morocco antique.</p><p >HOMES OF THE NEW WORLD. Impressions of America. By FREDERIKA BREMER, translated by Mr. Howitt. [<hi rend="italics">In preparation.</hi></p><p >SPECIMENS OF OLD INDIAN POETRY. Translated from the Original Sanskrit into English Verse, by RALPH T. II. GRIFFITHS, M.A., M.R.A.S., and Boden Sanskrit Scholar in the University of Oxford. Price 5s., post 8vo., cloth.</p><p >OLD FOREST RANGER; or, Wild Sports of India in the Neil- gherry Hills, in the Jungles, and on the Plains. By MAJOR WALTER CAMPBELL, of Skipness. With Illustrations on Steel. New Edition, in post 8vo. [<hi rend="italics">In preparation.</hi></p><p >A WEEK AT KILLARNEY. By Mr. &amp; Mrs. S. C. Hall. Being a Guide to Tourists to the Lakes of Killarney. Illustrated by Engravings on Steel and Wood, with Maps. New Edition, revised by a recent visit. Price 10s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p><p >MEMORIALS OF EARLY CHRISTIANITY; presenting, in a graphic, compact, and popular form some of the memorable events of Early Ecclesiastical History. By the Rev. J. G. MIALL, author of “Footsteps of Our Forefathers,” in post 8vo., with Illustrations.</p><p >FOOTSTEPS OF OUR LORD AND HIS APOSTLES, in Syria, Greece, and Italy. A Succession of Visits to the Scenes of New Testament Narrative, by W. H. BARTLETT. Third Edition, with Twenty-three Engravings on Steel, price 14s. cloth gilt edges; or 26s. morocco elegant.</p><p >BALLADS FOR THE TIMES, and other Poems. By Martin FARQUHAR TUPPER, Esq., D.C.L., F.R.S., &amp;c. &amp;c. Second Complete Edition, price 7s. 6d., with Vignette and Frontispiece, uniform with “PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.”</p><p >MODERN ROMANISM. By B. B. Woodward, B.A.</p><p >“Their religion, the more considered, the less can be acknowledged a religion; but a Roman principality rather; endeavouring to keep up her old universal dominion under a new name, and mere shadow of a Catholic Religion.”—MILTON. [<hi rend="italics">In preparation.</hi></p><p >THE CANADIAN CRUSOES. By Mrs. Traill (late Catherine Parr Strickland), author of “The Backwoods of Canada.” Price 6s., in fcap., cloth, gilt edges, with numerous Illustrations. [<hi rend="italics">Published this day.</hi></p><p >LOVE A REALITY, NOT ROMANCE. By Mrs. Thomas Geldart, author of “Truth is Everything,” &amp;c. With Illustrations by Gilbert. Price 3s. 6d. fcap., cloth, gilt edges.</p><p >YE MAIDEN and MARRIED LIFE of MARY POWELL, after- wards MISTRESS MILTON. New Edition, in post 8vo., with Portrait. Price 7s. 6d. antique.</p><p >YE HOUSEHOLD OF SIR THOMAS MORE. Libellus a Margareta More, quindecim annos nata, Chelseiae inceptus. Uniform with “Mary Powell.”</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, AND CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >THE TEN GUINEA HARMONIUM</head><p >has the full compass of five octaves, a powerful rich tone, and never requires tuning: is suited for Churches, Chapels, Schools, &amp;c., producing a sustained tone, susceptible of the utmost expression. An extensive variety of HARMONIUMS, with the Patent Pianoforte Hammer-action, from Sixteen to Twenty Guineas each.</p><p >WARREN'S TUTOR for the above, 4s. WHEATSTONE &amp; CO., Inventors and Patentees of the Concertina, who were awarded the only Exhibition Prize Medal for Harmoniums, 20, CONDUIT STREET, REGENT STREET.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MR. HENRY LOVELL'S NEW SONGS,</head><p >composed by N. J. SPORLE, and sung by Miss POOLE, Miss BLANCHE YOUNGE, Mr. GEORGE BUCKLAND, and others, are enjoying an unprecedented popularity in the Drawing Room, the School Room, and the Lecture Theatre.</p><p >“Of easy compass, never rising above E, and possessed of a catching melody, any one, with the least voice or ear, will find them decided acquisitions to their repertoire.”</p><p >The SERIO-COMIC BALLADS are, “St. Valentine's Day is a Dangerous Time,” “Faint Heart never won Fair Lady,” “A Friend in need is a Friend indeed,” “That's the Man,” “Draw round the Fire,” “Hope deferred,” and “Evergreen Leaves.”</p><p >G. CASE, 32, NEW BOND STREET.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER</head><p >is the most certain and elegant preparation for the removal of superfluous hair on the arms, neck, and face, so inimical to beauty. The genuine is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed “G. H. Hogard” for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor by Mr. HOOPER, Chemist, 24, Russell-street, Covent-garden, and 43, London-bridge, City, and by all respectable Perfumers, in packets, price 4s.; double ditto, 7s.; or by post, free, for 50 or 88 postage stamps.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HOLLOWAY'S PILLS, A MOST EFFICIENT REMEDY FOR BILE, INDIGESTION, AND DEBILITATED CONSTITUTIONS.—</head><p >The extraordinary powers of this medicine in curing disorders of the stomach, bile, indigestion, and liver complaints are wonderful. Thousands whose lives were a burden to them whilst suffering from these complaints are now enjoying the best of health by taking these invaluable pills, and now strongly recommend their use to others similarly afflicted. A few doses give relief, and a continuance of them for a short time effects a perfect cure. Persons whose constitutions have been weakened by long residence in hot climates cannot have a more certain remedy to restore them to robust health than Holloway's Pills.—Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOYER'S RELISH.</head><p >“To describe the Sauce would be to make our readers hungry,—rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poured.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p><p >THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents.</p><p >CROSSE AND ELACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen. GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >LADIES' BONNETS, <lb/> DUNSTABLE, RICE, CHIP.</head><p >English and Foreign Fancy Bonnets, in every shape, every size, and every quality. A large and superior assortment of Leghorn Bonnets and Children's Hats.</p><p >Millinery Bonnets in all colours and of the newest designs in shape and material. Also a variety of the choicest Bonnets direct from the first houses in Paris. Morning Bonnets. Wedding Bonnets.</p><p >ALL AT THE LOWEST POSSIBLE PRICES, FOR CASH ONLY.</p><p >BETHEL WARE, 217, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS</head><p >Differ from other Patterns, not merely in shape and design, but in their great superiority of Fit, quality of Material, and Workmanship.—<hi rend="italics">Globe, April</hi> 12, 1852. They are of two prices; viz. Six for 40s.; Second Quality Six for 30s. in both of which the principle is strictly carried out.</p><p >List of Prices, and mode of Self-measurement sent free per Post.</p><p >FORD'S REGISTERED SHIRT COLLARS, 11s. per dozen.</p><p >Patterns of the New Coloured Shirtings in every variety of Colours. Upwards of 200 different styles for making FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS sent to select from on the receipt of six postage stamps. Price 27s. the half dozen.</p><p >RICHARD FORD, 38, POULTRY, <lb/> LONDON, (Late 185, Strand.)</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >NOTICE OF REMOVAL.</opener><head >THE BABY JUMPER,</head><p >TO No. 18, TICHBORNE STREET, REGENT'S QUADRANT. (Near to SWAN &amp; EDGAR'S.)</p><p >This most useful and very interesting invention continues to give the most perfect satisfaction, and only requires to be seen to insure its introduction into every Nursery. Manufactured and Sold, Wholesale. Retail, and for Exportation, by H. S. ROGERS &amp; CO., 18, Tichborne street, Regent-street, late of 137, Strand. Price from 10s. to 30s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><head >Chubb's Fire-proof Safes and Locks.</head><p >CHUBB &amp; SON <lb/> Have now on Sale, at their Warehouses, an Assortment of their <lb/> FIRE-PROOF SAFES, <lb/> WHICH GAINED THE PRIZE MEDAL, WITH <lb/> SPECIAL APPROBATION, at the Great Exhibition, this distinction being awarded to them SOLELY by the Jurors of Class XXII., after a careful comparison with those of other makers from all parts of England.</p><p >These SAFES, undoubtedly the MOST SECURE FROM FORCE, FRAUD, and FIRE, are sold at moderate prices.</p><p >CHUBB'S LOCKS, with all the recent improvements, CASH BOXES and DEED BOXES of all sizes, may be inspected.</p><p >IRON DOORS and FRAMES for Strong Rooms.</p><p >Complete Lists, with Prices, will be sent on application.</p><p >CHUBB &amp; SON, 57, St. Paul's Churchyard, London; 28, Lord-street, Liverpool; 16, Market-street, Manchester; and Hornsley Fields, Wolverhampton.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRT.</head><p >No. 84.</p><p >31s. 6d. &amp; 37s. 6d. the Half-dozen.</p><p >THE most comfortable and perfect-fitting Shirts extant, combining the highest degree of excellence at the smallest cost. Satisfaction (as usual) guaranteed. or the money returned.</p><p >Superb Dress Shirts for evening wear, 6s. 6d., 7s, 6d., and 8s. 6d. each. Also, Fashionable Coloured Shirts, ready made, or made to order, 20s. 26s., and 31s. 6d. the half-dozen. A choice of 200 New Patterns.</p><p >The general Ready-made Stock is the best, the cheapest, and the largest assortment of Shirts in London, and embraces all the recent improvements in the art.</p><p >Illustrated Priced Lists, with directions for self-measurement, and full particulars, gratis and post-free.</p><p >Patterns of the new and elegant designs for Coloured Shirts sent post-paid on receipt of Four Stamps.</p><p >RODGERS &amp; CO., Shirt Makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing Cross, and No. 29, at the Corner of New-street, Covent-garden, London. Established Sixty Years.—N.B. Boys' Shirts in all Sizes.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy and preserving the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned. “ROBERT SHAW, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp, without which none is genuine. Prices, 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT!</head><p >METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN.</p><p >BY ROYAL COMMAND.</p><p >JOSEPH GILLOTT most respectfully begs to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic Institutions, and the Public generally, that by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times, he has introduced a <hi rend="italics">new series</hi> of his useful productions, which for <hi rend="italics">excellence of temper, quality of material,</hi> and, above all, <hi rend="italics">cheapness in price,</hi> he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition. Each pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of Boxes, containing One Gross each, with Label outside, and fac-simile of his signature.</p><p >Victoria Works, Graham-street, Birmingham, April 20th, 1852.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CLERICAL, MEDICAL, and GENERAL LIFE ASSURANCE SOCIETY.</head><p >Persons of all ages, and in every station, may assure with this Society, and the assured can reside in any part of Europe, the Holy Land, Egypt, Madeira, the Cape, Australia, New Zealand, and in most parts of North and South America, <hi rend="italics">without extra charge.</hi></p><p >FIFTH DIVISION OF PROFITS.</p><p >The FIFTH BONUS was declared in January last, and the amount varied with the different ages, from 24½ to 55 per cent. on the Premiums paid, during the last five years; or from £1 to £2.10s. per cent. per annum, on the sums assured.</p><p >The small share of Profit divisible in future among the Shareholders being now provided for, without entrenching on the amount made by the regular business, the ASSURED will hereafter derive all the benefits obtainable from a Mutual Office, with, at the same time, complete freedom from liability, secured by an ample Proprietary Capital,—thus combining, in the same office, <hi rend="italics">all the advantages of both systems.</hi></p><p >A copy of the last Report, setting forth full particulars, with a Prospectus, can now be obtained of any of the Society's Agents, or by addressing a line to GEO. H. PINCKARD, Resident Secretary.</p><p >99, Great Russell-street, Bloomsbury, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >EQUITY AND LAW LIFE ASSURANCE SOCIETY.</head><p >No. 26, LINCOLN'S INN FIELDS, LONDON.</p><p >Policies in this Office are INDISPUTABLE, except in cases of FRAUD.</p><p >“Free Policies” are issued, at a small increased rate of Premium, which remain in force although the Life assured may go to any part of the World.</p><p >Parties Assuring within Six Months of their last Birth-day, are allowed a proportionate diminution in the Premium.</p><p >The Tables are especially favourable to Young and Middle-aged Lives, and the Limits allowed to the Assured, without extra charge, are unusually extensive.</p><p >Eighty per cent. of the Profits are divided at the end of every Five Years among the Assured. At the first Division, to the end of 1849, the addition to the amount Assured averaged above 50 per cent. on the Premiums paid.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >SCHWEPPE'S SODA, POTASS and MAGNESIA WATERS and AERATED LEMONADE continue to be manufactured upon the largest scale at their several Establishments in London, Liverpool, Bristol, and Derby. The celebrity of these well-known waters, and the preference they universally command, are evidences that their original superior quality over all others is well sustained. Every bottle is protected by a label with the name of their firm, without which none is genuine, and it may be had of nearly all respectable chemists throughout the kingdom. Importers of the German Selters Water direct from the springs, as for the last twenty years.</p><p >51, BERNERS STREET, LONDON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >PRIZE MEDAL.</head><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN, Manufacturing Goldsmiths, Established A.D. 1798, beg to announce to the Nobility, Gentry, and Public in general, that in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them since the Great Exhibition, they have resolved to throw open their Manufactory to the public at <hi rend="italics">Manufacturers' Prices,</hi> a closer connexion than has hitherto existed between the real worker in the precious metals and the Public, being obviously an advantage to both parties.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S dealings will be principally to establish confidence in the gold employed in the manufacture of chains, where at present the greatest uncertainty exists, owing to the prevalence of electro-gilt articles, and weighing chains, frequently as low as 11 carats fine=38s. 11¼d., against sovereigns of 22 carats fine=77s. 10½. per oz., when there is no analogy between one and the other; a chain weighing 5 sovereigns being intrinsically worth only 50s. The object of the vendor is wholly to conceal the remaining 50s.</p><p >Gold is capable of being alloyed to any extent, and in order to protect the public, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN will make the Mint-price of 77s. 10½d. per oz. for British standard, the basis of all their operations, and making their profit on the workmanship alone, will charge the bullion in their chains at its intrinsic value, undertaking to repurchase it at any time at the same price: thus—</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>per oz.</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>15 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell><cell>53s.</cell><cell>1d.</cell></row><row><cell>18 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell><cell>63s.</cell><cell>8½d.</cell></row><row><cell>22 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise the Mint-price of</cell><cell>77s.</cell><cell>10½d.</cell></row></table>
</p><p >The price for workmanship will be charged according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern. For example—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>A Chain weighing 2 oz. of 15 Carat</cell><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Gold is worth, at 53s. 1d. per oz.</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2 intrinsic value.</cell></row><row><cell>Supposing the Workmanship to be</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>£7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table>
</p><p >By this arrangement the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">bullion</hi> in a gold chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S Stock consists of Gold Guard Chains, Albert Chains, Seals, Keys, Rings, Brooches, Bracelets, Diamond Setting, and every description of Goldsmiths' and Jewellers' Work, all made on the premises.</p><p >MANUFACTORY, No. 16, Henrietta-street, Covent-garden, London: where the processes of manipulation may be seen by those who are interested in the subject.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >LADIES TRAVELLING, <lb/> OR DURING THE DRIVE, AQUATIC EXCURSION, <lb/> or while otherwise exposed to the scorching rays of the Sun, and heated particles of Dust, will find</opener><head >ROWLAND'S <lb/> KALYDOR</head><p >a most refreshing preparation for the Complexion, dispelling the cloud of languor and relaxation, allaying all heat and irritability, and immediately affording the pleasing sensation attending restored elasticity and healthful state of the skin. Composed of choice exotics of balsamic nature, utterly free from all mineral admixture, and pleasing and delightful in its effects, ROWLANDS' KALYDOR tends to neutralise the effects of atmosphere upon the Skin, and to promote that healthy action of the microscopic vessels, by which its general well-being and the beauty of its appearance are so essentially promoted. Freckles, Tan, Spots, Pimples, Flushes, and Discolorations fly before its application, and give place to delicate clearness with the glow of beauty and of bloom. In cases of Sunburn, or Stings of Insects, its virtues have long been acknowledged.</p><p >Its <hi rend="italics">purifying and refreshing properties</hi> have obtained its selection by Royalty, and the several Courts throughout Europe, together with the <hi rend="italics">elite</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">Aristocracy.</hi>—Price 4s. 6d. and 8s. 6d. per bottle.</p><p >CAUTION.—The words ROWLANDS' KALYDOR are on the wrapper of each bottle.</p><p >Sold by A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS, 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by all Chemists and Perfumers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.—</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell>Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose</cell><cell>As dotted 1 to 1.</cell><cell>Inches.</cell><cell>Eighths.</cell></row><row><cell>From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required</cell><cell>As dotted 2 to 2.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows</cell><cell>As marked 3 to 3.</cell><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >‘THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY £1 10s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >70 BARKER &amp; COMPY. 70</head><p >The Anthropos.<lb/>£2 2 0</p><p >The Omega Shirts.<lb/>6 for £1 18 6</p><p >
<table><row><cell>THE ANTHROPOS OVER COAT</cell><cell>£2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>BLACK SAXONY DRESS COAT, SILK LININGS</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>BLACK SAXONY FROCK COAT, SILK LININGS</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>BLACK DRESS TROWSERS</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>SHRUNK SUMMER ANGOLA TROWSERS</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>NEW MORNING COAT</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>MORNING CASHMERE VEST</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>DERBY OVER COAT</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>DRESSING GOWNS</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>OMEGA SHIRTS SIX FOR £1 18s. 6d.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >Barker &amp; Company, Clothiers and Shirt Makers, 70, Cornhill, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES,</head><p >of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >IN FULL DRESS.</p><p >WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p><p >INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS, <lb/> BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY. </p><p >BABY LINEN, IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p><p >TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p><p >An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >A SOVEREIGN REMEDY FOR BAD TEA.</head><p >A LEADEN PACKAGE, containing FIVE POUNDS of FINE, TRUE, RICH, RIPE, RARE SOUCHONG TEA (which will please everybody), sent, CARRIAGE FREE, to any part of England, on receipt of a Post-office Order for ONE SOVEREIGN, by <lb/> PHILLIPS AND COMPANY, TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> No. 8, KING WILLIAM-STREET, CITY, LONDON.</p><p >And will prove indeed a Sovereign Remedy for Bad Tea.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'s REGISTERED PARDESSUS,</head><p >(6 &amp; 7 VIC. CAP. 65,) <lb/> The distinguished patronage bestowed upon this really economical and truly elegant <lb/> LIGHT SPRING AND SUMMER WALKING OVER-COAT, <lb/> (which can also be worn without another), has had but few precedents. It is made of an extremely fine though durable cloth, and, from its peculiarly soft and silky nature, produces a sensation of the most complete ease and comfort; it may be had ready for immediate use in all sizes and colours, at the very moderate charge of TWO GUINEAS.—The Pardessus d'Ete, for Heat, Dust, and Rain, ONE GUINEA. </p><p >In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s, Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94, REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head><p >THE Patentees consider that the advantages of this Umbrella have been fairly demonstrated by the very great quantity that have been made and sold during the last 4 years, and their anticipations of its superiority over any other material for an umbrella fully borne out.</p><p >These Umbrellas are now sold by most dealers in the kingdom, from 10s. 6d. each, and may be had wholesale of several large manufacturers, who have taken licences, as well as of the Patentees, at their Wholesale and Shipping Warehouse, 75, Cheapside, where Merchants can be supplied with them as well as with all kinds of Silk and Gingham Umbrellas at the lowest prices for cash.</p><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER <lb/> PATENTEES.</p><list  type="simple"><item>140, Regent Street.</item><item>94, Fleet Street.</item><item>10, Royal Exchange.</item><item>75, Cheapside.</item></list><p >SOLE AGENTS FOR THE UNITED STATES, Messrs. F. DERBY, &amp; CO., 12, PARK PLACE. NEW YORK.</p></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><p ><figure xml:id="ill21"><p>Caddy's flowers.</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><p ><figure xml:id="ill22"><p>The little church in the park.</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; in Monthly Parts, and in Half-yearly Volumes,</hi></opener><head > HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST <lb/> IN THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p><p >FOUR VOLUMES are published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, in cloth boards, and are always on sale,</p><div><opener ><hi rend="italics">Also, published at the end of every Month, at the same Office, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head > THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS;</head><p >Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Excheqner, a Legal Publication, not coming <lb/> within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The First and Second Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of</hi> 1850—51, <hi rend="italics">may always</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">be had, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s. each, neatly bound in cloth.</hi></p><p >OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p161"/><head >CHAPTER XVII. <lb/> ESTHER'S NARRATIVE.</head><p >RICHARD very often came to see us while we remained in London (though he soon failed in his letter-writing), and with his quick abilities, his good spirits, his good temper, his gaiety and freshness, was always delightful. But, though I liked him more and more, the better I knew him, I still felt more and more how much it was to be regretted that he had been educated in no habits of application and concentration. The system which had addressed him in exactly the same manner as it had addressed hundreds of other boys, all varying in character and capacity, had enabled him to dash through his tasks, always with fair credit, and often with distinction; but in a fitful, dazzling way that had confirmed his reliance on those very qualities in himself, which it had been most desirable to direct and train. They were great qualities, without which no high place can be meritoriously won; but, like fire and water, though excellent servants, they were very bad masters. If they had been under Richard's direction, they would have been his friends; but, Richard being under their direction, they became his enemies.</p><p >I write down these opinions, not because I believe that this or any other thing was so, because I thought so; but only because I did think so, and I want to be quite candid about all I thought and did. These were my thoughts about Richard. I thought I often observed besides, how right my guardian was in what he had said; and that the uncertainties and delays of the Chancery suit had imparted to his nature something of the careless spirit of a gamester, who felt that he was part of a great gaming system.</p><p >Mr. and Mrs. Bayham Badger coming one afternoon, when my guardian was not at home, in the course of conversation I naturally inquired after Richard.</p><p >“Why, Mr. Carstone,” said Mrs. Badger, “is very well, and is, I assure you, a great acquisition to our society. Captain Swosser used to say of me that I was always better than land a-head and a breeze a-starn to the midshipmen's mess when the purser's junk had become as tough as the fore-topsel weather earings. It was his naval way of mentioning generally that I was an acquisition to any society. I may render the same tribute, I am sure, to Mr. Carstone. But, I—you won't think me premature if I mention it?”</p><p >I said no, as Mrs. Badger's insinuating tone seemed to require such an answer.</p><p >“Nor Miss Clare?” said Mrs. Bayham Badger, sweetly. Ada said no, too, and looked uneasy.</p><p >“Why, you see, my dears,” said Mrs. Badger—“you'll excuse my calling you my dears?”</p><p >We entreated Mrs. Badger not to mention it.</p><pb  xml:id="p162"/><p >“Because you really are, if I may take the liberty of saying so,” pursued Mrs. Badger, “so perfectly charming. You see, my dears, that although I am still young—or Mr. Bayham Badger pays me the compliment of saying so—”</p><p >“No,” Mr. Badger called out, like some one contradicting at a public meeting. “Not at all!”</p><p >“Very well,” smiled Mrs. Badger, “we will say still young.”</p><p >(“Undoubtedly,” said Mr. Badger.)</p><p >“My dears, though still young, I have had many opportunities of observing young men. There were many such on board the dear old Crippler, I assure you. After that, when I was with Captain Swosser in the Mediterranean, I embraced every opportunity of knowing and befriending the midshipmen under Captain Swosser's command. <hi rend="italics">You</hi> never heard them called the young gentlemen, my dears, and probably would not understand allusions to their pipeclaying their weekly accounts; but it is otherwise with me, for blue water has been a second home to me, and I have been quite a sailor. Again, with Professor Dingo.”</p><p >(“A man of European reputation,” murmured Mr. Badger.)</p><p >“When I lost my dear first, and became the wife of my dear second,” said Mrs. Badger, speaking of her former husbands as if they were parts of a charade, “I still enjoyed opportunities of observing youth. The class attendant on Professor Dingo's lectures was a large one, and it became my pride, as the wife of an eminent scientific man seeking herself in science the utmost consolation it could impart, to throw our house open to the students, as a kind of Scientific Exchange. Every Tuesday evening there was lemonade and a mixed biscuit, for all who chose to partake of those refreshments. And there was Science to an unlimited extent.”</p><p >(“Remarkable assemblies those, Miss Summerson,” said Mr. Badger, reverentially. “There must have been great intellectual friction going on there, under the auspices of such a man!”)</p><p >“And now,” pursued Mrs. Badger, “now that I am the wife of my dear third, Mr. Badger, I still pursue those habits of observation which were formed during the lifetime of Captain Swosser, and adapted to new and unexpected purposes during the lifetime of Professor Dingo. I therefore have not come to the consideration of Mr. Carstone as a Neophyte. And yet I am very much of the opinion, my dears, that he has not chosen his profession advisedly.”</p><p >Ada looked so very anxious now, that I asked Mrs. Badger on what she founded her supposition?</p><p >“My dear Miss Summerson,” she replied, “on Mr. Carstone's character and conduct. He is of such a very easy disposition, that probably he would never think it worth while to mention how he really feels; but, he feels languid about the profession. He has not that positive interest in it which makes it his vocation. If he has any decided impression in reference to it. I should say it was that it is a tiresome pursuit. Now, this is not promising. Young men, like Mr. Allan Woodcourt, who take to it from a strong interest in all that it can do, will find some reward in it through a great deal of work for a very little money, and through years of considerable endurance and disappointment. But I am quite convinced that this would never be the case with Mr. Carstone.”</p><pb  xml:id="p163"/><p >“Does Mr. Badger think so too?” asked Ada, timidly.</p><p >“Why,” said Mr. Badger, “to tell the truth, Miss Clare, this view of the matter had not occurred to me until Mrs. Badger mentioned it. But, when Mrs. Badger put it in that light, I naturally gave great consideration to it; knowing that Mrs. Badger's mind, in addition to its natural advantages, has had the rare advantage of being formed by two such very distinguished (I will even say illustrious) public men as Captain Swosser of the Royal Navy and Professor Dingo. The conclusion at which I have arrived is—in short, is Mrs. Badger's conclusion.”</p><p >“It was a maxim of Captain Swosser's,” said Mrs. Badger, “speaking in his figurative naval manner, that when you make pitch hot, you cannot make it too hot; and that if you only have to swab a plank, you should swab it as if Davy Jones were after you. It appears to me that this maxim is applicable to the medical, as well as to the nautical profession.”</p><p >“To all professions,” observed Mr. Badger. “It was admirably said by Captain Swosser. Beautifully said.”</p><p >“People objected to Professor Dingo, when we were staying in the North of Devon, after our marriage,” said Mrs. Badger, “that he disfigured some of the houses and other buildings, by chipping off fragments of those edifices with his little geological hammer. But the Professor replied, that he knew of no building, save the Temple of Science. The principle is the same, I think?”</p><p >“Precisely the same,” said Mr. Badger. “Finely expressed! The Professor made the same remark, Miss Summerson, in his last illness; when (his mind wandering) he insisted on keeping his little hammer under the pillow, and chipping at the countenances of the attendants. The ruling passion!”</p><p >Although we could have dispensed with the length at which Mr. and Mrs. Badger pursued the conversation, we both felt that it was disinterested in them to express the opinion they had communicated to us, and that there was a great probability of its being sound. We agreed to say nothing to Mr. Jarndyce until we had spoken to Richard; and, as he was coming next evening, we resolved to have a very serious talk with him.</p><p >So, after he had been a little while with Ada, I went in and found my darling (as I knew she would be) prepared to consider him thoroughly right in whatever he said.</p><p >“And how do you get on, Richard?” said I. I always sat down on the other side of him. He made quite a sister of me.</p><p >“O! well enough!” said Richard.</p><p >“He can't say better than that, Esther, can he?” cried my pet, triumphantly.</p><p >I tried to look at my pet in the wisest manner, but of course I couldn't.</p><p >“Well enough?” I repeated.</p><p >“Yes,” said Richard, “well enough. It's rather jog-trotty and humdrum. But it'll do as well as any thing else!”</p><p >“O! my dear Richard!” I remonstrated.</p><p >“What's the matter?” said Richard.</p><p >“Do as well as anything else!”</p><p >“I don't think there's any harm in that, Dame Durden,” said Ada,
<pb xml:id="p164"/>
looking so confidingly at me across him! “Because if it will do as well as anything else, it will do very well, I hope.”</p><p >“O yes, I hope so,” returned Richard, carelessly tossing his hair from his forehead. “After all, it may be only a kind of probation till our suit is—I forgot though. I am not to mention the suit. Forbidden ground! O yes, it's all right enough. Let us talk about something else.”</p><p >Ada would have done so, willingly, and with a full persuasion that we had brought the question to a most satisfactory state. But I thought it would be useless to stop there, so I began again.</p><p >“No, but Richard,” said I, “and my dear Ada! Consider how important it is to you both, and what a point of honour it is towards your cousin, that you, Richard, should be quite in earnest without any reservation. I think we had better talk about this, really, Ada. It will be too late, very soon.”</p><p >“O yes! We must talk about it!” said Ada. “But I think Richard is right.”</p><p >What was the use of my trying to look wise, when she was so pretty, and so engaging, and so fond of him!</p><p >“Mr. and Mrs. Badger were here yesterday, Richard,” said I, “and they seemed disposed to think that you had no great liking for the profession.”</p><p >“Did they though?” said Richard, “O! Well, that rather alters the case, because I had no idea that they thought so, and I should not have liked to disappoint or inconvenience them. The fact is, I don't care much about it. But O, it don't matter! It'll do as well as anything else!”</p><p >“You hear him, Ada!” said I.</p><p >“The fact is,” Richard proceeded, half thoughtfully and half jocosely, “it is not quite in my way. I don't take to it. And I get too much of Mrs. Bayham Badger's first and second.”</p><p >“I am sure <hi rend="italics">that</hi>'s very natural!” cried Ada, quite delighted. “The very thing we both said yesterday, Esther!”</p><p >“Then,” pursued Richard, “it's monotonous, and to-day is too like yesterday, and to-morrow is too like to-day.”</p><p >“But I am afraid,” said I, “this is an objection to all kinds of application—to life itself, except under some very uncommon circumstances.”</p><p >“Do you think so?” returned Richard, still considering. “Perhaps! Ha! Why, then, you know,” he added, suddenly becoming gay again, “we travel outside a circle, to what I said just now. It'll do as well as anything else. O, it's all right enough! Let us talk about something else.”</p><p >But, even Ada, with her loving face—and if it had seemed innocent and trusting, when I first saw it in that memorable November fog, how much more so did it seem now, when I knew her innocent and trusting heart—even Ada shook her head at this, and looked serious. So I thought it a good opportunity to hint to Richard, that if he were sometimes a little careless of himself, I was very sure he never meant to be careless of Ada; and that it was a part of his affectionate consideration for her, not to slight the importance of a step that might influence both their lives. This made him almost grave.</p><p >“My dear Mother Hubbard,” he said, “that's the very thing! I
<pb xml:id="p165"/>
have thought of that, several times; and have been quite angry with myself for meaning to be so much in carnest, and—somehow—not exactly being so. I don't know how it is; I seem to want something or other to stand by. Even you have no idea how fond I am of Ada (my darling cousin, I love you, so much!), but I don't settle down to constancy in other things. It's such uphill work, and it takes such a time!” said Richard, with an air of vexation.</p><p >“That may be,” I suggested, “because you don't like what you have chosen.”</p><p >“Poor fellow!” said Ada. “I am sure I don't wonder at it!”</p><p >No. It was not of the least use my trying to look wise. I tried again; but how could I do it, or how could it have any effect if I could, while Ada rested her clasped hands upon his shoulder, and while he looked at her tender blue eyes, and while they looked at him!</p><p >“You see, my precious girl,” said Richard, passing her golden curls through and through his hand, “I was a little hasty, perhaps; or I misunderstood my own inclinations, perhaps. They don't seem to lie in that direction. I couldn't tell, till I tried. Now the question is, whether it's worth while to undo all that has been done. It seems like making a great disturbance about nothing particular.”</p><p >“My dear Richard,” said I, “how <hi rend="italics">can</hi> you say about nothing particular?”</p><p >“I don't mean absolutely that,” he returned. “I mean that it <hi rend="italics">may</hi> be nothing particular, because I may never want it.”</p><p >Both Ada and I urged, in reply, not only that it was decidedly worth while to undo what had been done, but that it must be undone. I then asked Richard whether he had thought of any more congenial pursuit?</p><p >“There, my dear Mrs. Shipton,” said Richard, “you touch me home. Yes, I have. I have been thinking that the law is the boy for me.”</p><p >“The law!” repeated Ada, as if she were afraid of the name.</p><p >“If I went into Kenge's office,” said Richard, “and if I were placed under articles to Kenge, I should have my eye on the—hum!—the forbidden ground—and should be able to study it, and master it, and to satisfy myself that it was not neglected, and was being properly conducted. I should be able to look after Ada's interests, and my own interests (the same thing!); and I should peg away at Blackstone and all those fellows with the most tremendous ardor.”</p><p >I was not by any means so sure of that; and I saw how his hankering after the vague things yet to come of those long-deferred hopes, cast a shade on Ada's face. But I thought it best to encourage him in any project of continuous exertion, and only advised him to be quite sure that his mind was made up now.</p><p >“My dear Minerva,” said Richard, “I am as steady as you are. I made a mistake; we are all liable to mistakes; I won't do so any more, and I'll become such a lawyer as is not often seen. That is, you know,” said Richard, relapsing into doubt, “if it really is worth while, after all, to make such a disturbance about nothing particular!”</p><p >This led to our saying again, with a great deal of gravity, all that we had said already, and to our coming to much the same conclusion afterwards. But, we so strongly advised Richard to be frank and open with Mr. Jarndyce, without a moment's delay; and his disposition was
<pb xml:id="p166"/>
naturally so opposed to concealment; that he sought him out at once (taking us with him), and made a full avowal. “Rick,” said my Guardian, after hearing him attentively, “we can retreat with honour, and we will. But we must be careful—for our cousin's sake, Rick, for our cousin's sake—that we make no more such mistakes. Therefore, in the matter of the law, we will have a good trial before we decide. We will look before we leap, and take plenty of time about it.”</p><p >Richard's energy was of such an impatient and fitful kind, that he would have liked nothing better than to have gone to Mr. Kenge's office in that hour, and to have entered into articles with him on the spot. Submitting, however, with a good grace to the caution that we had shown to be so necessary, he contented himself with sitting down among us in his lightest spirits, and talking as if his one unvarying purpose in life from childhood had been that one which now held possession of him. My guardian was very kind and cordial with him, but rather grave; enough so to cause Ada, when he had departed and we were going up-stairs to bed, to say:</p><p >“Cousin John, I hope you don't think the worse of Richard?”</p><p >“No, my love,” said he.</p><p >“Because it was very natural that Richard should be mistaken in such a difficult case. It is not uncommon.”</p><p >“No, no, my love,” said he. “Don't look unhappy.”</p><p >“O, I am not unhappy, cousin John!” said Ada, smiling cheerfully, with her hand upon his shoulder, where she had put it in bidding him good night. “But I should be a little so, if you thought at all the worse of Richard.”</p><p >“My dear,” said Mr. Jarndyce, “I should think the worse of him, only if you were ever in the least unhappy through his means. I should be more disposed to quarrel with myself, even then, than with poor Rick, for I brought you together. But, tut, all this is nothing! He has time before him, and the race to run. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> think the worse of him? Not I, my loving cousin! And not you, I swear!”</p><p >“No, indeed, cousin John,” said Ada, “I am sure I could not—I am sure I would not—think any ill of Richard, if the whole world did. I could, and I would, think better of him then, than at any other time!”</p><p >So quietly and honestly she said it, with her hands upon his shoulders—both hands now—and looking up into his face, like the picture of Truth!</p><p >“I think,” said my guardian, thoughtfully regarding her, “I think it must be somewhere written that the virtues of the mothers shall, occasionally, be visited on the children, as well as the sins of the fathers. Good night, my rosebud. Good night, little woman. Pleasant slumbers! Happy dreams!”</p><p >This was the first time I ever saw him follow Ada with his eyes, with something of a shadow on their benevolent expression. I well remembered the look with which he had contemplated her and Richard, when she was singing in the fire-light; it was but a very little while since he had watched them passing down the room in which the sun was shining, and away into the shade; but, his glance was changed, and even the silent look of confidence in me which now followed it once more, was not quite so hopeful and untroubled as it had originally been.</p><pb  xml:id="p167"/><p >Ada praised Richard more to me, that night, than ever she had praised him yet. She went to sleep, with a little bracelet he had given her clasped upon her arm. I fancied she was dreaming of him when I kissed her cheek after she had slept an hour, and saw how tranquil and happy she looked.</p><p >For I was so little inclined to sleep, myself, that night, that I sat up working. It would not be worth mentioning for its own sake, but I was wakeful and rather low-spirited. I don't know why. At least I don't think I know why. At least, perhaps I do, but I don't think it matters.</p><p >At any rate, I made up my mind to be so dreadfully industrious that I would leave myself not a moment's leisure to be low-spirited. For I naturally said, “Esther! You to be low-spirited. <hi rend="italics">You!</hi>” And it really was time to say so, for I—yes, I really did see myself in the glass, almost crying. “As if you had anything to make you unhappy, instead of everything to make you happy, you ungrateful heart!” said I.</p><p >If I could have made myself go to sleep, I would have done it directly; but, not being able to do that, I took out of my basket some ornamental work for our house (I mean Bleak House) that I was busy with at that time, and sat down to it with great determination. It was necessary to count all the stitches in that work, and I resolved to go on with it until I couldn't keep my eyes open, and then, to go to bed.</p><p >I soon found myself very busy. But I had left some silk down-stairs in a work-table drawer in the temporary Growlery; and coming to a stop for want of it, I took my candle and went softly down to get it. To my great surprise, on going in, I found my guardian still there, and sitting looking at the ashes. He was lost in thought, his book lay unheeded by his side, his silvered iron-grey hair was scattered confusedly upon his forehead as though his hand had been wandering among it while his thoughts were elsewhere, and his face looked worn. Almost frightened by coming upon him so unexpectedly, I stood still for a moment; and should have retired without speaking, had he not, in again passing his hand abstractedly through his hair, seen me and started.</p><p >“Esther!”</p><p >I told him what I had come for.</p><p >“At work so late, my dear?”</p><p >“I am working late to-night,” said I, “because I couldn't sleep, and wished to tire myself. But, dear guardian, you are late too, and look weary. You have no trouble, I hope, to keep you waking?”</p><p >“None, little woman, that <hi rend="italics">you</hi> would readily understand,” said he.</p><p >He spoke in a regretful tone so new to me, that I inwardly repeated, as if that would help me to his meaning, “That <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could readily understand!”</p><p >“Remain a moment, Esther,” said he. “You were in my thoughts.”</p><p >“I hope I was not the trouble, guardian?”</p><p >He slightly waved his hand, and fell into his usual manner. The change was so remarkable, and he appeared to make it by dint of so much self-command, that I found myself again inwardly repeating, “None that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could understand!”</p><p >“Little woman,” said my guardian, “I was thinking—that is, I
<pb xml:id="p168"/>
have been thinking since I have been sitting here—that you ought to know, of your own history, all I know. It is very little. Next to nothing.”</p><p >“Dear guardian,” I replied, “when you spoke to me before on that subject—”</p><p >“But, since then,” he gravely interposed, anticipating what I meant to say, “I have reflected that your having anything to ask me, and my having anything to tell you, are different considerations, Esther. It is perhaps my duty to impart to you the little I know.”</p><p >“If you think so, guardian, it is right.”</p><p >“I think so,” he returned, very gently, and kindly, and very distinctly. “My dear, I think so, now. If any real disadvantage can attach to your position, in the mind of any man or woman worth a thought, it is right that you, at least, of all the world should not magnify it to yourself, by having vague impressions of its nature.”</p><p >I sat down; and said, after a little effort to be as calm as I ought to be, “One of my earliest remembrances, guardian, is of these words. ‘Your mother, Esther, is your disgrace, and you were hers. The time will come, and soon enough, when you will understand this better, and will feel it too, as no one save a woman can.’ ” I had covered my face with my hands, in repeating the words; but I took them away now with a better kind of shame, I hope, and told him, that to him I owed the blessing that I had from my childhood to that hour never, never, never felt it. He put up his hand as if to stop me. I well knew that he was never to be thanked, and said no more.</p><p >“Nine years, my dear,” he said, after thinking for a little while, “have passed since I received a letter from a lady living in seclusion, written with a stern passion and power that rendered it unlike all other letters I have ever read. It was written to me (as it told me in so many words), perhaps, because it was the writer's idiosyncrasy to put that trust in me; perhaps, because it was mine to justify it. It told me of a child, an orphan girl then twelve years old, in some such cruel words as those which live in your remembrance. It told me that the writer had bred her in secresy from her birth, had blotted out all trace of her existence, and that if the writer were to die before the child became a woman, she would be left entirely friendless, nameless, and unknown. It asked me, to consider if I would, in that case, finish what the writer had begun?”</p><p >I listened in silence, and looked attentively at him.</p><p >“Your early recollection, my dear, will supply the gloomy medium through which all this was seen and expressed by the writer, and the distorted religion which clouded her mind with impressions of the need there was for the child to expiate an offence of which she was quite innocent. I felt concerned for the little creature, in her darkened life; and replied to the letter.”</p><p >I took his hand and kissed it.</p><p >“It laid the injunction on me that I should never propose to see the writer, who had long been estranged from all intercourse with the world, but who would see a confidential agent if I would appoint one. I accredited Mr. Kenge. The lady said, of her own accord, and not of his seeking, that her name was an assumed one. That she was, if there were any ties of blood in such a case, the child's aunt. That more than
<pb xml:id="p169"/>
this she would never (and he was well persuaded of the steadfastness of her resolution), for any human consideration, disclose. My dear, I have told you all.”</p><p >I held his hand for a little while in mine.</p><p >“I saw my ward oftener than she saw me,” he added, cheerily making light of it, “and I always knew she was beloved, useful, and happy. She repays me twenty-thousand fold, and twenty more to that, every hour in every day!”</p><p >“And oftener still,” said I, “she blesses the guardian who is a Father to her!”</p><p >At the word Father, I saw his former trouble come into his face. He subdued it as before, and it was gone in an instant; but, it had been there, and it had come so swiftly upon my words that I felt as if they had given him a shock. I again inwardly repeated, wondering, “That <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could readily understand. None that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> could readily understand!” No, it was true. I did not understand it. Not for many and many a day.</p><p >“Take a fatherly good-night, my dear,” said he, kissing me on the forehead, “and so to rest. These are late hours for working and thinking. You do that for all of us, all day long, little housekeeper!”</p><p >I neither worked nor thought, any more, that night. I opened my grateful heart to Heaven in thankfulness for its providence to me and its care of me, and fell asleep.</p><p >We had a visitor next day. Mr. Allan Woodcourt came. He came to take leave of us; he had settled to do so beforehand. He was going to China, and to India, as a surgeon on board ship. He was to be away a long, long time.</p><p >I believe—at least I know—that he was not rich. All his widowed mother could spare had been spent in qualifying him for his profession. It was not lucrative to a young practitioner, with very little influence in London; and although he was, night and day, at the service of numbers of poor people, and did wonders of gentleness and skill for them, he gained very little by it in money. He was seven years older than I. Not that I need mention it, for it hardly seems to belong to anything.</p><p >I think—I mean, he told us—that he had been in practice three or four years, and that if he could have hoped to contend through three or four more he would not have made the voyage on which he was bound. But he had no fortune or private means, and so he was going away. He had been to see us several times altogether. We thought it a pity he should go away. Because he was distinguished in his art among those who knew it best, and some of the greatest men belonging to it had a high opinion of him.</p><p >When he came to bid us goodbye, he brought his mother with him for the first time. She was a pretty old lady, with bright black eyes, but she seemed proud. She came from Wales; and had had, a long time ago, an eminent person for an ancestor, of the name of Morgan ap-Kerrig—of some place that sounded like Gimlet—who was the most illustrious person that ever was known, and all of whose relations were a sort of Royal Family. He appeared to have passed his life in always getting up into mountains and fighting somebody; and a Bard whose name sounded like Crumlinwallinwer had sung his praises, in a piece which was called, as nearly as I could catch it, Mewlinnwillinwodd.</p><pb  xml:id="p170"/><p >Mrs. Woodcourt, after expatiating to us on the fame of her great kinsman, said that, no doubt, wherever her son Allan went, he would remember his pedigree, and would on no account form an alliance below it. She told him that there were many handsome English ladies in India who went out on speculation, and that there were some to be picked up with property; but, that neither charms nor wealth would suffice for the descendant from such a line, without birth: which must ever be the first consideration. She talked so much about birth that, for a moment, I half fancied, and with pain—but, what an idle fancy to suppose that she could think or care what <hi rend="italics">mine</hi> was!</p><p >Mr. Woodcourt seemed a little distressed by her prolixity, but he was too considerate to let her see it, and contrived delicately to bring the conversation round to making his acknowledgments to my guardian for his hospitality, and for the very happy hours—he called them the very happy hours—he had passed with us. The recollection of them, he said, would go with him wherever he went, and would be always treasured. And so we gave him our hands, one after another—at least, they did—and I did; and so he put his lips to Ada's hand—and to mine; and so he went away upon his long, long voyage!</p><p >I was very busy indeed, all day, and wrote directions home to the servants, and wrote notes for my guardian, and dusted his books and papers, and jingled my housekeeping keys a good deal, one way and another. I was still busy between the lights, singing and working by the window, when who should come in but Caddy, whom I had no expectation of seeing!</p><p >“Why, Caddy, my dear,” said I, “what beautiful flowers!”</p><p >She had such an exquisite little nosegay in her hand.</p><p >“Indeed, I think so, Esther,” replied Caddy. “They are the loveliest I ever saw.”</p><p >“Prince, my dear?” said I, in a whisper.</p><p >“No,” answered Caddy, shaking her head, and holding them to me to smell. “Not Prince!”</p><p >“Well, to be sure, Caddy!” said I. “You must have two lovers!”</p><p >“What? Do they look like that sort of thing?” said Caddy.</p><p >“Do they look like that sort of thing!” I repeated, pinching her cheek.</p><p >Caddy only laughed in return; and telling me that she had come for half-an-hour, at the expiration of which time Prince would be waiting for her at the corner, sat chatting with me and Ada in the window: every now and then, handing me the flowers again, or trying how they looked against my hair. At last, when she was going, she took me into my room and put them in my dress.</p><p >“For me?” said I, surprised.</p><p >“For you,” said Caddy, with a kiss. They were left behind by Somebody.</p><p >“Left behind?”</p><p >“At poor Miss Flite's,” said Caddy. “Somebody who has been very good to her, was hurrying away an hour ago, to join a ship, and left these flowers behind. No, no! Don't take them out. Let the pretty little things lie here!” said Caddy, adjusting them with a careful hand,
<pb xml:id="p171"/>
“because I was present myself, and I shouldn't wonder if Somebody left them on purpose!”</p><p >“Do they look like that sort of thing?” said Ada, coming laughingly behind me, and clasping me merrily round the waist. “O, yes, indeed they do, Dame Durden! They look very, very like that sort of thing. O, very like it indeed, my dear!”</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XVIII. <lb/> LADY DEDLOCK.</head><p >IT was not so easy as it had appeared at first, to arrange for Richard's making a trial of Mr. Kenge's office. Richard himself was the chief impediment. As soon as he had it in his power to leave Mr. Badger at any moment, he began to doubt whether he wanted to leave him at all. He didn't know, he said, really. It wasn't a bad profession; he couldn't assert that he disliked it; perhaps he liked it as well as he liked any other—suppose he gave it one more chance! Upon that, he shut himself up, for a few weeks, with some books and some bones, and seemed to acquire a considerable fund of information with great rapidity. His fervor, after lasting about a month, began to cool; and when it was quite cooled, began to grow warm again. His vacillations between law and medicine lasted so long, that Midsummer arrived before he finally separated from Mr. Badger, and entered on an experimental course of Messrs. Kenge and Carboy. For all this waywardness, he took great credit to himself as being determined to be in earnest “this time.” And he was so good-natured throughout, and in such high spirits, and so fond of Ada, that it was very difficult indeed to be otherwise than pleased with him.</p><p >“As to Mr. Jarndyce,” who, I may mention, found the wind much given, during this period, to sticking in the east; “As to Mr. Jarndyce,” Richard would say to me, “he is the finest fellow in the world, Esther! I must be particularly careful, if it were only for his satisfaction, to take myself well to task, and have a regular wind-up of this business now.”</p><p >The idea of his taking himself well to task, with that laughing face and heedless manner, and with a fancy that everything could catch and nothing could hold, was ludicrously anomalous. However, he told us between-whiles, that he was doing it to such an extent, that he wondered his hair didn't turn grey. His regular wind-up of the business was (as I have said), that he went to Mr. Kenge's about Midsummer, to try how he liked it.</p><p >All this time he was, in money affairs, what I have described him in a former illustration: generous, profuse, wildly careless, but fully persuaded that he was rather calculating and prudent. I happened to say to Ada, in his presence, half-jestingly, half-seriously, about the time of his going to Mr. Kenge's, that he needed to have Fortunatus's purse, he made so light of money, which he answered in this way:</p><p >“My jewel of a dear cousin, you hear this old woman! Why does she say that? Because I gave eight pounds odd (or whatever it was) for a certain neat waistcoat and buttons a few days ago. Now, if I had stayed
<pb xml:id="p172"/>
at Badger's I should have been obliged to spend twelve pounds at a blow, for some heart-breaking lecture-fees. So I make four pounds—in a lump—by the transaction!”</p><p >It was a question much discussed between him and my guardian what arrangements should be made for his living in London, while he experimented on the law; for, we had long since gone back to Bleak House, and it was too far off to admit of his coming there oftener than once a week. My guardian told me that if Richard were to settle down at Mr. Kenge's he would take some apartments or chambers, where we, too, could occasionally stay for a few days at a time; “but, little woman,” he added, rubbing his head very significantly, “he hasn't settled down there yet!” The discussions ended in our hiring for him, by the month, a neat little furnished lodging in a quiet old house near Queen Square. He immediately began to spend all the money he had, in buying the oddest little ornaments and luxuries for this lodging; and as often as Ada and I dissuaded him from making any purchase that he had in contemplation which was particularly unnecessary and expensive, he took credit for what it would have cost, and made out that to spend anything less on something else was to save the difference.</p><p >While these affairs were in abeyance, our visit to Mr. Boythorn's was postponed. At length, Richard having taken possession of his lodging, there was nothing to prevent our departure. He could have gone with us at that time of the year, very well; but, he was in the full novelty of his new position, and was making most energetic attempts to unravel the mysteries of the fatal suit. Consequently, we went without him; and my darling was delighted to praise him for being so busy.</p><p >We made a pleasant journey down into Lincolnshire by the coach, and had an entertaining companion in Mr. Skimpole. His furniture had been all cleared off, it appeared, by the person who took possession of it on his blue-eyed daughter's birth-day; but, he seemed quite relieved to think that it was gone. Chairs and tables, he said, were wearisome objects; they were monotonous ideas, they had no variety of expression, they looked you out of countenance, and you looked them out of countenance. How pleasant, then, to be bound to no particular chairs and tables, but to sport like a butterfly among all the furniture on hire, and to flit from rosewood to mahogany, and from mahogany to walnut, and from this shape to that, as the humour took one!</p><p >“The oddity of the thing is,” said Mr. Skimpole, with a quickened sense of the ludicrous, “that my chairs and tables were not paid for, and yet my landlord walks off with them as composedly as possible. Now, that seems droll! There is something grotesque in it. The chair and table merchant never engaged to pay my landlord my rent. Why should my landlord quarrel with <hi rend="italics">him?</hi> If I have a pimple on my nose which is disagreeable to my landlord's peculiar ideas of beauty, my landlord has no business to scratch my chair and table merchant's nose, which has no pimple on it. His reasoning seems defective!”</p><p >“Well,” said my guardian, good-humouredly, “it's pretty clear that whoever became security for those chairs and tables will have to pay for them.”</p><p >“Exactly!” returned Mr. Skimpole. “That's the crowning point of unreason in the business! I said to my landlord, ‘My good man, you
<pb xml:id="p173"/>
are not aware that my excellent friend Jarndyce will have to pay for those things that you are sweeping off in that indelicate manner. Have you no consideration for <hi rend="italics">his</hi> property?’ He hadn't the least.”</p><p >“And refused all proposals?” said my guardian.</p><p >“Refused all proposals,” returned Mr. Skimpole. “I made him business proposals. I had him into my room. I said, ‘You are a man of business, I believe?’ He replied, ‘I am.’ ‘Very well,’ said I, ‘now let us be business-like. Here is an inkstand, here are pens and paper, here are wafers. What do you want? I have occupied your house for a considerable period, I believe to our mutual satisfaction until this unpleasant misunderstanding arose; let us be at once friendly and business-like. What do you want?’ In reply to this, he made use of the figurative expression—which has something Eastern about it—that he had never seen the colour of my money. ‘My amiable friend,’ said I, ‘I never have any money. I never know anything about money.’ ‘Well, sir,’ said he, ‘what do you offer, if I give you time?’ ‘My good fellow,’ said I, ‘I have no idea of time; but, you say you are a man of business, and whatever you can suggest to be done in a business-like way with pen, and ink, and paper—and wafers—I am ready to do. Don't pay yourself at another man's expense (which is foolish), but be business-like!’ However, he wouldn't be, and there was an end of it.”</p><p >If these were some of the inconveniences of Mr. Skimpole's childhood, it assuredly possessed its advantages too. On the journey he had a very good appetite for such refreshment as came in our way (including a basket of choice hot-house peaches), but never thought of paying for anything. So, when the coachman came round for his fee, he pleasantly asked him what he considered a very good fee indeed, now—a liberal one—and, on his replying, half-a-crown for a single passenger, said it was little enough too, all things considered; and left Mr. Jarndyce to give it him.</p><p >It was delightful weather. The green corn waved so beautifully, the larks sang so joyfully, the hedges were so full of wild flowers, the trees were so thickly out in leaf, the bean-fields, with a light wind blowing over them, filled the air with such a delicious fragrance! Late in the afternoon we came to the market-town where we were to alight from the coach—a dull little town, with a church-spire, and a market-place, and a market-cross, and one intensely sunny street, and a pond with an old horse cooling his legs in it, and a very few men sleepily lying and standing about in narrow little bits of shade. After the rustling of the leaves and the waving of the corn all along the road, it looked as still, as hot, as motionless a little town as England could produce.</p><p >At the inn, we found Mr. Boythorn on horseback, waiting with an open carriage, to take us to his house, which was a few miles off. He was overjoyed to see us, and dismounted with great alacrity.</p><p >“By Heaven!” said he, after giving us a courteous greeting, “this is a most infamous coach. It is the most flagrant example of an abominable public vehicle that ever encumbered the face of the earth. It is twenty-five minutes after its time, this afternoon. The coachman ought to be put to death!”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Is</hi> he after his time?” said Mr. Skimpole, to whom he happened to address himself. “You know my infirmity.”</p><p >“Twenty-five minutes! Twenty-six minutes!” replied Mr. Boythorn,
<pb xml:id="p174"/>
referring to his watch. “With two ladies in the coach, this scoundrel has deliberately delayed his arrival six-and-twenty minutes. Deliberately! It is impossible that it can be accidental! But his father—and his uncle—were the most profligate coachmen that ever sat upon a box.”</p><p >While he said this in tones of the greatest indignation, he handed us into the little phaeton with the utmost gentleness, and was all smiles and pleasure.</p><p >“I am sorry, ladies,” he said, standing bare-headed at the carriage-door, when all was ready, “that I am obliged to conduct you nearly two miles out of the way. But, our direct road lies through Sir Leicester Dedlock's park; and, in that fellow's property, I have sworn never to set foot of mine, or horse's foot of mine, pending the present relations between us, while I breathe the breath of life!” And here, catching my guardian's eye, he broke into one of his tremendous laughs, which seemed to shake even the motionless little market-town.</p><p >“Are the Dedlocks down here, Lawrence?” said my guardian as we drove along, and Mr. Boythorn trotted on the green turf by the roadside.</p><p >“Sir Arrogant Numskull is here,” replied Mr. Boythorn. “Ha ha ha! Sir Arrogant is here, and, I am glad to say, has been laid by the heels here. My lady,” in naming whom he always made a courtly gesture as if particularly to exclude her from any part in the quarrel, “is expected, I believe, daily. I am not in the least surprised that she postpones her appearance as long as possible. Whatever can have induced that transcendant woman to marry that effigy and figure-head of a baronet, is one of the most impenetrable mysteries that ever baffled human inquiry. Ha ha ha ha!”</p><p >“I suppose,” said my guardian laughing, “<hi rend="italics">we</hi> may set foot in the park while we are here? The prohibition does not extend to us, does it?”</p><p >“I can lay no prohibition on my guests,” he said, bending his head to Ada and me, with the smiling politeness which sat so gracefully upon him, “except in the matter of their departure. I am only sorry that I cannot have the happiness of being their escort about Chesney Wold, which is a very fine place! But, by the light of this summer day, Jarndyce, if you call upon the owner, while you stay with me, you are likely to have but a cool reception. He carries himself like an eight-day clock at all times; like one of a race of eight-day clocks in gorgeous cases that never go and never went—Ha ha ha!—but he will have some extra stiffness, I can promise you, for the friends of his friend and neighbour Boythorn!</p><p >“I shall not put him to the proof,” said my guardian. “He is as indifferent to the honor of knowing me, I dare say, as I am to the honor of knowing him. The air of the grounds, and perhaps such a view of the house as any other sight-seer might get, are quite enough for me.”</p><p >“Well!” said Mr. Boythorn, “I am glad of it on the whole. It's in better keeping. I am looked upon, about here, as a second Ajax defying the lightning. Ha ha ha ha! When I go into our little church on a Sunday, a considerable part of the inconsiderable congregation expect to see me drop, scorched and withered, on the pavement under the Dedlock displeasure. Ha ha ha ha! I have no doubt he is surprised that I don't. For he is, by Heaven! the most self-satisfied, and the shallowest, and the most coxcombical and utterly brainless ass!”</p><pb  xml:id="p175"/><p >Our coming to the ridge of a hill we had been ascending, enabled our friend to point out Chesney Wold itself to us, and diverted his attention from its master.</p><p >It was a picturesque old house, in a fine park richly wooded. Among the trees, and not far from the residence, he pointed out the spire of the little church of which he had spoken. O, the solemn woods over which the light and shadow travelled swiftly, as if Heavenly wings were sweeping on benignant errands through the summer air; the smooth green slopes, the glittering water, the garden where the flowers were so symmetrically arranged in clusters of the richest colours, how beautiful they looked! The house, with gable, and chimney, and tower, and turret, and dark doorway, and broad terrace-walk, twining among the balustrades of which, and lying heaped upon the vases, there was one great flush of roses, seemed scarcely real in its light solidity, and in the serene and peaceful hush that rested all around it. To Ada and to me, that, above all, appeared the pervading influence. On everything, house, garden, terrace, green slopes, water, old oaks, fern, moss, woods again, and far away across the openings in the prospect, to the distance lying wide before us with a purple bloom upon it, there seemed to be such undisturbed repose.</p><p >When we came into the little village, and passed a small inn with the sign of the Dedlock Arms swinging over the road in front, Mr. Boythorn interchanged greetings with a young gentleman sitting on a bench outside the inn-door, who had some fishing-tackle lying beside him.</p><p >“That's the housekeeper's grandson, Mr. Rouncewell by name,” said he; “and he is in love with a pretty girl up at the House. Lady Dedlock has taken a fancy to the pretty girl, and is going to keep her about her own fair person—an honor which my young friend himself does not at all appreciate. However, he can't marry just yet, even if his Rosebud were willing; so he is fain to make the best of it. In the meanwhile, he comes here pretty often, for a day or two at a time, to—fish. Ha ha ha ha!”</p><p >“Are he and the pretty girl engaged, Mr. Boythorn?” asked Ada.</p><p >“Why, my dear Miss Clare,” he returned, “I think they may perhaps understand each other; but you will see them soon, I dare say, and I must learn from you on such a point—not you from me.”</p><p >Ada blushed; and Mr. Boythorn, trotting forward on his comely gray horse, dismounted at his own door, and stood ready, with extended arm and uncovered head, to welcome us when we arrived.</p><p >He lived in a pretty house, formerly the Parsonage-house, with a lawn in front, a bright flower-garden at the side, and a well-stocked orchard and kitchen-garden in the rear, enclosed with a venerable wall that had of itself a ripened ruddy look. But, indeed, everything about the place wore an aspect of maturity and abundance. The old lime-tree walk was like green cloisters, the very shadows of the cherry-trees and apple-trees were heavy with fruit, the gooseberry-bushes were so laden that their branches arched and rested on the earth, the strawberries and raspberries grew in like profusion, and the peaches basked by the hundred on the wall. Tumbled about among the spread nets and the glass frames sparkling and winking in the sun, there were such heaps of drooping pods, and marrows, and cucumbers, that every foot of ground appeared a vegetable treasury, while the smell of sweet herbs and all kinds of wholesome growth
<pb xml:id="p176"/>
(to say nothing of the neighbouring meadows where the hay was carrying) made the whole air a great nosegay. Such stillness and composure reigned within the orderly precincts of the old red wall, that even the feathers hung in garlands to scare the birds hardly stirred; and the wall had such a ripening influence that where, here and there high up, a disused nail and scrap of list still clung to it, it was easier to fancy that they had mellowed with the changing seasons, than that they had rusted and decayed according to the common fate.</p><p >The house, though a little disorderly in comparison with the garden, was a real old house, with settles in the chimney of the brick-floored kitchen, and great beams across the ceilings. On one side of it was the terrible piece of ground in dispute, where Mr. Boythorn maintained a sentry in a smock-frock, day and night, whose duty was supposed to be, in case of aggression, immediately to ring a large bell hung up there for the purpose, to unchain a great bull-dog established in a kennel as his ally, and generally to deal destruction on the enemy. Not content with these precautions, Mr. Boythorn had himself composed and posted there, on painted boards to which his name was attached in large letters, the following solemn warnings: “Beware of the Bull-dog. He is most ferocious. Lawrence Boythorn.” “The blunderbuss is loaded with slugs. Lawrence Boythorn.” “Man-traps and spring-guns are set here at all times of the day and night. Lawrence Boythorn.” “Take notice. That any person or persons audaciously presuming to trespass on this property, will be punished with the utmost severity of private chastisement, and prosecuted with the utmost rigor of the law. Lawrence Boythorn.” These he showed us, from the drawing-room window, while his bird was hopping about his head; and he laughed, “Ha ha ha ha! Ha ha ha ha!” to that extent as he pointed them out, that I really thought he would have hurt himself.</p><p >“But, this is taking a good deal of trouble,” said Mr. Skimpole in his light way, “when you are not in earnest after all?”</p><p >“Not in earnest!” returned Mr. Boythorn with unspeakable warmth. “Not in earnest! If I could have hoped to train him, I would have bought a Lion instead of that dog, and would have turned him loose upon the first intolerable robber who should dare to make an encroachment on my rights. Let Sir Leicester Dedlock consent to come out and decide this question by single combat, and I will meet him with any weapon known to mankind in any age or country. I am that much in earnest. Not more!”</p><p >We arrived at his house on a Saturday. On the Sunday morning we all set forth to walk to the little church in the park. Entering the park, almost immediately by the disputed ground, we pursued a pleasant footpath winding among the verdant turf and the beautiful trees, until it brought us to the church porch.</p><p >The congregation was extremely small and quite a rustic one, with the exception of a large muster of servants from the House, some of whom were already in their seats, while others were yet dropping in. There were some stately footmen; and there was a perfect picture of an old coachman, who looked as if he were the official representative of all the pomps and vanities that had ever been put into his coach. There was a very pretty show of young women; and above them, the handsome old face and
<pb xml:id="p177"/>
fine responsible portly figure of the housekeeper, towered pre-eminent. The pretty girl, of whom Mr. Boythorn had told us, was close by her. She was so very pretty, that I might have known her by her beauty, even if I had not seen how blushingly conscious she was of the eyes of the young fisherman, whom I discovered not far off. One face, and not an agreeable one, though it was handsome, seemed maliciously watchful of this pretty girl, and indeed of everyone and everything there. It was a Frenchwoman's.</p><p >As the bell was yet ringing and the great people were not yet come, I had leisure to glance over the church, which smelt as earthy as a grave, and to think what a shady, ancient, solemn little church it was. The windows, heavily shaded by trees, admitted a subdued light that made the faces around me pale, and darkened the old brasses in the pavement, and the time and damp-worn monuments, and rendered the sunshine in the little porch, where a monotonous ringer was working at the bell, inestimably bright. But a stir in that direction, a gathering of reverential awe in the rustic faces, and a blandly-ferocious assumption on the part of Mr. Boythorn of being resolutely unconscious of somebody's existence, forewarned me that the great people were come, and that the service was going to begin.</p><p >“ ‘Enter not into judgment with thy servant, O Lord, for in thy sight—’ ”</p><p >Shall I ever forget the rapid beating at my heart, occasioned by the look I met, as I stood up! Shall I ever forget the manner in which those handsome proud eyes seemed to spring out of their languor, and to hold mine! It was only a moment before I cast mine down—released again, if I may say so—on my book; but, I knew the beautiful face quite well, in that short space of time.</p><p >And, very strangely, there was something quickened within me, associated with the lonely days at my godmother's; yes, away even to the days when I had stood on tiptoe to dress myself at my little glass, after dressing my doll. And this, although I had never seen this lady's face before in all my life—I was quite sure of it—absolutely certain.</p><p >It was easy to know that the ceremonious, gouty, grey-haired gentleman, the only other occupant of the great pew, was Sir Leicester Dedlock; and that the lady was Lady Dedlock. But why her face should be, in a confused way, like a broken glass to me, in which I saw scraps of old remembrances; and why I should be so fluttered and troubled (for I was still), by having casually met her eyes; I could not think.</p><p >I felt it to be an unmeaning weakness in me, and I tried to overcome it by attending to the words I heard. Then, very strangely, I seemed to hear them, not in the reader's voice, but in the well-remembered voice of my godmother. This made me think, did Lady Dedlock's face accidentally resemble my godmother's? It might be that it did, a little; but, the expression was so different, and the stern decision which had worn into my godmother's face, like weather into rocks, was so completely wanting in the face before me, that it could not be that resemblance which had struck me. Neither did I know the loftiness and haughtiness of Lady Dedlock's face, at all, in any one. And yet <hi rend="italics">I—I,</hi> little Esther Summerson, the child who lived a life apart, and on whose birth-day there was no rejoicing—seemed to arise before my own eyes, evoked out of the past by some power in this fashionable lady, whom I not only entertained no
<pb xml:id="p178"/>
fancy that I had ever seen, but whom I perfectly well knew I had never seen until that hour.</p><p >It made me tremble so, to be thrown into this unaccountable agitation, that I was conscious of being distressed even by the observation of the French maid, though I knew she had been looking watchfully here, and there, and everywhere, from the moment of her coming into the church. By degrees, though very slowly, I at last overcame my strange emotion. After a long time, I looked towards Lady Dedlock again. It was while they were preparing to sing, before the sermon. She took no heed of me, and the beating at my heart was gone. Neither did it revive for more than a few moments, when she once or twice afterwards glanced at Ada or at me through her glass.</p><p >The service being concluded, Sir Leicester gave his arm with much state and gallantry to Lady Dedlock—though he was obliged to walk by the help of a thick stick—and escorted her out of church to the pony carriage in which they had come. The servants then dispersed, and so did the congregation: whom Sir Leicester had contemplated all along (Mr. Skimpole said to Mr. Boythorn's infinite delight), as if he were a considerable landed proprietor in Heaven.</p><p >“He believes he is!” said Mr. Boythorn. “He firmly believes it. So did his father, and his grandfather, and his great-grandfather!”</p><p >“Do you know,” pursued Mr. Skimpole, very unexpectedly to Mr. Boythorn, “it's agreeable to me to see a man of that sort.”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Is</hi> it!” said Mr. Boythorn.</p><p >“Say that he wants to patronise me,” pursued Mr. Skimpole. “Very well! I don't object.”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">I</hi> do,” said Mr. Boythorn, with great vigor.</p><p >“Do you really?” returned Mr. Skimpole, in his easy light vein. “But, that's taking trouble, surely. And why should you take trouble? Here am I, content to receive things childishly, as they fall out: and I never take trouble! I come down here, for instance, and I find a mighty potentate, exacting homage. Very well! I say ‘Mighty potentate, here <hi rend="italics">is</hi> my homage! It's easier to give it, than to withhold it. Here it is. If you have anything of an agreeable nature to show me, I shall be happy to see it; if you have anything of an agreeable nature to give me, I shall be happy to accept it.’ Mighty potentate replies in effect, ‘This is a sensible fellow. I find him accord with my digestion and my bilious system. He doesn't impose upon me the necessity of rolling myself up like a hedgehog with my points outward. I expand, I open, I turn my silver lining outward like Milton's cloud, and it's more agreeable to both of us.’ That's my view of such things: speaking as a child!”</p><p >“But suppose you went down somewhere else to-morrow,” said Mr. Boythorn, “where there was the opposite of that fellow—or of this fellow. How then?”</p><p >“How then?” said Mr. Skimpole, with an appearance of the utmost simplicity and candor. “Just the same, then! I should say, ‘My esteemed Boythorn’—to make you the personification of our imaginary friend—‘my esteemed Boythorn, you object to the mighty potentate? Very good. So do I. I take it that my business in the social system is to be agreeable; I take it that everybody's business in the social system is to be agreeable. It's a system of harmony, in short.
<pb xml:id="p179"/>
Therefore, if you object, I object. Now, excellent Boythorn, let us go to dinner!’ ”</p><p >“But, excellent Boythorn might say,” returned our host, swelling and growing very red, “I'll be—”</p><p >“I understand,” said Mr. Skimpole. “Very likely he would.”</p><p >“—if I <hi rend="italics">will</hi> go to dinner!” cried Mr. Boythorn, in a violent burst, and stopping to strike his stick upon the ground. “And he would probably add, ‘Is there such a thing as principle, Mr. Harold Skimpole?’ ”</p><p >“To which Harold Skimpole would reply, you know,” he returned in his gayest manner, and with his most ingenuous smile, “ ‘Upon my life I have not the least idea! I don't know what it is you call by that name, or where it is, or who possesses it. If you possess it and find it comfortable, I am quite delighted, and congratulate you heartily. But I know nothing about it, I assure you; for I am a mere child, and I lay no claim to it, and I don't want it!’ So, you see, excellent Boythorn and I would go to dinner after all!”</p><p >This was one of many little dialogues between them, which I always expected to end, and which I dare say would have ended under other circumstances, in some violent explosion on the part of our host. But, he had so high a sense of his hospitable and responsible position as our entertainer, and my guardian laughed so sincerely at and with Mr. Skimpole, as a child who blew bubbles and broke them all day long, that matters never went beyond this point. Mr. Skimpole, who always seemed quite unconscious of having been on delicate ground, then betook himself to beginning some sketch in the park which he never finished, or to playing fragments of airs on the piano, or to singing scraps of songs, or to lying down on his back under a tree, and looking at the sky—which he couldn't help thinking, he said, was what he was meant for; it suited him so exactly.</p><p >“Enterprise and effort,” he would say to us (on his back), “are delightful to me. I believe I am truly cosmopolitan. I have the deepest sympathy with them. I lie in a shady place like this, and think of adventurous spirits going to the North Pole, or penetrating to the heart of the Torrid Zone, with admiration. Mercenary creatures ask, ‘What is the use of a man's going to the North Pole? What good does it do?’ I can't say; but, for anything I <hi rend="italics">can</hi> say, he may go for the purpose—though he don't know it—of employing my thoughts as I lie here. Take an extreme case. Take the case of the Slaves on American plantations. I dare say they are worked hard, I dare say they don't altogether like it, I dare say theirs is an unpleasant experience on the whole; but, they people the landscape for me, they give it a poetry for me, and perhaps that is one of the pleasanter objects of their existence. I am very sensible of it, if it be, and I shouldn't wonder if it were!”</p><p >I always wondered on these occasions whether he ever thought of Mrs. Skimpole and the children, and in what point of view they presented themselves to his cosmopolitan mind. So far as I could understand, they rarely presented themselves at all.</p><p >The week had gone round to the Saturday following that beating of my heart in the church; and every day had been so bright and blue, that to ramble in the woods, and to see the light striking down among the transparent leaves, and sparkling in the beautiful interlacings of the
<pb xml:id="p180"/>
shadows of the trees, while the birds poured out their songs, and the air was drowsy with the hum of insects, had been most delightful. We had one favourite spot, deep in moss and last year's leaves, where there were some felled trees from which the bark was all stripped off. Seated among these, we looked through a green vista supported by thousands of natural columns, the whitened stems of trees, upon a distant prospect made so radiant by its contrast with the shade in which we sat, and made so precious by the arched perspective through which we saw it, that it was like a glimpse of the better land. Upon the Saturday we sat here, Mr. Jarndyce, Ada, and I, until we heard thunder muttering in the distance, and felt the large rain-drops rattle through the leaves.</p><p >The weather had been all the week extremely sultry; but, the storm broke so suddenly—upon us, at least, in that sheltered spot—that before we reached the outskirts of the wood, the thunder and lightning were frequent, and the rain came plunging through the leaves, as if every drop were a great leaden bead. As it was not a time for standing among trees, we ran out of the wood, and up and down the moss-grown steps which crossed the plantation-fence like two broad-staved ladders placed back to back, and made for a keeper's lodge which was close at hand. We had often noticed the dark beauty of this lodge standing in a deep twilight of trees, and how the ivy clustered over it, and how there was a steep hollow near, where we had once seen the keeper's dog dive down into the fern as if it were water.</p><p >The lodge was so dark within, now the sky was overcast, that we only clearly saw the man who came to the door when we took shelter there, and put two chairs for Ada and me. The lattice-windows were all thrown open, and we sat, just within the doorway, watching the storm. It was grand to see how the wind awoke, and bent the trees, and drove the rain before it like a cloud of smoke; and to hear the solemn thunder, and to see the lightning; and, while thinking with awe of the tremendous powers by which our little lives are encompassed, to consider how beneficent they are, and how upon the smallest flower and leaf there was already a freshness poured from all this seeming rage, which seemed to make creation new again.</p><p >“Is it not dangerous to sit in so exposed a place?”</p><p >“O no, Esther dear!” said Ada, quietly.</p><p >Ada said it to me; but, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> had not spoken.</p><p >The beating at my heart came back again. I had never heard the voice, as I had never seen the face, but it affected me in the same strange way. Again, in a moment, there arose before my mind innumerable pictures of myself.</p><p >Lady Dedlock had taken shelter in the lodge, before our arrival there, and had come out of the gloom within. She stood behind my chair, with her hand upon it. I saw her with her hand close to my shoulder, when I turned my head.</p><p >“I have frightened you?” she said.</p><p >No. It was not fright. Why should I be frightened!</p><p >“I believe,” said Lady Dedlock to my guardian, “I have the pleasure of speaking to Mr. Jarndyce.”</p><p >“Your remembrance does me more honor than I had supposed it would, Lady Dedlock,” he returned.</p><pb  xml:id="p181"/><p >“I recognised you in church on Sunday. I am sorry that any local disputes of Sir Leicester's—they are not of his seeking, however, I believe—should render it a matter of some absurd difficulty to show you any attention here.”</p><p >“I am aware of the circumstances,” returned my guardian with a smile, “and am sufficiently obliged.”</p><p >She had given him her hand, in an indifferent way that seemed habitual to her, and spoke in a correspondingly indifferent manner, though in a very pleasant voice. She was as graceful as she was beautiful; perfectly self-possessed; and had the air, I thought, of being able to attract and interest any one, if she had thought it worth her while. The keeper had brought her a chair, on which she sat, in the middle of the porch between us.</p><p >“Is the young gentleman disposed of, whom you wrote to Sir Leicester about, and whose wishes Sir Leicester was sorry not to have it in his power to advance in any way?” she said, over her shoulder, to my guardian.</p><p >“I hope so,” said he.</p><p >She seemed to respect him, and even to wish to conciliate him. There was something very winning in her haughty manner; and it became more familiar—I was going to say more easy, but that could hardly be—as she spoke to him over her shoulder.</p><p >“I presume this is your other ward, Miss Clare?”</p><p >He presented Ada, in form.</p><p >“You will lose the disinterested part of your Don Quixote character,” said Lady Dedlock to Mr. Jarndyce, over her shoulder again, “if you only redress the wrongs of beauty like this. But present me,” and she turned full upon me, “to this young lady too!”</p><p >“Miss Summerson really is my ward,” said Mr. Jarndyce. “I am responsible to no Lord Chancellor in her case.”</p><p >“Has Miss Summerson lost both her parents?” said my Lady.</p><p >“Yes.”</p><p >“She is very fortunate in her guardian.”</p><p >Lady Dedlock looked at me, and I looked at her, and said I was indeed. All at once she turned from me with a hasty air, almost expressive of displeasure or dislike, and spoke to him over her shoulder again.</p><p >“Ages have passed since we were in the habit of meeting, Mr. Jarndyce.”</p><p >“A long time. At least I thought it was a long time, until I saw you last Sunday,” he returned.</p><p >“What! Even you are a courtier, or think it necessary to become one to me!” she said, with some disdain. “I have achieved that reputation, I suppose.”</p><p >“You have achieved so much, Lady Dedlock,” said my guardian, “that you pay some little penalty, I dare say. But, none to me.”</p><p >“So much!” she repeated, slightly laughing. “Yes!”</p><p >With her air of superiority, and power, and fascination, and I know not what, she seemed to regard Ada and me as little more than children. So, as she slightly laughed, and afterwards sat looking at the rain, she was as self-possessed, and as free to occupy herself with her own thoughts she had been alone.</p><pb  xml:id="p182"/><p >“I think you knew my sister, when we were abroad together, better than you knew me?” she said, looking at him again.</p><p >“Yes, we happened to meet oftener,” he returned.</p><p >“We went our several ways,” said Lady Dedlock, “and had little in common even before we agreed to differ. It is to be regretted, I suppose, but it could not be helped.”</p><p >Lady Dedlock again sat looking at the rain. The storm soon began to pass upon its way. The shower greatly abated, the lightning ceased, the thunder rolled among the distant hills, and the sun began to glisten on the wet leaves and the falling rain. As we sat there, silently, we saw a little pony phaeton coming towards us at a merry pace.</p><p >“The messenger is coming back, my Lady,” said the keeper, “with the carriage.”</p><p >As it drove up, we saw that there were two people inside. There alighted from it, with some cloaks and wrappers, first the Frenchwoman whom I had seen in church, and secondly the pretty girl; the Frenchwoman, with a defiant confidence; the pretty girl, confused and hesitating.</p><p >“What now?” said Lady Dedlock. “Two!”</p><p >“I am your maid, my Lady, at the present,” said the Frenchwoman. “The message was for the attendant.”</p><p >“I was afraid you might mean me, my Lady,” said the pretty girl.</p><p >“I did mean you, child,” replied her mistress, calmly. “Put that shawl on me.”</p><p >She slightly stooped her shoulders to receive it, and the pretty girl lightly dropped it in its place. The Frenchwoman stood unnoticed, looking on with her lips very tightly set.</p><p >“I am sorry,” said Lady Dedlock to Mr. Jarndyee, “that we are not likely to renew our former acquaintance. You will allow me to send the carriage back for your two wards. It shall be here directly.”</p><p >But, as he would on no account accept this offer, she took a graceful leave of Ada—none of me—and put her hand upon his proffered arm, and got into the carriage; which was a little, low, park carriage, with a hood.</p><p >“Come in, child!” she said to the pretty girl, “I shall want you. Go on!”</p><p >The carriage rolled away; and the Frenchwoman, with the wrappers she had brought hanging over her arm, remained standing where she had alighted.</p><p >I suppose there is nothing Pride can so little bear with, as Pride itself, and that she was punished for her imperious manner. Her retaliation was the most singular I could have imagined. She remained perfectly still until the carriage had turned into the drive, and then, without the least discomposure of countenance, slipped off her shoes, left them on the ground, and walked deliberately in the same direction, through the wettest of the wet grass.</p><p >“Is that young woman mad?” said my guardian.</p><p >“O no, sir!” said the keeper, who, with his wife, was looking after her. “Hortense is not one of that sort. She has as good a head-piece as the best. But, she's mortal high and passionate—powerful high and passionate; and what with having notice to leave, and having others put above her, she don't take kindly to it.”</p><pb  xml:id="p183"/><p >“But why should she walk, shoeless, through all that water?” said my guardian.</p><p >“Why, indeed, sir, unless it is to cool her down!” said the man.</p><p >“Or unless she fancies it's blood,” said the woman. “She'd as soon walk through that as anything else, I think, when her own's up!”</p><p >We passed not far from the House, a few minutes afterwards. Peaceful as it had looked when we first saw it, it looked even more so now, with a diamond spray glittering all about it, a light wind blowing, the birds no longer hushed but singing strongly, everything refreshed by the late rain, and the little carriage shining at the doorway like a fairy carriage made of silver. Still, very steadfastly and quietly walking towards it, a peaceful figure too in the landscape, went Mademoiselle Hortense, shoeless, through the wet grass.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XIX. <lb/> MOVING ON.</head><p >IT is the long vacation in the regions of Chancery Lane. The good ships Law and Equity, those teak-built, copper-bottomed, iron-fastened, brazened-faced, and not by any means fast-sailing Clippers, are laid up in ordinary. The Flying Dutchman, with a crew of ghostly clients imploring all whom they may encounter to peruse their papers, has drifted, for the time being, Heaven knows where. The Courts are all shut up; the public offices lie in a hot sleep; Westminster Hall itself is a shady solitude where nightingales might sing, and a tenderer class of suitors than is usually found there, walk.</p><p >The Temple, Chancery Lane, Serjeants' Inn, and Lincoln's Inn even unto the Fields, are like tidal harbors at low water; where stranded proceedings, offices at anchor, idle clerks lounging on lop-sided stools that will not recover their perpendicular until the current of Term sets in, lie high and dry upon the ooze of the long vacation. Outer doors of chambers are shut up by the score, messages and parcels are to be left at the Porter's Lodge by the bushel. A crop of grass would grow in the chinks of the stone pavement outside Lincoln's Inn Hall, but that the ticket-porters, who have nothing to do beyond sitting in the shade there, with their white aprons over their heads to keep the flies off, grub it up and eat it thoughtfully.</p><p >There is only one Judge in town. Even he only comes twice a-week to sit in chambers. If the country folks of those assize towns on his circuit could only see him now! No full-bottomed wig, no red petticoats, no fur, no javelin-men, no white wands. Merely a close-shaved gentleman in white trousers and a white hat, with sea-bronze on the judicial countenance, and a strip of bark peeled by the solar rays from the judicial nose, who calls in at the shell-fish shop as he comes along, and drinks iced ginger-beer!</p><p >The bar of England is scattered over the face of the earth. How England can get on through four long summer months without its bar—which is its acknowledged refuge in adversity, and its only legitimate
<pb xml:id="p184"/>
triumph in prosperity—is beside the question; assuredly that shield and buckler of Britannia are not in present wear. The learned gentleman who is always so tremendously indignant at the unprecedented outrage committed on the feelings of his client by the opposite party, that he never seems likely to recover it, is doing infinitely better than might be expected, in Switzerland. The learned gentleman who does the withering business, and who blights all opponents with his gloomy sarcasm, is as merry as a grig at a French watering-place. The learned gentleman who weeps by the pint on the smallest provocation, has not shed a tear these six weeks. The very learned gentleman who has cooled the natural heat of his gingery complexion in pools and fountains of law, until he has become great in knotty arguments for Term-time, when he poses the drowsy Bench with legal “chaff,” inexplicable to the uninitiated and to most of the initiated too, is roaming, with a characteristic delight in aridity and dust, about Constantinople. Other dispersed fragments of the same great Palladium are to be found on the canals of Venice, at the second cataract of the Nile, in the baths of Germany, and sprinkled on the seasand all over the English coast. Scarcely one is to be encountered in the deserted region of Chancery Lane. If such a lonely member of the bar do flit across the waste, and come upon a prowling suitor who is unable to leave off haunting the scenes of his anxiety, they frighten one another, and retreat into opposite shades.</p><p >It is the hottest long vacation known for many years. All the young clerks are madly in love, and, according to their various degrees, pine for bliss with the beloved object, at Margate, Ramsgate, or Gravesend. All the middle-aged clerks think their families too large. All the unowned dogs who stray into the Inns of Court, and pant about staircases and other dry places, seeking water, give short howls of aggravation. All the blind mens' dogs in the streets draw their masters against pumps, or trip them over buckets. A shop with a sun-blind, and a watered pavement, and a bowl of gold and silver fish in the window, is a sanctuary. Temple Bar gets so hot, that it is, to the adjacent Strand and Fleet Street, what a heater is in an urn, and keeps them simmering all night.</p><p >There are offices about the Inns of Court in which a man might be cool, if any coolness were worth purchasing at such a price in dulness; but, the little thoroughfares immediately outside those retirements seem to blaze. In Mr. Krook's court, it is so hot that the people turn their houses inside out, and sit in chairs upon the pavement—Mr. Krook included, who there pursues his studies, with his cat (who never is too hot) by his side. The Sol's Arms has discontinued the harmonic meetings for the season, and Little Swills is engaged at the Pastoral Gardens down the river, where he comes out in quite an innocent manner, and sings comic ditties of a juvenile complexion, calculated (as the bill says) not to wound the feelings of the most fastidious mind.</p><p >Over all the legal neighbourhood, there hangs, like some great veil of rust, or gigantic cobweb, the idleness and pensiveness of the long vacation. Mr. Snagsby, law-stationer of Cook's Court, Cursitor Street, is sensible of the influence; not only in his mind as a sympathetic and contemplative man, but also in his business as a law-stationer aforesaid. He has more leisure for musing in Staple Inn and in the Rolls Yard, during the long vacation, than at other seasons; and he says to the two
<pb xml:id="p185"/>
'prentices, what a thing it is in such hot weather to think that you live in an island, with the sea a rolling and a bowling right round you.</p><p >Guster is busy in the little drawing-room, on this present afternoon in the long vacation, when Mr. and Mrs. Snagsby have it in contemplation to receive company. The expected guests are rather select than numerous, being Mr. and Mrs. Chadband, and no more. From Mr. Chadband's being much given to describe himself, both verbally and in writing, as a vessel, he is occasionally mistaken by strangers for a gentleman connected with navigation; but, he is, as he expresses it, “in the ministry.” Mr. Chadband is attached to no particular denomination; and is considered by his persecutors to have nothing so very remarkable to say on the greatest of subjects as to render his volunteering, on his own account, at all incumbent on his conscience; but, he has his followers, and Mrs. Snagsby is of the number. Mrs. Snagsby has but recently taken a passage upward by the vessel, Chadband; and her attention was attracted to that Bark A 1, when she was something flushed by the hot weather.</p><p >“My little woman,” says Mr. Snagsby to the sparrows in Staple Inn, “likes to have her religion rather sharp, you see!”</p><p >So, Guster, much impressed by regarding herself for the time as the handmaid of Chadband, whom she knows to be endowed with the gift of holding forth for four hours at a stretch, prepares the little drawing-room for tea. All the furniture is shaken and dusted, the portraits of Mr. and Mrs. Snagsby are touched up with a wet cloth, the best tea-service is set forth, and there is excellent provision made of dainty new bread, crusty twists, cool fresh butter, thin slices of ham, tongue and German sausage, and delicate little rows of anchovies nestling in parsley; not to mention new laid eggs, to be brought up warm in a napkin, and hot buttered toast. For, Chadband is rather a consuming vessel—the persecutors say a gorging vessel; and can wield such weapons of the flesh as a knife and fork, remarkably well.</p><p >Mr. Snagsby in his best coat, looking at all the preparations when they are completed, and coughing his cough of deference behind his hand, says to Mrs. Snagsby, “At what time did you expect Mr. and Mrs. Chadband, my love?”</p><p >“At six,” says Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >Mr. Snagsby observes in a mild and casual way, that “it's gone that.”</p><p >“Perhaps you'd like to begin without them,” is Mrs. Snagsby's reproachful remark.</p><p >Mr. Snagsby does look as if he would like it very much, but he says, with his cough of mildness, “No, my dear, no. I merely named the time.”</p><p >“What's time,” says Mrs. Snagsby, “to eternity?”</p><p >“Very true, my dear,” says Mr. Snagsby. “Only when a person lays in victuals for tea, a person does it with a view—perhaps—more to time. And when a time is named for having tea, it's better to come up to it.”</p><p >“To come up to it!” Mrs. Snagsby repeats with severity. “Up to it! As if Mr. Chadband was a fighter!”</p><p >“Not at all, my dear,” says Mr. Snagsby.</p><p >Here, Guster, who has been looking out of the bed-room window, comes rustling and scratching down the little staircase like a popular ghost, and, falling flushed into the drawing-room, announces that Mr. and
<pb xml:id="p186"/>
Mrs. Chadband have appeared in the court. The bell at the inner door in the passage immediately thereafter tinkling, she is admonished by Mrs. Snagsby, on pain of instant reconsignment to her patron saint, not to omit the ceremony of announcement. Much discomposed in her nerves (which were previously in the best order) by this threat, she so fearfully mutilates that point of state as to announce “Mr. and Mrs. Cheescming, least which, Imeantersay whatsername!” and retires conscience-stricken from the presence.</p><p >Mr. Chadband is a large yellow man, with a fat smile, and a general appearance of having a good deal of train oil in his system. Mrs. Chadband is a stern, severe-looking, silent woman. Mr. Chadband moves softly and cumbrously, not unlike a bear who has been taught to walk upright. He is very much embarrassed about the arms, as if they were inconvenient to him, and he wanted to grovel; is very much in a perspiration about the head; and never speaks without first putting up his great hand, as delivering a token to his hearers that he is going to edify them.</p><p >“My friends,” says Mr. Chadband. “Peace be on this house! On the master thereof, on the mistress thereof, on the young maidens, and on the young men! My friends, why do I wish for peace? What is peace? Is it war? No. Is it strife? No. Is it lovely, and gentle, and beautiful, and pleasant, and serene, and joyful? O yes! Therefore, my friends, I wish for peace, upon you and upon yours.”</p><p >In consequence of Mrs. Snagsby looking deeply edified, Mr. Snagsby thinks it expedient on the whole to say Amen, which is well received.</p><p >“Now, my friends,” proceeds Mr. Chadband, “since I am upon this theme—”</p><p >Guster presents herself. Mrs. Snagsby, in a spectral bass voice, and without removing her eyes from Chadband, says, with dread distinctness, “Go away!”</p><p >“Now, my friends,” says Chadband, “since I am upon this theme, and in my lowly path improving it—”</p><p >Guster is heard unaccountably to murmur “one thousing seven hunderd and eighty-two.” The spectral voice repeats more solemnly, “Go away!”</p><p >“Now, my friends,” says Mr. Chadband, “we will inquire in a spirit of love—”</p><p >Still Guster reiterates “one thousing seven hunderd and eighty-two.”</p><p >Mr. Chadband, pausing with the resignation of a man accustomed to be persecuted, and languidly folding up his chin into his fat smile, says, “Let us hear the maiden! Speak, maiden!”</p><p >“One thousing seven hunderd and eighty-two, if you please, sir. Which he wish to know what the shilling ware for,” says Guster, breathless.</p><p >“For?” returns Mrs. Chadband. “For his fare!”</p><p >Guster replied that “he insistes on one and eightpence, or on summonsizzing the party.” Mrs. Snagsby and Mrs. Chadband are proceeding to grow shrill in indignation, when Mr. Chadband quiets the tumult by lifting up his hand.</p><p >“My friends,” says he, “I remember a duty unfulfilled yesterday. It is right that I should be chastened in some penalty. I ought not to murmur. Rachael, pay the eightpence!”</p><pb  xml:id="p187"/><p >While Mrs. Snagsby, drawing her breath, looks hard at Mr. Snagsby, as who should say, “you hear this Apostle!” and while Mr. Chadband glows with humility and train oil, Mrs. Chadband pays the money. It is Mr. Chadband's habit—it is the head and front of his pretensions indeed—to keep this sort of debtor and creditor account in the smallest items, and to post it publicly on the most trivial occasions.</p><p >“My friends,” says Chadband, “eightpence is not much; it might justly have been one and fourpence; it might justly have been half-a-crown. O let us be joyful, joyful! O let us be joyful!”</p><p >With which remark, which appears from its sound to be an extract in verse, Mr. Chadband stalks to the table, and, before taking a chair, lifts up his admonitory hand.</p><p >“My friends,” says he, “what is this which we now behold as being spread before us? Refreshment. Do we need refreshment then, my friends? We do. And why do we need refreshment, my friends? Because we are but mortal, because we are but sinful, because we are but of the earth, because we are not of the air. Can we fly, my friends? We cannot. Why can we not fly, my friends?</p><p >Mr. Snagsby, presuming on the success of his last point, ventures to observe in a cheerful and rather knowing tone, “No wings.” But, is immediately frowned down by Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >“I say, my friends,” pursues Mr. Chadband, utterly rejecting and obliterating Mr. Snagsby's suggestion, “why can we not fly? Is it because we are calculated to walk? It is. Could we walk, my friends, without strength? We could not. What should we do without strength, my friends? Our legs would refuse to bear us, our knees would double up, our ankles would turn over, and we should come to the ground. Then from whence, my friends, in a human point of view, do we derive the strength that is necessary to our limbs? Is it,” says Chadband, glancing over the table, “from bread in various forms, from butter which is churned from the milk which is yielded untoe us by the cow, from the eggs which are laid by the fowl, from ham, from tongue, from sausage, and from such like? It is. Then let us partake of the good things which are set before us!”</p><p >The persecutors denied that there was any particular gift in Mr. Chadband's piling verbose flights of stairs, one upon another, after this fashion. But this can only be received as a proof of their determination to persecute, since it must be within everybody's experience, that the Chadband style of oratory is widely received and much admired.</p><p >Mr. Chadband, however, having concluded for the present, sits down at Mrs. Snagsby's table, and lays about him prodigiously. The conversion of nutriment of any sort into oil of the quality already mentioned, appears to be a process so inseparable from the constitution of this exemplary vessel, that in beginning to eat and drink, he may be described as always becoming a kind of considerable Oil Mills, or other large factory for the production of that article on a wholesale scale. On the present evening of the long vacation, in Cook's Court, Cursitor Street, he does such a powerful stroke of business, that the warehouse appears to be quite full when the works cease.</p><p >At this period of the entertainment, Guster, who has never recovered
<pb xml:id="p188"/>
her first failure, but has neglected no possible or impossible means of bringing the establishment and herself into contempt—among which may be briefly enumerated her unexpectedly performing clashing military music on Mr. Chadband's head with plates, and afterwards crowning that gentleman with muffins—at this period of the entertainment, Guster whispers Mr. Snagsby that he is wanted.</p><p >“And being wanted in the—not to put too fine a point upon it—in the shop!” says Mr. Snagsby rising, “perhaps this good company will excuse me for half a minute.”</p><p >Mr. Snagsby descends, and finds the two 'prentices intently contemplating a police constable, who holds a ragged boy by the arm.</p><p >“Why, bless my heart,” says Mr. Snagsby, “what's the matter!”</p><p >“This boy,” says the constable, “although he's repeatedly told to, won't move on—”</p><p >“I'm always a moving on, sir,” cries the boy, wiping away his grimy tears with his arm. “I've always been a moving and a moving on, ever since I was born. Where can I possible move to, sir, more nor I do move!”</p><p >“He won't move on,” says the constable, calmly, with a slight professional hitch of his neck involving its better settlement in his stiff stock, “although he has been repeatedly cautioned, and therefore I am obliged to take him into custody. He's as obstinate a young gonoph as I know. He WON'T move on.”</p><p >“O my eye! Where can I move to!” cries the boy, clutching quite desperately at his hair, and beating his bare feet upon the floor of Mr. Snagsby's passage.</p><p >“Don't you come none of that, or I shall make blessed short work of you!” says the constable, giving him a passionless shake. “My instructions are, that you are to move on. I have told you so five hundred times.”</p><p >“But where?” cries the boy.</p><p >“Well! Really, constable, you know,” says Mr. Snagsby wistfully, and coughing behind his hand his cough of great perplexity and doubt; “really, that does seem a question. Where, you know?”</p><p >“My instructions don't go to that,” replies the constable. “My instructions are that this boy is to move on.”</p><p >Do you hear, Jo? It is nothing to you or to any one else, that the great lights of the parliamentary sky have failed for some few years, in this business, to set you the example of moving on. The one grand recipe remains for you—the profound philosophical prescription—the be-all and the end-all of your strange existence upon earth. Move on! You are by no means to move off, Jo, for the great lights can't at all agree about that. Move on!</p><p >Mr. Snagsby says nothing to this effect; says nothing at all, indeed; but coughs his forlornest cough, expressive of no thoroughfare in any direction. By this time, Mr. and Mrs. Chadband, and Mrs. Snagsby, hearing the altercation, have appeared upon the stairs. Guster having never left the end of the passage, the whole household are assembled.</p><p >“The simple question is, sir,” says the constable, “whether you know this boy. He says you do.”</p><p >Mrs. Snagsby, from her elevation, instantly cries out “No he don't!”</p><p >“My lit-tle woman!” says Mr. Snagsby, looking up the staircase. “My
<pb xml:id="p189"/>
love, permit me! Pray have a moment's patience, my dear. I do know something of this lad, and in what I know of him, I can't say that there's any harm; perhaps on the contrary, constable.” To whom the law-stationer relates his Joful and woful experience, suppressing the half-crown fact.</p><p >“Well!” says the constable, “so far, it seems, he had grounds for what he said. When I took him into custody up in Holborn, he said you knew him. Upon that, a young man who was in the crowd said he was acquainted with you, and you were a respectable housekeeper, and if I'd call and make the enquiry he'd appear. The young man don't seem inclined to keep his word, but—Oh! Here <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the young man!”</p><p >Enter Mr. Guppy, who nods to Mr. Snagsby, and touches his hat with the chivalry of clerkship to the ladies on the stairs.</p><p >“I was strolling away from the office just now, when I found this row going on,” says Mr. Guppy to the law-stationer; “and as your name was mentioned, I thought it was right the thing should be looked into.”</p><p >“It was very good-natured of you, sir,” says Mr. Snagsby, “and I am obliged to you.” And Mr. Snagsby again relates his experience, again suppressing the half-crown fact.</p><p >“Now, I know where you live,” says the constable, then, to Jo. “You live down in Tom-all-alone's. That's a nice innocent place to live in, ain't it?”</p><p >“I can't go and live in no nicer place, sir,” replies Jo. “They wouldn't have nothink to say to me if I wos to go to a nice innocent place fur to live. Who ud go and let a nice innocent lodging to such a reg'lar one as me!”</p><p >“You are very poor, ain't you?” says the constable.</p><p >“Yes, I am indeed, sir, wery poor in gin'ral,” replies Jo.</p><p >“I leave you to judge now! I shook these two half-crowns out of him,” says the constable producing them to the company, “in only putting my hand upon him!”</p><p >“They're wot's left, Mr. Sangsby,” says Jo, “out of a sov'ring as wos give me by a lady in a wale as sed she wos a servant and as come to my crossin one night and asked to be showd this 'ere ouse and the ouse wot him as you giv the writin to died at, and the berrin ground wot he's berrid in. She ses to me she ses ‘are you the boy at the Inkwhich?’ she ses. I ses ‘yes’ I ses. She ses to me she ses ‘can you show me all them places?’ I ses ‘yes I can’ I ses. And she ses to me ‘do it’ and I dun it and she giv me a sov'ring and hooked it. And I an't had much of the sov'ring neither,” says Jo, with dirty tears, “fur I had to pay five bob, down in Tom-all-alone's, afore they'd square it fur to giv me change, and then a young man he thieved another five while I was asleep and another boy he thieved ninepence and the landlord he stood drains round with a lot more on it.”</p><p >“You don't expect anybody to believe this, about the lady and the sovereign, do you?” says the constable, eyeing him aside with ineffable disdain.</p><p >“I don't know as I do, sir,” replies Jo. “I don't expect nothink at all, sir, much, but that's the true hist'ry on it.’</p><p >“You see what he is!” the constable observes to the audience. “Well, Mr. Snagsby, if I don't lock him up this time, will you engage for his moving on?”</p><pb  xml:id="p190"/><p >“No!” cries Mrs. Snagsby from the stairs.</p><p >“My little woman!” pleads her husband. “Constable, I have no doubt he'll move on. You know you really must do it,” says Mr. Snagsby.</p><p >“I'm everyways agreeable, sir,” says the hapless Jo.</p><p >“Do it, then,” observes the constable. “You know what you have got to do. Do it! And recollect you won't get off so easy next time. Catch hold of your money. Now, the sooner you're five mile off, the better for all parties.”</p><p >With this farewell hint, and pointing generally to the setting sun, as a likely place to move on to, the constable bids his auditors good afternoon; and makes the echoes of Cook's Court perform slow music for him as he walks away on the shady side, carrying his iron-bound hat in his hand for a little ventilation.</p><p >Now, Jo's improbable story concerning the lady and the sovereign has awakened more or less the curiosity of all the company. Mr. Guppy, who has an enquiring mind in matters of evidence, and who has been suffering severely from the lassitude of the long vacation, takes that interest in the case, that he enters on a regular cross-examination of the witness, which is found so interesting by the ladies that Mrs. Snagsby politely invites him to step up-stairs, and drink a cup of tea, if he will excuse the disarranged state of the tea-table, consequent on their previous exertions. Mr. Guppy yielding his assent to this proposal, Jo is requested to follow into the drawing-room doorway, where Mr. Guppy takes him in hand as a witness, patting him into this shape, that shape, and the other shape, like a butterman dealing with so much butter, and worrying him according to the best models. Nor is the examination unlike many such model displays, both in respect of its eliciting nothing, and of its being lengthy; for, Mr. Guppy is sensible of his talent, and Mrs. Snagsby feels, not only that it gratifies her inquisitive disposition, but that it lifts her husband's establishment higher up in the law. During the progress of this keen encounter, the vessel Chadband, being merely engaged in the oil trade, gets aground, and waits to be floated off.</p><p >“Well!” says Mr. Guppy, “either this boy sticks to it like cobbler's wax, or there is something out of the common here that beats anything that ever came into my way at Kenge and Carboy's.”</p><p >Mrs. Chadband whispers Mrs. Snagsby, who exclaims, “You don't say so!”</p><p >For years!” replies Mrs. Chadband.</p><p >“Has known Kenge and Carboy's office for years,” Mrs. Snagsby triumphantly explains to Mr. Guppy. “Mrs. Chadband—this gentleman's wife—Reverend Mr. Chadband.”</p><p >“Oh, indeed!” says Mr. Guppy.</p><p >“Before I married my present husband,” says Mrs. Chadband.</p><p >“Was you a party in anything, ma'am?” says Mr. Guppy, transferring his cross-examination.</p><p >“No.”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Not</hi> a party in anything, ma'am?” says Mr. Guppy.</p><p >Mrs. Chadband shakes her head.</p><p >“Perhaps you were acquainted with somebody who was a party in something, ma'am?” says. Mr. Guppy, who likes nothing better than to model his conversation on forensic principles.</p><pb  xml:id="p191"/><p >“Not exactly that, either,” replies Mrs. Chadband, humouring the joke with a hard-favored smile.</p><p >“Not exactly that, either!” repeats Mr. Guppy. “Very good. Pray, ma'am, was it a lady of your acquaintance who had some transactions (we will not at present say what transactions) with Kenge and Carboy's office, or was it a gentleman of your acquaintance? Take time, ma'am. We shall come to it presently. Man or woman, ma'am?”</p><p >“Neither,” says Mrs. Chadband, as before.</p><p >“Oh! A child!” says Mr. Guppy, throwing on the admiring Mrs. Snagsby the regular acute professional eye which is thrown on British jurymen. “Now, ma'am, perhaps you'll have the kindness to tell us <hi rend="italics">what</hi> child.”</p><p >“You have got at it at last, sir,” says Mrs. Chadband, with another hard-favored smile. “Well, sir, it was before your time, most likely, judging from your appearance. I was left in charge of a child named Esther Summerson, who was put out in life by Messrs. Kenge and Carboy.”</p><p >“Miss Summerson, ma'am!” cries Mr. Guppy, excited.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">I</hi> call her Esther Summerson,” says Mrs. Chadband, with austerity. “There was no Miss-ing of the girl in my time. It was Esther. ‘Esther, do this! Esther, do that!’ and she was made to do it.”</p><p >“My dear ma'am,” returns Mr. Guppy, moving across the small apartment, “the humble individual who now addresses you received that young lady in London, when she first came here from the establishment to which you have alluded. Allow me to have the pleasure of taking you by the hand.”</p><p >Mr. Chadband, at last seeing his opportunity, makes his accustomed signal, and rises with a smoking head, which he dabs with his pocket-handkerchief. Mrs. Snagsby whispers “Hush!”</p><p >“My friends,” says Chadband, “we have partaken, in moderation” (which was certainly not the case so far as he was concerned), “of the comforts which have been provided for us. May this house live upon the fatness of the land; may corn and wine be plentiful therein; may it grow, may it thrive, may it prosper, may it advance, may it proceed, may it press forward! But, my friends, have we partaken of anything else? We have. My friends, of what else have we partaken? Of spiritual profit? Yes. From whence have we derived that spiritual profit? My young friend, stand forth!”</p><p >Jo, thus apostrophised, gives a slouch backward, and another slouch forward, and another slouch to each side, and confronts the eloquent Chadband, with evident doubts of his intentions.</p><p >“My young friend,” says Chadband, “you are to us a pearl, you are to us a diamond, you are to us a gem, you are to us a jewel. And why, my young friend?”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">I</hi> don't know,” replies Jo. “I don't know nothink.”</p><p >“My young friend,” says Chadband, “it is because you know nothing that you are to us a gem and jewel. For what are you, my young friend? Are you a beast of the field? No. A bird of the air? No. A fish of the sea or river? No. You are a human boy, my young friend. A human boy. O glorious to be a human boy! And why glorious, my young friend? Because you are capable of receiving the lessons of wisdom, because you are capable of profiting by this discourse which I now
<pb xml:id="p192"/>
deliver for your good, because you are not a stick, or a staff, or a stock, or a stone, or a post, or a pillar.</p><q ><p>O running stream of sparkling joy</p><p>To be a soaring human boy!</p></q><p >And do you cool yourself in that stream now, my young friend? No. Why do you not cool yourself in that stream now? Because you are in a state of darkness, because you are in a state of obscurity, because you are in a state of sinfulness, because you are in a state of bondage. My young friend, what <hi rend="italics">is</hi> bondage? Let us, in a spirit of love, inquire.”</p><p >At this threatening stage of the discourse, Jo, who seems to have been gradually going out of his mind, smears his right arm over his face, and gives a terrible yawn. Mrs. Snagsby indignantly expresses her belief that he is a limb of the arch-fiend.</p><p >“My friends,” says Mr. Chadband, with his persecuted chin folding itself into its fat smile again as he looks round, “it is right that I should be humbled, it is right that I should be tried, it is right that I should be mortified, it is right that I should be corrected. I stumbled, on Sabbath last, when I thought with pride of my three hours' improving. The account is now favorably balanced; my creditor has accepted a composition. O let us be joyful, joyful! O let us be joyful!”</p><p >Great sensation on the part of Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >“My friends,” says Chadband, looking round him, in conclusion, “I will not proceed with my young friend now. Will you come to-morrow, my young friend, and enquire of this good lady where I am to be found to deliver a discourse untoe you, and will you come like the thirsty swallow upon the next day, and upon the day after that, and upon the day after that, and upon many pleasant days, to hear discourses?” (This, with a cow-like lightness.)</p><p >Jo, whose immediate object seems to be to get away on any terms, gives a shuffling nod. Mr. Guppy then throws him a penny, and Mrs. Snagsby calls to Guster to see him safely out of the house. But, before he goes down stairs, Mr. Snagsby loads him with some broken meats from the table, which he carries away, hugging in his arms.</p><p >So, Mr. Chadband—of whom the persecutors say that it is no wonder he should go on for any length of time uttering such abominable nonsense, but that the wonder rather is that he should ever leave off, having once the audacity to begin—retires into private life until he invests a little capital of supper in the oil-trade. Jo moves on, through the long vacation, down to Blackfriars Bridge, where he finds a baking stony corner, wherein to settle to his repast.</p><p >And there he sits, munching and gnawing, and looking up at the great Cross on the summit of St. Paul's Cathedral, glittering above a red and violet-tinted cloud of smoke. From the boy's face one might suppose that sacred emblem to be, in his eyes, the crowning confusion of the great, confused city; so golden, so high up, so far out of his reach. There he sits, the sun going down, the river running fast, the crowd flowing by him in two streams—everything moving on to some purpose and to one end—until he is stirred up, and told to “move on” too.</p></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><head >THE OAK<lb/>Mutual Life Assurance &amp; Loan Company.</head><p >OFFICES, 49, MOORGATE-STREET, LONDON.</p><p >GUARANTEED FUND, £50,000.</p><list  type="simple"><head>Directors.</head><item><hi rend="italics">Chairman.</hi>—THE RT. HON. THE EARL OF HARDWICKE, P.M.G.</item><item>A. A. DORIA, Esq.</item><item>MAJOR HAWKES.</item><item>THOMAS HUNT, Esq. F.R.C.S.</item><item>C. BROWNE, Esq.</item><item>SIR PHILIP CLARKE, BART.</item><item>SAMUEL NOBLE, Esq.</item><item>THE REV. R. R. KNOTT, M.A.</item><item>J. SIMMONS, Esq.</item><item>THE REV. J. J. REW, M.A.</item><item>HENRY REMINGTON, Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Trustees.</head><item>W. C. JAY, Esq.</item><item>T. HUTCHINGS, Esq.</item><item>H. REMINGTON, Esq.</item><item>J. WATTS, Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Auditors.</head><item>GEO. BANKS, Esq.</item><item>ANDREW DORIA, Esq.</item><item>FRED. SADGROVE. Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Bankers.</head><item>SIR CHAS. PRICE, MARRVAT, &amp; CO. 3, King William Street, City.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Standing Counsel.</head><item>GILLERY PIGOTT, Esq.</item><item>EDWARD HEDGE, Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Physicians.</head><item>J. MACLEAN, M.D.</item><item>H. G. NOYES, M.D.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Surgeon.</head><item>JOHN W. SMITH, Esq.<lb/>M.R.C.S.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Solicitors.</head><item>HENRY BRADDON, Esq.</item><item>BLUNDELL HAWKES, Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Surveyor.</head><item>HENRY FLOWER, Esq.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Actuary and Secretary.</head><item>WILLIAM SWINEY, Esq. A.I.A.</item></list><pb  xml:id="p2a"/><p >THE OAK LIFE OFFICE undertakes all transactions involving the contingencies of human life, whether they relate to the Upper or Middle Classes, which are now almost peculiarly the objects of Life Assurance, or to those in a humbler sphere,—the industrious Labourer, Mechanic, or Artisan.</p><p >The constitution of the Office is upon the Mutual Principle, and embraces Assurances upon Single or Joint Lives and Survivorships, Endowments, and the granting of Immediate or Deferred Annuities.</p><p >Another important feature of this Office is, that after the 31st December, 1859, its Bonuses will be declared annually; while for the convenience of those Assurers who do not seek a participation of profits, a Table of Premiums has been expressly prepared. Great care has also been taken in the construction of Tables for the use of the Working Classes, upon strictly economical principles. In the case of Endowments, the Policies may, if desired, be made payable not only on the child <hi rend="italics">attaining twenty-one, but on its previous</hi> MARRIAGE <hi rend="italics">or advancement;</hi> and where death precedes either of those events, the Premiums already paid, subject to the deduction of a moderate commission, will be returned to the Assurer.</p><p >Loans of £20 and upwards are granted to Assurers on approved personal security; but the Borrower must, in every case, as a condition to the transaction, have effected a policy upon his own life with the Company.</p><p >The following are the leading features of this Office:—</p><p >1. ALL POLICIES INDISPUTABLE, except in cases of fraud.</p><p >2. The age of the Assured, on reasonable proof, admitted in the Policy.</p><p >3. If the Policy be effected within Three Months after the last Birthday of the Assured, the age is taken as of that data.</p><p >4. The first division of profits amongst Policy-holders assured by Table No 1, will take place on the 31st December, 1859, and every future division will be annual.</p><p >5. Bonuses may either be added to the sum assured, received in cash, or applied in diminution or extinction of future premiums.</p><p >6. Non-participating Tables of premiums on the lowest terms consistent with security.</p><p >7. No extra premiums for residence in any part of Europe, the North American Colonies, the United States of America, not further west than the river Mississippi, nor further south than the latitude of Washington; New Zealand, Australia, Bourbon, the Mauritius or the Cape.</p><p >8. All other Foreign and Colonial risks undertaken on liberal terms.</p><p >9. No Entrance Fees charged to Assurers, and the Stamp Duty on Policies paid by the Office.</p><p >10. Transfers of Policies registered without charge.</p><p >11. The Medical Referees of Proposed Assurers in all cases remunerated by the Office.</p><p >12. Proposed Assurers not required to attend personally before the Directors.</p><p >13. <hi rend="italics">Assurances effected daily, and Policies may be completed on the day of proposal.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p3a"/><p >14. Lapsed Policies in all cases renewable within Twelve Months, on proof of health and payment of a moderate fine.</p><p >15. Premiums payable yearly, half-yearly, or quarterly.</p><p >16. No extra premium charged to Officers in the Army and Navy not on active service, and members of Militia or Volunteer Corps treated as civilians.</p><p >17. Declined and Diseased Lives, in all cases where Life is not immediately affected, taken upon terms commensurate with the risk. <hi rend="italics">The greatest facilities are afforded to Agents of other offices in assuring the lives declined from time to time in their respective agencies.</hi></p><p >18. The Industrial and Working Classes may effect Assurances of not less than £10: the premium may be paid monthly.</p><p >19. The Office will purchase or make advances on Life Policies on which three annual premiums have been paid, <hi rend="italics">and will in special cases, where the Assurer is unable to continue the payment of the Premiums, maintain the Policy for the benefit of the family of the Assured, all advances so made by the Office being a debt upon the policy, upon which</hi> £5 <hi rend="italics">per cent, interest will be charged.</hi></p><p >20. One moiety of the premiums payable during the first seven years, on Policies effected for the whole term of life, may remain as a permanent charge on the Policy; or one-third of the premiums may remain as a permanent charge during the entire term.</p><p >21. Claims payable Three Months after satisfactory proof of death, or immediately after such proof, on deduction of the usual discount.</p><p >22. <hi rend="italics">Loans granted to Assurers, and all charges strictly moderate.</hi></p><p >23. Endowments, and every species of contingent Assurance, and immediate and deferred Annuities, on highly advantageous terms.</p><p >24 Thirty days granted for payment of annual premiums, fifteen for premiums payable half-yearly, and seven for premiums payable quarterly.—Premiums payable on the usual quarter days.</p><div type="section"><head >WIDOWS' AND ORPHANS' ANNUITY AND <lb/> ENDOWMENT FUND.</head><p >No species of Assurance is, perhaps, so much needed by the Professional, Commercial, and Industrial Classes as that which will secure to Widows and Orphans,—</p><p >1st. Annuities or Pensions of £10 and upwards, payable to Widows during life, or to their Children until parental support is no longer required by them.</p><p >2nd. Endowments or Fixed Sums, payable at a given period, to enable Widows to establish themselves in business, or to Children for the purposes of Education, or Premiums of Apprenticeship.</p><p >These objects, however, capable as they are of being carried out to the <hi rend="italics">mutual advantage</hi> of the Assurers and Assured, have been too generally neglected, although the few instances extant of Associations which have been especially established for their promotion, afford abundant proof of the extreme value, to the Members, of such Family Provisions, and of the complete success which has pecuniarily attended the Institutions themselves.</p><p >This Company, therefore, embraces the opportunity of rendering their <hi rend="italics">Scheme of Life Assurance</hi> as perfect as may be, by the
<pb xml:id="p4a"/>
Granting of Assurances of the kind above named, and devoting particular attention to them, so as to make this Department one of the most prominent and extensively useful of its distinctive features.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">A Board of Directors meets every Tuesday, at three o'clock; but Assurances may be effected daily.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">A liberal commission allowed to all parties introducing business.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">Prospectuses and Forms for Proposals may be had at the Company's Offices, and of the Agents throughout the Kingdom.</hi></p><closer >
<signed>W. SWINEY, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Actuary and Secretary.</hi></signed>
</closer></div><div type="section"><head >LIFE ASSURANCE.</head><p >“LIFE ASSURANCE places it within the power of every man of ordinary prudence, to decide whether he shall leave to his family the legacy of penury or independence.”</p><p >“It is unquestionably the duty of every man to provide, while he yet lives, for his own; we would say, that it is not more his duty to provide for their daily bread during his life, than it is to provide, as for as he can, against their being left penniless in the event of his death. Indeed, between these two duties there is no essential distinction, for Life Assurance makes the one as much a matter of current expenditure as the other. One part of his income can be devoted by the head of a family to the necessities of the present; another may be stored up by means of Life Assurance to provide against the future; and thus he may be said to do the whole of his duty towards his family, instead of, as is generally the case, only doing the half of it.”—<hi rend="italics">Chambers's Journal.</hi></p><p >“Whilst I respect the feelings of any man when sincerely and temperately expressed, yet I find great difficulty in understanding upon what grounds any husband or parent can excuse himself from employing all proper means to provide for those dependent on him; or, in providing for their present necessities how he can be content to leave the future in doubt and uncertainty. Is it right that those whom he professes to love and cherish should, in the event of his death, depend for their support on an appeal to the benevolent sympathies of friends or of strangers?</p><p >* * * * *</p><p >“The most common and fatal error committed by those who depend solely on their own exertions, for all that they now enjoy or can ever hope to possess, is in attempting to make a suitable provision for survivors by the slow and too frequently deceptive process of accumulating savings through a long course of years,—a process which is at any time liable to be interrupted by sickness to say nothing of the innumerable accidents and reverses incidental to humanity.”—<hi rend="italics">Rutter.</hi></p><p >“It ought farther to be considered that, without a system of mutual contribution, the savings of individuals would be ineffectual for the object proposed (securing a family provision). These savings, being small in amount could not be laid out to advantage. The proverbial uncertainty of human life would, in many instances, frustrate plans requiring years for development and completion. On the other hand, when the savings of a number are added, their added amount gives the facility of investing them to advantage. Experience has shown how easily and beneficially this can be done by means of Life Assurance, securing at once the best return for those savings, and a provision against that contingency which baffles human foresight, and otherwise also baffles human precaution.”—<hi rend="italics">Thoms.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p5a"/><p >To illustrate a few of the instances in which Life Assurance may be rendered beneficial, the following examples are given:—</p><p >A Person aged (say) 25 may secure £500 to be paid to his surviving family (or to any nominee whom he so wishes to benefit), in the event of his death, by the payment of £2. 15s. 0d. per quarter; £5. 7s. 1d. half-yearly; or £10. 8s. 4d. per annum.</p><p >A Person of the same age (25) may secure £1,000 in like manner, by the payment (on the half-credit system), for the first seven years, of £10. 18s. 9d. per annum.</p><p >Endowment Assurances may be effected, by which any fixed amount may be secured to be paid to the Assured on his attaining a specified age, or to his representatives in the event of his death occurring before he shall attain that age. Thus, a person aged 30 wishes to assure the sum of £500 to be paid him on his attaining the age of 60; if he survive that age, he has the whole benefit of the Assurance himself; if he die before attaining such age, it will be paid to his representatives. By this mode of Assurance, therefore (the most valuable in the whole scheme of Life Assurance), <hi rend="italics">a double object is secured, and a double contingency provided against:</hi> viz. if the Assured lives, he <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>rec ives</sic><corr>receives</corr></choice> the reward of his prudence and foresight; and if he dies, his representatives are benefited to the same extent, and this with but a trifling increase of premium.</p><p >A Party entitled to a Sum of Money, or other reversionary property, provided he survives another, may, by effecting a Policy of Assurance, secure his family against the loss which would otherwise ensue should his death occur before that of the party then in possession.</p><p >Occupiers of Property held under Leases determinable <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>e ther</sic><corr>either</corr></choice> by effluxion of time or on death, but renewable on payment of a fine, may, by effecting a Policy to an equivalent amount, receivable at the same period as the fine would become due, secure to themselves or their families the means of paying such fine.</p><p >A Person possessing only an Annuity ceasing at his death, may by setting apart only a small portion of his income, secure to his surviving relatives, or dependants, a future provision.</p><p >Partners through the medium of Life Assurance may secure the firm against financial <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>embarras ment</sic><corr>embarrassment</corr></choice>, consequent on the sudden withdrawal, by the excutors of a deceased partner, of such portion of the capital as may have been contributed by him.</p><p >Various pecuniary arrangements in connection with Marriage Settlement, may be safety and advantageously carried out by means of Life Assurance; where it would be competent for the Trustees to allow the husband the use of some portion of the Trust funds for business-capital, or otherwise, during his life, without prejudicing or endangering the interests of his children, who might be entitled to the funds after his decease.</p><p >A Creditor may secure eventual payment from his Debtor. A Debtor may secure eventual payment to his Creditor Many Mercantile and other transactions may be facilitated by means of assurances effected for short periods, adapted to the peculiar nature of the case.</p><pb  xml:id="p6a"/><p >Premiums payable Yearly, Half-Yearly, or Quarterly, for the Assurance of £100 on a Single Life, FOR THE WHOLE TERM OF LIFE.</p><p >
<table><head>WITH Participation of Profits.</head><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>Annual Premium</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Half Yearly.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Quarterly</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>20</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>25</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>26</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>27</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>28</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>29</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>31</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>32</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>33</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>34</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>35</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>36</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>37</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>38</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>39</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>40</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>41</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>42</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>43</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>44</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>45</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>46</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>47</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>48</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>49</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>50</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>51</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>52</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>53</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>54</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>55</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>56</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>57</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>58</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>59</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>60</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>11</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>WITHOUT Participation of Profits.</head><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>Annual Premium</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Half Yearly.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Quarterly</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£.</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>20</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>25</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>26</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>27</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>28</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>29</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>31</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>32</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>33</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>34</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>35</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>36</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>37</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>38</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>39</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>40</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>41</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>42</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>43</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>44</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>45</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>46</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>47</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>48</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>49</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>50</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>51</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>52</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>53</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>54</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>55</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>56</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>57</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>58</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>59</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>60</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table>
</p><p >_____ <hi rend="italics">Medical Referee, and Mr.</hi> _____ <hi rend="italics">Agent for</hi> _____ <hi rend="italics">and its Vicinity.</hi></p><p >Applications for the Appointment of Agent to be addressed to <lb/> the Actuary and Secretary.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7a"/><head >New Serial Work by Mr. Charles Lever.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 31<hi rend="italics">st of August will be published, Price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> THE FIRST MONTHLY NUMBER <lb/> OF <lb/> THE DOOD FAMILY ABROAD.</p><p >BY CHARLES LEVER, <lb/> AUTHOR OF “HARRY LORREQUER,” “CHARLES O'MALLEY,” &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >EACH NUMBER WILL CONTAIN <lb/> TWO ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</p><p >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8a"/><head >NEW WORKS AND NEW EDITIONS,</head><p >PUBLISHED BY <lb/> VIRTUE, HALL, &amp; VIRTUE, 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><div type="section"><head >NEW WORK BY FRANK FAIRLEGH.</head><div type="section"><opener >In 1 vol. 8vo, price 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, with Forty-two Illustrations by “PHIZ.”</opener><head >LEWIS ARUNDEL: <lb/> OR, <lb/> THE RAILROAD OF LIFE.</head><p >BY FRANK E. SMEDLEY, (FRANK FAIRLEGH.)</p><p >Tho main line, the branch lines, in short, <hi rend="italics">every line</hi> connected with this railroad is now completed, and the work thrown open to public inspection. Buy a copy! <hi rend="italics">that</hi> will be THE TICKET!</p><p >“The task of the reviewer becomes a pleasant one when such works as the one before us is forced upon his perusal. We must once more commend the taste and talent of the author of ‘Lewis Arundel.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Times.</hi></p><p >“The best tale going is ‘Lewis Arundel,’ by the author of ‘Frank Fairlegh.’ It displays a great deal of that sort of feeling for which we can find no better term than gentlemanly.”—<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“A very interesting and well told story, the style of which is remarkable for vivacity and freshness.”—<hi rend="italics">Birmingham Journal.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><opener >BY THE AUTHOR OF “LEWIS ARUNDEL.” <lb/> Complete in 1 vol. 8vo, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt,</opener><head >FRANK FAIRLEGH; <lb/> OR, <lb/> SCENES FROM THE LIFE OF A PRIVATE PUPIL.</head><p >With Thirty Illustrations by George Cruikshank.</p><p >“Its fame is very likely to be more durable than that of the majority of works of the kind.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life in London.</hi></p><p >“There is no writer of fiction since Sir Walter Scott who has so well deserved popularity as the author of this story.”—<hi rend="italics">Exeter Gazette.</hi></p></div></div><div type="section"><opener ><hi rend="italics">On July</hi> 1, 1852, <hi rend="italics">was Published, (to be continued Monthly),</hi>
<lb/> PART I. OF A NEW SERIES <lb/> OF</opener><head >SHARPE'S LONDON MAGAZINE.</head><p >CONDUCTED BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >The aid of the Publishers will be cordially given to obtain the best assistance that literary talent can supply. The work will be printed on improved paper, with new type; each Part will contain sixty-four pages of letter-press, with two interesting Engravings on steel; the price of One Shilling monthly will place the work within the reach of all classes, and with the active zeal of Editor, Authors, and Publishers in combination, the enlarged circulation and consequent augmentation of its utility, may be hoped for and anticipated.</p><p >Vols. I. to IX. of the First Series of “SHARPE'S LONDON MAGAZINE” may be had, elegantly bound in scarlet cloth, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each. Vols. X. to XV. (each containing Six Monthly Parts,) price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> are also ready. Neat Cloth Cases, for binding the Parts into half-yearly volumes, price 1<hi rend="italics">s,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, may be had through any Bookseller.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p9a"/><head >WORKS BY MR. AND MRS. S. C. HALL.</head><div><opener >Beautifully Illustrated, embellished, and bound in fancy cloth, 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> gilt edges,</opener><head >MIDSUMMER EVE. A FAIRY TALE OF LOVE.</head><p >BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><list  type="simple"><head>The Designs by</head><item>D. MACLISE, R.A.</item><item>C. STANFIELD, RA.</item><item>T. CRESWICK, A.R.A.</item><item>E. M. WARD, A.R.A.</item><item>A. ELMORE, A.R.A.</item><item>W. FROST, A.R.A.</item><item>F. W. TOPHAM.</item><item>KENNY MEADOWS.</item><item>F. W. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A.</item><item>&amp;c. &amp;c.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>The Engravings by</head><item>W. T. GREEN,</item><item>G. DALZIEL.</item><item>E. DALZIEL.</item><item>J. BASTIN.</item><item>J. WILLIAMS.</item><item>H. LINTON.</item><item>G. MEASOM.</item><item>W. MEASOM.</item><item>A. S. MASON.</item><item>&amp;c. &amp;c.</item></list><p >Embellished with upwards of Two Hundred Engravings on Wood.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >NEW EDITION REVISED BY A RECENT VISIT.<lb/>Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth gilt, </opener><head >A WEEK AT KILLARNEY,</head><p >BY MR. AND MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >BEING <lb/> A GUIDE TO TOURISTS TO THE LAKES OF KILLARNEY.</p><p >The Work is Illustrated by Twenty Engravings on Steel, <lb/> FROM DRAWINGS BY T. CRESWICK, A.R.A., &amp; W. H. BARTLETT.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Also,</hi> 110 <hi rend="italics">Engravings on Wood by various Artists.</hi></p><p >Describing the most Picturesque of the Beauties, the most remarkable of the Natural <lb/> Features, and the most interesting of the Ancient Ruins, of the Killarney Lakes, <lb/> and the several Routes through Ireland which conduct to them.</p><p >WITH MAPS OF THE LAKES AND THE ADJACENT DISTRICTS.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >New Edition, in 3 vols. super-royal 8vo, price 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt,</opener><head >IRELAND: ITS SCENERY, CHARACTER, &amp;c.</head><p >BY MR. AND MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >Illustrated with Forty-eight Steel Engravings, <lb/> AFTER DRAWINGS BY T. CRESWICK, A.R.A.</p><p >FIVE HUNDRED EXQUISITE WOOD ENGRAVINGS, AND EIGHTEEN <lb/> MAPS OF THE COUNTIES.</p><p >The Authors of this Work have laboured with zeal and industry to obtain such topographical and statistical information as may be useful to those who visit Ireland, or who desire the means of judging correctly as to its capabilities and condition. But their especial duty has been to associate with more important details such incidents, descriptions, legends, traditions, and personal sketches, as may excite interest in those who might be deterred from the perusal of mere facts, if communicated in a less popular form.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10a"/><opener >DEDICATED, BY COMMAND, TO H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, &amp;c. &amp;c.</opener><head >THE ART-JOURNAL: <lb/> MONTHLY JOURNAL OF THE ARTS.</head><p >Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">COMMENCING A NEW VOLUME WITH EACH YEAR.</hi></p><p >Each Monthly Part contains Three Original Works engraved on Steel, by the best British Engravers; also between Forty and Fifty fine Engravings on Wood.</p><p >TO NEW SUBSCRIBERS.</p><p >The ART-JOURNAL for the three years, 1849, 1850, and 1851 properly form a New Series of that work. With these Volumes it was enlarged in size and improved in character; and with the year 1849 began the “VERNON GALLERY,” a series of fine and original Engravings on Steel. New Subscribers, therefore, are informed that a complete series of the ART-JOURNAL may be obtained by procuring these THREE volumes. Each volume contains Twenty-four Line Engravings of the “VERNON GALLERY,” and Twelve Engravings of Statues on Steel, with about Eight Hundred Engravings on Wood, elegantly bound in cloth, for One Guinea and a Half.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >In One handsome Volume, price One Guinea, cloth gilt,</opener><head >THE ART-JOURNAL <lb/> ILLUSTRATED CATALOGUE <lb/> OF THE <lb/> GREAT INDUSTRIAL EXHIBITION OF 1851, <lb/> CONTAINING <lb/> UPWARDS OF FOURTEEN HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD, <lb/> AND A FRONTISPIECE ON STEEL.</head><p >This Volume will be soon OUT OF PRINT: it cannot be reprinted: and there is no question of its largely augmenting in value when classed among Scarce Works: those by whom it is required will therefore do well to obtain copies early.</p><p >“It is at once interesting, useful, and beautiful;” “a valuable reminder of the Exhibition to those by whom it was visited, and equally valuable to those to whom the enjoyment was denied.” “A beautiful book for the drawing-room, and a useful instructor for all classes.”</p></div><div type="section"><opener >Now publishing, in Parts at One Shilling,</opener><head >A CYCLOPEDIA OF USEFUL ARTS,</head><p >MECHANICAL AND CHEMICAL, MANUFACTURES, MINING, AND <lb/> ENGINEERING, <lb/> EDITED BY CHARLES TOMLINSON.</p><p >Illustrated with about Two Thousand Engravings.</p><p >LONDON:—VIRTUE, HALL, AND VIRTUE, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11a"/><head >NEW WORK OF FINE ART.</head><div type="section"><head >THE <lb/> NATIONAL GALLERY OF BRITISH PICTURES</head><p >(PRESENTED TO THE NATION BY ROBERT VERNON, ESQ.) <lb/> AND OF MODERN SCULPTURE.</p><p >In Monthly Parts.</p><p >Each containing THREE LINE-ENGRAVINGS from the PICTURES in the VERNON GALLERY, and ONE ENGRAVING OF MODERN SCULPTURE. With accompanying Letter-press, from the pens of several eminent Authors. Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each Part.</p><p >EDITED BY S. C. HALL, ESQ.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >UNDER THE PATRONAGE OF HER MOST GRACIOUS MAJESTY, AND HIS ROYAL <lb/> HIGHNESS PRINCE ALBERT, K.G.</opener><head >PROOF IMPRESSIONS OF THE ENGRAVINGS <lb/> OF <lb/> THE VERNON COLLECTION.</head><p >These Proofs are all printed on India paper, and published in Monthly Parts, each Part to consist of Three Plates. With the First Part will be delivered a handsome Portfolio, made to contain the Series of Proofs for Twelve Months; and a similar Portfolio will be given to the Subscribers at regular intervals. Explanatory letterpress pages accompany each volume.</p><p >
<table><head>TERMS OF SUBSCRIPTION:—</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>ARTIST'S PROOFS, of which only 150 will be printed. The Part</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>PROOFS BEFORE LETTERS, of which only 200 will be printed. The Part</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>LETTERED PROOFS, of which only 150 will be printed. The Part</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Early application for these Proofs is necessary, as the above numbers are strictly adhered to.</hi></p></div></div><div type="section"><head >DAILY FAMILY DEVOTION;<lb/>OR, GUIDE TO FAMILY WORSHIP.</head><p >BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., <lb/> Minister of the Scotch National Church, Russell Street, London.</p><p >This work, consisting of a Hymn, a portion of Scripture, and an appropriate Prayer for the Morning and Evening of every day in the year, is designed to introduce or facilitate the practice of Family Worship; and by constructing the daily prayers on the passage of Scripture selected for reading, greater variety, interest, and practical use are associated with the exercise.</p><p >The Work will be published in Monthly Parts, price One Shilling each. Every Part will contain four sheets, or 32 Quarto pages. It will be completed in about 23 Parts, forming One Volume. The printing and paper will be of a superior character.</p><p >LONDON:—VIRTUE, HALL, AND VIRTUE, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p12a"/><opener >12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> NEW SILVER ELECTRO PLATE,</head><p >Possessing in a pre-eminent degree the qualities of Sterling Silver.</p><p >A table may be elegantly furnished with this beautiful manufacture at a <lb/> fifth of the cost of Silver, from which it cannot be distinguished.</p><p >W. MOTT invites particular attention to his very extensive stock of all articles of Plate required for the Sideboard, Dinner and Breakfast Tables, now manufactured in this elegant material, comprising superb Epergnes, Candelabra, Salad Stands, Wine Coolers, Waiters, Corner Dishes, Meat and Venison Dishes, Dish Covers, Cruet Frames, Liqueur Stands, Spoons, and Forks, Tea and Coffee Services, Tea Kettles, Toast Racks, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>TEA POTS from</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0 to</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0 each</cell></row><row><cell>CRUET FRAMES, great variety from</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0 to</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0 each</cell></row><row><cell>LIQUEUR FRAMES, elegant designs from</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0 to</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0 each</cell></row><row><cell>WAITERS, of every size, from 8 to 24 inches, commencing at</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0 each</cell></row><row><cell>FLOWER VASES, with glass linings at</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0 to</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0 each</cell></row><row><cell>DISH COVERS, 12 to 20 Guineas the set.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SPOONS AND FORKS.</head><row><cell/><cell/><cell>Fiddle.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Threaded.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>King's.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Table Spoons</cell><cell>per dozen</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table Forks</cell><cell>per dozen</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Dessert Spoons</cell><cell>per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Dessert Forks</cell><cell>per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Tea Spoons</cell><cell>per dozen</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Gravy Spoons</cell><cell>per pair</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Sauce Ladles</cell><cell>per pair</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Soup Ladles</cell><cell>each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Salt Spoons</cell><cell>per pair</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLETS OF PRICES GRATIS.</p><p >W. MOTT, 12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</p><div><pb  xml:id="p13a"/><opener >Manufactory, 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON.</opener><head >English Watches that may be relied upon for <lb/> Accuracy and Durability.</head><p >MOTT'S <lb/> English Patent Levers in Gold Cases and <lb/> Gold Dial.—Ten Guineas.</p><p >In order to assimilate as nearly as possible the cost of his best English Watches to the price of Foreign, over which they possess an immeasurable superiority in the grand requirements of correct performance and durability, W. MOTT has made a considerable reduction in the scale of prices, at the same time maintaining the high character by which, for so many years, they have been distinguished.</p><p >
<table><head>GOLD CASES.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Ladies' Gold Watches, double back and gold dial</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Ladies' Gold Watches, with engraved back</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Ladies' Gold Watches, full size, highly finished</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Ladies' Gold Watches, engraved back</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Gentlemen's Gold Watches, enamel dial</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial engraved back</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, very flat construction</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SILVER CASES.</head><row><cell>Patent Lever, double back, jewelled</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, to go while winding</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, very flat construction</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Patent Lever, Hunting cases</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >WATCHES REPAIRED, AND ONE LENT GRATIS DURING THE TIME, <lb/> AT THE <lb/> MANUFACTORY, <lb/> No. 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, <lb/> CONNER OF FRIDAY STREET.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14a"/><head >CROCHET COTTON <lb/> FOR THE MILLION.</head><p >MARSLAND, SON, &amp; CO.</p><p >Beg to present the annexed CROCHET PATTERN, and solicit and recommend a trial of their COTTON, which is superior to any other in use.</p><p >Their CROCHET COTTON is made of a peculiar material, which renders it exceedingly pleasant to work with; it has a soft, yet cabled surface, is extremely free from fibre, is warranted not to twist or curl in the working, or to shrink in the washing, and has an extraordinary silkiness of finish, which causes the pattern, when crocheted and washed, to possess a beautiful pearly appearance never before attained by any other manufacture.</p><p >M. S. &amp; Co.'s manufacture of CROCHET COTTON contains every variety of Colors, warranted fast.</p><p >The Editresses of the “Ladies' Newspaper,” the “Ladies' Own Book,” the Editor of the “Shortway Edging and Round D'Oyley,” the “Exhibition and Teingnmouth,” the Editor of the “Bijou,” and all the leading Publishers of the present day, are bringing out their works and patterns to suit the numbers of MARSLAND, SON, &amp; Co.'s Crochet Cotton.</p><p >M S. &amp; Co. also manufacture NINE CORD, SIX CORD, and THREE CORD SEWING COTTON, of a quality equal to their Crochet Cotton, which is sold at the same establishments.</p><div type="section"><head >The full Lengths are guaranteed.</head><p >Sold retail by the principal Berlin wool venders, drapers, haberdashers, smallware dealers, &amp;c.</p><p >N.B.—The trade supplied by Messrs. BLOCK and SON, Newgate Street, LONDON; and at the Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester, where all orders by post or personal application will be attended to.</p><p >LONDON AGENT: EDWARD WRIGHT, 33, LAWRENCE LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15a"/><head >CRESTS AND CENTRES FOR D'OYLEYS, &amp;C.</head><p >MARSLAND, SON, &amp; Co.'s Crochet Thread, No. 24; Penelope Crochet Hook, No. 3. Work the ground in open, and the design in close squares. <hi rend="italics">Vide “Ladies' Newspaper,”</hi> page 205, 1851.—Edited by Madlle. DUFOUR.</p><p >Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16a"/><head >A BOLD STROKE.</head><p >IT is rather a Bold Stroke when a Man whose earthly property, including a Wife and a very large Family, will not fetch more than Fifty Pounds, but firm in his resolution, and determined in his steps, he avows he will be possessed of Fifty Thousand Pounds, Yet such a Stroke is reasonable and safe enough if he procures a suitable and economical OUTFIT at E. MOSES &amp; SON's, and with that proceeds to Australia, the land for gold and wages.</p><p >It is rather a Bold Stroke when a Lady or Gentleman shakes off all old associations, breaks through the restrictions of habit, abandons a whole category of Tradesmen, and resolves the whole of their patronage shall be given to one establishment. Yet this is very frequently and very constantly done. When such Lady or Gentleman has inspected the novel styles, materials, fashions, and inventions which at E. MOSES &amp; SON's are accompanied with the most reasonable charges.</p><p >It may be thought a Bold Stroke, but it is a sure and effective one, to claim for E. MOSES &amp; SON the first and foremost place as MERCHANT TAILORS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, and OUTFITTERS TO ALL PARTS OF THE WORLD. Such a Stroke has the strongest confirmation in the united testimony of thousands who give their constant patronage to the establishment of E. MOSES &amp; SON.</p><p >JUVENILE CLOTHING and DRESS for young Gentlemen about to return to the duties of the School, <hi rend="italics">comfortable, graceful, fashionable, and serviceable.</hi></p><p >MAGNIFICENT STYLES OF SUMMER DRESS in every elegant <hi rend="italics">fabric, style,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">fashion.</hi></p><p >SPORTING DRESS, celebrated throughout the world for <hi rend="italics">appropriate styles,</hi> which afford perfect case and comfort, at E. MOSES AND SON's.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >LIST OF PRICES,<lb/>READY MADE OR MADE TO MEASURE.</head><p >
<table><head>SPRING AND SUMMER OVERCOATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>The New Vicuna Summer Overcoat from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Lustre Coats, in a variety of light and elegant textures from 8s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The Albert Wrapper, in a registered light material from 15s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super light texture cloths, in every shape, including the Bequeme from 18s. to</cell><cell>2.</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The New Parisian Coat-Cape, made only by E. MOSES &amp; SON from 30s. to</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The Nepaulese Wrapper, weighing only six ounces from</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Boys Spring and Summer Coats, in all the above materials and shapes, at proportionably low prices.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LOUNGING AND MORNING COATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Holland Cambridge Coats from</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Alpaca Lustre Coats from 5s. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Cashmere and Orleans Coats 6s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Mixed Summer Cloth, in all shades from 15s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super cloth, of a light texture, black and coloured from 16s. to</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Shooting Jackets, in a variety of materials, &amp;c from 10s. 6d. to</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>DRESS COATS.</head><row><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><cell>Dress Coat from 17s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super Saxony Coat from 25s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Imperial, usually called best</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Best quality, West of England</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>FROCK COATS.</head><row><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><cell>Frock Coat from</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Super Coat from</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Saxony Coat from</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Imperial Coat from</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Very best from</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SPRING AND SUMMER WAISTCOATS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Fancy Quilting Vest from 2s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Plain and long Alpaca Lustre from 3s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>White Quilting, for Dress from 4s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black Cassimere from 4s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Embroidered Cloth from 10s. 6d. to</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>A large assortment of Fancy Thibets and other materials from 4s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SPRING AND SUMMER TROUSERS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Tweeds from 4s. 8d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Scotch Tweeds, in great variety from 8s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black Cassimere, for Dress from 9s. 6d. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fancy Summer Doeskin from 8s. 6d. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>A large variety of Fancy Checks and Stripes, with borders from 10s. 6d. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>White Drill Trousers from 5s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Plain and Fancy Gambroon from 6s. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>A splendid assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskin 18s., 22s. to</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Summer cloth, with ⅞ train, from</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Superior cloth</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Superfine cloth</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LIVERIES.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Page's suit, from</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Footman's</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Groom's</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Coachman's</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MOURNING.</head><row><cell/><cell>£</cell><cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell></row><row><cell>Ready made at Five Minutes' Notice.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Suit complete</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Boy's complete</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Made to Measure in Five Hours.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><p >A HANDSOME ALMANACK for the year 1852, to be had Gratis on application.</p><p >NOTICE.—The Parasol and Mantle Departments are now replete with every novelty of the season.</p><p >A New Book, entitled “The Library of Elegance,” containing full directions for self-measurement, can be had gratis on application or forwarded post free to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >OBSERVE.—Any article purchased either ready made or made to measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged or the money returned.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON have no connection with any other house, in or out of London, except the following:—</p><p >London City Establishments:—154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, 86, Aldgate, opposite the Church, all communicating.</p><p >London West End Branch:—506, 507, 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, 3, Hart-street, all communicating.</p><p >Bradford, Yorkshire Branch, 19, Bridge-street.</p><p >Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p><p >TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT &amp; SHOE MAKERS, <lb/> AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed from sunset, on Friday, till sunset, on Saturday, when business is</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">resumed till</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p17a"/><head >HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS,</head><p >Sent free by post.</p><p >It contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One <lb/> Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> Sent free by post.</p><p >In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, <lb/> Mahogany, Rosewood, &amp; Walnut Tree Woods; <lb/> Also their <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Their New Warerooms enable them to keep one of each design fixed for inspection.</hi></p><p >They have also, in addition to their usual stock, a great variety of the best designs of <lb/> PARISIAN BEDSTEADS, <lb/> BOTH IN WOOD AND IRON, WHICH THEY HAVE JUST IMPORTED.</p><p >HEAL &amp; SON, <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTURERS, <lb/> 196, (opposite the Chapel), Tottenham Court Road.</p><p >Bradbury and Evans, Printers, Whitefriars.</p></div></back></text></TEI>