<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>Bleak House No. XIV:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Ingrid Pohl</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Andrew Leiter, and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.  265 K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page Bleak House No. XIV. April.</title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition/></editionStmt><extent>   80  p.,   ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">London:Bradbury &amp; Evans, Bouverie Street.</publisher><date>1853</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Dickens 21   c.2  (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p/></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings </title>
</bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language><language ident="ara">Arabic</language><language ident="fre">French</language><language ident="lat">Latin</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords scheme="LCSH"><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-18"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-16">Andrew Leiter finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-02">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_verso_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">No. XIV. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate> APRIL.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE
</docAuthor><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLACHAN, DUBLIN.<lb/>
The Author of this Work notifies that it is his intention to reserve the
<gap extent="four words" reason="page cut off"/></docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx2"/><head >TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</head><p >EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT.</p><p >WEIGHT 10 oz.</p><p >Sole Manufacturers of the celebrated Pocket Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on Saddle; the most <hi rend="italics">important</hi> feature in this <hi rend="italics">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.—Price according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat.</p><p >Stout Siphonias, 25s. to 35s. Overalls, 10s. 6d. Yacht Jackets, 18s. 6d.</p><p >Reversible Alpacas, &amp;c.</p><p >NOTICE.—NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p><p >EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416, STRAND, <lb/> Four Doors West of the Adelphi Theatre.</p><div type="section"><head >OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head><p >WATERPROOF.—“The lightest and most effectual, is the SIPHONIA, made by EDMISTON &amp; SON, of 69, Strand; they can be carried in the hat or pocket.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life, April</hi> 20<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><p >“A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable weather of the season, has been manufactured by EDMISTON &amp; SON. It is remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome umbrella.”—<hi rend="italics">Home News, May</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p><p >Leggings or Overalls. Yacht Jackets. Fishing and Shooting Hats or Caps. Driving Gloves. Gun Covers. Gig Aprons. Sou-Westers. Goloshes.</p><p >Ladies' Capes, with Hoods. Ditto Paletots. Air Cushions. Ditto Beds &amp; Pillows. India Rubber Portable Folding Baths. Nursing Aprons. Crib Sheets.</p><p >The Newly Invented Swimming Gloves, <lb/> Of great propelling power.</p><p >EDMISTON'S LIFE-BELTS NONE SHOULD BE WITHOUT.</p><p >FISHING AND SHOOTING BOOTS, soft and pliable, require no dressing; Fishing Stockings, 25s. per pair; and every description of India Rubber and Gutta Percha Goods, Piping. Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c.</p><p >WATER BEDS ON SALE OR HIRE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">To Shippers a liberal Discount to the Trade.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416. STRAND, Four Doors West of the Adelphi.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisements"><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. XIV.—April, 1853.</opener><head >BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing in Monthly Parts, at</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s., and in Volumes,</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s., the</hi> </opener><head >ENCYCLOPÆDIA BRITANNICA </head><p >EIGHTH EDITION GREATLY IMPROVED AND BROUGHT UP TO <lb/> THE PRESENT TIME.</p><p >Just Published, Volume I., Part II., containing <lb/> A NEW DISSERTATION ON THE RISE, PROGRESS, AND <lb/> CORRUPTIONS OF CHRISTIANITY, <lb/> BY RICHARD WHATELY, D. D., ARCHBISHOP OF DUBLIN.</p><p >VOLUME II., <hi rend="italics">the</hi> FIRST PART <hi rend="italics">of which will be Published on the</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st of June, besides numerous New Articles, will contain the following:</hi>—AGRICULTURE, <hi rend="italics">the Practical Part, with all the latest Improvements, by</hi> JOHN WILSON, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">Farmer, Berwickshire.</hi> AGRICULTURAL CHEMISTRY, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> THOMAS ANDERSON, M.D., <hi rend="italics">Professor of Chemistry in the University of Glasgow, and Lecturer on Agricultural Chemistry to the Highland and Agricultural Society.</hi> AFFGHANISTAN <hi rend="italics">and several other articles on</hi> INDIA, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> EDWARD THORNTON, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">of the Statistical Department in the East India House, and Author of the Gazetteer of Scinde, &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> ÆSCHYLUS, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> JOHN STUART BLACKIE, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">Professor of Greek in the University of Edinburgh.</hi> ADDISON, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> WILLIAM SPALDING, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">Professor of Rhetoric in the University of St. Andrews.</hi> AFRICA, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> AUGUSTUS PETERMANN, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">Physical Geographer to the Queen, and Secretary to the Geographical Society.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">Other new articles for future volumes are now in progress. Among these may be mentioned—</hi>ATTERBURY, <hi rend="italics">by the</hi> RIGHT HON. THOMAS BABBINGTON MACAULAY, M.P. BOTANY, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> JOHN HUTTON BALFOUR, M.D., F.R.S.E., <hi rend="italics">Professor of Botany in the University of Edinburgh.</hi></p><p >All the Articles will be brought up to the present advanced state of knowledge. The Work will be completed in 21 Volumes; and it will be the endeavour of the Proprietors to secure the utmost regularity of publication.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Just Published in Folio, half-bound Morocco gilt, Price</hi> 56<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></opener><head >BLACK'S GENERAL ATLAS OF THE WORLD,</head><p >  With New Edition 1853, Seventy Maps, Engraved and Coloured in the first style of Art, embracing all the latest Discoveries, including those of CAPTAIN INGLEFIELD, in the Arctic Regions, &amp;c., and a COMPLETE INDEX of 60,000 Names.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">This Work is published on the plan of small impressions, and frequent new and corrected issues. The Publishers are thus enabled to take advantage of every Discovery as it appears, and to offer the Public an Atlas that can be relied upon for accuracy, beauty, and comprehensiveness.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Lately Published in</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">Vols.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo., Price</hi> 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >LIFE OF LORD JEFFREY.</head><p >By LORD COCKBURN, one of the Judges of the Court of Session. Second Edition. 2 vols. 8vo, 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p><p >“Our expectations on taking up these volumes were very high, and they have not been disappointed. The book contains a variety of excellent matter, and the letters of Lord Jeffrey will heighten the respect that attaches to his name.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >“Taken altogether, this is a most pleasing and satisfactory book.”—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now Ready, beautifully bound in Cloth, Gilt Edges, Price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> <lb/> A NEW AND ELEGANT EDITION OF </opener><head > UNCLE TOM'S CABIN,</head><p > Profusely Illustrated by MR. MATTHEW URLWIN SEARS, with a Frontispiece by JOHN GILBERT <lb/> and Ornamental Title-Page by “PHIZ.”</p><closer >EDINBURGH: ADAM &amp; CHARLES BLACK.</closer><closer >LONDON: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; CO.; LONGMAN &amp; CO.; WHITTAKER &amp; CO.; <lb/> HAMILTON ADAMS, &amp; CO.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >PEOPLE'S EDITION.</head><head >ALISON'S <lb/> HISTORY OF EUROPE, <lb/> FROM THE <lb/> COMMENCEMENT OF THE FRENCH REVOLUTION IN 1789 <lb/> TO THE BATTLE OF WATERLOO.</head><p >TO BE PUBLISHED</p><p >Monthly, in 44 Parts, with Illustrations, at One Shilling;</p><p >Weekly, in Numbers, at Three-halfpence;</p><p >In Volumes, Quarterly, price Four Shillings, handsomely bound in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Publication will commence on Saturday, the</hi> 30<hi rend="italics">th April, and will be continued</hi> <lb/> <hi rend="italics">regularly till the Work is completed.</hi></p><p >THE period embraced in this History is by far the most important and interesting which has occurred in the history of mankind, and the one to which the attention of future generations of men, to the end of the world, will be turned with undying eagerness. The immense number of works relating to the subject which have issued from the press in every country of Europe, and the avidity with which they are still bought and read, proves the universality and durability of this interest. Every social question was agitated, every element of social happiness, every spring of social improvement, developed during that period. It was then, for the first time, that the principles of freedom, inherent in the human heart, were fully unfolded, and the passions evolved, which are manifestly destined to move and affect mankind in every succeeding age. In treating of so great and important a subject, it has been the aim of the Author to attend chiefly to the following subjects:—</p><p >1. To unfold, so far as it is given to mortals to do so, the ends of the Almighty in the direction of human affairs, and the laws of the moral world by which these ends are wrought out. He believes that these laws are as fixed and irresistible as those of gravitation, and that the greatest misfortunes of mankind have arisen from their having, in ignorance or error, run counter to them.</p><p >2. To illustrate the temporal as well as spiritual blessings which Christianity has conferred upon mankind; the fatal consequences which have everywhere
<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p >[Continued on opposite page</p></note>
<pb xml:id="p3"/>
immediately followed the oblivion of its precepts; and the evils which have as invariably attended the corruptions which human ambition has engrafted on the Divine original.</p><p >3. To bring forward into bright light the many noble and generous actions of men <hi rend="italics">in all ranks,</hi> and in all countries, during that eventful period; and exhibit as prominently the selfish and vicious deeds by which it was disgraced, holding up the former to the admiration, the latter to the execration of mankind.</p><p >4. To unfold the causes and errors which have hitherto so much impeded, in so many countries, the march of freedom; to show how it has happened that that blessing—one of the greatest accorded by Providence to mankind—has been generally lost, and by what means it can alone be permanently won, and its advantages secured to the future generations of men.</p><p >5. To commemorate the glorious deeds of <hi rend="italics">all the nations</hi> engaged in the terrible strife which the History narrates; and in an especial manner, without deviating from the impartiality which is the first duty of an historian, to record the memorable part which this country took in the course of it, the immortal actions of her sons, and the lasting consequences which have resulted to Great Britain and the world from the triumph which they achieved.</p><p >6. To record the arguments, on both sides, on all the great political and social questions which were agitated in this country, and on the Continent, during the period; and by tracing the measures adopted on either side to their ultimate effects, to endeavour to discover where the truth really lies between them, and what course of policy, on the part of Government and the People, is most conducive to the great ends of social improvement and general happiness.</p><p >The size to which the work necessarily extended, rendered the earlier Editions in a great degree known only to the wealthier classes. But the success which has attended the cheaper reprint in 20 volumes, of which 9000 have been sold, has suggested the idea of placing the work within the reach of a class who might find even that edition beyond their means; while the great circulation of the People's Editions which have been published in America, of which above 50,000 copies have issued from the press in that country, induces the hope that a similar undertaking in this country will meet with corresponding public approval. As it was for the general welfare of humanity that the Author has exerted himself, and for no class interest or separate advantage, it is in the approbation of the great body of the People that he looks for his highest reward, and the attainment of the chief object of his ambition.</p><closer >WILLIAM BLACKWOOD &amp; SONS, EDINBURGH AND LONDON.</closer><closer >Orders received by all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >WORKS IN PREPARATION.</head><p >I. <lb/> ROME: REGAL AND REPUBLICAN. A History for Families. By JANE M. STRICKLAND. Edited by AGNES STRICKLAND, Authoress of “Lives of the Queens of England.” [<hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st. of May.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> BREMER—HOMES IN THE NEW WORLD. Impressions of America. By FREDRIKA BREMER. [<hi rend="italics">In May.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> MEMORIALS OF EARLY CHRISTIANITY, presenting, in a graphic, compact, and popular form. some of the Memorable Events of Early Ecclesiastical History. By Rev. J. G. MIALL, Author of “Footsteps of our Forefathers.” Post 8vo., with Illustrations. [<hi rend="italics">Shortly.</hi></p><p >IV. <lb/> THE PHILOSOPHY OF ATHEISM EXAMINED AND COMPARED WITH CHRISTIANITY; a Course of Popular Lectures delivered at the Mechanics' Institute, Bradford, on Sunday Afternoons in the Winter of 1852—53. By Rev. B. GODWIN, D.D.</p><p >V. <lb/> ROSALIE; or, “The Truth shall make you Free.” An Authentic Narrative. Edited by Rev. JOSEPH RIDGEWAY, A.M., of Sydenham. With recommendatory Preface by M. ADOLPH MONOD. In fcap 8vo.</p><p >VI. <lb/> JERDAN (William), AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF, with his Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences, and Correspondence, during the last Forty Years. Vol. IV., completing the Work. With a Portrait of Sir E. B. Lytton, and View of Knebworth.</p><p >VII. <lb/> RODWELL'S CHILDREN'S FIRST STEPS TO ENGLISH HISTORY. With numerous Illustrations. New Edition, revised.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> THE FARMER'S ASSISTANT, AND AGRICULTURIST'S CALENDAR. New and Enlarged Edition. By JOHN GRIEVE, Engineer, &amp;c.</p><p >IX. <lb/> MOWBRAY'S TREATISE ON DOMESTIC AND ORNAMENTAL POULTRY. Plates. New Edition, enlarged.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RECENTLY PUBLISHED.</head><p >X. <lb/> BASES OF BELIEF. An Examination of Christianity as a Divine Revelation by the Light of Recognised Facts and Principles. In Four Parts. By EDWARD MIALL, M.P., 8vo. cloth, 10s. 6d.</p><p >XI. <lb/> THE HISTORICAL GEOGRAPHY OF THE OLD AND NEW TESTAMENTS. By J. T. WHEELER, F.R.G.S. Illustrated with Five coloured Maps, and large View of Jerusalem, with a Plan of the ancient City. In small folio, neatly bound, price 7s. 6d.</p><p >XII. <lb/> ANALYSIS AND SUMMARY OF OLD AND NEW TESTAMENT HISTORY. By the same Author. New Edition. 2 vols. post 8vo, price 5s. 6d. each.</p><p >XIII. <lb/> LETTERS AND POEMS, BY BERNARD BARTON. With Memoir. Edited by his Daughter. New Edition, with Portrait. Fcap. cloth, 3s. 6d; large paper, 10s.</p><p >XIV. <lb/> NAOMI; or, The Last Days of Jerusalem. By Mrs. J. B. WEBB. New Edition, with Cuts. Foolscap 8vo, cloth lettered, price 7s. 6d.</p><p >“One of the most interesting works we have read for some time. The sentiments are appropriate, the style is graceful, and the tale is well contrived. * * * We are not, then, surprised at the popularity it has attained, it deserves it; and we cordially wish it further success.”—<hi rend="italics">Metropolitan.</hi></p><p >XV. <lb/> CANADIAN CRUSOES. By Mrs. TRAILL, (late CATHERINE PARR STRICKLAND). Price 6s., in fcap. cloth, gilt edges, with numerous Illustrations.</p><p >XVI. <lb/> WINTER EVENINGS; or, Tales of Travellers. By MARIA HACK. New Edition, with Illustrations. Foolscap cloth, 3s. 6d.</p><p >XVII. <lb/> SANDFORD AND MERTON. New Edition, with Gilbert's Designs. 18mo. cloth, 2s.</p><closer >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><head >NEW SPORTING NEWSPAPER.</head><p >Enlarged to 72 Columns.</p><p >THE Proprietors have great pleasure in announcing that the Patronage bestowed upon this New Sporting and Family Paper, justifies them in enlarging it to the full extent allowed by Act of Parliament, and that on and after the 2nd of April (being the First Number of the New Quarter), <lb/> THE FIELD, <lb/> OR, <lb/> COUNTRY GENTLEMAN'S NEWSPAPER, <lb/> Will consist of Twenty-four Pages, <lb/> WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY LEECH, ANSDELL, BROWNE, <lb/> WEIR, DUTTON, WEEDON, &amp; OTHERS.</p><p >THIS PAPER IS ESPECIALLY DEVOTED TO <lb/> HUNTING, <lb/> RACING, <lb/> FISHING, <lb/> SHOOTING, <lb/> COURSING, <lb/> ARCHERY, <lb/> YACHTING, <lb/> CRICKETING, <lb/> FARMING, <lb/> AND POULTRY KEEPING; <lb/> Agricultural and Health-giving pursuits generally. At the same time it contains ample and original summaries of all the News of the Week, Parliamentary Proceedings, Law and Police Reports, full Lists of Markets, Theatricals, Fashionable Intelligence, Reviews of Books, Veterinary Information, &amp;c. &amp;c. The conductors hope by a careful exclusion of every subject of objectionable character, to render “THE FIELD” all that a Gentleman's Sporting and Family Paper should be.</p><p > THE FIELD, Price Sixpence, is published every Saturday in time for the Morning Mails, <lb/> It may be obtained from all respectable News Agents.</p><closer >PUBLISHING OFFICE, 4, BRYDGES STREET, COVENT GARDEN, <lb/> Where Advertisements and Communications to the Editor can be addressed.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Now ready, at all the Libraries, in 3 vols.,</opener><head > HARRY MUIR. A Story of Scottish Life.</head><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “PASSAGES IN THE LIFE OF MRS. MARGARET MAITLAND,” &amp;c.</p><p >“We prefer ‘Harry Muir’ to most of the Scottish novels that have appeared since Galt's domestic stories were published. This new tale by the Author of ‘Margaret Maitland’ is a real picture of the weakness of man's nature and the depths of woman's kindness. The narrative, to repeat our praise, is not one to be entered on or parted from without our regard for its writer being increased.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p><closer >HURST &amp; BLACKETT, PUBLISHERS, SUCCESSORS TO HENRY COLBURN, 13, GREAT <lb/> MARLBOROUGH-STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just published, crown 8vo, cloth, price 5s.</opener><head >SPIRITS OF THE PAST.</head><p >AN HISTORICAL POEM: With copious Biographical Notes.</p><p >By NICHOLAS MICHELL, Author of “Ruins of Many Lands,” &amp;c.</p><p >CONTENTS:—<hi rend="italics">Scripture Characters;</hi> Cain to Esther—<hi rend="italics">Military Heroes;</hi> Xerxes to Napoleon—<hi rend="italics">Celebrated Women;</hi>
<lb/> Aspasia of Athens to Lady Jane Grey.</p><p >“ <hi rend="italics">‘Spirits of the Past’</hi> is a work worthy the Author of ‘Ruins of Many Lands.’ The historical and biographical <hi rend="italics">tableaux</hi> are numerous, and most admirably delineated.”—<hi rend="italics">Tait's Edinburgh Magazine.</hi></p><p >“He has evoked with great success the Illustrious Dead of all ages.—The work has singular variety, fascinating grace, and thrilling power.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“He shows himself at once to be a poet and a philosopher.—We would instance Lucretia, Dante's Beatrice, Laura, and Lady Jane Grey, as highly wrought, and most touching pictures. Mr. Michell is entitled to take a high rank among the poets of the age.”—<hi rend="italics">New Quarterly Review.</hi></p><p >“He may be compared to Byron.”—<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; CO., 85, QUEEN STREET, CHEAPSIDE, AND ALL BOOKSELLERS.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >T. BOSWORTH'S NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >I. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Now ready, with Portrait of the Author.</hi></p><p >THE KEY TO UNCLE TOM'S <lb/> CABIN.</p><p >BY HARRIET BEECHER STOWE.</p><p >Containing the Incidents, Facts and Documents upon which that Story was founded, and furnishing such an illustration of Slavery as it actually exists, as is calculated to startle even the Readers of Uncle Tom's Cabin. It is well printed in crown 8vo, uniform with the “Author's Edition” of Uncle Tom's Cabin. Price 3s. 6d.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Be particular to order Bosworth's Edition.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> “&amp;c.”</p><p >BY THE LADY EMMELINE STUART WORTLEY.</p><p >Post 8vo, cloth, 10s. 6d.</p><p >III. <lb/> THE FINE ARTS; <lb/> THEIR NATURE &amp; RELATIONS.</p><p >With Detailed Criticisms on Certain Pictures of the <lb/> Italian and French Schools.</p><p >BY M. GUIZOT.</p><p >Translated from the French, with the assistance of the Author, by GEORGE GROVE. With Illustrations drawn on Wood, by GEORGE SCHARF, Jun. Medium 8vo, cloth extra, 14s.</p><p >IV. <lb/> SIGHTS AND SOUNDS; <lb/> THE MYSTERY OF THE DAY.</p><p >Comprising an entire History of the American “Spirit” Manifestations from their origin to the present time.</p><p >BY HENRY SPICER, ESQ.</p><p >“A remarkable and interesting work.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >“The work now before us is one of the fairest we have ever met with.”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p><p >V. <lb/> THE REVIVAL OF THE FRENCH <lb/> EMPERORSHIP <lb/> ANTICIPATED FROM THE NECESSITY <lb/> OF PROPHECY.</p><p >BY THE <lb/> REV. GEORGE STANLEY FABER, B.D.</p><p >Master of Sherburn Hospital and Prebendary of Salisbury.</p><p >3<hi rend="italics">rd Edition, revised and enlarged.</hi></p><p >Fcap. 8vo. cloth, 2s. or by Post, 2s. 6d.</p><p >VI. <lb/> A BOOK FOR EVERY CHURCHMAN.</p><p >LAST GLIMPSES OF CONVOCATION <lb/>  IN THE CHURCH OF <lb/> ENGLAND.</p><p >BY ARTHUR J. JOYCE.</p><p >Fcap. 8vo. cloth, price 4s. 6d.; or by post, 5s.</p><p >“A very ably-written book. The real object of the author is to show the impolicy of reviving Convocation, by proving that when endowed with more power of debate it never did any good to the Church, but, on the contrary, produced evil. With this object Mr. Joyce takes an historical view of the proceedings from Papal times to the extinction of Convocation.”—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p><p >“A concise and well-digested narrative. We most earnestly recommend this volume to the consideration of every Churchman.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >VII. <lb/> A HUNDRED TALES FOR <lb/> CHILDREN.</p><p >Translated from the German of CHRISTOPH VON SCHMID.</p><p >BY FRANCIS B. WELLS, <lb/> Rector of Woodchurch, Kent.</p><p >With Frontispiece and Vignette. 16mo. cloth, 2s. 6d. <lb/> or by post, 3s.</p><p >“A good collection of fables, apologues, &amp;c., by a writer deservedly popular—to be recommended.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p><p >VIII. <lb/> CASES OF CONSCIENCE, <lb/> FOR THE USE OF THE LAITY.</p><p >BY PASCAL THE YOUNGER.</p><p >With a Prefatory Letter to the Right Hon. W. E. GLADSTONE, M.P., and a Reply to the Defence of the Church of Rome in the “Dublin Review.” Sixth Edition, Fcap. 8vo. cloth. 3s. 6d.</p><p >“No Antipapal pamphlet has appeared in modern times more lucid in its arguments—more logical in its conclusions—more astounding in its statements—or more powerful in its language—than ‘Cases of Conscience.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">The Bulwark,</hi> for May.</p><p >IX. <lb/> THE STANDARD COOK.</p><p >Containing upwards of Seven Hundred Practical Receipts in Cookery, and One Hundred in Confectionary.</p><p >TO WHICH IS ADDED, <lb/> Bottling of Fruits and Juices, Home-made Wines, Distilling, Pickling, and Preserving. With an Appendix, containing the Duties of the Steward, Housekeeper, and Man Cook; and other Information necessary to be known by every Mistress of a Family and Servant.</p><p >BY ROBERT REYNOLDS, <lb/> Cook to his Grace the Duke of Portland.</p><p >Post 8vo. cloth, 7s. 6d.</p><p >X. <lb/> THE LIFE OF WALLENSTEIN, <lb/> DUKE OF FRIEDLAND.</p><p >BY LIEUT.-COL. MITCHELL.</p><p >Second Edition, crown 8vo. cloth, reduced to 5s.</p><p >“A work written with the feelings of a soldier, the principles of a patriot, and the penetration of a statesman.”—<hi rend="italics">Alison's History of Europe.</hi></p><p >“We shall be glad if we can convey to the reader any part of the pleasure which we have received ourselves from the perusal of this work.”—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: THOMAS BOSWORTH, 215, REGENT STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >Works by Charles Dickens.</head><p >Now ready, price 3s. 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, neatly bound in cloth, <lb/> THE FIRST AND SECOND VOLUMES <lb/> OF <lb/> A CHILD'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</p><p >BY CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >WITH FRONTISPIECES FROM DRAWINGS BY F. W. TOPHAM.</p><p >CORRECTED AND REVISED FROM “HOUSEHOLD WORDS,” WITH A TABLE OF DATES.</p><p > <hi rend="italics">The History will be completed in Three Volumes.</hi></p><p >BLEAK HOUSE. WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. Now Publishing in Monthly Parts, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each. (To be completed in Twenty.)</p><p >DAVID COPPERFIELD. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >DOMBEY AND SON. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST. With Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Price 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >PICTURES FROM ITALY. In fcap. 8vo. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound in cloth, gilt edges, the Illustrations by</hi> D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON <lb/> STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, JOHN TENNIEL, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> RICHARD DOYLE.</p><p >A CHRISTMAS CAROL, IN PROSE.</p><p >THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH. A Fairy Tale of Home.</p><p >THE BATTLE OF LIFE. A LOVE STORY.</p><p >THE HAUNTED MAN AND THE GHOST'S BARGAIN. A Fancy for Christmas Time.</p><p >THE CHIMES. A GOBLIN STORY OF SOME BELLS THAT RANG AN OLD YEAR OUT AND A NEW YEAR IN.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. in cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE SIXTH VOLUME OF </opener><head > HOUSEHOLD WORDS: </head><p > A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST IN <lb/> THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p><p > <hi rend="italics">Volumes I. to V., price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. each, in cloth boards, may be had by order of any</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Bookseller or Newsvender.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">Also, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s. each in cloth, the First, Second, and Third Volumes of</hi>
<lb/> THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS; <lb/> BEING A RECORD OF PUBLIC EVENTS OF 1850-51, AND 52.</p><closer >OFFICE, 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >The <lb/> Leader.</head><head >A COMPLETE <lb/> FIRST CLASS WEEKLY NEWSPAPER: <lb/> Political and Literary Review.</head><p >(ESTABLISHED 1850.)</p><p >PUBLISHED EVERY SATURDAY IN TIME FOR THE AFTERNOON MAILS, <lb/> Price Sixpence.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">And can be procured from News Agents in all parts of England,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">or direct from the</hi>
<lb/> Office—7, WELLINGTON STREET, STRAND, LONDON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Approved Educational Works for Schools and Families.</head><p >Thirteenth Edition, price 3s. 6d., or with 30 Maps on Steel. 5s. 6d., <lb/> A SCHOOL GEOGRAPHY. By JAMES CORNWELL, Ph. D.</p><p >“We are qualified by ample trial of the books in our own classes to speak to their great efficiency and value. We have never known so much interest evinced, or so much progress made in the study of geography, as since we have employed these as our school books.”—<hi rend="italics">Educational Times.</hi></p><p >“Without exception, the best book of its class we have seen.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >Also, by the same Author, price 2s. 6d., or 4s. coloured, <lb/> A SCHOOL ATLAS; consisting of 30 MAPS on Steel, containing every name found in the School Geography, and a list of several hundred places, with their latitude and longitude, and the accentuation and pronunciation of all difficult names. The Maps of England and Scotland enlarged.</p><p >20th Edition. price 2s. Red, 1s. 9d. cloth, <lb/> ALLEN and CORNWELL'S SCHOOL GRAMMAR; with very copious EXERCISES, and a Systematic View of the FORMATION and DERIVATION of Words, together with Anglo-Saxon, Latin, and Greek roots, which explain the Etymology of above 7000 English words.</p><p >“Written by those who are profoundly acquainted with the sources of our language, and who have brought this acquaintance to bear on its grammatical structure. This grammar will make its way in schools.”—<hi rend="italics">Church of England Quarterly.</hi></p><p >“A complete, well-arranged, and thoroughly scientific manual of the English language. The whole chapter on the formation and derivation of words is one of great interest, and is a valuable exposition of the modes of verbal development; to it are added ample lists of the roots of foreign words.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >GRAMMAR FOR BEGINNERS. 21st Edition, price 1s. 6d. cloth, 9d. sewed.</p><p >“We have never seen a more desirable elementary work.”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p><p >THE YOUNG COMPOSER; or, Progressive Exercises in English Composition.</p><p >By JAMES CORNWELL, Ph. D. 13th Edition, price 1s. 6d.</p><p >“An invaluable little work for beginners. If they go through it steadily they will not only learn how to write, but how to think.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“Dr. Cornwell has executed this work with great ability. We have seen no other of the kind so clear, so well arranged, so comprehensive, so thoroughly adapted to the practical business of tuition; or, in short, so fully entitled to be named ‘Progressive Exercises in English Composition.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">Scotsman.</hi></p><p >Also, price 3s. <lb/> A KEY TO THE YOUNG COMPOSER; with Suggestions as to the Mode of using the Book.</p><p >6th Edition, much improved, price 4s. <lb/> SELECT ENGLISH POETRY. Edited by the late Dr. ALLEN.</p><p >“We can confidently recommend it for young persons in general, as calculated to promote the cultivation of poetical taste and an acquaintance with the different styles of many of our English poets.”—<hi rend="italics">English Journal of Education.</hi></p><p >DR. ALLEN'S EUTROPIUS; with a Complete Dictionary. New Edition, price 3s. cloth.</p><closer >London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co: HAMILTON, ADAMS, &amp; Co. Edinburgh: OLIVER &amp; BOYD <lb/> W. P. KENNEDY.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><head >NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >This day, 1 vol. 8vo, cloth, 18s., <lb/> CHAMOIS HUNTING IN THE <lb/> MOUNTAINS OF BAVARIA.</p><p >By CHARLES BONER.</p><p >With Illustrations.</p><p >In 1 vol., post 8vo, cloth, 9s., <lb/> THE DIARY OF MARTHA <lb/> BETHUNE BALIOL.</p><p >FROM 1753 TO 1754.</p><p >Forming the new Volume of Chapman &amp; Hall's Series of Original Works of Fiction, Biography, and General Literature.</p><p >In 2 vols, post 8vo, cloth, £1 1s., with a Map, <lb/> NARRATIVE OF A MISSION <lb/> TO CENTRAL AFRICA.</p><p >Performed in the Years 1850-51, under the orders, and <lb/> at the expense, of Her Majesty's Government.</p><p >By the late JAMES RICHARDSON, <lb/> Author of “Travels in the Great Desert of Sahara.”</p><p >2 vols., crown 8vo, cloth, 16s.</p><p >LANGUAGE AS A MEANS OF <lb/> MENTAL CULTURE <lb/> AND <lb/> INTERNATIONAL COMMUNICATION; <lb/> OR, <lb/> A MANUAL OF THE TEACHER AND THE <lb/> LEARNER OF LANGUAGES.</p><p >By C. MARCEL, Knt. L.H., French Consul.</p><p >CHEAP EDITION OF SIR E. BULWER LYTTON'S <lb/> NOVELS AND TALES.</p><p >Crown 8vo, cloth, 3s. 6d.</p><p >ZANONI.</p><p >Corrected and revised. With a New Preface by the <lb/> Author and a Frontispiece.</p><p >RUTH.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “MARY BARTON.”</p><p >3 vols. post 8vo.</p><p >CHEAP EDITION OF THE <lb/> WORKS OF MR. CHARLES <lb/> DICKENS.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown octavo. Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces by the Author, and Frontispieces, and handsomely bound in cloth.</hi></p><p >THE PICKWICK PAPERS. 5s.</p><p >NICHOLAS NICKLEBY. 5s.</p><p >THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP. 4s.</p><p >BARNABY RUDGE. 4s.</p><p >MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT. 5s.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST. 3s. 6d.</p><p >AMERICAN NOTES. 2s. 6d.</p><p >SKETCHES BY BOZ. 3s. 6d.</p><p >CHRISTMAS BOOKS. 3s. 6d.</p><closer >London: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 193, Piccadilly.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Now ready, the Fourteenth Thousand, 5s. cloth,</opener><head >  THE SUCCESSFUL MERCHANT:</head><p >Sketches of the Life of Mr. SAMUEL BUDGETT, late of Kingswood Hill, Bristol. By the Rev. WILLIAM ARTHUR, A.M.</p><p >“A novelty in our literature. . . . The volume is a very interesting one.”—<hi rend="italics">Chambers's Journal.</hi></p><p >“A more suitable and useful gift-book to a young man going out into business or trade could not be found than this commercial biography.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“It is such a biography as Daniel Defoe would have revelled in.”—<hi rend="italics">Globe.</hi></p><p >“Enchanting as a novel, profitable as a sermon.”— <hi rend="italics">New York Advocate.</hi></p><p >“A very remarkable book; embodies a perfectly new literary idea. It has laid, we trust, the foundation of a new national biography.”—<hi rend="italics">Dublin Warder.</hi></p><p >“Though the work is quite as much religious as commercial—and in that respect not quite adequately described by its title—there is still sufficient matter of general, universal interest to repay the intelligent and curious reader.”—<hi rend="italics">The Daily News.</hi></p><p >“The moral of such a work cannot be too highly extolled.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser.</hi></p><closer >London: HAMILTON, ADAMS, &amp; CO., and JOHN MASON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW FAMILY MAGAZINE.—PRICE 2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></head><p >HOME THOUGHTS; a Monthly Magazine of Literature, Science, and Domestic Economy.</p><p >The APRIL NUMBER contains a STEEL ENGRAVING, two Designs in Crochet Work, 32 pages of Letter-press, 8vo, and Wrapper, for TWOPENCE.</p><p >GENERAL CONTENTS.—Original Essays, Poetry, and Fiction—Science and History—Biography—Natural History and the Arts—Embroidery. Crochet, Netting and Knitting—Chess—Draughts—Domestic Management—Useful Receipts—Gardening—Answers to Correspondents, &amp;c.—With Steel and Wood Engravings by first-rate Artists.</p><closer >KENT &amp; CO., Paternoster-row; and sold by all <lb/> Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RAPHAEL'S ROYAL BOOK OF FATE.</head><p >QUEEN ELIZABETH'S ORACLE OF FUTURE EVENTS.—with a large folding Coloured Plate, containing 64 Mystical Emblems, relating to Riches, Love, Marriage, Dreams foretold, and all subjects of Fate, Chance, and Mortal Destiny; with 4090 Answers to most important Questions in Human Life. 8vo, red cloth, gilt edges, 5s. Sold by all Booksellers, or sent free by Post on receipt of a Post Office Order.</p><closer >JAMES CORNISH, 297, Holborn, London.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">In a few days will be published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s. cloth, (nearly</hi> 300 <hi rend="italics">pages).</hi></opener><head >A VERBATIM REPORT of the <lb/>PUBLIC DISCUSSION</head><p > between the Rev. B. GRANT and G. J. HOLYOAKE, Esq., held in the Royal British Institution, Finsbury, on six successive Thursday evenings, in January and February, 1853.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Question:</hi>—What advantages would accrue to Mankind, and the Working Classes in particular, by the removal of Christianity, and the substitution of Secularism in its place?</p><closer >WARD &amp; CO., 27, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >WARRANTED CUTLERY</head><p > and ELECTRO-PLATED FORKS AND SPOONS. A. LAYBOURN &amp; CO., from William S. Burton's. The extensive building operations around Hyde Park and Bayswater have induced A. L. &amp; Co. to open a West End Depot, for the convenience of residents and parties furnishing. Every description of General Furnishing Ironmongery, Lamps, Baths, &amp;c., without any advance on former prices, having made extensive cash purchases and contracts previous to the late extraordinary rise in the markets. Gas Fitting, Bell Hanging, and General Repairing. Estimates given and Lists of Prices sent per post. Country orders, to the amount of £2, forwarded carriage free. The money returned for any article not approved of. 10, London-street, Paddington, adjoining the Great Western Royal Hotel.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><head >Works on Gardening and Botany.</head><div type="section"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s. in cloth, the Sixth Edition of</hi> </opener><head >THE LADIES' COMPANION to the FLOWER-GARDEN.</head><p >Being an Alphabetical Arrangement of all the Ornamental Plants grown in Gardens and Shrubberies; <lb/> with full directions for their culture.</p><p >BY MRS. LOUDON.</p><p >WITH CONSIDERABLE ADDITIONS, AND CORRECTED TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p></div><div><opener ><hi rend="italics">Shortly will be published, a New Edition, enlarged and improved, of</hi></opener><head >THE VEGETABLE KINGDOM:</head><p >OR, THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS. Illustrated upon the Natural System.</p><p >BY DR. LINDLEY, Ph. D., F.R.S., &amp;c.</p></div><div><head >PAXTON'S FLOWER-GARDEN.</head><p >EDITED BY SIR JOSEPH PAXTON AND DR. LINDLEY.</p><p >Complete in Three Volumes, Illustrated by 108 highly-finished Coloured Plates, and 600 beautiful Wood Engravings.</p><p >Price £4 19s. elegantly bound in cloth.</p><p > Each Volume may be had separately, price 33s. in cloth; or any of Parts, 1 to 36, price 2s. 6d. each, to <lb/> complete sets.</p><closer >BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p > furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. The elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature. “ROBERT SHAW, London,” is in white letters on the Government stamp. Price 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >FLOWERS, &amp;c., MODELLED IN LEATHER,</head><p > SOHO BAZAAR, LONDON. Counter 127. Specimens unequalled. Box of Tools, containing Patterns, &amp;c., with full Instructions and all the Materials, on sale. Priced List forwarded for postage stamp. Country orders address R. GILBERT, 13, Soho-square. (late Dobbs &amp; Co.)</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE, in Imperial Quarts and Pints.</head><p >BARON LIEBIG SAYS:—“The specimens of your Pale Ale sent to me afforded me another opportunity of confirming its valuable qualities. I am myself an admirer of this beverage, and my own experience enables me to recommend it, in accordance with the opinion of the most eminent English physicians, as a very agreeable and efficient tonic, and as a general beverage, both for the invalid and the robust.—Giessen, May 6.”</p><p >Influenced by so eminent an authority, I have resolved to sell ALLSOPP'S ALES exclusively, at 5½, Pall Mall. I guarantee it, first, genuine, as from Burton-on-Trent; secondly, in the finest condition; and, thirdly, to be bottled in quarts and pints of IMPERIAL MEASURE ONLY. I have laid down some thousands of dozens at 5½, Pall Mall, and am prepared immediately to supply</p><p >
<table><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE, in Imperial Quarts </cell><cell> 8s. </cell><cell> 0d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S PALE ALES, in Imperial Pints </cell><cell> 5s. </cell><cell> 0d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S MILD ALES, in Imperial Quarts </cell><cell> 8s. </cell><cell> 6d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S MILD ALES, in Imperial Pints </cell><cell> 5s. </cell><cell> 6d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S STRONG (THE OLD BURTON) ALE, in Imperial Quarts </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 6d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S STRONG (THE OLD BURTON) ALE, in Imperial Pints </cell><cell> 6s. </cell><cell> 6d. </cell><cell> per dozen. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >But there is something more that I can do for the public good. It ought to be more generally known to families, that there is a great advantage in having the Ale fresh—of the year's brewing—as the tonic properties and fragrant bitterness of the Hop are best elicited in the fresh state of draught from the cask. I am, therefore, prepared to supply “ALLSOPP'S PALE AND BITTER ALES” at once in casks, as follows,—</p><p >
<table><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE, 18-gallon Casks </cell><cell> 30s. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S MILD ALE, 18-gallon Casks </cell><cell> 33s. </cell></row><row><cell> ALLSOPP'S STRONG (THE OLD BURTON) ALE, 18-gallon Casks </cell><cell> 45s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >I wish it to be distinctly understood by the public, once for all, that, whenever my name appears on cask or bottle, the measure is full, true, and Imperial, the Ale of the finest, and the Brewers Messrs. ALLSOPP and SONS only.</p><closer >HARRINGTON PARKER, Beer Merchant, 5½, Pall Mall.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BREIDENBACH, <lb/> PERFUMER, DISTILLER OF FLOWERS, &amp;.</head><p >157, NEW BOND STREET.</p><p >THE NEW ODEURS FOR THE SEASON 1853 ARE NOW READY.</p><p >ESSENCE OF WHITE LILAC.</p><p >EMPRESS EUGENIE'S NOSEGAY.</p><p >THE ROYAL HUNT BOUQUET.</p><p >GENUINE EAU DE COLOGNE, 10s. A CASE OF SIX BOTTLES, OR 2s. EACH.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><head >THE WORKING TAILORS</head><p > JOINT STOCK COMPANY, 314, OXFORD. STREET. near Hanover-square. Registered under 7 and 8 Victoria, cap. 110. The above Company beg leave to call the attention of their customers and the public to the fact that they have lately made alterations in some of their arrangements and officers, in order that increased efficiency may be given to their business transactions, and greater satisfaction to their customers. The result of the experiment which they have now been engaged for three years in making has proved the practicability of the principle of self-dependence on which they set out, relying for success on supplying good articles at a moderate price, in the fair way of ordinary business.</p><p >They are grateful for the extensive support they have already received. They are conscious that, to deserve its continuance and increase, unremitting attention on their part is needed to the arrangements of their establishment and to the skill and attention of their appointed officers. It is for these reasons that they have lately made those alterations which now enable them, with a confidence greater than they have ever before felt, to appeal not only to their former and present customers for the renewal and continuance of their support, but to the public in general, for the bestowal of an extended patronage. The workmanship of every article supplied is done on the premises, and by members of the Company. This is a feature in the business of this establishment to which particular attention is invited.</p><closer >JAMES CAMPBELL, Manager and Secretary. March, 1853.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRTS,</head><p > 31s. 6d., and 37s. 6d. the Half-dozen, cut upon a new principle. ILLUSTRATED PRICED LISTS, with directions for self-measurement, gratis and post-free.</p><p >RODGERS &amp; CO., Improved Shirt-makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing-cross, London. Established 60 years.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Chubb's Fire-proof Safes and Locks.</head><p >CHUBB &amp; SON <lb/> Have now on Sale, at their Warehouses, and Assortment <lb/> of their <lb/> FIRE-PROOF SAFES, <lb/> WHICH GAINED THE PRIZE MEDAL, WITH <lb/> SPECIAL APPROBATION, <lb/> at the Great Exhibition, this distinction being awarded to them SOLELY by the Jurors of Class XXII., after a careful comparison with those of other makers from all parts of England.</p><p >These SAFES, undoubtedly the MOST SECURE FROM FORCE, FRAUD, and FIRE, are sold at moderate prices.</p><p >CHUBB'S LOCKS, with all the recent improvements. CASH BOXES and DEED BOXES of all sizes; may be inspected.</p><p >IRON DOORS and FRAMES for Strong Rooms.</p><p > Complete Lists, with Prices, will be sent on application.</p><p >CHUBB &amp; SON, 57, St. Paul's Churchyard, London; 28, Lord-street, Liverpool; 16, Market-street, Manchester; and Hornsley Fields, Wolverhampton.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT</opener><head >METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN.<lb/>
BY ROYAL COMMAND.</head><p >JOSEPH GILLOTT most respectfully begs to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic Institutions, and the Public generally, that by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times, he has introduced a <hi rend="italics">new series</hi> of his useful productions, which for <hi rend="italics">excellence of temper, quality of material,</hi> and, above all, <hi rend="italics">cheapness in price,</hi> he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition. Each pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of Boxes, containing One Gross each, with Label outside, and fact-simile of his signature.</p><closer >Victoria Works, Graham-street, Birmingham.</closer><closer >April 20th. 1852.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BENJAMIN EDGINGTON</head><p ><lb/> RESPECTFULLY informs the Public, that he has at length been successful in obtaining a Warehouse sufficiently lofty and extensive to allow of TENTS of different character and description to be erected, and would invite all who are in want of Tents, whether for Military Purposes, Emigration, Floral and Horticultural Societies, Shooting in the Highlands, or for Garden Lawns, to a View at <lb/> No. 2, DUKE STREET, SOUTHWARK, <lb/> Where every information and explanation will be given.</p><p >The Military and Emigration Tents, Trophy of Flags, &amp;c.. as also a model of Rick Cloth, exhibited in Class 8, and for which a PRIZE MEDAL was awarded by the Jurors, may now be seen at the above warehouse.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">N.B.—A few second-hand Marquees of large dimensions to be sold at a reasonable price.</hi></p><p >NETTING AND BUNTING FOR FRUIT TREES.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALBANY LAMP AND CANDLE-MANUFACTORY —</head><p > CLARKE'S Russian Wax Candles, 1s. per lb., burn superior to all others. Best Albany Composite Candles, 8d. per lb., do not require snuffing; for ordinary purposes the Cheapest Candles that can be used. Moulds, 7d., Store Candles, 6d. per lb.; Express Pale Soap, very old and dry, 54s. per cwt.; Good Yellow, 50s. and 44s.; Best Mottled. 56s.; Honey Soap, 1s.; Old Brown Windsor, 2s.; all other Scented Soaps, 1s. 6d. per lb.; Patent Albany Oil, 4s. 6d. per gallon, superior to Sperm; CLARKE'S Refined Oil for French Lamps, 4s. per gallon; Solar, 3s. 6d. Italian goods of the finest quality at the Wholesale Price; Lamps of every description manufactured on the premises, for cash only.</p><p >SAMUEL CLARKE, Albany Lamp and Candle Manufactory, 55, Albany-street, Regent's-park, London, within two minutes' walk of the Colosseum.</p><p >N.B. Country Orders, amounting to £10 or upwards, Carriage Free.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.</head><p >HOLLOWAY'S PILLS FOR RHEUMATIC PAINS AND THE CURE OF TIC DOLOUREUX.—Mrs. Harriet O'Connell, a lady of property residing in Union-street, Plymouth, states, in a letter to Professor Holloway, dated Nov. 10, 1852,—That she was afflicted for nearly 5 years with frequent attacks of Tic Doloureux and Rheumatic pains. Medical aid had no effect whatever in alleviating her sufferings. The attacks left her in a weak and debilitated condition, and her bodily health was very much impaired. In this deplorable state she was induced to try Holloway's Pills, and by persevering in their use the pains became gradually diminished, and ultimately she was restored to perfect health and strength.</p><p >Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p12"/><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES</head><p >of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >IN FULL DRESS.</p><p >WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p><p >INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS, <lb/> BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >BABY LINEN IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p><p >TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p><p >An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information, sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >MOTHERS! MOTHERS!! MOTHERS!!!</opener><head >THE BEST MEDICINE IN THE WORLD for INFANTS AND YOUNG CHILDREN</head><p > IS ATKINSON AND BARKER'S ROYAL INFANTS' PRESERVATIVE.—Under the Patronage of the Queen.—The high and universal celebrity which this medicine continues to maintain for the prevention and cure of those disorders incident to infants; affording instant relief in convulsions, flatulency, affections of the bowels, difficult teething, the thrush, rickets, measles, hooping-cough, cow-pox, or vaccine inoculation, and may be given with safety immediately after birth. It is no misnomer cordial!—no stupefactive, deadly narcotic!—but a veritable preserver of infants! Mothers would do well in always keeping it in the nursery. Many thousands of children are annually saved by this much-esteemed medicine, which is an immediate remedy, and the infants rather like it than otherwise.</p><p >Prepared only by ROBERT BARKER, Ollerenshaw Hall, Chapel-en-le-Frith, Derbyshire, late of Manchester, (Chemist to Her most Gracious Majesty Queen Victoria), in bottles at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 11s. each.</p><p >Sold by all druggists and medicine vendors throughout the United Kingdom.</p><p >CAUTION.—Observe the name of “ATKINSON &amp; BARKER,” on the Government Stamp. Established in the year 1793.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE ROYAL TURKISH TOWELS</head><p >UNDER the Patronage of Her Majesty the Queen, and which received the Prize Medal at the Great Exhibition. The brown Linen combines the advantages of a flesh-brush with the qualities most desirable in a Towel. The white cotton is the softest Towel ever made, and absorbs moisture without the necessity of using friction. To be had of all respectable Linendrapers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.—</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13"/><head >PRIZE MEDAL.</head><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S <lb/> GOLD CHAINS.</p><p >By Troy Weight, at realisable value; and the Workmanship <lb/> at Wholesale Manufacturers' Prices.</p><p >THE Great Exhibition having established the Advantage of Purchasing from the Wholesale Manufacturer, wherever it can be accomplished, and thereby dispensing with an intermediate profit, WATHERSTON &amp; BRODGEN beg to announce that, in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them, they have thrown open their Manufactory to the Public at the same prices they have been in the habit (for the last half century) of charging to the Trade in London, India, and the Colonies.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to caution the Public against the Electro Gold Chains, and Polished Zinc Gold, so extensively put forth in the present day, under the titles of “Pure Gold” and “Fine Gold,” and to call attention to the genuine Gold Chains made from their own ingots, and sold by Troy Weight at its bullion or realisable value.</p><p >The system of Weighing Chains against Sovereigns being one of the greatest frauds ever practised on the Public, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN guarantee the Gold in their Chains, and will re-purchase it at the price charged; the workmanship, according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> EXAMPLE.—Intrinsic value of a Chain of 15-Carat Gold, weighing 2 Ounces </cell><cell> £5 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 2 </cell></row><row><cell> Supposing the workmanship to be </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Total </cell><cell> £7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 2 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >By this arrangement, the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">Bullion</hi> in a Gold Chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">An extensive assortment of Jewellery, of the first quality, all made at their Manufactory,</hi> <lb/> 16, HENRIETTA STREET, COVENT GARDEN, LONDON.</p><p >ESTABLISHED A.D. 1798.</p><p >N.B. Australian and Californian Gold made into articles of Jewellery at a moderate charge for the workmanship.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOYER'S RELISH.</head><p >“To describe the Sauce would be to make our readers hungry,—rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poured.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p><p >THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents, <lb/> CROSSE AND BLACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen.</p><closer >GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >DO YOU KEEP LIVERY SERVANTS</head><p > DOUDNEYS' LIVERIES PLEASE MASTERS &amp; SERVANTS.</p><p >Footman's Suit, £3 3s. Groom's Suit, £3 10s. Coachman's Suit, £3 18s. 6d.</p><p >ALL THE BEST QUALITY.</p><p >Patronized by the QUEEN, PRINCE ALBERT, and the Nobility.</p><p >SEE THEIR FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS AND PATRONAGE BOOK.</p><p >EST<hi rend="superscript">D</hi> 1784 DOUDNEYS 25 BURLINGTON ARCADE <lb/> 17, OLD BOND S<hi rend="superscript">T</hi> AND 49, LOMBARD ST<hi rend="superscript">T</hi></p><p >All Gentlemen who take exercise, or are weakly, should wear DOUDNEYS' <lb/> OLYMPIC GIRTH. Superior to all other Belts for Spinal and Abdominal support, <lb/> and upward pressure.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14"/><head >THE TEETH AND BREATH.</head><p >“HOW often do we find the human face divine disfigured by neglecting the chiefest of its ornaments, and the breath made disagreeable to companions by non-attention to the Teeth! Though perfect in their structure and composition, to keep them in a pure and healthy state requires some little trouble; and if those who are blessed with well-formed teeth knew how soon decay steals into the mouth, making unsightly what otherwise are delightful to admire, and designating unhealthiness by the impurity of the breath, they would spare no expense to chase away these fatal blemishes. But although most ladies are careful, and even particular in these delicate matters, yet few are sufficiently aware of the imperative necessity of avoiding all noxious and mineral substances of an acrid nature, and of which the greater part of the cheap tooth-powders of the present day are composed. It is highly satisfactory to point out Messrs. ROWLANDS' ODONTO, or Pearl Dentifrice, as a preparation free from all injurious elements, and eminently calculated to embellish and preserve the dental structure, to impart a graceful fragrance to the breath, and to embellish and perpetuate the graces of the mouth.”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p><p >ROWLANDS' ODONTO.</p><p >A White Powder. Prepared from Oriental Herbs with unusual care, transmitted to this country at great expense, this unique compound will be found of inestimable value in <hi rend="italics">preserving and beautifying the Teeth, strengthening the Gums,</hi> and in giving sweetness and perfume to the breath.—Price 2s. 9d. per box.</p><p >SOLD BY A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS, 20, HATTON GARDEN, LONDON, AND BY CHEMISTS AND PERFUMERS.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BONUS FORTY PER CENT. <lb/> DEFENDER FIRE &amp; LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY.</head><p >34, NEW BRIDGE STREET, BLACKFRIARS, LONDON, <lb/> AND <lb/> 4, BOULEVARD DES ITALIENS, PARIS.</p><p >A BONUS was declared on the 3rd of January last on all Life Policies effected prior to 1852, equal on the average to FORTY PER CENT. upon the premiums paid thereon.</p><p >In the FIRE DEPARTMENT the rates are adapted to the actual risk.</p><p >Prospectuses and full information may be obtained at the Chief Offices, or of any of the Agents. Respectable active Agents Wanted.</p><p >JOHN KELDAY, Managing Director.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GORGET PATENT SELF ADJUSTING SHIRT</head><p >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> TO FASTEN AT THE BACK, <lb/> WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><p >A most perfect and easy-fitting Shirt, and by a simple invention of the Patentee, adjusts itself to all movements of the body, both back and front, either walking, sitting, or riding. Price, including the REGISTERED ELLIPTIC WRISTBAND, 42s. the half-dozen. The Elliptic Collar, quite unique, in all shapes, with Patent Elastic Fastenings, 12s. the dozen. The Patent Elastic Collar Fastening can be attached to any Collar, opening back or front. Six sent by post on receipt of 13 Postage Stamps.</p><p >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR <lb/> TO FASTEN IN FRONT.</p><p >WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><list  type="simple"><head>Directions for Self Measurement.</head><item>1. Round the Chest, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>2. Round the Waist, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>3. Round the Neck, taken about the middle of the Throat.</item><item>4. Round the Wrist.</item><item>5. The length of Coat Sleeve, from the centre of Back, down the seam of Sleeve to bottom of cuff.</item><item>6. The length of Shirt at Back.</item></list><p >Say if the Shirts are to open back or front. If with Collars attached (3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> the half-dozen extra).</p><p >PATENTEES, <lb/> COOPER &amp; FRYER, <lb/> Removed next door to the <lb/> HAYMARKET THEATRE</p></div><div type="advertisement"><div><head >RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p > (as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Disinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p><p >Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p></div><div><head >RIMMEL'S HAIR DYE</head><p > imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.—Price 5s. 6d.</p><p >RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended.—Beware of counterfeits.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39, Gerard-street, Soho, London.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15"/><head >OPERA GLASSES.</head><p >THE attention of the Nobility, Gentry, and Subscribers to the Royal Italian Opera is respectfully directed to THOMAS HARRIS &amp; SON'S Newly improved Opera Glasses.</p><p >The acme of perfection is attained in these Glasses, viz.—great magnifying power, with a clear and much extended range of view; they are now offered at lower prices than is usually charged for those made on the old principle.</p><p >
<table><head>A large Assortment of every description of Opera Glasses from 10 Shillings each.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> THOMAS HARRIS &amp; SON'S celebrated RACE GLASS, with Patent Leather Case </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> A powerful Waistcoat Pocket Glass (defines clearly 1½ miles) </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Keeper's Pocket Telescopes </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Yachting and Deer Stalking Glasses on a new construction.</hi></p><p >THOMAS HARRIS &amp; SON, <lb/> OPTICIANS TO THE ROYAL FAMILY, <lb/> 52, GREAT RUSSELL STREET, <lb/> OPPOSITE THE BRITISH MUSEUM ENTRANCE.</p><p >ESTABLISHED 70 YEARS.</p><p >CAUTION.—Number 52, is directly facing the New Entrance Gate to the Museum. Recollect this, and you will avoid mistaking the house; there being a person in the same street who displays the words “15 years with HARRIS &amp; SON.” designed to cause mistakes.</p><closer >52, OPPOSITE THE BRITISH MUSEUM GATES, 52.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >“THE BEST IS THE CHEAPEST.”</head><p >
<table><row><cell> The Best Congou Tea </cell><cell> 3s. </cell><cell> 8d. </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Imperial Souchong Tea </cell><cell> 4s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Moyune Gunpowder </cell><cell> 5s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Plantation Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Mocha Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. </cell><cell> 4d. </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Tea or Coffee to the value of 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> or upwards sent, Carriage Free, to any part of England, by </p><closer > PHILLIPS &amp; COMPANY, <lb/> TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> 8, KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.</head><p >A CERTAIN REMEDY for disorders of the Pulmonary Organs—in Difficulty of Breathing—in Redundancy of Phlegm—in Incipient CONSUMPTION (of which COUGH is the most positive indication) they are of unerring efficacy. In ASTHMA, and in WINTER COUGH, they <hi rend="italics">have never</hi> been known to fail. Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1s. 1½d., and Tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Church Yard, London. Sold Retail by all Druggists and Patent Medicine Venders in the Kingdom. N.B.—To prevent spurious imitations, please to observe that the words “KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES,” are engraved on the GOVERNMENT STAMP of each box.</p><p >IMPORTANT TESTIMONIAL.</p><p >Copy of a Letter from “COLONEL HAWKER, (the well-known Author on GUNS AND SHOOTING.)”</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Longparish House, near Whitchurch, Hants, October</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">st,</hi> 1846.</p><p >SIR,—I cannot resist informing you of the extraordinary effect I have experienced by taking only a few of your LOZENGES. I had a cough for several weeks that defied all that had been prescribed for me; and yet I got completely rid of it by taking about half a small box of your Lozenges, which I find are the only ones that relieve the cough without deranging the stomach or digestive organs.</p><p >I am, Sir, your humble Servant, <lb/> P. HAWKER.</p><closer >To Mr. KEATING, 79, St. Paul's Churchyard.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16"/><opener >94, REGENT STREET, LONDON, <lb/> And 7, GREAT VINE STREET.
</opener><head >Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'s REGISTERED PARDESSUS,</head><p >OF FINE AUSTRALIAN and LLAMA WOOLS, (6TH &amp; 7TH VICTORIA, CAP. 65), <lb/> FOR WALKING OR RIDING. <lb/> THIS is an improved style of Coat for Spring use, of a light convenient form, which admits of its being worn either over or without the ordinary coat. It is neatly and handsomely made, care being bestowed in its construction, to impart to it that graceful and appropriate character which, since its first introduction, has so greatly recommended it to public favour; it is produced in all colours with silk sleeve linings, at the very moderate price of TWO GUINEAS. This comfort-promoting garment has been truthfully pronounced by a leading Journal as <hi rend="italics">Cheap, Elegant, and Durable.</hi> The IMPROVED ELASTIC SPRING GUINEA TROUSERS are also ready for selection from a choice variety of patterns.
</p><p >In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s, Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94, REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PARASOLS.</head><p >W. &amp; J. SANGSTER respectfully solicit an inspection of their Stock of PARASOLS for this Season, comprising the richest Brocaded Silks in Points from Lyons ever manufactured for their trade.</p><p >W. &amp; J. S. beg also to offer for notice their China Crape Parasols, universally admired last Season; Parasols in Moiré Antique, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and of every other description, whether for the Fête, Promenade, or Sea-side.</p><p >The inconvenience of the ordinary method of folding a Parasol handle, has induced W. &amp; J. S. to patent an Invention which will enable a Lady to fold her Parasol instantaneously without trouble.</p><p >Umbrellas for Ladies made on Fox's Patent Paragon Frames, stronger and lighter than any yet offered to the Public.</p><closer >W. AND J. SANGSTER, <lb/> 140, Regent Street. 10, Royal Exchange. 94, Fleet Street. 75, Cheapside.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><opener > Dedicated, by Permission, to Her Majesty.
<lb/><hi rend="italics">On Saturday, the</hi> 30<hi rend="italics">th April,</hi> 1853, <hi rend="italics">will be published,</hi></opener><head > No. I. OF THE <lb/> ENGLISH CYCLOPÆDIA.
</head><p >A New Dictionary of Universal Knowledge.</p><p >BASED ON THE “PENNY CYCLOPÆDIA,” <lb/> AND <lb/> ILLUSTRATED WITH MANY HUNDRED WOOD ENGRAVINGS.</p><p >CONDUCTED BY MR. CHARLES KNIGHT.</p><p >IN the announcement of a CYCLOPÆDIA which, although based upon one already in existence, is to all intents and purposes a new work, some few words of introduction from the Conductor may be deemed necessary.</p><p >More than twenty years having elapsed since the commencement, and ten since the completion, of the “Penny Cyclopædia,” the time seems to have arrived for a new work, incorporating all the excellences of that great book of reference, but carefully corrected, and brought up to the present state of knowledge in every department.</p><p >Possessing the exclusive right of reprinting the “Penny Cyclopædia,” Mr. KNIGHT feels that he cannot offer a more acceptable service to the general body of the Public, than by the production of such a work as the “ENGLISH CYCLOPÆDIA,” published at the lowest rate of price, and finished in the shortest time. Maintaining the same high character as its predecessor, the “ENGLISH CYCLOPÆDIA” will be issued so cheaply, as to be within the reach of thousands of persons who have become readers during the last quarter of a century.</p><p >At a period like the present, when education is penetrating all the various strata of society, like a fertilising rain; when discovery and invention are marching on with such rapid steps and so multiplying employments, that very few indeed can afford to remain uninformed; when the great body of the people are more at ease than at any previous time of our history; when the literary and scientific range of what belongs to our age is as extensive as the social and
<pb xml:id="p2a"/> 
geographical relations of our country; the general desire for the acquisition of a vast repository of knowledge, like that now under-taken, must have greatly increased since the publication of the original “Penny Cyclopædia.”</p><p >Feeling very strongly that the important duties devolving upon the conductor of so great a work demand his undivided attention, Mr. KNIGHT has associated with himself in this undertaking the firm of Messrs. BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, of Whitefriars, as printers and publishers; whose names will be a sufficient guarantee for mechanical execution and punctuality; and by whose assistance he hopes to produce the best and cheapest original CYCLOPÆDIA of any time or country.</p><div type="section"><head >MODE OF PUBLICATION.</head><p >The “ENGLISH CYCLOPÆDIA” will be published in Four Divisions; each having its own alphabetical arrangement, and each forming, when complete, four distinct volumes:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell> GEOGRAPHY </cell><cell> 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> NATURAL HISTORY </cell><cell> 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> SCIENCES AND ARTS </cell><cell> 4 Vols. </cell></row><row><cell> HISTORY, BIOGRAPHY, MORAL SCIENCES, LITERATURE </cell><cell> 4 Vols. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Two Divisions will be published at the same time; and on their completion the others will immediately follow.</p><p >The work will be issued in Weekly Numbers and Monthly Parts.</p><p >In the Weekly Numbers the Two Divisions will be published alternately, each containing on the average thirty-six pages of letter-press, stitched in a wrapper, price 6d. Thus, one week, a Number of Geography will be issued; the next a Number of Natural History, and so on; and, as each will be in a distinct wrapper, either Division may be purchased separately.</p><p >In the Monthly Part, the Two Divisions will proceed together, comprising 144 pages of print in a wrapper, price 2s. The space allotted to each Division will be equal in each part.</p><p >The work will be completed in about 65 Parts or 260 Weekly Numbers.</p><p >Every four months a Volume will be published, neatly bound in cloth, and containing about 600 pages.</p><p >The work will commence with GEOGRAPHY and NATURAL HISTORY.</p><p > <hi rend="italics">Communications for the Editor to be addressed to</hi> 90, <hi rend="italics">Fleet Street; Orders and Business Correspondence to</hi> MESSRS. BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, <hi rend="italics">Bouverie Street.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pxxx3"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill1"><p>Sir Leicester Dedlock.</p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pxxx4"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill2"><p>Tom all alone's.</p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx5"/><div><opener ><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; in Monthly Parts, and in Half-yearly Volumes,</hi> <lb/></opener><head > HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST <lb/> IN THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p><p >SIX VOLUMES are published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, in cloth boards, and are always on sale.</p></div><div><opener ><hi rend="italics">Also, published at the end of every Month, at the same Office, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> </opener><head >THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS; </head><p > Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Exchequer, a Legal Publication, not coming <lb/> within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved. <lb/>  The First, Second, and Third Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of 1850, 1851, and <lb/> 1852, may always be had, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, neatly bound in cloth. Each Volume contains a <lb/> copious Index.
</p><closer > OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</closer></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p417"/><head >CHAPTER XLIII. <lb/> ESTHER'S NARRATIVE.</head><p >IT matters little now, how much I thought of my living mother who had told me evermore to consider her dead. I could not venture to approach her, or to communicate with her in writing, for my sense of the peril in which her life was passed was only to be equalled by my fears of increasing it. Knowing that my mere existence as a living creature was an unforeseen danger in her way, I could not always conquer that terror of myself which had seized me when I first knew the secret. At no time did I dare to utter her name. I felt as if I did not even dare to hear it. If the conversation anywhere, when I was present, took that direction, as it sometimes naturally did, I tried not to hear—I mentally counted, repeated something that I knew, or went out of the room. I am conscious, now, that I often did these things when there can have been no danger of her being spoken of; but I did them in the dread I had of hearing anything that might lead to her betrayal, and to her betrayal through me.</p><p >It matters little now how often I recalled the tones of my mother's voice, wondered whether I should ever hear it again as I so longed to do, and thought how strange and desolate it was that it should be so new to me. It matters little that I watched for every public mention of my mother's name; that I passed and repassed the door of her house in town, loving it, but afraid to look at it; that I once sat in the theatre when my mother was there and saw me, and when we were so wide asunder, before the great company of all degrees, that any link or confidence between us seemed a dream. It is all, all over. My lot has been so blest that I can relate little of myself which is not a story of goodness and generosity in others. I may well pass that little, and go on.</p><p >When we were settled at home again, Ada and I had many conversations with my guardian, of which Richard was the theme. My dear girl was deeply grieved that he should do their kind cousin so much wrong; but she was so faithful to Richard, that she could not bear to blame him, even for that. My guardian was assured of it, and never coupled his name with a word of reproof. “Rick is mistaken, my dear,” he would say to her. “Well, well! we have all been mistaken over and over again. We must trust to you and time to set him right.”</p><p >We knew afterwards what we suspected then; that he did not trust to time until he had often tried to open Richard's eyes. That he had written to him, gone to him, talked with him, tried every gentle and persuasive art his kindness could devise. Our poor devoted Richard was deaf and blind to all. If he were wrong, he would make amends when the Chancery suit was over. If he were groping in the dark, he could not do better than do his utmost to clear away those clouds in which so much was confused and obscured. Suspicion and misunderstanding
<pb xml:id="p418"/>
were the fault of the suit? Then let him work the suit out, and come through it to his right mind. This was his unvarying reply. Jarndyce and Jarndyce had obtained such possession of his whole nature, that it was impossible to place any consideration before him which he did not—with a distorted kind of reason—make a new argument in favor of his doing what he did. “So that it is even more mischievous,” said my guardian once to me, “to remonstrate with the poor dear fellow, than to leave him alone.”</p><p >I took one of these opportunities of mentioning my doubts of Mr. Skimpole as a good adviser for Richard.</p><p >“Adviser?” returned my guardian, laughing. “My dear, who would advise with Skimpole?”</p><p >“Encourager would perhaps have been a better word,” said I.</p><p >“Encourager!” returned my guardian again. “Who could be encouraged by Skimpole?”</p><p >“Not Richard?” I asked.</p><p >“No,” he replied. “Such an unworldly, uncalculating, gossamer creature, is a relief to him, and an amusement. But as to advising or encouraging, or occupying a serious station towards anybody or anything, it is simply not to be thought of in such a child as Skimpole.”</p><p >“Pray, cousin John,” said Ada, who had just joined us, and now looked over my shoulder, “what made him such a child?”</p><p >“What made him such a child?” inquired my guardian, rubbing his head, a little at a loss.</p><p >“Yes, cousin John.”</p><p >“Why,” he slowly replied, roughening his head more and more, “he is all sentiment, and—and susceptibility, and—and sensibility—and—and imagination. And these qualities are not regulated in him, somehow. I suppose the people who admired him for them in his youth, attached too much importance to them, and too little to any training that would have balanced and adjusted them; and so he became what he is. Hey?” said my guardian, stopping short, and looking at us hopefully. “What do you think, you two?”</p><p >Ada, glancing at me, said she thought it was a pity he should be an expense to Richard.</p><p >“So it is, so it is,” returned my guardian, hurriedly. “That must not be. We must arrange that. I must prevent it. That will never do.”</p><p >And I said I thought it was to be regretted that he had ever introduced Richard to Mr. Vholes, for a present of five pounds.</p><p >“Did he?” said my guardian, with a passing shade of vexation on his face. “But there you have the man. There you have the man! There is nothing mercenary in that, with him. He has no idea of the value of money. He introduces Rick; and then he is good friends with Mr. Vholes, and borrows five pounds of him. He means nothing by it, and thinks nothing of it. He told you himself, I'll be bound, my dear?”</p><p >“O yes!” said I.</p><p >“Exactly!” cried my guardian, quite triumphant. “There you have the man! If he had meant any harm by it, or was conscious of any harm in it, he wouldn't tell it. He tells it as he does it, in mere simplicity. But you shall see him in his own home, and then you'll
<pb xml:id="p419"/>
understand him better. We must pay a visit to Harold Skimpole, and caution him on these points. Lord bless you, my dears, an infant, an infant!”</p><p >In pursuance of this plan, we went into London on an early day, and presented ourselves at Mr. Skimpole's door.</p><p >He lived in a place called the Polygon, in Somers Town, where there were at that time a number of poor Spanish refugees walking about in cloaks, smoking little paper cigars. Whether he was a better tenant than one might have supposed, in consequence of his friend Somebody always paying his rent at last, or whether his inaptitude for business rendered it particularly difficult to turn him out, I don't know; but he had occupied the same house some years. It was in a state of dilapidation quite equal to our expectation. Two or three of the area railings were gone; the water-butt was broken; the knocker was loose; the bell handle had been pulled off a long time, to judge from the rusty state of the wire; and dirty footprints on the steps were the only signs of its being inhabited.</p><p >A slatternly full-blown girl, who seemed to be bursting out at the rents in her gown and the cracks in her shoes, like an over-ripe berry, answered our knock by opening the door a very little way, and stopping up the gap with her figure. As she knew Mr. Jarndyce (indeed Ada and I both thought that she evidently associated him with the receipt of her wages), she immediately relented and allowed us to pass in. The lock of the door being in a disabled condition, she then applied herself to securing it with the chain which was not in good action either, and said would we go up-stairs?</p><p >We went up-stairs to the first floor, still seeing no other furniture than the dirty footprints. Mr. Jarndyce, without further ceremony, entered a room there, and we followed. It was dingy enough, and not at all clean; but furnished with an odd kind of shabby luxury, with a large footstool, a sofa, and plenty of cushions, an easy-chair, and plenty of pillows, a piano, books, drawing materials, music, newspapers, and a few sketches and pictures. A broken pane of glass in one of the dirty windows was papered and wafered over; but there was a little plate of hothouse nectarines on the table, and there was another of grapes, and another of sponge-cakes, and there was a bottle of light wine. Mr. Skimpole himself reclined upon the sofa, in a dressing-gown, drinking some fragrant coffee from an old china cup—it was then about midday—and looking at a collection of wallflowers in the balcony.</p><p >He was not in the least disconcerted by our appearance, but rose and received us in his usual airy manner.</p><p >“Here I am, you see!” he said, when we were seated: not without some little difficulty, the greater part of the chairs being broken. “Here I am! This is my frugal breakfast. Some men want legs of beef and mutton for breakfast; I don't. Give me my peach, my cup of coffee, and my claret; I am content. I don't want them for themselves, but they remind me of the sun. There's nothing solar about legs of beef and mutton. Mere animal satisfaction!”</p><p >“This is our friend's consulting room (or would be, if he ever prescribed), his sanctum, his studio,” said my guardian to us.</p><p >“Yes,” said Mr. Skimpole, turning his bright face about, “this is
<pb xml:id="p420"/>
the bird's cage. This is where the bird lives and sings. They pluck his feathers now and then, and clip his wings; but he sings, he sings!”</p><p >He handed us the grapes, repeating in his radiant way, “he sings! Not an ambitious note, but still he sings.”</p><p >“These are very fine,” said my guardian. “A present?”</p><p >“No,” he answered. “No! Some amiable gardener sells them. His man wanted to know, when he brought them last evening, whether he should wait for the money. ‘Really, my friend,’ I said, ‘I think not—if your time is of any value to you.’ I suppose it was, for he went away.”</p><p >My guardian looked at us with a smile, as though he asked us, “is it possible to be worldly with this baby?”</p><p >“This is a day,” said Mr. Skimpole, gaily taking a little claret in a tumbler, “that will ever be remembered here. We shall call it the Saint Clare and Saint Summerson day. You must see my daughters. I have a blue-eyed daughter who is my Beauty daughter, I have a Sentiment daughter, and I have a Comedy daughter. You must see them all. They'll be enchanted.”</p><p >He was going to summon them, when my guardian interposed, and asked him to pause a moment, as he wished to say a word to him first. “My dear Jarndyce,” he cheerfully replied, going back to his sofa, “as many moments as you please. Time is no object here. We never know what o'clock it is, and we never care. Not the way to get on in life, you'll tell me? Certainly. But we <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> get on in life. We don't pretend to do it.”</p><p >My guardian looked at us again, plainly saying, “You hear him?”</p><p >“Now Harold,” he began, “the word I have to say, relates to Rick.”</p><p >“The dearest friend I have!” returned Mr. Skimpole, cordially. “I suppose he ought not to be my dearest friend, as he is not on terms with you. But he is, I can't help it; he is full of youthful poetry, and I love him. If you don't like it, I can't help it. I love him.”</p><p >The engaging frankness with which he made this declaration, really had a disinterested appearance, and captivated my guardian; if not, for the moment, Ada too.</p><p >“You are welcome to love him as much as you like,” returned Mr. Jarndyce, “but we must save his pocket, Harold.”</p><p >“Oh!” said Mr. Skimpole. “His pocket? Now, you are coming to what I don't understand.” Taking a little more claret, and dipping one of the cakes in it, he shook his head, and smiled at Ada and me with an ingenuous foreboding that he never could be made to understand.</p><p >“If you go with him here or there,” said my guardian, plainly, “you must not let him pay for both.”</p><p >“My dear Jarndyce,” returned Mr. Skimpole, his genial face irradiated by the comicality of this idea, “what am I to do? If he takes me anywhere, I must go. And how can <hi rend="italics">I</hi> pay? I never have any money. If I had any money, I don't know anything about it. Suppose I say to a man, how much? Suppose the man says to me seven and sixpence? I know nothing about seven and sixpence. It is impossible for me to
<pb xml:id="p421"/>
pursue the subject, with any consideration for the man. I don't go about asking busy people what seven and sixpence is in Moorish—which I don't understand. Why should I go about asking them what seven and sixpence is in Money—which I don't understand?”</p><p >“Well,” said my guardian, by no means displeased with this artless reply, “if you come to any kind of journeying with Rick, you must borrow the money of me (never breathing the least allusion to that circumstance), and leave the calculation to him.”</p><p >“My dear Jarndyce,” returned Mr. Skimpole, “I will do anything to give you pleasure, but it seems an idle form—a superstition. Besides, I give you my word, Miss Clare and my dear Miss Summerson, I thought Mr. Carstone was immensely rich. I thought he had only to make over something, or to sign a bond, or a draft, or a cheque, or a bill, or to put something on a file somewhere, to bring down a shower of money.”</p><p >“Indeed it is not so, sir,” said Ada. “He is poor.”</p><p >“No, really?” returned Mr. Skimpole, with his bright smile, “you surprise me.”</p><p >“And not being the richer for trusting in a rotten reed,” said my guardian, laying his hand emphatically on the sleeve of Mr. Skimpole's dressing-gown, “be you very careful not to encourage him in that reliance, Harold.”</p><p >“My dear good friend,” returned Mr. Skimpole, “and my dear Miss Summerson, and my dear Miss Clare, how can I do that? It's business, and I don't know business. It is he who encourages me. He emerges from great feats of business, presents the brightest prospects before me as their result, and calls upon me to admire them. I do admire them—as bright prospects. But I know no more about them, and I tell him so.”</p><p >The helpless kind of candor with which he presented this before us, the lighthearted manner in which he was amused by his innocence, the fantastic way in which he took himself under his own protection and argued about that curious person, combined with the delightful ease of everything he said exactly to make out my guardian's case. The more I saw of him, the more unlikely it seemed to me, when he was present, that he could design, conceal, or influence anything; and yet the less likely that appeared when he was not present, and the less agreeable it was to think of his having anything to do with anyone for whom I cared.</p><p >Hearing that his examination (as he called it) was now over, Mr. Skimpole left the room with a radiant face to fetch his daughters (his sons had run away at various times), leaving my guardian quite delighted by the manner in which he had vindicated his childish character. He soon came back, bringing with him the three young ladies and Mrs. Skimpole, who had once been a beauty, but was now a delicate high-nosed invalid suffering under a complication of disorders.</p><p >“This,” said Mr. Skimpole, “is my Beauty daughter, Arethusa—plays and sings odds and ends like her father. This is my Sentiment daughter, Laura—plays a little but don't sing. This is my Comedy daughter, Kitty—sings a little but don't play. We all draw a little, and compose a little, and none of us have any idea of time or money.”</p><p >Mrs. Skimpole sighed, I thought, as if she would have been glad to
<pb xml:id="p422"/>
strike out this item in the family attainments. I also thought that she rather impressed her sigh upon my guardian, and that she took every opportunity of throwing in another.</p><p >“It is pleasant,” said Mr. Skimpole, turning his sprightly eyes from one to the other of us, “and it is whimsically interesting, to trace peculiarities in families. In this family we are all children, and I am the youngest.”</p><p >The daughters, who appeared to be very fond of him, were amused by this droll fact; particularly the Comedy daughter.</p><p >“My dears, it is true,” said Mr. Skimpole, “is it not? So it is, and so it must be, because, like the dogs in the hymn, ‘it is our nature to.’ Now, here is Miss Summerson with a fine administrative capacity, and a knowledge of details perfectly surprising. It will sound very strange in Miss Summerson's ears, I dare say, that we know nothing about chops in this house. But we don't; not the least. We can't cook anything whatever. A needle and thread we don't know how to use. We admire the people who possess the practical wisdom we want; but we don't quarrel with them. Then why should they quarrel with us? Live, and let live, we say to them. Live upon your practical wisdom, and let us live upon you!”</p><p >He laughed, but, as usual, seemed quite candid, and really to mean what he said.</p><p >“We have sympathy, my roses,” said Mr. Skimpole, “sympathy for everything. Have we not?”</p><p >“O yes, papa!” cried the three daughters.</p><p >“In fact, that is our family department,” said Mr. Skimpole, “in this hurly-burly of life. We are capable of looking on and of being interested, and we <hi rend="italics">do</hi> look on, and we <hi rend="italics">are</hi> interested. What more can we do! Here is my Beauty daughter, married these three years. Now, I dare say her marrying another child, and having two more, was all wrong in point of political economy; but it was very agreeable. We had our little festivities on those occasions, and exchanged social ideas. She brought her young husband home one day, and they and their young fledgelings have their nest up-stairs. I dare say, at some time or other, Sentiment and Comedy will bring <hi rend="italics">their</hi> husbands home, and have <hi rend="italics">their</hi> nests up-stairs too. So we get on; we don't know how, but somehow.”</p><p >She looked very young indeed, to be the mother of two children; and I could not help pitying both her and them. It was evident that the three daughters had grown up as they could, and had had just as little hap-hazard instruction as qualified them to be their father's playthings in his idlest hours. His pictorial tastes were consulted, I observed, in their respective styles of wearing their hair; the Beauty daughter being in the classic manner; the Sentiment daughter luxuriant and flowing; and the Comedy daughter in the arch style, with a good deal of sprightly forehead, and vivacious little curls dotted about the corners of her eyes. They were dressed to correspond, though in a most untidy and negligent way.</p><p >Ada and I conversed with these young ladies, and found them wonderfully like their father. In the meanwhile Mr. Jarndyce (who had been rubbing his head to a great extent, and hinting at a change in the wind) talked with Mrs. Skimpole in a corner, where we could not
<pb xml:id="p423"/>
help hearing the chink of money. Mr. Skimpole had previously volunteered to go home with us, and had withdrawn to dress himself for the purpose.</p><p >“My roses,” he said, when he came back, “take care of mamma. She is poorly to-day. By going home with Mr. Jarndyce for a day or two, I shall hear the larks sing, and preserve my amiability. It has been tried, you know, and would be tried again if I remained at home.”</p><p >“That bad man!” said the Comedy daughter.</p><p >“At the very time when he knew papa was lying down by his wall-flowers, looking at the blue sky,” Laura complained.</p><p >“And when the smell of hay was in the air!” said Arethusa.</p><p >“It showed a want of poetry in the man,” Mr. Skimpole assented; but with perfect good-humour. “It was coarse. There was an absence of the finer touches of humanity in it! My daughters have taken great offence,” he explained to us, “at an honest man —”</p><p >“Not honest, Papa. Impossible!” they all three protested.</p><p >“At a rough kind of fellow—a sort of human hedge-hog rolled up,” said Mr. Skimpole, “who is a baker in this neighbourhood, and from whom we borrowed a couple of arm-chairs. We wanted a couple of arm-chairs, and we hadn't got them, and therefore of course we looked to a man who <hi rend="italics">had</hi> got them, to lend them. Well! this morose person lent them, and we wore them out. When they were worn out, he wanted them back. He had them back. He was contented, you will say. Not at all. He objected to their being worn. I reasoned with him, and pointed out his mistake. I said, ‘Can you, at your time of life, be so headstrong, my friend, as to persist that an arm-chair is a thing to put upon a shelf and look at? That it is an object to contemplate, to survey from a distance, to consider from a point of sight? Don't you <hi rend="italics">know</hi> that these arm-chairs were borrowed to be sat upon?’ He was unreasonable and unpersuadable, and used intemperate language. Being as patient as I am at this minute, I addressed another appeal to him. I said, ‘Now, my good man, however our business capacities may vary, we are all children of one great mother, Nature. On this blooming summer morning here you see me’ (I was on the sofa) ‘with flowers before me, fruit upon the table, the cloudless sky above me, the air full of fragrance, contemplating Nature. I entreat you, by our common brotherhood, not to interpose between me and a subject so sublime, the absurd figure of an angry baker!’ But he did,” said Mr. Skimpole, raising his laughing eyebrows in playful astonishment; “he did interpose that ridiculous figure, and he does, and he will again. And therefore I am very glad to get out of his way, and to go home with my friend Jarndyce.”</p><p >It seemed to escape his consideration that Mrs. Skimpole and the daughters remained behind to encounter the baker; but this was so old a story to all of them that it had become a matter of course. He took leave of his family with a tenderness as airy and graceful as any other aspect in which he showed himself, and rode away with us in perfect harmony of mind. We had an opportunity of seeing through some open doors, as we went down-stairs, that his own apartment was a palace to the rest of the house.</p><p >I could have no anticipation, and I had none, that something very starting to me at the moment, and ever memorable to me in what
<pb xml:id="p424"/>
ensued from it, was to happen before this day was out. Our guest was in such spirits on the way home, that I could do nothing but listen to him and wonder at him; nor was I alone in this, for Ada yielded to the same fascination. As to my guardian, the wind, which had threatened to become fixed in the east when we left Somer's Town, veered completely round, before we were a couple of miles from it.</p><p >Whether of questionable childishness or not, in any other matters, Mr. Skimpole had a child's enjoyment of change and bright weather. In no way wearied by his sallies on the road, he was in the drawing-room before any of us; and I heard him at the piano while I was yet looking after my housekeeping, singing refrains of barcaroles and drinking songs Italian and German by the score.</p><p >We were all assembled shortly before dinner, and he was still at the piano idly picking out in his luxurious way little strains of music, and talking between whiles of finishing some sketches of the ruined old Verulam wall, to-morrow, which he had begun a year or two ago and had got tired of; when a card was brought in, and my guardian read aloud in a surprised voice:</p><p >“Sir Leicester Dedlock!”</p><p >The visitor was in the room while it was yet turning round with me, and before I had the power to stir. If I had had it, I should have hurried away. I had not even the presence of mind, in my giddiness, to retire to Ada in the window, or to see the window, or to know where it was. I heard my name, and found that my guardian was presenting me, before I could move to a chair.</p><p >“Pray be seated, Sir Leicester.”</p><p >“Mr. Jarndyce,” said Sir Leicester in reply, as he bowed and seated himself, “I do myself the honor of calling here—”</p><p >“You do <hi rend="italics">me</hi> the honor, Sir Leicester.”</p><p >“Thank you—of calling here on my road from Lincolnshire, to express my regret that any cause of complaint, however strong, that I may have against a gentleman who—who is known to you and has been your host, and to whom therefore I will make no farther reference, should have prevented you, still more ladies under your escort and charge, from seeing whatever little there may be to gratify a polite and refined taste, at my house, Chesney Wold.”</p><p >“You are exceedingly obliging, Sir Leicester, and on behalf of those ladies (who are present) and for myself, I thank you very much.”</p><p >“It is possible, Mr. Jarndyce, that the gentleman to whom, for the reasons I have mentioned I refrain from making further allusion—it is possible, Mr. Jarndyce, that that gentleman may have done me the honor so far to misapprehend my character, as to induce you to believe that you would not have been received by my local establishment in Lincolnshire with that urbanity, that courtesy, which its members are instructed to show to all ladies and gentlemen who present themselves at that house. I merely beg to observe, sir, that the fact is the reverse.”</p><p >My guardian delicately dismissed this remark without making any verbal answer.</p><p >“It has given me pain, Mr. Jarndyce,” Sir Leicester weightily proceeded. “I assure you, sir, it has given—Me—pain—to learn from the housekeeper at Chesney Wold, that a gentleman who was in your company
<pb xml:id="p425"/>
in that part of the county, and who would appear to possess a cultivated taste for the Fine Arts, was likewise deterred, by some such cause, from examining the family pictures with that leisure, that attention, that care, which he might have desired to bestow upon them, and which some of them might possibly have repaid.” Here he produced a card, and read, with much gravity and a little trouble, through his eye-glass, “Mr. Hirrold,—Herald—Harold—Skampling—Skumpling—I beg your pardon,—Skimpole.”</p><p >“This is Mr. Harold Skimpole,” said my guardian, evidently surprised.</p><p >“Oh!” exclaimed Sir Leicester, “I am happy to meet Mr. Skimpole, and to have the opportunity of tendering my personal regrets. I hope, sir, that when you again find yourself in my part of the county, you will be under no similar sense of restraint.”</p><p >“You are very obliging, Sir Leicester Dedlock. So encouraged, I shall certainly give myself the pleasure and advantage of another visit to your beautiful house. The owners of such places as Chesney Wold,” said Mr. Skimpole with his usual happy and easy air, “are public benefactors. They are good enough to maintain a number of delightful objects for the admiration and pleasure of us poor men; and not to reap all the admiration and pleasure that they yield, is to be ungrateful to our benefactors.”</p><p >Sir Leicester seemed to approve of this sentiment highly. “An artist, sir?”</p><p >“No,” returned Mr. Skimpole. “A perfectly idle man. A mere amateur.”</p><p >Sir Leicester seemed to approve of his even more. He hoped he might have the good fortune to be at Chesney Wold when Mr. Skimpole next came down into Lincolnshire. Mr. Skimpole professed himself much flattered and honored.</p><p >“Mr. Skimpole mentioned,” pursued Sir Leicester, addressing himself again to my guardian; “mentioned to the housekeeper, who, as he may have observed, is an old and attached retainer of the family—”</p><p >(“That is, when I walked through the house the other day, on the occasion of my going down to visit Miss Summerson and Miss Clare,” Mr. Skimpole airily explained to us.)</p><p >“That the friend with whom he had formerly been staying there, was Mr. Jarndyce.” Sir Leicester bowed to the bearer of that name. “And hence I became aware of the circumstance for which I have professed my regret. That this should have occurred to any gentleman, Mr. Jarndyce, but especially a gentleman formerly known to Lady Dedlock, and indeed claiming some distant connection with her, and for whom (as I learn from my Lady herself) she entertains a high respect, does, I assure you, give—Me—pain.”</p><p >“Pray say no more about it, Sir Leicester,” returned my guardian. “I am very sensible, as I am sure we all are, of your consideration. Indeed the mistake was mine, and I ought to apologise for it.”</p><p >I had not once looked up. I had not seen the visitor, and had not even appeared to myself to hear the conversation. It surprises me to find that I can recall it, for it seemed to make no impression on me as it passed. I heard them speaking, but my mind was so confused, and my
<pb xml:id="p426"/>
instinctive avoidance of this gentleman made his presence so distressing to me, that I thought I understood nothing, through the rushing in my head and the beating of my heart.</p><p >“I mentioned the subject to Lady Dedlock,” said Sir Leicester, rising, “and my Lady informed me that she had had the pleasure of exchanging a few words with Mr. Jarndyce and his wards, on the occasion of an accidental meeting during their sojourn in the vicinity. Permit me, Mr. Jarndyce, to repeat to yourself, and to these ladies, the assurance I have already tendered to Mr. Skimpole. Circumstances undoubtedly prevent my saying that it would afford me any gratification to hear that Mr. Boythorn had favored my house with his presence; but those circumstances are confined to that gentleman himself, and do not extend beyond him.”</p><p >“You know my old opinion of him,” said Mr. Skimpole, lightly appealing to us. “An amiable bull, who is determined to make every colour scarlet!”</p><p >Sir Leicester Dedlock coughed, as if he could not possibly hear another word in reference to such an individual; and took his leave with great ceremony and politeness. I got to my own room with all possible speed, and remained there until I had recovered my self-command. It had been very much disturbed; but I was thankful to find, when I went downstairs again, that they only rallied me for having been shy and mute before the great Lincolnshire baronet.</p><p >By that time I had made up my mind that the period was come when I must tell my guardian what I knew. The possibility of my being brought into contact with my mother, of my being taken to her house,—even of Mr. Skimpole's, however distantly associated with me, receiving kindnesses and obligations from her husband,—was so painful, that I felt I could no longer guide myself without his assistance.</p><p >When we had retired for the night, and Ada and I had had our usual talk in our pretty room, I went out at my door again, and sought my guardian among his books. I knew he always read at that hour; and as I drew near, I saw the light shining out into the passage from his reading-lamp.</p><p >“May I come in, guardian?”</p><p >“Surely, little woman. What's the matter?”</p><p >“Nothing is the matter. I thought I would like to take this quiet time of saying a word to you about myself.”</p><p >He put a chair for me, shut his book, and put it by, and turned his kind attentive face towards me. I could not help observing that it wore that curious expression I had observed in it once before—on that night when he had said that he was in no trouble which I could readily understand.</p><p >“What concerns you, my dear Esther,” said he “concerns us all. You cannot be more ready to speak than I am to hear.”</p><p >“I know that, guardian. But I have such need of your advice and support. O! you don't know how much need I have to-night.”</p><p >He looked unprepared for my being so earnest, and even a little alarmed.</p><p >“Or how anxious I have been to speak to you,” said I, “ever since the visitor was here to-day.”</p><pb  xml:id="p427"/><p >“The visitor, my dear! Sir Leicester Dedlock?”</p><p >“Yes.”</p><p >He folded his arms, and sat looking at me with an air of the profoundest astonishment, awaiting what I should say next. I did not know how to prepare him.</p><p >“Why, Esther,” said he, breaking into a smile, “our visitor and you are the two last persons on earth I should have thought of connecting together!”</p><p >“O yes, guardian, I know it. And I too, but a little while ago.”</p><p >The smile passed from his face, and he became graver than before. He crossed to the door to see that it was shut (but I had seen to that), and resumed his seat before me.</p><p >“Guardian,” said I, “do you remember, when we were overtaken by the thunderstorm, Lady Dedlock's speaking to you of her sister?”</p><p >“Of course. Of course I do.”</p><p >“And reminding you that she and her sister had differed; had ‘gone their several ways?’”</p><p >“Of course.”</p><p >“Why did they separate, guardian?”</p><p >His face quite altered as he looked at me. “My child, what questions are these! I never knew. No one but themselves ever did know, I believe. Who could tell what the secrets of those two handsome and proud women were! You have seen Lady Dedlock. If you had ever seen her sister, you would know her to have been as resolute and haughty as she.”</p><p >“O guardian, I have seen her many and many a time!”</p><p >“Seen her?”</p><p >He paused a little, biting his lip. “Then, Esther, when you spoke to me long ago of Boythorn, and when I told you that he was all but married once, and that the lady did not die, but died to him, and that that time had had its influence on his later life—did you know it all, and know who the lady was?”</p><p >“No, guardian,” I returned, fearful of the light that dimly broke upon me. “Nor do I know yet.”</p><p >“Lady Dedlock's sister.”</p><p >“And why,” I could scarcely ask him, “why, guardian, pray tell me why were <hi rend="italics">they</hi> parted?”</p><p >“It was her act, and she kept its motives in her inflexible heart. He afterwards did conjecture (but it was mere conjecture), that some injury which her haughty spirit had received in her cause of quarrel with her sister, had wounded her beyond all reason; but she wrote him that from the date of that letter she died to him—as in literal truth she did—and that the resolution was exacted from her by her knowledge of his proud temper and his strained sense of honour, which were both her nature too. In consideration for those master points in him, and even in consideration for them in herself, she made the sacrifice, she said, and would live in it and die in it. She did both, I fear: certainly he never saw her, never heard of her from that hour. Nor did any one.”</p><p >“O guardian, what have I done!” I cried, giving way to my grief; “what sorrow have I innocently caused!”</p><p >“You caused, Esther?”</p><pb  xml:id="p428"/><p >“Yes, guardian. Innocently, but most surely. That secluded sister is my first remembrance.”</p><p >“No, no!” he cried, starting.</p><p >“Yes, guardian, yes! And <hi rend="italics">her</hi> sister is my mother!”</p><p >I would have told him all my mother's letter, but he would not hear it then. He spoke so tenderly and wisely to me, and he put so plainly before me all I had myself imperfectly thought and hoped in my better state of mind, that, penetrated as I had been with fervent gratitude towards him through so many years, I believed I had never loved him so dearly, never thanked him in my heart so fully, as I did that night. And when he had taken me to my room and kissed me at the door, and when at last I lay down to sleep, my thought was how could I ever be busy enough, how could I ever be good enough, how in my little way could I ever hope to be forgetful enough of myself, devoted enough to him, and useful enough to others, to show him how I blessed and honored him.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XLIV. <lb/> THE LETTER AND THE ANSWER.</head><p >MY guardian called me into his room next morning, and then I told him what had been left untold on the previous night. There was nothing to be done, he said, but to keep the secret, and to avoid another such encounter as that of yesterday. He understood my feeling, and entirely shared it. He charged himself even with restraining Mr. Skimpole from improving his opportunity. One person whom he need not name to me, it was not now possible for him to advise or help. He wished it were; but no such thing could be. If her mistrust of the lawyer whom she had mentioned were well-founded, which he scarcely doubted, he dreaded discovery. He knew something of him, both by sight and by reputation, and it was certain that he was a dangerous man. Whatever happened, he repeatedly impressed upon me with anxious affection and kindness, I was as innocent of, as himself; and as unable to influence.</p><p >“Nor do I understand,” said he, “that any doubts tend towards you, my dear. Much suspicion may exist without that connexion.”</p><p >“With the lawyer,” I returned. “But two other persons have come into my mind since I have been anxious.” Then I told him all about Mr. Guppy, who I feared might have had his vague surmises when I little understood his meaning, but in whose silence after our last interview I expressed perfect confidence.”</p><p >“Well,” said my guardian. “Then we may dismiss him for the present. Who is the other?”</p><p >I called to his recollection the French maid, and the eager offer of herself she had made to me.</p><p >“Ha!” he returned thoughtfully, “that is a more alarming person
<pb xml:id="p429"/>
than the clerk. But after all, my dear, it was but seeking for a new service. She had seen you and Ada a little while before, and it was natural that you should come into her head. She merely proposed herself for your maid, you know. She did nothing more.”</p><p >“Her manner was strange,” said I.</p><p >“Yes, and her manner was strange when she took her shoes off, and showed that cool relish for a walk that might have ended in her deathbed,” said my guardian. “It would be useless self-distress and torment to reckon up such chances and possibilities. There are very few harmless circumstances that would not seem full of perilous meaning, so considered. Be hopeful, little woman. You can be nothing better than yourself; be that, through this knowledge, as you were before you had it. It is the best you can do, for everybody's sake. I sharing the secret with you—”</p><p >“And lightening it, guardian, so much,” said I.</p><p >“—Will be attentive to what passes in that family, so far as I can observe it from my distance. And if the time should come when I can stretch out a hand to render the least service to one whom it is better not to name even here, I will not fail to do it for her dear daughter's sake.”</p><p >I thanked him with my whole heart. What could I ever do but thank him! I was going out at the door, when he asked me to stay a moment. Quickly turning round, I saw that same expression on his face again; and all at once, I don't know how, it flashed upon me as a new and far off possibility that I understood it.</p><p >“My dear Esther,” said my guardian, “I have long had something in my thoughts that I have wished to say to you.”</p><p >“Indeed?”</p><p >“I have had some difficulty in approaching it, and I still have. I should wish it to be so deliberately said, and so deliberately considered. Would you object to my writing it?”</p><p >“Dear guardian, how could I object to your writing anything for <hi rend="italics">me</hi> to read?”</p><p >“Then see, my love,” said he, with his cheery smile; “am I at this moment quite as plain and easy—do I seem as open, as honest and old-fashioned, as I am at any time?”</p><p >I answered, in all earnestness, “Quite.” With the strictest truth, for his momentary hesitation was gone (it had not lasted a minute), and his fine, sensible, cordial, sterling manner was restored.</p><p >“Do I look as if I suppressed anything, meant anything but what I said, had any reservation at all, no matter what?” said he, with his bright clear eyes on mine.</p><p >I answered, most assuredly he did not.</p><p >“Can you fully trust me, and thoroughly rely on what I profess, Esther?”</p><p >“Most thoroughly,” said I with my whole heart.</p><p >“My dear girl,” returned my guardian, “give me your hand.”</p><p >He took it in his, holding me lightly with his arm, and, looking down into my face with the same genuine freshness and faithfulness of manner—the old protecting manner which had made that house my home in a moment—said, “You have wrought changes in me, little woman, since the winter day in the stage coach. First and last you have done me a world of good, since that time.”</p><pb  xml:id="p430"/><p >“Ah, guardian, what have you done for me since that time!”</p><p >“But,” said he, “that is not to be remembered now.”</p><p >“It never can be forgotten.”</p><p >“Yes, Esther,” said he, with a gentle seriousness, “it is to be forgotten now; to be forgotten for a while. You are only to remember now, that nothing can change me as you know me. Can you feel quite assured of that, my dear?”</p><p >“I can, and I do,” I said.</p><p >“That's much,” he answered. “That's everything. But I must not take that, at a word. I will not write this something in my thoughts, until you have quite resolved within yourself that nothing can change me as you know me. If you doubt that in the least degree I will never write it. If you are sure of that, on good consideration, send Charley to me this night week—‘for the letter.’ But if you are not quite certain, never send. Mind, I trust to your truth, in this thing as in everything. If you are not quite certain on that one point, never send!”</p><p >“Guardian,” said I, “I am already certain. I can no more be changed in that conviction, than you can be changed towards me. I shall send Charley for the letter.”</p><p >He shook my hand and said no more. Nor was any more said in reference to this conversation, either by him or me, through the whole week. When the appointed night came, I said to Charley as soon as I was alone, “Go and knock at Mr. Jarndyce's door, Charley, and say you have come from me—‘for the letter.’” Charley went up the stairs, and down the stairs, and along the passages—the zig-zag way about the old-fashioned house seemed very long in my listening ears that night—and so came back, along the passages, and down the stairs, and up the stairs, and brought the letter. “Lay it on the table, Charley,” said I. So Charley laid it on the table and went to bed, and I sat looking at it without taking it up, thinking of many things.</p><p >I began with my overshadowed childhood, and passed through those timid days to the heavy time when my aunt lay dead, with her resolute face so cold and set; and when I was more solitary with Mrs. Rachael, than if I had had no one in the world to speak to or to look at. I passed to the altered days when I was so blest as to find friends in all around me, and to be beloved. I came to the time when I first saw my dear girl, and was received into that sisterly affection which was the grace and beauty of my life. I recalled the first bright gleam of welcome which had shone out of those very windows upon our expectant faces on that cold bright night, and which had never paled. I lived my happy life there over again, I went through my illness and recovery, I thought of myself so altered and of those around me so unchanged; and all this happiness shone like a light, from one central figure, represented before me by the letter on the table.</p><p >I opened it and read it. It was so impressive in its love for me, and in the unselfish caution it gave me, and the consideration it showed for me in every word, that my eyes were too often blinded to read much at a time. But I read it through three times, before I laid it down. I had thought beforehand that I knew its purport, and I did. It asked me would I be the mistress of Bleak House.</p><p >It was not a love letter though it expressed so much love, but was
<pb xml:id="p431"/>
written just as he would at any time have spoken to me. I saw his face, and heard his voice, and felt the influence of his kind protecting manner, in every line. It addressed me as if our places were reversed: as if all the good deeds had been mine, and all the feelings they had awakened, his. It dwelt on my being young, and he past the prime of life; on his having attained a ripe age, while I was a child; on his writing to me with a silvered head, and knowing all this so well as to set it in full before me for mature deliberation. It told me that I would gain nothing by such a marriage, and lose nothing by rejecting it; for no new relation could enhance the tenderness in which he held me, and whatever my decision was, he was certain it would be right. But he had considered this step anew, since our late confidence, and had decided on taking it; if it only served to show me, through one poor instance, that the whole world would readily unite to falsify the stern prediction of my childhood. I was the last to know what happiness I could bestow upon him, but of that he said no more; for I was always to remember that I owed him nothing, and that he was my debtor, and for very much. He had often thought of our future; and, foreseeing that the time must come, and fearing that it might come soon, when Ada (now very nearly of age) would leave us, and when our present mode of life must be broken up, had become accustomed to reflect on this proposal. Thus he made it. If I felt that I could ever give him the best right he could have to be my protector, and if I felt that I could happily and justly become the dear companion of his remaining life, superior to all lighter chances and changes than Death, even then he could not have me bind myself irrevocably, while this letter was yet so new to me; but, even then, I must have ample time for reconsideration. In that case, or in the opposite case, let him be unchanged in his old relation, in his old manner, in the old name by which I called him. And as to his bright Dame Durden and little housekeeper, she would ever be the same, he knew.</p><p >This was the substance of the letter; written throughout with a justice and a dignity, as if he were indeed my responsible guardian, impartially representing the proposal of a friend against whom in his integrity he stated the full case.</p><p >But he did not hint to me, that when I had been better-looking, he had had this same proceeding in his thoughts, and had refrained from it. That when my old face was gone from me, and I had no attractions, he could love me just as well as in my fairer days. That the discovery of my birth gave him no shock. That his generosity rose above my disfigurement, and my inheritance of shame. That the more I stood in need of such fidelity, the more firmly I might trust in him to the last.</p><p >But <hi rend="italics">I</hi> knew it, I knew it well now. It came upon me as the close of the benignant history I had been pursuing, and I felt that I had but one thing to do. To devote my life to his happiness was to thank him poorly, and what had I wished for the other night but some new means of thanking him?</p><p >Still I cried very much; not only in the fulness of my heart after reading the letter, not only in the strangeness of the prospect—for it was strange though I had expected the contents—but as if something for which there was no name or distinct idea were indefinitely lost to
<pb xml:id="p432"/>
me. I was very happy, very thankful, very hopeful; but I cried very much.</p><p >By-and-by I went to my old glass. My eyes were red and swollen, and I said, “O Esther, Esther, can that be you!” I am afraid the face in the glass was going to cry again at this reproach, but I held up my finger at it, and it stopped.</p><p >“That is more like the composed look you comforted me with, my dear, when you showed me such a change!” said I, beginning to let down my hair. “When you are mistress of Bleak House, you are to be as cheerful as a bird. In fact, you are always to be cheerful; so let us begin for once and for all.”</p><p >I went on with my hair now, quite comfortably. I sobbed a little still, but that was because I had been crying; not because I was crying then.</p><p >“And so Esther, my dear, you are happy for life. Happy with your best friends, happy in your old home, happy in the power of doing a great deal of good, and happy in the undeserved love of the best of men.”</p><p >I thought, all at once, if my guardian had married some one else, how should I have felt, and what should I have done! That would have been a change indeed. It presented my life in such a new and blank form, that I rang my housekeeping keys and gave them a kiss before I laid them down in their basket again.</p><p >Then I went on to think, as I dressed my hair before the glass, how often had I considered within myself that the deep traces of my illness, and the circumstances of my birth, were only new reasons why I should be busy, busy, busy—useful, amiable, serviceable, in all honest unpretending ways. This was a good time, to be sure, to sit down morbidly and cry! As to its seeming at all strange to me at first (if that were any excuse for crying, which it was not) that I was one day to be the mistress of Bleak House, why should it seem strange? Other people had thought of such things, if I had not. “Don't you remember, my plain dear,” I asked myself, looking at the glass, “what Mrs. Woodcourt said before those scars were there, about your marrying—”</p><p >Perhaps the name brought them to my remembrance. The dried remains of the flowers. It would be better not to keep them now. They had only been preserved in memory of something wholly past and gone, but it would be better not to keep them now.</p><p >They were in a book, and it happened to be in the next room—our sitting-room, dividing Ada's chamber from mine. I took a candle, and went softly in to fetch it from its shelf. After I had it in my hand, I saw my beautiful darling, through the open door, lying asleep, and I stole in to kiss her.</p><p >It was weak in me, I know, and I could have no reason for crying; but I dropped a tear upon her dear face, and another, and another. Weaker than that, I took the withered flowers out, and put them for a moment to her lips. I thought about her love for Richard; though, indeed, the flowers had nothing to do with that. Then I took them into my own room, and burned them at the candle, and they were dust in an instant.</p><p >On entering the breakfast-room next morning, I found my guardian
<pb xml:id="p433"/>
just as usual; quite as frank, as open, and free. There being not the least constraint in his manner, there was none (or I think there was none) in mine. I was with him several times in the course of the morning, in and out, when there was no one there; and I thought it not unlikely that he might speak to me about the letter; but he did not say a word.</p><p >So, on the next morning, and the next, and for at least a week; over which time Mr. Skimpole prolonged his stay. I expected, every day, that my guardian might speak to me about the letter; but he never did.</p><p >I thought then, growing uneasy, that I ought to write an answer. I tried over and over again in my own room at night, but I could not write an answer that at all began like a good answer; so I thought each night I would wait one more day. And I waited seven more days, and he never said a word.</p><p >At last Mr. Skimpole having departed, we three were one afternoon going out for a ride; and I being dressed before Ada, and going down, came upon my guardian, with his back towards me, standing at the drawing-room window looking out.</p><p >He turned on my coming in, and said, smiling, “Aye, it's you, little woman, is it?” and looked out again.</p><p >I had made up my mind to speak to him now. In short, I had come down on purpose. “Guardian,” I said, rather hesitating and trembling, “when would you like to have the answer to the letter Charley came for?”</p><p >“When it's ready, my dear,” he replied.</p><p >“I think it is ready,” said I.</p><p >“Is Charley to bring it?” he asked, pleasantly.</p><p >“No. I have brought it myself, guardian,” I returned.</p><p >I put my two arms round his neck and kissed him; and he said was this the mistress of Bleak House; and I said yes; and it made no difference presently, and we all went out together, and I said nothing to my precious pet about it.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XLV. <lb/> IN TRUST.</head><p >ONE morning when I had done jingling about with my baskets of keys, as my beauty and I were walking round and round the garden I happened to turn my eyes towards the house, and saw a long thin shadow going in which looked like Mr. Vholes. Ada had been telling me only that morning, of her hopes that Richard might exhaust his ardor in the Chancery suit by being so very earnest in it; and therefore, not to damp my dear girl's spirits, I said nothing about Mr. Vholes's shadow.</p><p >Presently came Charley, lightly winding among the bushes, and tripping along the paths, as rosy and pretty as one of Flora's attendants
<pb xml:id="p434"/>
instead of my maid, saying, “O if you please, miss, would you step and speak to Mr. Jarndyce!”</p><p >It was one of Charley's peculiarities, that whenever she was charged with a message she always began to deliver it as soon as she beheld, at any distance, the person for whom it was intended. Therefore I saw Charley, asking me in her usual form of words, to “step and speak” to Mr. Jarndyce, long before I heard her. And when I did hear her, she had said it so often that she was out of breath.</p><p >I told Ada I would make haste back, and inquired of Charley, as we went in, whether there was not a gentleman with Mr. Jarndyce? To which Charley, whose grammar, I confess to my shame, never did any credit to my educational powers, replied, “Yes, miss. Him as come down in the country with Mr. Richard.”</p><p >A more complete contrast than my guardian and Mr. Vholes, I suppose there could not be. I found them looking at one another across a table; the one so open, and the other so close; the one so broad and upright, and the other so narrow and stooping; the one giving out what he had to say in such a rich ringing voice, and the other keeping it in in such a cold-blooded, gasping, fish-like manner; that I thought I never had seen two people so unmatched.</p><p >“You know Mr. Vholes, my dear,” said my guardian. Not with the greatest urbanity, I must say.</p><p >Mr. Vholes rose, gloved and buttoned up as usual, and seated himself again, just as he had seated himself beside Richard in the gig. Not having Richard to look at, he looked straight before him.</p><p >“Mr. Vholes,” said my guardian, eyeing his black figure, as if he were a bird of ill omen, “has brought an ugly report of our most unfortunate Rick.” Laying a marked emphasis on most unfortunate, as if the words were rather descriptive of his connexion with Mr. Vholes.</p><p >I sat down between them; Mr. Vholes remained immoveable, except that he secretly picked at one of the red pimples on his yellow face with his black glove.</p><p >“And as Rick and you are happily good friends, I should like to know,” said my guardian, “what you think, my dear. Would you be so good as to—as to speak up, Mr. Vholes?”</p><p >Doing anything but that, Mr. Vholes observed:</p><p >“I have been saying that I have reason to know, Miss Summerson, as Mr. C's professional adviser, that Mr. C's circumstances are at the present moment in an embarrassed state. Not so much in point of amount, as owing to the peculiar and pressing nature of liabilities Mr. C has incurred, and the means he has of liquidating or meeting the same. I have staved off many little matters for Mr. C; but there is a limit to staving off, and we have reached it. I have made some advances out of pocket to accommodate these unpleasantnesses, but I necessarily look to being repaid, for I do not pretend to be a man of capital, and I have a father to support in the Vale of Taunton, besides striving to realise some little independence for three dear girls at home. My apprehension is, Mr. C's circumstances being such, lest it should end in his obtaining leave to part with his commission; which at all events is desirable to be made known to his connexions.”</p><p >Mr. Vholes, who had looked at me while speaking, here merged into
<pb xml:id="p435"/>
the silence he could hardly be said to have broken, so stifled was his tone and looked before him again.</p><p >“Imagine the poor fellow without even his present resource,” said my guardian to me. “Yet what can I do?” You know him, Esther. He would never accept of help from me, now. To offer it, or hint at it, would be to drive him to an extremity, if nothing else did.”</p><p >Mr. Vholes hereupon addressed me again.</p><p >“What Mr. Jarndyce remarks, miss, is no doubt the case, and is the difficulty. I do not see that anything is to be done. I do not say that anything is to be done. Far from it. I merely come down here under the seal of confidence and mention it, in order that everything may be openly carried on, and that it may not be said afterwards that everything was not openly carried on. My wish is that everything should be openly carried on. I desire to leave a good name behind me. If I consulted merely my own interests with Mr. C, I should not be here. So insurmountable, as you must well know, would be his objections. This is not a professional attendance. This can be charged to nobody. I have no interest in it, except as a member of society and a father—<hi rend="italics">and</hi> a son,” said Mr. Vholes, who had nearly forgotten that point.</p><p >It appeared to us that Mr. Vholes said neither more nor less than the truth, in intimating that he sought to divide the responsibility, such as it was, of knowing Richard's situation. I could only suggest that I should go down to Deal, where Richard was then stationed, and see him, and try if it were possible to avert the worst. Without consulting Mr. Vholes on this point, I took my guardian aside to propose it, while Mr. Vholes gauntly stalked to the fire, and warmed his funeral gloves.</p><p >The fatigue of the journey formed an immediate objection on my guardian's part; but as I saw he had no other, and as I was only too happy to go, I got his consent. We had then merely to dispose of Mr. Vholes.</p><p >“Well, sir,” said Mr. Jarndyce, “Miss Summerson will communicate with Mr. Carstone, and we can only hope that his position may be yet retrievable. You will allow me to order you lunch after your journey, sir.”</p><p >“I thank you, Mr. Jarndyce,” said Mr. Vholes, putting out his long black sleeve, to check the ringing of the bell, “not any. I thank you, no, not a morsel. My digestion is much impaired, and I am but a poor knife and fork at any time. If I was to partake of solid food at this period of the day, I don't know what the consequences might be. Everything having been openly carried on, sir, I will now with your permission take my leave.”</p><p >“And I would that you could take your leave, and we could all take our leave, Mr. Vholes,” returned my guardian, bitterly, “of a Cause you know of.”</p><p >Mr. Vholes, whose black dye was so deep from head to foot that it had quite steamed before the fire, diffusing a very unpleasant perfume. made a short one-sided inclination of his head from the neck, and slowly shook it.</p><p >“We whose ambition it is to be looked upon in the light of respectable practitioners, sir, can but put our shoulders to the wheel. We do it, sir. At least, I do it myself; and I wish to think well of my professional
<pb xml:id="p436"/>
brethren, one and all. You are sensible of an obligation not to refer to me, miss, in communicating with Mr. C?”</p><p >I said I would be careful not to do it.</p><p >“Just so, miss. Good morning. Mr. Jarndyce, good morning, sir.” Mr. Vholes put his dead glove, which scarcely seemed to have any hand in it, on my fingers, and then on my guardian's fingers, and took his long thin shadow away. I thought of it on the outside of the coach, passing over all the sunny landscape between us and London, chilling the seed in the ground as it glided along.</p><p >Of course it became necessary to tell Ada where I was going, and why I was going; and of course she was anxious and distressed. But she was too true to Richard to say anything but words of pity and words of excuse; and in a more loving spirit still—my dear, devoted girl!—she wrote him a long letter, of which I took charge.</p><p >Charley was to be my travelling companion, though I am sure I wanted none, and would willingly have left her at home. We all went to London that afternoon, and finding two places in the mail, secured them. At our usual bed-time, Charley and I were rolling away seaward, with the Kentish letters.</p><p >It was a night's journey in those coach times; but we had the mail to ourselves, and did not find the night very tedious. It passed with me as I suppose it would with most people under such circumstances. At one while, my journey looked hopeful, and at another hopeless. Now I thought that I should do some good, and now I wondered how I could ever have supposed so. Now it seemed one of the most reasonable things in the world that I should have come, and now one of the most unreasonable. In what state I should find Richard, what I should say to him, and what he would say to me, occupied my mind by turns with these two states of feeling; and the wheels seemed to play one tune (to which the burden of my guardian's letter set itself) over and over again all night.</p><p >At last we came into the narrow streets of Deal: and very gloomy they were, upon a raw misty morning. The long flat beach, with its little irregular houses, wooden and brick, and its litter of capstans, and great boats, and sheds, and bare upright poles with tackle and blocks, and loose gravelly waste places overgrown with grass and weeds, wore as dull an appearance as any place I ever saw. The sea was heaving under a thick white fog; and nothing else was moving but a few early ropemakers, who, with the yarn twisted round their bodies, looked as if, tired of their present state of existence, they were spinning themselves into cordage.</p><p >But when we got into a warm room in an excellent hotel, and sat down, comfortably washed and dressed, to an early breakfast (for it was too late to think of going to bed), Deal began to look more cheerful. Our little room was like a ship's cabin, and that delighted Charley very much. Then the fog began to rise like a curtain; and numbers of ships, that we had had no idea were near, appeared. I don't know how many sail the waiter told us were then lying in the Downs. Some of these vessels were of grand size: one was a large Indiaman, just come home: and when the sun shone through the clouds, making silvery pools in the dark sea, the way in which these ships brightened, and shadowed, and changed, amid a bustle of boats putting off from the shore to them
<pb xml:id="p437"/>
and from them to the shore, and a general life and motion in themselves and everything around them, was most beautiful.</p><p >The large Indiaman was our great attraction, because she had come into the Downs in the night. She was surrounded by boats; and we said how glad the people on board of her must be to come ashore. Charley was curious, too, about the voyage, and about the heat in India, and the serpents and the tigers; and as she picked up such information much faster than grammar, I told her what I knew on those points. I told her, too, how people in such voyages were sometimes wrecked and cast on rocks, where they were saved by the intrepidity and humanity of one man. And Charley asking how that could be, I told her how we knew at home of such a case.</p><p >I had thought of sending Richard a note, saying I was there, but it seemed so much better to go to him without preparation. As he lived in barracks I was a little doubtful whether this was feasible, but we went out to reconnoitre. Peeping in at the gate of the barrack yard, we found everything very quiet at that time in the morning; and I asked a serjeant standing on the guardhouse-steps, where he lived. He sent a man before to show me, who went up some bare stairs, and knocked with his knuckles at a door, and left us.</p><p >“Now then!” cried Richard, from within. So I left Charley in the little passage, and going on to the half-open door, said, “Can I come in, Richard. It's only Dame Durden.”</p><p >He was writing at a table, with a great confusion of clothes, tin cases, books, boots, brushes, and portmanteaus, strewn all about the floor. He was only half-dressed—in plain clothes, I observed, not in uniform—and his hair was unbrushed, and he looked as wild as his room. All this I saw after he had heartily welcomed me, and I was seated near him, for he started upon hearing my voice and caught me in his arms in a moment. Dear Richard! He was ever the same to me. Down to—ah, poor poor fellow!—to the end, he never received me but with something of his old merry boyish manner.</p><p >“Good Heaven, my dear little woman,” said he, “how do you come here. Who could have thought of seeing you! Nothing the matter? Ada is well?”</p><p >“Quite well. Lovelier than ever, Richard!”</p><p >“Ah!” he said, leaning back in his chair. “My poor cousin! I was writing to you, Esther.”</p><p >So worn and haggard as he looked, even in the fulness of his handsome youth, leaning back in his chair, and crushing the closely written sheet of paper in his hand!</p><p >“Have you been at the trouble of writing all that, and am I not to read it after all?” I asked.</p><p >“Oh my dear,” he returned, with a hopeless gesture. “You may read it in the whole room. It is all over here.”</p><p >I mildly entreated him not to be despondent. I told him that I had heard by chance of his being in difficulty, and had come to consult with him what could best be done.</p><p >“Like you, Esther, but useless, and so <hi rend="italics">not</hi> like you!” said he with a melancholy smile. “I am away on leave this day—should have been gone in another hour—and that is to smooth it over, for my selling out. Well!
<pb xml:id="p438"/>
Let bygones be bygones. So this calling follows the rest. I only want to have been in the church, to have made the round of all the professions.”</p><p >“Richard,” I urged, “it is not so hopeless as that?”</p><p >“Esther,” he returned, “it is indeed. I am just so near disgrace as that those who are put in authority over me (as the catechism goes) would far rather be without me than with me. And they are right. Apart from debts and duns, and all such drawbacks, I am not fit even for this employment. I have no care, no mind, no heart, no soul, but for one thing. Why, if this bubble hadn't broken now,” he said, tearing the letter he had written into fragments, and moodily casting them away, by driblets, “how could I have gone abroad? I must have been ordered abroad; but how could I have gone. How could I, with my experience of that thing, trust even Vholes unless I was at his back!”</p><p >I suppose he knew by my face what I was about to say, but he caught the hand I had laid upon his arm, and touched my own lips with it to prevent me from going on.</p><p >“No, Dame Durden! Two subjects I forbid—must forbid. The first is John Jarndyce. The second, you know what. Call it madness, and I tell you I can't help it now, and can't be sane. But it is no such thing; it is the one object I have to pursue. It is a pity I ever was prevailed upon to turn out of my road for any other. It would be wisdom to abandon it now, after all the time, anxiety, and pains I have bestowed upon it! O yes, true wisdom. It would be very agreeable, too, to some people; but I never will.”</p><p >He was in that mood in which I thought it best not to increase his determination (if anything could increase it) by opposing him. I took out Ada's letter, and put it in his hand.</p><p >“Am I to read it now?” he asked.</p><p >As I told him yes, he laid it on the table, and, resting his head upon his hand, began. He had not read far, when he rested his head upon his two hands—to hide his face from me. In a little while he rose as if the light were bad, and went to the window. He finished reading it there, with his back towards me; and, after he had finished and had folded it up, stood there for some minutes with the letter in his hand. When he came back to his chair, I saw tears in his eyes.</p><p >“Of course, Esther, you know what she says here?” He spoke in a softened voice, and kissed the letter as he asked me.</p><p >“Yes, Richard.”</p><p >“Offers me,” he went on, tapping his foot upon the floor, “the little inheritance she is certain of so soon—just as little and as much as I have wasted—and begs and prays me to take it, set myself right with it, and remain in the service.”</p><p >“I know your welfare to be the dearest wish of her heart,” said I. “And O, my dear Richard, Ada's is a noble heart!”</p><p >“I am sure it is. I—I wish I was dead!”</p><p >He went back to the window, and laying his arm across it, leaned his head down on his arm. It greatly affected me to see him so; but I hoped he might become more yielding, and I remained silent. My experience was very limited; I was not at all prepared for his rousing himself out of this emotion to a new sense of injury.</p><p >“And this is the heart that the same John Jarndyce, who is not otherwise
<pb xml:id="p439"/> to be mentioned between us, stepped in to estrange from me,” said he, indignantly. “And the dear girl makes me this generous offer from under the same John Jarndyce's roof, and with the same John Jarndyce's gracious consent and connivance, I dare say, as a new means of buying me off.”</p><p >“Richard!” I cried out, rising hastily, “I will not hear you say such shameful words!” I was very angry with him indeed, for the first time in my life; but it only lasted a moment. When I saw his worn young face looking at me, as if he were sorry, I put my hand on his shoulder, and said, “If you please, my dear Richard, do not speak in such a tone to me. Consider!”</p><p >He blamed himself exceedingly; and told me in the most generous manner, that he had been very wrong, and that he begged my pardon a thousand times. At that I laughed, but trembled a little too, for I was rather fluttered after being so fiery.</p><p >“To accept this offer, my dear Esther,” said he, sitting down beside me, and resuming our conversation,—“once more, pray, pray forgive me; I am deeply grieved—to accept my dearest cousin's offer is, I need not say, impossible. Besides, I have letters and papers that I could show you, which would convince you it is all over here. I have done with the red coat, believe me. But it is some satisfaction, in the midst of my troubles and perplexities, to know that I am pressing Ada's interests in pressing my own. Vholes has his shoulder to the wheel, and he cannot help urging it on as much for her as for me, thank God!”</p><p >His sanguine hopes were rising within him, and lighting up his features, but they made his face more sad to me than it had been before.</p><p >“No, no!” cried Richard, exultingly. “If every farthing of Ada's little fortune were mine, no part of it should be spent in retaining me in what I am not fit for, can take no interest in, and am weary of. It should be devoted to what promises a better return, and should be used where she has a larger stake. Don't be uneasy for me! I shall now have only one thing on my mind, and Vholes and I will work it. I shall not be without means. Free of my commission, I shall be able to compound with some small usurers, who will hear of nothing but their bond now—Vholes says so. I should have a balance in my favor any way, but that will swell it. Come, come! You shall carry a letter to Ada from me, Esther, and you must both of you be more hopeful of me, and not believe that I am quite cast away just yet, my dear.”</p><p >I will not repeat what I said to Richard. I know it was tiresome, and nobody is to suppose for a moment that it was at all wise. It only came from my heart. He heard it patiently and feelingly; but I saw that on the two subjects he had reserved, it was at present hopeless to make any representation to him. I saw too, and had experienced in this very interview, the sense of my guardian's remark that it was even more mischievous to use persuasion with him than to leave him as he was.</p><p >Therefore I was driven at last to asking Richard if he would mind convincing me that it really was all over there, as he had said, and that it was not his mere impression. He showed me without hesitation a correspondence making it quite plain that his retirement was arranged. I found, from what he told me, that Mr. Vholes had copies of these papers,
<pb xml:id="p440"/>
and had been in consultation with him throughout. Beyond ascertaining this, and having been the bearer of Ada's letter, and being (as I was going to be) Richard's companion back to London, I had done no good by coming down. Admitting this to myself with a reluctant heart, I said I would return to the hotel and wait until he joined me there; so he threw a cloak over his shoulders and saw me to the gate, and Charley and I went back along the beach.</p><p >There was a concourse of people in one spot, surrounding some naval officers who were landing from a boat, and pressing about them with unusual interest. I said to Charley this would be one of the great Indiaman's boats now, and we stopped to look.</p><p >The gentlemen came slowly up from the waterside, speaking good-humoredly to each other and to the people around, and glancing about them as if they were glad to be in England again. “Charley, Charley!” said I, “come away!” And I hurried on so swiftly that my little maid was surprised.</p><p >It was not until we were shut up in our cabin-room, and I had had time to take breath, that I began to think why I had made such haste. In one of the sun-burnt faces I had recognised Mr. Allan Woodcourt, and I had been afraid of his recognising me. I had been unwilling that he should see my altered looks. I had been taken by surprise, and my courage had quite failed me.</p><p >But I knew this would not do, and I now said to myself, “My dear, there is no reason—there is and there can be no reason at all—why it should be worse for you now, than it ever has been. What you were last month, you are to-day; you are no worse, you are no better. This is not your resolution; call it up, Esther, call it up!” I was in a great tremble—with running—and at first was quite unable to calm myself; but I got better, and I was very glad to know it.</p><p >The party came to the hotel. I heard them speaking on the staircase. I was sure it was the same gentlemen because I knew their voices again—I mean I knew Mr. Woodcourt's. It would still have been a great relief to me to have gone away without making myself known, but I was determined not to do so. “No my dear, no. No, no, no!”</p><p >I untied my bonnet and put my veil half up—I think I mean half down, but it matters very little—and wrote on one of my cards that I happened to be there with Mr. Richard Carstone; and I sent it in to Mr. Woodcourt. He came immediately. I told him I was rejoiced to be by chance among the first to welcome him home to England. And I saw that he was very sorry for me.</p><p >“You have been in shipwreck and peril since you left us, Mr. Woodcourt,” said I, “but we can hardly call that a misfortune which enabled you to be so useful and so brave. We read of it with the truest interest. It first came to my knowledge through your old patient poor Miss Flite, when I was recovering from my severe illness.”</p><p >“Ah! little Miss Flite!” he said. “She lives the same life yet?”</p><p >“Just the same.”</p><p >I was so comfortable with myself now, as not to mind the veil, and to be able to put it aside.</p><p >“Her gratitude to you, Mr. Woodcourt, is delightful. She is a most affectionate creature, as I have reason to say.”</p><pb  xml:id="p441"/><p >“You—you have found her so?” he returned. “I—I am glad of that.” He was so very sorry for me that he could scarcely speak.</p><p >“I assure you,” said I, “that I was deeply touched by her sympathy and pleasure at the time I have referred to.”</p><p >“I was grieved to hear that you had been very ill.”</p><p >“I was very ill.”</p><p >“But you have quite recovered?”</p><p >“I have quite recovered my health and my cheerfulness,” said I. “You know how good my guardian is, and what a happy life we lead; and I have everything to be thankful for, and nothing in the world to desire.”</p><p >I felt as if he had greater commiseration for me than I had ever had for myself. It inspired me with new fortitude, and new calmness, to find that it was I who was under the necessity of reassuring him. I spoke to him of his voyage out and home, and of his future plans, and of his probable return to India. He said that was very doubtful. He had not found himself more favoured by fortune there, than here. He had gone out a poor ship's surgeon, and had come home nothing better. While we were talking, and when I was glad to believe that I had alleviated (if I may use such a term) the shock he had had in seeing me, Richard came in. He had heard down-stairs who was with me, and they met with cordial pleasure.</p><p >I saw that after their first greetings were over, and when they spoke of Richard's career, Mr. Woodcourt had a perception that all was not going well with him. He frequently glanced at his face, as if there were something in it that gave him pain; and more than once he looked towards me, as though he sought to ascertain whether I knew what the truth was. Yet Richard was in one of his sanguine states, and in good spirits; and was thoroughly pleased to see Mr. Woodcourt again, whom he had always liked.</p><p >Richard proposed that we all should go to London together; but Mr. Woodcourt having to remain by his ship a little longer, could not join us. He dined with us, however, at an early hour; and became so much more like what he used to be, that I was still more at peace to think I had been able to soften his regrets. Yet his mind was not relieved of Richard. When the coach was almost ready, and Richard ran down to look after his luggage, he spoke to me about him.</p><p >I was not sure that I had a right to lay his whole story open; but I referred in a few words to his estrangement from Mr. Jarndyce, and to his being entangled in the ill-fated Chancery suit. Mr. Woodcourt listened with interest and expressed his regret.</p><p >“I saw you observe him rather closely,” said I. “Do you think him so changed?”</p><p >“He is changed,” he returned, shaking his head.</p><p >I felt the blood rush into my face for the first time, but it was only an instantaneous emotion. I turned my head aside, and it was gone.</p><p >“It is not,” said Mr. Woodcourt, “his being so much younger or older, or thinner or fatter, or paler or ruddier, as there being upon his face such a singular expression. I never saw so remarkable a look in a young person. One cannot say that it is all anxiety, or all weariness; yet it is both, and like ungrown despair.”</p><pb  xml:id="p442"/><p >“You do not think he is ill?” said I.</p><p >No. He looked robust in body.</p><p >“That he cannot be at peace in mind, we have too much reason to know,” I proceeded. “Mr. Woodcourt, you are going to London?”</p><p >“To-morrow or the next day.”</p><p >“There is nothing Richard wants so much, as a friend. He always liked you. Pray see him when you get there. Pray help him sometimes with your companionship, if you can. You do not know of what service it might be. You cannot think how Ada, and Mr. Jarndyce, and even I—how we should all thank you, Mr. Woodcourt!”</p><p >“Miss Summerson,” he said, more moved than he had been from the first, “before Heaven, I will be a true friend to him! I will accept him as a trust, and it shall be a sacred one!”</p><p >“God bless you!” said I, with my eyes filling fast; but I thought they might, when it was not for myself. “Ada loves him—we all love him, but Ada loves him as we cannot. I will tell her what you say. Thank you, and God bless you, in her name!”</p><p >Richard came back as we finished exchanging these hurried words, and gave me his arm to take me to the coach.</p><p >“Woodcourt,” he said, unconscious with what application, “pray let us meet in London!”</p><p >“Meet?” returned the other. “I have scarcely a friend there, now, but you. Where shall I find you?”</p><p >“Why, I must get a lodging of some sort,” said Richard, pondering. “Say at Vholes's, Symond's Inn.”</p><p >“Good! Without loss of time.”</p><p >They shook hands heartily. When I was seated in the coach, and Richard was yet standing in the street, Mr. Woodcourt laid his friendly hand on Richard's shoulder, and looked at me. I understood him, and waved mine in thanks.</p><p >And in his last look as we drove away, I saw that he was very sorry for me. I was glad to see it. I felt for my old self as the dead may feel if they ever revisit these scenes. I was glad to be tenderly remembered, to be gently pitied, not to be quite forgotten.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XLVI. <lb/> STOP HIM!</head><p >DARKNESS rests upon Tom-all-Alone's. Dilating and dilating since the sun went down last night, it has gradually swollen until it fills every void in the place. For a time there were some dungeon lights burning, as the lamp of Life burns in Tom-all-Alone's, heavily, heavily, in the nauseous air, and winking—as that lamp, too, winks in Tom-all-Alone's—at many horrible things. But they are blotted out. The moon has eyed Tom with a dull cold stare, as admitting some puny emulation of herself in his desert region unfit for life and blasted by volcanic fires; but she has passed on, and is gone. The blackest nightmare in the infernal stables grazes on Tom-all-Alone's, and Tom is fast asleep.</p><pb  xml:id="p443"/><p >Much mighty speech-making there has been, both in and out of Parliament, concerning Tom, and much wrathful disputation how Tom shall be got right. Whether he shall be put into the main road by constables, or by beadles, or by bell-ringing, or by force of figures, or by correct principles of taste, or by high church, or by low church, or by no church; whether he shall be set to splitting trusses of polemical straws with the crooked knife of his mind, or whether he shall be put to stone-breaking instead. In the midst of which dust and noise, there is but one thing perfectly clear, to wit, that Tom only may and can, or shall and will, be reclaimed according to somebody's theory but nobody's practice. And in the hopeful meantime, Tom goes to perdition head foremost in his old determined spirit.</p><p >But he has his revenge. Even the winds are his messengers, and they serve him in these hours of darkness. There is not a drop of Tom's corrupted blood but propagates infection and contagion somewhere. It shall pollute, this very night, the choice stream (in which chemists on analysis would find the genuine nobility) of a Norman house, and his Grace shall not be able to say Nay to the infamous alliance. There is not an atom of Tom's slime, not a cubic inch of any pestilential gas in which he lives, not one obscenity or degradation about him, not an ignorance, not a wickedness, not a brutality of his committing, but shall work its retribution, through every order of society, up to the proudest of the proud, and to the highest of the high. Verily, what with tainting, plundering, and spoiling, Tom has his revenge.</p><p >It is a moot point whether Tom-all-Alone's be uglier by day or by night; but on the argument that the more that is seen of it the more shocking it must be, and that no part of it left to the imagination is at all likely to be made so bad as the reality, day carries it. The day begins to break now; and in truth it might be better for the national glory even that the sun should sometimes set upon the British dominions, than that it should ever rise upon so vile a wonder as Tom.</p><p >A brown sunburnt gentleman, who appears in some inaptitude for sleep to be wandering abroad rather than counting the hours on a restless pillow, strolls hitherward at this quiet time. Attracted by curiosity, he often pauses and looks about him, up and down the miserable byways. Nor is he merely curious, for in his bright dark eye there is compassionate interest; and as he looks here and there, he seems to understand such wretchedness, and to have studied it before.</p><p >On the banks of the stagnant channel of mud which is the main street of Tom-all-Alone's, nothing is to be seen but the crazy houses, shut up and silent. No waking creature save himself appears, except in one direction where he sees the solitary figure of a woman sitting on a doorstep. He walks that way. Approaching, he observes that she has journeyed a long distance, and is footsore and travel-stained. She sits on the doorstep in the manner of one who is waiting, with her elbow or her knee and her head upon her hand. Beside her is a canvas bag, or bundle, she has carried. She is dozing probably, for she gives no heed to his steps as he comes towards her.</p><p >The broken footway is so narrow, that when Allan Woodcourt comes to where the woman sits, he has to turn into the road to pass her. Looking down at her face, his eye meets hers, and he stops.</p><pb  xml:id="p444"/><p >“What is the matter?”</p><p >“Nothing, sir.”</p><p >“Can't you make them hear? Do you want to be let in?”</p><p >“I'm waiting till they get up at another house—a lodging-house—not here,” the woman patiently returns. “I'm waiting here because there will be sun here presently to warm me.”</p><p >“I am afraid you are tired. I am sorry to see you sitting in the street.”</p><p >“Thank you, sir. It don't matter.”</p><p >A habit in him of speaking to the poor, and of avoiding patronage or condescension, or childishness (which is the favorite device, many people deeming it quite a subtlety to talk to them like little spelling books), has put him on good terms with the woman easily.</p><p >“Let me look at your forehead,” he says, bending down. “I am a doctor. Don't be afraid. I wouldn't hurt you for the world.”</p><p >He knows that by touching her with his skilful and accustomed hand, he can soothe her yet more readily. She makes a slight objection, saying, “It's nothing;” but he has scarcely laid his fingers on the wounded place when she lifts it up to the light.</p><p >“Aye! A bad bruise, and the skin sadly broken. This must be very sore.”</p><p >“It do ache a little, sir,” returns the woman, with a started tear upon her cheek.</p><p >“Let me try to make it more comfortable. My handkerchief won't hurt you.”</p><p >“O dear no sir, I'm sure of that!”</p><p >He cleanses the injured place and dries it; and having carefully examined it and gently pressed it with the palm of his hand, takes a small case from his pocket, dresses it, and binds it up. While he is thus employed, he says, after laughing at his establishing a surgery in the street:</p><p >“And so your husband is a brickmaker?”</p><p >“How do you know that, sir?” asks the woman, astonished.</p><p >“Why, I suppose so, from the color of the clay upon your bag and on your dress. And I know brickmakers go about working at piecework in different places. And I am sorry to say I have known them cruel to their wives too.”</p><p >The woman hastily lifts up her eyes as if she would deny that her injury is referable to such a cause. But feeling the hand upon her forehead, and seeing his busy and composed face, she quietly drops them again.</p><p >“Where is he now?” asks the surgeon.</p><p >“He got into trouble last night, sir; but he'll look for me at the lodging-house.”</p><p >“He will get into worse trouble if he often misuses his large and heavy hand as he has misused it here. But you forgive him, brutal as he is, and I say no more of him, except that I wish he deserved it. You have no young child?”</p><p >The woman shakes her head. “One as I calls mine, sir, but it's Liz's.”</p><p >“Your own is dead. I see! Poor little thing!”</p><pb  xml:id="p445"/><p >By this time he has finished, and is putting up his case. “I suppose you have some settled home. Is it far from here?” he asks, good-humoredly making light of what he has done, as she gets up and curtseys.</p><p >“It's a good two or three-and-twenty mile from here, sir. At Saint Albans. You know Saint Albans, sir? I thought you gave a start like, as if you did?”</p><p >“Yes, I know something of it. And now I will ask you a question in return. Have you money for your lodging?”</p><p >“Yes, sir,” she says, “really and truly.” And she shows it. He tells her, in acknowledgment of her many subdued thanks, that she is very welcome, gives her good day, and walks away. Tom-all-Alone's is still asleep, and nothing is astir.</p><p >Yes, something is! As he retraces his way to the point from which he descried the woman at a distance sitting on the step, he sees a ragged figure coming very cautiously along, crouching close to the soiled walls—which the wretchedest figure might as well avoid—and furtively thrusting a hand before it. It is the figure of a youth, whose face is hollow, and whose eyes have an emaciated glare. He is so intent on getting along unseen, that even the apparition of a stranger in whole garments does not tempt him to look back. He shades his face with his ragged elbow as he passes on the other side of the way, and goes shrinking and creeping on, with his anxious hand before him, and his shapeless clothes hanging in shreds. Clothes made for what purpose, or of what material, it would be impossible to say. They look, in color and in substance, like a bundle of rank leaves of swampy growth, that rotted long ago.</p><p >Allan Woodcourt pauses to look after him and note all this, with a shadowy belief that he has seen the boy before. He cannot recall how, or where; but there is some association in his mind with such a form. He imagines that he must have seen it in some hospital or refuge; still, cannot make out why it comes with any special force on his remembrance.</p><p >He is gradually emerging from Tom-all-Alone's in the morning light, thinking about it, when he hears running feet behind him; and looking round, sees the boy scouring towards him at great speed, followed by the woman.</p><p >“Stop him, stop him!” cries the woman, almost breathless. “Stop him, sir!”</p><p >He darts across the road into the boy's path, but the boy is quicker than he—makes a curve—ducks—dives under his hands—comes up half-a-dozen yards beyond him, and scours away again. Still, the woman follows, crying, “Stop him, sir, pray stop him!” Allan, not knowing but that he has just robbed her of her money, follows in chase, and runs so hard, that he runs the boy down a dozen times; but each time he repeats the curve, the duck, the dive, and scours away again. To strike at him, on any of these occasions, would be to fell and disable him; but the pursuer cannot resolve to do that; and so the grimly ridiculous pursuit continues. At last the fugitive, hard-pressed, takes to a narrow passage, and a court which has no thoroughfare. Here, against a hoarding of decaying timber, he is brought to bay, and tumbles down, lying gasping at his pursuer, who stands and gasps at him until the woman comes up.</p><p >“O you, Jo!” cries the woman. “What? I have found you at last!’</p><pb  xml:id="p446"/><p >“Jo,” repeats Allan, looking at him with attention, “Jo! Stay. To be sure! I recollect this lad some time ago being brought before the coroner.”</p><p >“Yes, I see you once afore at the Inkwhich,” whimpers Jo. “What of that? Can't you never let such an unfortnet as me alone? An't I unfortnet enough for you yet? How unfortnet do you want me fur to be? I've been a chivied and a chivied, fust by one on you and nixt by another on you, till I'm worrited to skins and bones. The Inkwhich warn't <hi rend="italics">my</hi> fault. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> done nothink. He wos wery good to me, he wos; he wos the only one I knowed to speak to, as ever come across my crossing. It an't wery likely I should want him to be Inkwhich'd. I only wish I wos, myself. I don't know why I don't go and make a hole in the water, I'm sure I don't.”</p><p >He says it with such a pitiable air, and his grimy tears appear so real, and he lies in the corner up against the hoarding so like a growth of fungus or any unwholesome excrescence produced there in neglect and impurity, that Allan Woodcourt is softened towards him. He says to the woman, “Miserable creature, what has he done?”</p><p >To which she only replies, shaking her head at the prostrate figure more amazedly than angrily: “O you Jo, you Jo. I have found you at last!”</p><p >“What has he done?” says Allan. “Has he robbed you?”</p><p >“No sir, no. Robbed me? He did nothing but what was kind-hearted by me, and that's the wonder of it.”</p><p >Allan looks from Jo to the woman, and from the woman to Jo, waiting for one of them to unravel the riddle.</p><p >“But he was along with me, sir,” says the woman,—“O you Jo!—he was along with me, sir, down at Saint Albans, ill, and a young lady Lord bless her for a good friend to me took pity on him when I durstn't, and took him home—”</p><p >Allan shrinks back from him with a sudden horror.</p><p >“Yes sir, yes. Took him home, and made him comfortable, and like a thankless monster he ran away in the night, and never has been seen or heard of since, till I set eyes on him just now. And that young lady that was such a pretty dear, caught his illness, lost her beautiful looks, and wouldn't hardly be known for the same young lady now, if it wasn't for her angel temper, and her pretty shape, and her sweet voice. Do you know it? You ungrateful wretch, do you know that this is all along of you and of her goodness to you?” demands the woman, beginning to rage at him as she recalls it, and breaking into passionate tears.</p><p >The boy, in rough sort stunned by what he hears, falls to smearing his dirty forehead with his dirty palm, and to staring at the ground, and to shaking from head to foot until the crazy hoarding against which he leans, rattles.</p><p >Allan restrains the woman, merely by a quiet gesture, but effectually.</p><p >“Richard told me,” he falters, “—I mean, I have heard of this—don't mind me for a moment, I will speak presently.”</p><p >He turns away, and stands for a while looking out at the covered passage. When he comes back, he has recovered his composure; except that he contends against an avoidance of the boy, which is so very remarkable, that it absorbs the woman's attention.</p><pb  xml:id="p447"/><p >“You hear what she says. But get up, get up!”</p><p >Jo, shaking and chattering, slowly rises, and stands, after the manner of his tribe in a difficulty, sideways against the hoarding, resting one of his high shoulders against it, and covertly rubbing his right hand over his left, and his left foot over his right.</p><p >“You hear what she says, and I know it's true. Have you been here ever since?”</p><p >“Wishermaydie if I seen Tom-all-alone's till this blessed morning,” replies Jo, hoarsely.</p><p >“Why have you come here now?”</p><p >Jo looks all round the confined court, looks at his questioner no higher than the knees, and finally answers:</p><p >“I don't know how to do nothing, and I can't get nothing to do. I'm wery poor and ill, and I thought I'd come back here when there warn't nobody about, and lay down and hide somewheres as I knows on till arter dark, and then go and beg a trifle of Mr. Sangsby. He wos allus willin fur to give me somethink he wos, though Mrs. Sangsby she was allus a chivying on me—like everybody everywheres.”</p><p >“Where have you come from?”</p><p >Jo looks all round the court again, looks at his questioner's knees again, and concludes by laying his profile against the hoarding in a sort of resignation.</p><p >“Did you hear me ask you where you have come from?”</p><p >“Tramp then,” says Jo.</p><p >“Now, tell me,” proceeds Allan, making a strong effort to overcome his repugnance, going very near to him, and leaning over him with an expression of confidence, “tell me how it came about that you left that house, when the good young lady had been so unfortunate as to pity you, and take you home.”</p><p >Jo suddenly comes out of his resignation, and excitedly declares, addressing the woman, that he never known about the young lady, that he never heern about it, that he never went fur to hurt her, that he would sooner have hurt his own self, that he'd sooner have had his unfortnet ed chopped off than ever gone a-nigh her, and that she wos wery good to him, she wos. Conducting himself throughout as if in his poor fashion he really meant it, and winding up with some very miserable sobs.</p><p >Allan Woodcourt sees that this is not a sham. He constrains himself to touch him. “Come, Jo. Tell me.”</p><p >“No. I dustn't,” says Jo, relapsing into the profile state. “I dustn't, or I would.”</p><p >“But I must know,” returns the other, “all the same. Come, Jo.”</p><p >After two or three such adjurations, Jo lifts up his head again, looks round the court again, and says in a low voice, “Well, I'll tell you somethink. I was took away. There!”</p><p >“Took away? In the night?”</p><p >“Ah!” Very apprehensive of being overheard, Jo looks about him, and even glances up some ten feet at the top of the hoarding, and through the cracks in it, lest the object of his distrust should be looking over, or hidden on the other side.</p><p >“Who took you away?”</p><p >“I dustn't name him,” says Jo. “I dustn't do it, sir.”</p><pb  xml:id="p448"/><p >“But I want, in the young lady's name, to know. You may trust me. No one else shall hear.”</p><p >“Ah, but I don't know,” replies Jo, shaking his head fearfully, “as he <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> hear.”</p><p >“Why, he is not in this place.”</p><p >“Oh, ain't he though?” says Jo. “He's in all manner of places, all at wunst.”</p><p >Allan looks at him in perplexity, but discovers some real meaning and good faith at the bottom of this bewildering reply. He patiently awaits an explicit answer; and Jo, more baffled by his patience than by anything else, at last desperately whispers a name in his ear.</p><p >“Aye!” says Allan. “Why, what had you been doing?”</p><p >“Nothing, sir. Never done nothink to get myself into no trouble, 'sept in not moving on and the Inkwhich. But I'm a moving on now. I'm a moving on to the berryin ground—that's the move as I'm up to.”</p><p >“No, no, we will try to prevent that. But what did he do with you?”</p><p >“Put me in a horsepittle,” replied Jo, whispering, “till I was discharged, then giv me a little money—four half bulls, wot you may call halfcrowns—and ses ‘Hook it! Nobody wants you here,’ he ses. ‘You hook it. You go and tramp,’ he ses. ‘You move on,’ he ses. ‘Don't let me ever see you nowheres within forty mile of London, or you'll repent it.’ So I shall, if ever he doos see me, and he'll see me if I'm above ground,” concludes Jo, nervously repeating all his former precautions and investigations.</p><p >Allan considers a little; then remarks, turning to the woman, but keeping an encouraging eye on Jo; “He is not so ungrateful as you supposed. He had a reason for going away, though it was an insufficient one.”</p><p >“Thank'ee, sir, thank'ee!” exclaims Jo. “There now! See how hard you wos upon me. But ony you tell the young lady wot the genlmn ses, and it's all right. For <hi rend="italics">you</hi> wos wery good to me too, and I knows it.”</p><p >“Now, Jo,” says Allan, keeping his eye upon him, “come with me, and I will find you a better place than this to lie down and hide in. If I take one side of the way and you the other, to avoid observation, you will not run away, I know very well, if you make me a promise.”</p><p >“I won't, not unless I wos to see <hi rend="italics">him</hi> a coming, sir.”</p><p >“Very well. I take your word. Half the town is getting up by this time, and the whole town will be broad awake in another hour. Come along. Good day again, my good woman.”</p><p >“Good day again, sir, and I thank you kindly many times again.”</p><p >She has been sitting on her bag, deeply attentive, and now rises and takes it up. Jo, repeating, “Ony you tell the young lady as I never went fur to hurt her and wot the genlmn ses!” nods and shambles and shivers, and smears and blinks, and half laughs and half cries, a farewell to her, and takes his creeping way along after Allan Woodcourt, close to the houses on the opposite side of the street. In this order, the two come up out of Tom-all-Alone's into the broad rays of the sunlight and the purer air.</p></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx6"/><head >ALI AHMED'S <lb/> TREASURES OF THE DESERT</head><head >A BRIEF TREATISE <lb/> ON THE SYSTEM OF MEDICINE <lb/> AS DEVELOPED IN THE WORKS OF THE CELEBRATED</head><p >ALI AHMED MASCUIELI, <lb/> PHYSICIAN OF ALEPPO AND DAMASCUS, <lb/> CONTAINING A FULL DESCRIPTION OF HIS <lb/> CELEBRATED PILLS &amp; PLAISTER <lb/> FOR THE CURE OF <lb/> Colds, Catarrhs, Bronchitis, Asthma, Quinsey, Rheumatic Affections of the Face and Head, Headache, Acidity in the Stomach, Giddiness, Palpitation of the Heart, Constipation, Flatulency, Diarrhœa, Noises in the Head and Ears, Eruption on the Skin, Sleeplessness, Tremor, Vertigo, Ulcers, Cancers, Contused Wounds, Gangrene, Boils, Chilblains, Whitlows, and Varicose Veins.</p><p >LONDON: <lb/> MANUFACTURED BY THE PROPRIETORS, <lb/> Nos. 9 &amp; 10, St. Bride's Avenue, Fleet Street.</p><p >M.DCCC.LIII.</p><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="pxxx7"/><head >ESSAY ON ORIENTAL MEDICINE</head><p >
“WHAT! more atrocities in the quack line? More conspiracies against the poor stomach?”Such we can easily believe to be the exclamation of the reader as he scans the heading of this paper. If he be a man in the enjoyment of robust health, we heartily hope he may long continue so; but still, we should strongly advise him to lay this by for a wintry day, and in the season of sickness he will thank his stars that he has been so wise. Perhaps he may have a sick friend—let <hi rend="italics">him</hi>, at any rate, have the benefit of these remarks, and he will have much cause for thankfulness—<hi rend="italics">because</hi> such exclamations as we have already quoted are entirely without foundation; but to prove this assertion, and to throw a light upon the matter, we will quote, for the reader's benefit, from the contents of a letter received by a friend of the proprietor, from a gentleman well known for his researches in the East, and to whose philanthropic endeavours hundreds are indebted, and thousands will yet live to be thankful. The letter is dated front Syria:—</p><quote><floatingText><body ><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="letter"><opener ><dateline><date>“<hi rend="italics">Damascus, Nov. </hi>1<hi rend="italics">st, </hi>1844.</date></dateline></opener><p >“I mentioned, in my last letter, the fact of my having some time ago forwarded a large supply of Pills and Plaisters to my friend Mr. James Hayes, of the firm of Hunter and Co., of Bangkok, in Siam, requesting him that, while himself benefiting by so inestimable a boon, he would also be so kind as to supply the Prince Chou Faa [the present king of Siam], and other friends, with a small quantity of both Pills and Plaisters. I now enclose Mr. Hayes' answer, by which you will perceive that the efficacy of the remedies has been proved beyond a doubt, even in such a remote and unhealthy corner of the world as Bangkok.</p><p >“As regards this country. I can only say, that the experiments I have tried have been attended with the most marvellous results; and such has been the <hi rend="italics">furor</hi> for the medicine, that the <hi rend="italics"><foreign xml:lang="fre">soi-disant</foreign></hi> French and Italian doctors, most of whom are in the Turkish employ, are all up in arms against me; and one idiot actually went so far as to say, that he would complain of me to the local authorities for practising without a licence—a threat I very soon silenced by recalling to his mind the ludicrous fact of his having ordered a wholesale supply of common table-salt, believing that it was some cheap but valuable medicine (from its being invoiced under its scientific name), which would just answer his ends to dose the poor natives with. So much for the learned doctors we have in the East! I would rather, under any circumstances, avail myself of the simple native physician, whose knowledge has been handed down through successive generations, from father to son, and augmented by self-taught experience in a climate to which he is familiar from his childhood. He understands the diseases peculiar to the locality; his drugs—the kindest gifts of nature to suffering humanity—are simple and pure; the mountain side furnishes him with herbs and roots, and the plains are bountiful in bulbs. You would hardly credit me
<pb xml:id="pxxx8"/>
when I tell you, that to such an extent do they carry out this knowledge, that one man, who had nothing in his appearance that indicated talent, was in possession of some mixture of herbs, by the doses of which, as administered by him, the number of times they would operate could be regulated: I had ocular demonstration of this fact; and if we come to argue such matters, what more convincing proof can we have of the skill of Oriental practitioners, than the very medicines which form the subject of this letter? and I certainly think you will be now convinced, that unless you at once take measures for bringing them before the British public, you will be guilty of a great crime.”</p></div></body></floatingText></quote><quote><floatingText><body ><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head >EXTRACT OF A LETTER FROM MR. JAMES HAYES.</head><opener ><dateline><date><hi rend="italics">Bangkok, June</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">rd</hi>, 1843.</date></dateline>
</opener><p >“Truly you have been mindful of us in our affliction. Nothing could have been more opportune than your invaluable Pills and Plaister; and heaven bless the name of the old Arab that invented them! I speak feelingly; for I have myself been materially benefited. Coughs, indigestion, and bilious fevers, were raging at Bangkok, and hundreds fell victims for want of proper treatment. Chou Faa himself was very much inconvenienced by a bad cough, which not all the skill of the resident American physician could cure or even alleviate, though he was by no means sparing of the medicines he administered. Two doses of Ali Ahmed's Pills entirely cured him; and he feels so grateful for this providential cure, that he desires me, while conveying to you his regards and compliments, to beg that you will not fail to send him a large supply, because he is desirous of distributing these excellent remedies amongst all the native doctors in Bangkok, for general use in their practice. As for myself, you know what a bilious subject I always was, and how I continually suffered from twinges of the liver-complaint. Of late this grew worse than ever. I could never put anything in my mouth till long after mid-day, and suffered martyrdom from continual nausea and sickness at the stomach. I persevered in taking the Pills as directed for one short week, and at the end of that period, I seldom awoke of a morning without a ravenous appetite; and as I continue taking them at intervals of every three weeks or so, I am getting quite hale and lusty, and may say, thank God, that I never enjoyed better health from the time that I left England. Really the inventor's name ought to be perpetuated, and himself, if he be alive, knighted or made a baronet of; at least such is my humble opinion, and Chou Faa coincides with me perfectly.”
</p></div></body></floatingText></quote><p >
Such, reader, are the testimonials of gentlemen situated far and widely apart, who had no inducement to puff up the medicine, no hopes of gain in any way—if we may except the truly philanthropic and Christian motives of endeavouring to promote the weal of all, by administering to their relief in the hour of woe. There is no better proof of the eminent skill of Oriental physicians, than the fact that they exercised their calling, with great success, in the days of the wise King Solomon, and even before that period; and that they were venerated by the people, and their profession ordered to be honoured. Look to the book of <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Ecclesiasticus</sic><corr>Ecclesiastics</corr></choice>, chap. xxxviii., and you will read these words—“Honour a physician with the honour due unto him, for the uses which ye may have of him; for the Lord hath created him. For of the Most High cometh healing; and he shall receive honour of the king. The skill of the physician shall lift up his head, and in the sight of great men he shall be in admiration.”Now these words sufficiently indicate that the first, and probably
<pb xml:id="pxxx9"/>
the greatest, physicians upon earth—those who were endowed with peculiar talents from on high—were the countrymen of the justly celebrated Hakeem Ali Ahmed Mascuieli, whose excellent remedies we are now bringing before the British public. They lived in the same land, visited patients afflicted with the same maladies, and effected cures with the self-same simple and harmless remedies—viz., the roots and bulbs of the earth. But you ask, “What proof have we of this?” Our answer is, to refer you to the same chapter as the quotation is taken from which we have cited above: read on, and you come to these remarkable words: “The Lord hath created medicines out of the earth, and he that is wise will not abhor them.” Now what have we out of the earth that is suited for medicinal purposes, save the roots and leaves of shrubs, and bulbous matters? “With such doth he heal [men], and taketh away their pains; of such doth the apothecary make a confection.”</p><p >
Before proceeding further, perhaps we may be allowed to give a sketch of the life of the beneficent and kind man whose medicines we are about to describe, extracted from the well-known work of Abulfeda, entitled,<foreign xml:lang="ara"><hi rend="italics">Tarikhi Abi-l Feda. </hi></foreign>
</p><p >“Ali Ahmed Mascuieli was of a noble Persian descent; but owing to political disturbances, he was compelled, at an early age, to migrate from his native country; and after wandering about the desert for many years, he eventually fixed his home at the celebrated city of Aleppo, the capital of all Northern Syria. Possessed of wonderful natural talents, which had been well developed by education and intense study, this wonderful and inventive genius planned and executed, in that dark age, most of the surgical instruments which have now descended, as priceless boons, to other nations. His works are well known to students of Oriental literature. The first book published by the noble doctor was styled, <foreign xml:lang="ara">‘THE BOOK OF THE GREAT VICTORY’</foreign>—an excellent title, we must all admit, considering the fact of suffering humanity, through its instrumentality and the skill of the surgeon, being at once relieved from temporary anguish, which in the main so detracts from the blessings of a life of peace and health—and which in many instances would, beyond a doubt, terminate fatally, but for the interposition of surgical skill. The planner of this skill may well proclaim to the world <hi rend="italics">a great victory achieved</hi>. His other works were of a like nature; and they evince one benign object, one aspect, throughout—and that is, the relief of suffering. But perhaps the greatest victory achieved—a universal boon—was
<pb xml:id="pxxx10"/>
the depth of Ali Ahmed's researches into the vegetable kingdom, and which he fully developed in his great work entitled—<foreign xml:lang="ara"><hi rend="italics">Kitabi Tarkib al-bajat min al Ta'mat.</hi></foreign>
</p><p >“These researches were crowned with every imaginable success, and the invaluable remedies became a heirloom—that in simple vegetable productions of the earth, the Almighty had showered upon his creatures the simplest and yet the surest remedies against almost every evil to which their own negligence of the blessings of health almost invariably exposes them. He also published a work on the composition of medicine from vegetable matter—a work replete with erudite information; but which, with the exception of perhaps the MS. in the possession of his descendants, were all destroyed and burnt by order of one of the most tyrannical and ignorant Caliphs of the time, who, acting upon the suggestion of a favourite quack physician, occasioned this outrage to the laws of humanity.</p><p >“Ali Ahmed Mascuieli flourished between the years of the He rah 420-488.”</p><p >The most eminent physicians in Europe have now found out the error of administering violent remedies. Look at the thousands whose constitutions have been entirely shattered by the use of calomel and mercury. Look at such violent remedies as strychnine and morphine, and a whole catalogue of poisonous decoctions, which are so frequently resorted to. Why, if these were requisite for the health of mankind, or for the cure of diseases, then India, Syria, Egypt, Turkey, and the whole of Africa, would be depopulated, or at best be inhabited by a wretched sickly race, to whom death would prove a blessing, as putting a stop to their misery. But is this the case? No: the self-same authority whose letter we first quoted, in speaking of the Syrians, says—“I have invariably remarked, in my travels through the East that in those parts of the country  where the quackeries of European doctors have not as yet reached, the people <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>enoyed</sic><corr>enjoyed</corr></choice> almost uninterrupted health; any slight indisposition was speedily cured by an early application to the Hakeem of the village. He boiled marshmallows for some, bulbs for others—made tea from the leaves of plants for a third, and so on—almost in every instance effecting a speedy cure.”</p><p >When Hakeem Ali Ahmed was on his death-bed, he confided the invaluable secret of these compositions to his near relatives, in whose hands they have continued till within the last few years, until their astounding effects were observed by an excellent and philanthropic Englishman. Anxious that his countrymen should
<pb xml:id="pxxx11"/>
be benefited by so invaluable a discovery, the gentleman in question urged upon some friends in England the duty of introducing the remedies at home—supplying them, at the same time, with samples of the various vegetable substances which constitute the different medicines, as well as a minute detail of those countries in the East from which a supply might annually be obtained; and the present proprietors have in their constant employ accredited agents, who travel from the banks of the Jordan, in the South of Palestine, as far as the wilds and plains of Cilicia and Asia Minor, in search of the requisite bulbs and vegetables.</p><p >The medicines consist of different qualities of Pills, equally possessed of intrinsic virtue for the cure of that class of maladies which is specified under their particular heads—and of one healing Plaister of such excellence, as to have already obtained for itself the encomiums and approbation of the most efficient medical practitioners in this vast metropolis.</p><p >Of the Pills, let us first treat of the qualities and use of the Sphairopeptic or Antibilious Pill, known amongst the Arabs, from its peculiar excellence, as                <foreign xml:lang="ara"><hi rend="italics">Haboobul Murarati</hi></foreign> or “The Pill of the Essence of Health”—so mild in its component parts, yet so efficacious in its results, that it may at all hours, and at all stages of a complaint, be administered to both sexes of all ages, and with equally beneficial effects to the female far advanced in pregnancy, as to the tender infant. Let us call your attention, reader, to this particular remedy. What man amongst us is so fortunate as to escape, during his pilgrimage through life, a headache for instance, acidity on the stomach, giddiness, palpitation of the heart, constipation, flatulency, diarrhœa, noises of the head and ears, eruption on the skin, sleeplessness, tremor, vertigo—in short, the thousand and one ailments resulting either from undue secretion of bile, or from some derangement of the bilious system? To this man we say, Try our Pills; give them one fair trial—and if they fail, then blazon us forth to the world as worse than charlatans. But we know too well the ground we stand upon, to fear challenging such an alternative; and we know well the result—viz., that those who give us one fair trial, will ever afterwards consider it a duty incumbent on them to herald forth their fame.</p><p >No. 2. The Pectoral Antiphthisis, or the Cough Pill, known amongst the Arabs as <foreign xml:lang="ara"><hi rend="italics">Haboobu'l Salati.</hi></foreign> It would be superfluous here to enter into any detailed encomiums of a medicine which must ever be, especially in this country,
<pb xml:id="pxxx12"/>
the safeguard of health to all classes and all ages of either sex. When does winter arrive unaccompanied by colds, catarrhs, bronchitis, asthma, quinsey, rheumatic affections of the face and head, and countless other ills—all more or less connected with that irritation which gives birth to coughs, simple and aggravated? Even in so genial a climate as Syria, where the winter can barely be said to exceed in cold our vernal equinox, the natives are not exempt from those multifarious ills to which all flesh is heir. But now they no longer fear the fatal termination of a simple cough into a fearful malady settling upon the lungs—  such as sweeps thousands of our fairest and most promising youth away annually just as they are entering upon the threshold of life; they have a remedy in Hakeem Ali Ahmed's Cough Pills, and run and buy them on the slightest indication of any indisposition, brought about by coughs and colds. So well is this known to be the case, that in Antab and all the cities about Aleppo, it has become a proverb to say, that a man “runs as though he were running for the celebrated Cough Pills.“They say :
<q type="verse"><foreign xml:lang="ara"><figure/>
</foreign></q>
which may be translated thus :—
<q type="verse"><lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">“Men of all ages, four-score years or nigh,</l><l part="N">
Run to the mart, old Ali Ahmed's Pills to buy.”</l></lg></q>
</p><p >These Pills are also tasteless, being silvered over, their pearl-like appearance destroys the nauseous idea of medicine, and they possess the golden qualities of soothing and regulating the functions of the stomach, without ever leaving behind any deleterious effects; and then their cheapness is such as to place them within the reach of every one. A few short years, and the deadly catalogue of consumptive patients will be greatly diminished—the hacking cough will no longer find an echo in the halls of the hospital; and this and other grand revolutions will, we are convinced, be brought about by these boons, conferred upon a nation through the perseverance and skill of a descendant of the Patriarchs, who himself a Patriarch in years and honors, was gathered to his fathers, not before pouring out upon suffering humanity, from the deep fountain of his benevolence, a blessing which, like the dew of Hermon, is exceeding rich, and comprehensive indeed.</p><p >
<pb xml:id="pxxx13"/>
We now come to the ANTISEPTIC MALAGMA. The qualities of this Plaister are two-fold—drawing and healing; but this has been already extensively used in our hospitals, and the best proof we can give of its excellence will be the certificates furnished by the various medical practitioners in London, who have been so fortunate as to make use of it in cases where barely any other remedy, and certainly no nostrum, could have succeeded.</p><p >One word more, and we have done. To shew the superiority of Eastern remedies over those practised in England, we shall simply quote the instance of Mahomed's Shampooing Baths at Brighton. People are supposed to go to Brighton for seabathing, whereas they invariably frequent the shampooing baths, finding greater benefit result from their use.</p><p >To persons curious in such matters, the proprietors have to announce, that they have secured a cast from a very old bust of the celebrated and good man, whose life they have described; and a highly gifted artist has been employed, whose magic touch has re-produced a living resemblance of Ali Ahmed, which may be seen at the depôt.</p><p >The Sphairopeptic or Antibilious Pill. This is a purely vegetable compound, constituting an agreeable medicine, and an effectual remedy in cases of Indigestion, and Bilious and Liver Complaints. No medicine has ever been found more efficacious in the cure of Hepatitis, or Inflammation of the Liver, than this Pill. It is equally efficacious in all disorders arising from the digestive organs—sickness, swimming in the head, constipation, flatulency, diarrhœa, palpitation of the heart, spasms, and nervous debility of every kind.</p><p >The Pectoral Antiphthisis or Cough Pill. An infallible remedy for Coughs, Asthma, Incipient Consumption, and every other Disease of the Lungs. This medicine never causes that nausea invariably connected with cough medicines where ipecacuanha and other baneful drugs are commonly used.</p><p >The Antiseptic Malagma. A most invaluable Plaister, for the cure of Ulcers, Cancers, Contused Wounds, Gangrene, Varicose Veins, Whitlows, Boils, Chilblains, etc.</p><p >
<hi rend="italics">These</hi> TREASURES OF THE DESERT <hi rend="italics">are to be had in Boxes at</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>, <hi rend="italics">silver-gilt in the Oriental style, by which any disagreeable taste is removed; at the Depot. 9 &amp; 10, St. Bride's Avenue, and of most respectable Medicine Venders.</hi>
</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx14"/><head >NEW GEOGRAPHICAL AND EDUCATIONAL WORKS,</head><p > Published by W. and A. K. JOHNSTON, <lb/><hi rend="italics">Geographers and Engravers to the Queen,</hi>
<lb/> 4 ST. ANDREW SQUARE, EDINBURGH.</p><p >Agents by Appointment for the Sale of the Ordnance Maps and Admiralty Charts.</p><p >W. and A. K. JOHNSTON beg to apprise Teachers that the Lists recently issued by the Committee of Council on Education do not contain more than one half of their Maps and Atlases—these Lists having been made up four years ago, since which time many of their most valuable works have been projected.</p><p >As the progress of Geographical knowledge requires the constant production of new works, they intend in future to issue to Teachers periodical lists of their publications.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Annexed is a complete List of their Works to January,</hi> 1853.</p><p >JOHNSTONS' COLLEGE AND SCHOOL-ROOM MAPS.</p><p >Set of Maps in Case.</p><p >The CASE for hanging on a wall contains 10 Coloured Maps on Cloth and Rollers, and is so constructed that any Map can be drawn down as required, and pulled up again by the Cords at the side.</p><p >LIST OF THE MAPS.</p><p >E. Hemisphere, W. Hemisphere, Europe, Asia, Africa, America, England, Scotland, Ireland, and Palestine.</p><p >The Maps measure 4 feet 2 inches by 3 feet 6 inches. The Case is 4 feet 8 inches long by 1 foot 9 inches high; and as it is only 4 inches thick, it projects very little from the wall: it can be packed in matting, and sent with safety to any part of the country.</p><p >Price of the 10 Maps and Painted Case, 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Single Maps in sheets, Coloured, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each; on Cloth and Rollers, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each; Varnished, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Johnstons' Second Series of School Maps, <lb/> Uniform with the above, consists of France, Spain, Central Europe, Italy, India, and Chart of the World. Size, 4 feet 2 inches by 3 feet 6 inches. Price in sheets, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, coloured; on cloth and rollers, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each; varnished, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Johnstons' School Classical Maps, <lb/> Uniform with the above, comprise <foreign xml:lang="lat">Orbis Veteribus notus, Italia Antiqua, Græcia Antiqua</foreign>, Asia Minor, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">Orbis Romanus</foreign>. Size, 4 feet 2 inches by 3 feet 6 inches. Price in sheets, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each; on cloth and rollers, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each; varnished, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Johnstons' School Physical Chart of the World, <lb/> Shewing the Great Mountain Ranges, Currents of the Air and Ocean, and Lines of Equal Heat and Cold. This Map is the First of a Series on Physical Geography. Size, 4 feet 2 inches by 3 feet 6 inches. Price in sheets, 8<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> on cloth and rollers, 10<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> varnished, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The above Maps and Illustrations have the approval of the Committee of Council on Education, and are extensively purchased by Government for distribution in England and the Colonies; they are also used in the Normal Schools of the Establishment and Free Church, in Scotland.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx15"/><head >JOHNSTONS' SCHOOL AND FAMILY MAPS.</head><p >EAST HEMISPHERE, WEST HEMISPHERE, EUROPE, ASIA, AFRICA, AMERICA, ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, IRELAND, and PALESTINE. Size, 33 by 27 inches.</p><p >The above 10 Maps, mounted. In <hi rend="italics">Case,</hi> (see preceding page,) the 10 Maps cost 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Size of the Case, 3 feet 3 inches by 1 foot 6 inches.</p><p >Single Maps, coloured, in sheets, 3<hi rend="italics">s.:</hi> on Cloth and Rollers, 5<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Varnished, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Uniform with the above in size and price,—I. A CHART OF THE WORLD. II. A MAP ILLUSTRATIVE OF GEOGRAPHICAL TERMS, with Glossary, by J. R. JACKSON, F.R.S., &amp;c.</p><p >Johnstons' Illustrations of Natural Philosophy.</p><p >SHEET No. 2, MECHANICAL POWERS, 47 DIAGRAMS.</p><p >SHEET No. 1, <lb/> PROPERTIES <lb/> OF BODIES, <lb/> 37 DIAGRAMS.</p><p >SHEET No. 3, <lb/> HYDROSTATICS, <lb/> 28 DIAGRAMS.</p><p >The Illustrations of Natural Philosophy are carefully drawn and coloured after nature, and the series in preparation will include all the most interesting Phenomena of general Science. Each sheet is accompanied by a Hand-book explanatory of the subject. Price, including Hand-book, mounted on Cloth and Roller, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> plain, or 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> varnished, each. Size of each sheet, 4 ft. 2 in. by 3 ft. 6 in.</p><p >Johnstons' Chart of the World on Mercator's Projection.</p><p >Size, 6 feet by 4 feet 8 inches. Price on roller, varnished, or in quarto morocco Case, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >
<table><head>SCHOOL ATLASES.</head><row><cell> Keith Johnston's School Atlas of General Geography, 22 Maps, half-bound, beautifully colrd. </cell><cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Keith Johnston's School Physical Atlas, 18 Maps </cell><cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Keith Johnston's School Atlas of Classical Geography, 20 Maps, half-bound, (nearly ready) </cell><cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Keith Johnston's Elementary Atlas of General Geography 20 Maps </cell><cell> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Eight Geographical Projections, on black boards, for Drawing Maps with coloured chalks </cell><cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Preparing for publication, uniform with the above,</p><p >A School Atlas of Scripture Geography.</p><p >THE USUAL DISCOUNT TO TEACHERS.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Opinions of the Press Regarding School Atlases.</hi></p><p >“I have taught Geography more or less in the High School and University of Edinburgh for the last forty years, and I have no hesitation in saying that I look upon the publication of Mr. Keith Johnston's <hi rend="italics">General and Physical School Atlases</hi> as the greatest boon that has been conferred, in my time, on a branch of knowledge and of public instruction which is becoming every day more important and more popular.”—JAMES PILLANS, Esq., <hi rend="italics">Professor of Humanity in the University of Edinburgh.</hi></p><p >“The rector and my other colleagues unite with me in hereby tendering to you our best thanks for your handsome present. We desire also to assure you that we, after a careful examination of the two publications, have no hesitation in pronouncing them, in point of beauty, accuracy, and cheapness, superior to any other thing of the kind which we have yet seen; and we conceive that teachers owe you a heavy debt of gratitude for this admirable contribution to the means at present in use for facilitating, in their hands, the acquisition to their pupils of two highly important branches of knowledge—‘General’ and ‘Physical’ Geography.”—(Signed) JNO. MACMILLAN, <hi rend="italics">Librarian. The Rector and Masters of the High School, Edinburgh.</hi></p><p >These two publications are important contributions to educational literature—distinguished for new matter, as well as for a better mode of presenting the old to the eye, and for facilitating reference, which in maps is all in all—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p><p >(<hi rend="italics">Physical Atlas</hi>)—Mr. Johnston, whose labours in this department of science have won him great renown, has, by the publication before us, done much to facilitate and encourage the study of physical geography. . . . Nothing could be better calculated to illustrate the various elementary treatises on physical geography which have lately appeared. (<hi rend="italics">General Atlas</hi>)—The Maps composing this School Atlas are distinguished by several points of superiority over those generally used in schools. . . . The whole work is adapted to the present state of geographical knowledge.—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p><closer >AGENTS IN LONDON:</closer><closer >SAUNDERS AND STANFORD, CHARING CROSS; R. THEOBALD,</closer><closer >PATERNOSTER ROW; C. H. LAW, FLEET STREET.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx16"/><opener >12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> NEW SILVER ELECTRO-PLATE, </head><p > Possessing in a pre-eminent degree the qualities of Sterling Silver, <lb/> from which it cannot be distinguished; at a fifth of the cost.</p><p >
<table><head>SPOONS AND FORKS.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Fiddle </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Threaded. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> King's. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Table Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Table Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Tea Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gravy Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Sauce Ladles </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Soup Ladles </cell><cell> each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Salt Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Superb Epergnes, Candelabra, Salad Stands, Wine Coolers, Waiters, Corner Dishes, Meat and Venison Dishes, Dish Covers, Cruet Frames, Liqueur Stands, Spoons and Forks, Tea and Coffee Services, Tea Kettles, Toast Racks, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLETS OF PRICES GRATIS.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx17"/><opener >Manufactory, 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON.<lb/>
English Watches that may be relied upon for <lb/> Accuracy and Durability.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> English Patent Levers in Gold Cases and <lb/> Gold Dial. Ten Guineas.</head><p >In order to assimilate as nearly as possible the cost of his best English Watches to the price of Foreign, over which they possess an immeasurable superiority in the grand requirements of correct performance and durability, W. MOTT has made a considerable reduction in the scale of prices, at the same time maintaining the high character by which, for so many years, they have been distinguished.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> GOLD CASES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, double back and gold dial </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, with engraved back </cell><cell> 11 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, full size, highly finished </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, engraved back </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, enamel dial </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial engraved back </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, very flat construction </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> SILVER CASES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, double back, jewelled </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, to go while winding </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, very flat construction </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, Hunting cases </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><closer >WATCHES REPAIRED, AND ONE LENT GRATIS DURING THE TIME, <lb/> AT THE <lb/> MANUFACTORY, <lb/> No. 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, <lb/> CORNER OF FRIDAY STREET.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx18"/><head >WATERLOW'S <lb/> PATENT IMPROVED AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, </head><p > OR PORTABLE <lb/> PRINTING MACHINE, <lb/> FOR THE COUNTING-HOUSE, OFFICE, OR LIBRARY, <lb/> BY MEANS OF WHICH <lb/> EVERY PERSON MAY BECOME HIS OWN PRINTER.</p><p >The process is simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing, piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.</p><p >Many hundreds of these Presses have now been sold, and are being successfully used by Railway and Public Companies, Bankers, Merchants, Amateurs, &amp;c., &amp;c.; also in Public and Private Schools, for the production of Lessons in Music, Drawing, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >The Press may be seen at work at the Patentees,’ and specimens of its production will be forwarded free, upon application.</p><p >
<table><head>PRICES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> On Mahogany Stand. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 11 × 9 </cell><cell> £7 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 16½ × 10½ </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 18 × 13½ </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >PATENT AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS FOR TRAVELLERS, <lb/> WHICH FROM ITS COMPACT FORM IS RECOMMENDED FOR USE ON <lb/> VOYAGES AND FOREIGN MISSIONS.</p><p >To Print a Subject 11 × 9 Price complete £9 9 0.</p><p >PATENTEES—WATERLOW AND SONS, 65 TO 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</p><p >From the City Article of “The Times.”</p><p >A very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, which will be productive of great convenience to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared paper, with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a piece of stone, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly valuable.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx19"/><head >PATENT LETTER COPYING PRESSES.</head><p >Lever Press.</p><p >Screw Press.</p><p >First Quality <lb/> Screw Press.</p><p >Wrought Iron Beam <lb/> Screw Press.</p><p >These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press, wrt. iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell></row><row><cell> Large 4to </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 11s. </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12s. </cell></row><row><cell> Post Folio </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MAHOGANY STANDS FOR COPYING PRESSES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Quarto. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Foolscap. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Folio. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 2 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 2 </cell><cell> drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 </cell><cell> drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>COPYING BOOKS, OF BLUE OR CREAM-WOVE COPYING PAPER, OF FIRST QUALITY, TYPE-PAGED BY STEAM POWER.</head><row><cell> QUARTER BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell><cell> HALF BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell></row><row><cell> 500 LEAVES </cell><cell> 8s. </cell><cell> 84s. </cell><cell> 500 LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 102s. </cell></row><row><cell> 750 LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 105s. </cell><cell> 750 LEAVES </cell><cell> 13s. </cell><cell> 138s. </cell></row><row><cell> 1000 LEAVES </cell><cell> 12s. </cell><cell> 126s. </cell><cell> 1000 LEAVES </cell><cell> 15s. </cell><cell> 156s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink, <lb/> FOR COPYING LETTERS.</p><p >The only <hi rend="italics">really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="italics">used</hi> in many of the <hi rend="italics">Principal Establishments in London,</hi> <lb/> and is universally admitted the best yet produced.</p><p >Per PINT, 2s. Per QUART, 3s. Per DOZEN QUARTS, 30s. Per GALLON, 10s.</p><p >Per HALF-GALLON, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per GALLON, do., do., 12s.</p><p >
<table><head>STATIONERY CASES, OF POLISHED MAHOGANY OR OAK.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> No. 1, with secret drawer, lock, and key, &amp;c., to hold foolscap and letter papers, envelopes, wax, &amp;c., and fitted with pen-tray and inkstand </cell><cell> 35 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> No. 2, for large letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c. </cell><cell> 24 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> No. 3, for small letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c. </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Sufficient paper, envelopes, &amp;c., to fill the above cases, of the best quality, would be respectively about 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >These Stationery Cases are admirably adapted for presents.</p><closer >WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65 to 68, London Wall, London.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="p1b"/><head >IMPORTANT FAMILY MEDICINE.</head><head >NORTON'S CAMOMILE PILLS, <lb/> THE <lb/> MOST CERTAIN PRESERVER OF HEALTH; <lb/> A MILD, YET SPEEDY, SAFE, AND <lb/> EFFECTUAL AID IN CASES OF INDIGESTION, <lb/> AND ALL STOMACH COMPLAINTS, <lb/> AND, AS A NATURAL CONSEQUENCE, <lb/> A PURIFIER OF THE BLOOD, AND A SWEETENER OF THE WHOLE SYSTEM.</head><p >INDIGESTION is a weakness or want of power of the digestive juices in the stomach to convert what we eat and drink into healthy matter, for the proper nourishment of the whole system. It is caused by every thing which weakens the system in general, or the stomach in particular. From it proceed nearly all the diseases to which we are liable; for it is very certain, that if we could always keep the stomach right we should only die by old age or accident. Indigestion produces a great variety of unpleasant sensations: amongst the most prominent of its miserable effects are a want of, or an inordinate, appetite, sometimes attended with a constant craving for drink, a distension or feeling of enlargement of the stomach, flatulency, heartburn, pains in the stomach, acidity, unpleasant taste in the mouth, perhaps sickness, rumbling noise in the bowels: in some cases of depraved digestion there is nearly a complete disrelish for food, but still the appetite is not greatly impaired, as at the stated period of meals persons so afflicted can eat heartily, although without much gratification; a long train of nervous symptoms are also frequent attendants, general debility, great languidness, and incapacity for exertion. The minds of persons so afflicted frequently become irritable and desponding, and great anxiety is observable in the countenance; they appear thoughtful, melancholy, and dejected, under great apprehension of some imaginary danger, will start at any unexpected noise or occurrence, and become so agitated that they require some time to calm and collect themselves; yet for all this the mind is exhilarated without much difficulty; pleasing events, society, will for a time dissipate all appearance of disease but the excitement produced by an agreeable change vanishes soon after the cause has gone by. Other symptoms are, violent palpitations, restlessness, the sleep disturbed by frightful dreams and startings, and affording little or no refreshment: occasionally there is much moaning, with a sense of weight and oppression upon the chest, nightmare, &amp;c.</p><p >It is almost impossible to enumerate all the symptoms of this first invader upon the constitution, as in a hundred cases of <hi rend="italics">Indigestion</hi> there will probably be something peculiar to each; but, be they what they may, they are all occasioned by the food becoming a burden rather than a support to the stomach; and in all its stages the medicine most wanted is that which will afford speedy and effectual assistance to the digestive organs, and give energy to the nervous and muscular systems,—nothing can more speedily or with more certainty effect so desirable an object than <hi rend="italics">Norton's Extract of Camomile Flowers.</hi> The herb has from time immemorial been highly esteemed in England as a grateful anodyne, imparting an aromatic bitter to the taste, and a pleasing degree of warmth and strength to the stomach; and in all cases of indigestion, gout in the stomach, windy colic, and general weakness, it has for ages been strongly recommended by the most eminent practitioners as very useful and beneficial. The great, indeed only, objection to its use has been the large quantity of water which it takes to dissolve a small part of the flowers, and which must be taken with it into the
<pb xml:id="p2b"/> 
stomach. It requires a quarter of a pint of boiling water to dissolve the soluble portion or one drachm of camomile flowers; and, when one or even two ounces may be taken with advantage, it must at once be seen how impossible it is to take a proper dose of this wholesome herb in the form of tea; and the only reason why it has not long since been placed the very first in rank of all restorative medicines is that in taking it the stomach has always been loaded with water, which tends in a great measure to counteract, and very frequently wholly to destroy the effect. It must be evident that loading a weak stomach with a large quantity of water, merely for the purpose of conveying into it a small quantity of medicine must be injurious; and that the medicines must possess powerful renovating properties only to counteract the bad effects likely to be produced by the water. Generally speaking, this has been the case with camomile flowers, a herb possessing the highest restorative qualities, and when properly taken, decidedly the most speedy restorer, and the most certain preserver of health.</p><p >These PILLS are wholly CAMOMILE, prepared by a peculiar process, accidentally discovered, and known only to the proprietor, and which he firmly believes to be one of the most valuable modern discoveries in medicine, by which all the essential and extractive matter of more than an ounce of the flowers is concentrated in four moderate-sized pills. Experience has afforded the most ample proof that they possess all the fine aromatic and stomachic properties for which the herb has been esteemed; and, as they are taken into the stomach unencumbered by any diluting or indigestible substance, in the same degree has their benefit been more immediate and decided. Mild in their operation and pleasant in their effect, they may be taken at any age, and under any circumstance, without danger or inconvenience. A person exposed to cold and wet a whole day or night could not possibly receive any injury from taking them, but, on the contrary, they would effectually prevent a cold being taken. After a long acquaintance with and strict observance of the medicinal properties of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> it is only doing them justice to say, that they are really the most valuable of all TONIC MEDICINES. By the word tonic is meant a medicine which gives strength to the stomach sufficient to digest in proper quantities all wholesome food, which increases the power of every nerve and muscle of the human body, or, in other words, invigorates the nervous and muscular systems. The solidity or firmness of the whole tissue of the body which so quickly follows the use of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> their certain and speedy effects in repairing the partial dilapidations from time or intemperance, and their lasting salutary influence on the whole frame, is most convincing, that in the smallest compass is contained the largest quantity of the tonic principle, of so peculiar a nature as to pervade the whole system, through which it diffuses health and strength sufficient to resist the formation of disease, and also to fortify the constitution against contagion; as such, their general use is strongly recommended as a preventative during the prevalence of malignant fever or other infectious diseases, and to persons attending sick rooms they are invaluable as in no one instance have they ever failed in preventing the taking of illness, even under the most trying circumstances.</p><p >As <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills</hi> are particularly recommended for all stomach complaints or indigestion, it will probably be expected that some advice should be given respecting diet, though after all that has been written upon the subject, after the publication of volume upon volume, after the country has, as it were, been inundated with practical essays on diet, as a means of prolonging life, it would be unnecessary to say more, did we not feel it our duty to make the humble endeavour of inducing the public to regard them not, but to adopt that course which is dictated by nature, by reason, and by common sense. Those persons who study the wholesomes, and are governed by the opinions of writers on diet, are uniformly both unhealthy in body and weak in mind. There can be no doubt that the palate is designed to inform us what is proper for the stomach, and of course that must best instruct us what food to take and what to avoid: we want no other adviser. Nothing can be more clear than that those articles which are agreeable to the taste were by nature intended for our food and sustenance, whether liquid or solid, foreign or of native production: if they are pure and unadulterated, no harm need be dreaded by their
<pb xml:id="p3a"/>
use; they will only injure by abuse. Consequently, whatever the palate approves, eat and drink always in moderation, but never in excess; keeping in mind that the first process of digestion is performed in the mouth, the second in the stomach; and that, in order that the stomach may be able to do its work properly, it is requisite the first process should be well performed; this consists in masticating or chewing the solid food, so as to break down and separate the fibres and small substances of meat and vegetables, mixing them well, and blending the whole together before they are swallowed; and it is particularly urged upon all to take plenty of time to their meals and never cat in haste. If you conform to this short and simple, but comprehensive advice, and find that there are various things which others eat and drink with pleasure and without inconvenience, and which would be pleasant to yourself only that they disagree, you may at once conclude that the fault is in the stomach, that it does not possess the power which it ought to do, that it wants assistance, and the sooner that assistance is afforded the better. A very short trial of this medicine will best prove how soon it will put the stomach in a condition to perform with case all the work which nature intended for it. By its use you will soon be able to enjoy, in moderation, whatever is agreeable to the taste, and unable to name one individual article of food which disagrees with or sits unpleasantly on the stomach. Never forget that a small meal well digested affords more nourishment to the system than a large one, even of the same food, when digested imperfectly. Let the dish be ever so delicious, ever so enticing a variety offered, the bottle ever so enchanting, never forget that temperance tends to preserve health, and that health is the soul of enjoyment. But should an impropriety be at any time, or ever so often, committed, by which the stomach becomes overloaded or disordered, render it immediate aid by taking a dose of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> which will so promptly assist in carrying off the burden thus imposed upon it that all will soon be right again.</p><p >It is most certainly true that every person in his lifetime consumes a quantity of noxious matter, which if taken at one meal would be fatal; it is these small quantities of noxious matter, which are introduced into our food, either by accident or wilful adulteration, which we find so often upset the stomach, and not unfrequently lay the foundation of illness, and perhaps final ruination to health. To preserve the constitution, it should be our constant care, if possible, to counteract the effect of these small quantities of unwholesome matter; and whenever, in that way, an enemy to the constitution finds its way into the stomach, a friend should be immediately sent after it, which would prevent its mischievous effects, and expel it altogether; no better friend can be found, nor one which will perform the task with greater certainty, than NORTON'S CAMOMILE PILLS. And let it be observed that the longer this medicine is taken the less it will be wanted; it can in no case become habitual, as its entire action is to give energy and force to the stomach, which is the spring of life, the source from which the whole frame draws its succour and support. After an excess of eating or drinking, and upon every occasion of the general health being at all disturbed, these PILLS should be immediately taken, as they will stop and eradicate disease at its commencement. Indeed it is most confidently asserted, that by the timely use of this medicine only, and a common degree of caution, any person may enjoy all the comforts within his reach, may pass through life without an illness, and with the certainty of attaining a healthy OLD AGE.</p><p >On account of their volatile properties, they must be kept in bottles; and if closely corked their qualities are neither impaired by time nor injured by any change of climate whatever. Price 13½d. and 2s. 9d. each, with full directions. The large bottle contains the quantity of three small ones, or PILLS equal to fourteen ounces of CAMOMILE FLOWERS.</p><p >Sold by nearly all respectable Medicine Vendors.</p><p >Be particular to ask for “NORTON'S PILLS,” and <lb/> do not be persuaded to purchase an imitation.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx20"/><head >A CURE FOR GOUT AND RHEUMATISM.</head><p >“<hi rend="italics">The Eighth Plague,</hi>” said the learned Dr. Johnson, <hi rend="italics">“is the Gout, and that man who discovers a Medicine to alleviate its torments deserves well of his country; but he who can effect a cure should have a Monument raised to his memory as high as St. Paul's as wide as the Thames, and as lasting as time.”</hi></p><p >SIMCO'S GOUT AND RHEUMATIC PILLS <lb/> are sold by nearly all Medicine Vendors at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d., and</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d. per Box; the former containing doses for</hi> five <hi rend="italics">and the latter for</hi> fifteen <hi rend="italics">days;</hi> and so many individuals, who considered themselves martyrs to Gout or Rheumatism, are now ready and willing to bear testimony of the wonderful effects of Simco's Pills, that the Proprietor fearlessly challenges the whole world to produce a Medicine which at all deserves to be compared to them. There are <hi rend="italics">many</hi> instances in which persons have been completely restored to health and activity by taking SIMCO'S GOUT PILLS, who have suffered from Rheumatic Gout for several years, and had drawn on a miserable existence, having lost the use of their limbs, believing that death alone could terminate their sufferings.</p><p >Whilst taking the Pills, no particular rules or restrictions are necessary, as they are warranted not to contain any preparation of Mercury whatever; they seldom produce perspiration, purging, or sickness, but invariably improve the general health, sharpen the appetite, and facilitate digestion. Those periodically subject to Gout, Rheumatic Gout Rheumatic Fever, &amp;c., should keep these Pills by them, as by their timely use an approaching attack may always be averted, and the tendency of these complaints to attack a vital part be effectually counteracted.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >A CLEAR COMPLEXION.</head><p >GODFREY'S EXTRACT OF ELDER FLOWER <lb/> is strongly recommended for Softening, Improving, Beautifying, and Preserving the SKIN, and giving it a blooming and charming appearance; being at once a most fragrant perfume and delightful cosmetic. It will completely remove Tan, Sunburn, Redness, &amp;c.; and, by its Balsamic and Healing qualities, render the skin soft, pliable, and free from dryness, scurf, &amp;c.; clear it from every humour, pimple, or eruption; and, by continuing its use only a short time, the skin will become and continue soft and smooth, and the complexion perfectly clear and beautiful. In the process of shaving it is invaluable, as it allays the irritation and smarting pain, annihilates every pimple and all roughness, and renders the skin smooth and firm. It protects the skin from the effects of the cold winds and damp atmosphere which prevail during the winter months, and will be found beyond all praise to use as a Family Lotion on all occasions.</p><p >Sold in Bottles, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> with Directions for using it, by all Medicine Vendors and Perfumers.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >INFLUENZA, COUGHS, AND COLDS.</head><p >SIMCO'S ESSENCE OF LINSEED <lb/> is the most efficacious remedy ever discovered for the relief of persons suffering from Influenza; the first two doses generally arrest the progress of this distressing complaint, and a little perseverance completely removes it. Children's Coughs, as well as recent ones in Adults, will be removed by a few doses (frequently by the first); and Asthmatic persons, who previously had not been able to lie down in bed, have received the utmost benefit from the use of</p><p >SIMCO'S ESSENCE OF LINSEED. <lb/> Sold in Bottles at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx21"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">Now ready and may be had at every Library,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In two volumes, Price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >FRANK MERRYWEATHER;</head><p >A Novel, <lb/> BY <lb/> HENRY G. AINSLIE YOUNG, ESQ.</p><p >LONDON: T. C. NEWBY. 30, Welbeck Street, Cavendish Square.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx22"/><opener >In One Shilling Monthly Parts.
<lb/><hi rend="italics">To be Completed in Six Monthly Parts, with two</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italics">Illustrations on steel, by ASHLEY.</hi></opener><head >THE TWO WIDOWS: <lb/> OR, <lb/> MATRIMONIAL JUMBLES.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">“In power of description the author equals Dickens.”—Dispatch.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">“Worthy of Charles Dickens in his happiest moments.”—Standard.</hi></p><closer ><hi rend="italics">LONDON: T. C. NEWBY,</hi> 30, <hi rend="italics">Welbeck Street, Cavendish Square.</hi></closer><closer >Orders received by every Bookseller and Newsvender</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx23"/><head >USE MARSLAND, SON, &amp; CO'S<lb/>UNRIVALLED AND REGISTERED <lb/> GRIFFIN CROCHET COTTON.</head><p >NEW WORK!!! NOW READY!</p><p >PART 1 &amp; 2.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In Demy Quarto, (to be continued on the</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st of every month), Price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> <lb/> MARSLAND'S MANUAL, <lb/> OF <lb/> CROCHET, GUIPURE, <lb/> LACÊT AND EMBROIDERY DESIGNS.</p><p >MARSLAND, SON and Co., have been induced to publish the above work, for the purpose of supplying THE VERY BEST PATTERNS AT THE LOWEST POSSIBLE PRICE.</p><p >Each Part of their “MANUAL” will contain TWELVE NEW AND ORIGINAL DESIGNS, with NOTES and EXPLANATIONS, by Artists of acknowledged talent, PRACTICALLY acquainted with the various branches of work illustrated, and who have been engaged by them for this special purpose.</p><p >The various Designs which will appear in the above work, are secured by MARSLAND, SON, and Co., under the “Registration of Designs Act,” 5 and 6 Vict., Cap. 65.</p><p >May be had at ALL BERLIN WOOL DEALERS, THROUGHOUT THE KINGDOM, or at the <lb/> Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p><p >LONDON AGENT, EDWARD WRIGHT, 4½, LAWRENCE LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx24"/><head >USE MARSLAND, SON, AND CO.'S GRIFFIN CROCHET COTTON.</head><p >Work the ground in open, and the design in close squares. <hi rend="italics">Vide “Ladies Newspaper.”</hi> Edited by Madlle. DUFOUR, for recommendation <lb/> of Marsland, Son, and Co's. Cotton. Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p><p >Work the ground in open and the design in close squares. Vide “Ladies Newspaper.” Edited by Madlle. DUFOUR, for recommendation<lb/>
of Marsland, Son, and Co.s. Cotton. Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p><p >Crests and Centres for D'Oyley's, &amp;c.—Marsland's Crochet Thread, No.'s 16 to 24. For Antimacassar's, , &amp;c., <lb/> Nos. 10 to 16 LONDON AGENT: EDWD. WRIGHT, 4½, LAWRENCE LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx25"/><div><head >PROLOGUE TO MANY CHANGES.</head><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">SOME changes are for worse, and some for better—</l><l part="N">'Tis bad to lose your cash; but welcome is that letter</l><l part="N">In which is neatly cased a Bank of England cheque,</l><l part="N">Rightly endorsed, this better is than direful wreck</l><l part="N">Of house and fortune—friends and all.</l><l part="N">To changes pleasing more we your attention call.</l><l part="N">Changes from wet, and damp, and fog, and snow,</l><l part="N">To times when flowers peep out and rivers flow;</l><l part="N">And spirits raised by sunny, cheerful days,</l><l part="N">Make business pleasing, as it then displays</l><l part="N">Its thousand charms at Messrs. MOSES' store,</l><l part="N">Where fashions meet, and stylish DRESS implore</l><l part="N">Ladies' and gentlemen's minute inspection,</l><l part="N">Assured the goods can never meet rejection.</l><l part="N">As rich they are as courtly eyes desire:</l><l part="N">Their novel STYLES will every one inspire</l><l part="N">To purchase for themselves, or for their Heirs.</l><l part="N">As every Patron such advantage always shares,</l><l part="N">When Messrs. MOSES' SPRING and SUMMER Prices</l><l part="N">To careful calculation only once entices.</l></lg><p >THE SPRING GOODS selected from the most celebrated Manufactories in the world, are now ready for inspection at E. MOSES &amp; SON's. The new Styles of DRESS for JUVENILES and ADULTS surpass all previous displays.</p><p >EMIGRANTS are OUTFITTED by E. MOSES &amp; SON at Shipping prices. The GOODS and CLOTHING are suitable for every occupation or profession, for Ladies, Gentlemen, and Children; Cabin, Intermediate, or Steerage Passengers. SHIPSAILING information and full LISTS of OUTFITS for LADIES and GENTLEMEN may be had on application, or post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p></div><div><head >E. MOSES &amp; SON'S <lb/> SPRING AND SUMMER LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Paletots in every new material from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Lustre Coats, a variety of light and elegant textures from 12s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Albert Wrapper, a registered light material 15s. to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> New Parisian Cape, made by E. Moses &amp; Son (only) from 30s. to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Nepaulese Wrapper, weighs only 6 oz. </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Coats in the above materials and shapes at proportionably low prices. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Boys Blouses in endless variety from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 9 </cell></row><row><cell> LOUNGING AND MORNING COATS </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> In EVERY NEW STYLE. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Holland from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Tweed, Cashmere, and Orleans 8s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Lustre, Alpaca, Angola, &amp;c. 10s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Melton Mowbray, a new material, in all colours from 16s. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine Cloth of light textures, black or coloured 16s. to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Shooting Jackets in endless variety of materials 10s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Boys' Coats, as above, at proportionally low prices. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> DRESS COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Dress Coats from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Super Coats </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best quality </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Frock quality from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> WAISTCOATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Fancy Vests from 2s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Fancy Alpacas 3s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> White, for Dress 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black and Figured Satins </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Embroidered Cloth from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black and Fancy Velvets from 14S. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Every elegant Material and Style, for Balls and Weddings from 16s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> TROUSERS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Trousers in every Novel Material. Plain and Fancy from 4s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> A large assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskins 18s., 22s. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> JUVENILE ATTIRE. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Tunic Suit from 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Hussar Suits, Jacket, Vest, and Trousers 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> LADIES' RIDING HABITS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> LADIES' HABITS, WITH ⅞ TRAIN from 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Uniforms, according to present Regulations, AT THE LOWEST CHARGES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> LIVERIES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Page's suit from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Groom's </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Coachman's from 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gamekeeper's from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p > The PARASOL, MANTLE, and CHILDREN'S DRESS DEPARTMENT, is replete with every Novelty of the Season.</p><p >HATS AND Cars in every novel Style, and all Goods charged at considerably lower prices than at any other House.</p><p >The “Herald of the Seasons,” containing Facts relative to Australia, Advice for Emigrants, System of self-measurement, and full Lists of Prices, may be had on application, or post-free to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the Public against imposition, having learned that the <hi rend="italics">untradesmanlike falsehood</hi> of “being connected with their Establishment,” or “It's the same concern,” has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons. They beg to state they have NO CONNECTION WITH ANY OTHER HOUSE IN OR OUT OF LONDON, EXCEPT THEIR OWN ESTABLISHMENTS, as follows:—</p><p >London City Establishments:—154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, (opposite the Church) all communicating.</p><p >London West End Branch:—506, 507, and 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, and 3, Hart-street, all communicating.</p><p >Bradford, “Yorkshire” Branch, 19 and 20, Bridge-street.</p><p >Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p><p >IMPORTANT.—Should any article not give satisfaction, it will be exchanged, if desired, or, if preferred, the money will be returned without hesitation. All Goods are marked, in plain figures, the lowest prices, from which no abatement can be made.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Establishments close from sunset on Fridays till sunset on Saturdays, when business is resumed till</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p><closer >E. MOSES &amp; SON, <lb/> MERCHANT TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, <lb/> AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx26"/><head >HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS</head><p >AND PRICED LIST OF BEDDING, <lb/> SENT FREE BY POST, <lb/> The Catalogue contains Designs and Prices of upwards <lb/> of One Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, Mahogany, <lb/> Rosewood, and Walnut Tree Woods.</p><closer >FROM THEIR <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTORY, <lb/> 196, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, <lb/> LONDON.</closer><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer></div></back></text></TEI>