<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>Bleak House, No. XI:</emph> Electronic 
Edition.</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Ingrid Pohl</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Andrew Leiter, and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.   300 K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page Bleak House </title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>   79   p.,  ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">London:Bradbury &amp; Evans, Bouverie Street.</publisher><date>1853</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Dickens 21  c.2  (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p/></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language><language ident="fre">French</language><language ident="lat">Latin</language><language ident="spa">Spanish</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002">Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther  revised TEIHeader and created catalog record for the electronic edition.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-10"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-13">Andrew Leiter finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-02">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"> No. XI. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate>JANUARY.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docImprint>
<seg part="N">WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</seg>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
<lb/>The Author of this Work notifies that it is his intention to reserve the <lb/> right of translating it
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisements"><pb  xml:id="pxxx2"/><head >WILLIAM S. BURTON'S <lb/> GENERAL FURNISHING IRONMONGERY WAREHOUSE </head><p >39, OXFORD STREET, <lb/> (CORNER OF NEWMAN STREET); <lb/> Nos. 1 &amp; 2, Newman Street; and 4 &amp; 5, Perry's Place, London.
</p><div type="section"><head >THE BEST SHOW OF IRON BEDSTEADS in the KINGDOM is <lb/> WILLIAM S. BURTON'S.</head><p >He has added to his SHOW-ROOMS Two very large ones, which are devoted to the exclusive show of IRON and BRASS BEDSTEADS and CHILDREN'S COTS, with appropriate Bedding and Mattresses. Many of these are quite new, and all are marked in plain figures, at prices proportionate with those that have tended to make his Establishment the most distinguished in this country. Common Iron Bedsteads, 15s. 6d; Portable Folding Bedsteads, from 13s. 6d.; Patent Iron Bedsteads, fitted with dove-tail joints and patent iron sacking, from 19s. 9d.; and Cots from 21s. each. Handsome Ornamental Iron and Brass Bedsteads in great variety, from £3 5s. to £31.</p></div><div><p >LAMPS OF ALL SORTS AND PATTERNS, <lb/> The largest, as well as the choicest, Assortment in existence of PALMER'S MAGNUM and other LAMPS, CAMPHINE, ARGAND, SOLAR, and MODERATEUR LAMPS, with all the latest Improvements, and of the newest and most recherché patterns in ormulu, Bohemian, and plain glass, or papier mâché, is at WILLIAM S. BURTON'S; and they are arranged in one large room, so that patterns, sizes, and sorts can be instantly selected.</p><p >PALMER'S CANDLES, 7½d. per lb.—PALMER'S PATENT CANDLES, all marked “PALMER.”</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Single or double wicks </cell><cell> 7½d. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> Middle size, three wicks </cell><cell> 8½d. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> Magnums, three or four wicks </cell><cell> 9d. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> English's Patent Camphine, in scaled cans </cell><cell> 4s. 9d. per gallon. </cell></row><row><cell> Best French Colza Oil </cell><cell> 4s. per gallon. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div><head >The Perfect Substitute for Silver.</head><head >THE REAL NICKEL SILVER, </head><p > Introduced twenty years ago by WILLIAM S. BURTON, when plated by the patent process of Messrs. Elkington &amp; Co., is beyond all comparison the very best article next to sterling silver that can be employed as such, either usefully or ornamentally, as by no possible test can it be distinguished from real silver.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell><cell> Thread or Brunswick Pattern. </cell><cell> King's Pattern. </cell></row><row><cell> Tea Spoons, per dozen </cell><cell> 18s. </cell><cell> 23s. </cell><cell> 36s. </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Forks </cell><cell> 30s. </cell><cell> 42s. </cell><cell> 58s. </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Spoons </cell><cell> 30s. </cell><cell> 42s. </cell><cell> 62s. </cell></row><row><cell> Table Forks </cell><cell> 40s. </cell><cell> 55s. </cell><cell> 70s. </cell></row><row><cell> Table Spoons </cell><cell> 40s. </cell><cell> 55s. </cell><cell> 75s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Tea and Coffee Sets, Waiters, Candlesticks, &amp;c., at proportionate prices. All kinds of re-plating done by the patent process.</p><p >
<table><head>CHEMICALLY PURE NICKEL NOT PLATED.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Fiddle. </cell><cell> Thread. </cell><cell> King's. </cell></row><row><cell> Table Spoons and Forks, full size, per doz. </cell><cell> 12s. </cell><cell> 28s. </cell><cell> 30s. </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Spoons and Forks </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 21s. </cell><cell> 25s. </cell></row><row><cell> Tea Spoons </cell><cell> 5s. </cell><cell> 11s. </cell><cell> 12s. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div><head >WILLIAM S. BURTON <lb/> HAS TEN LARGE SHOW ROOMS </head><p >(all communicating), exclusive of the shop, devoted solely to the show of <lb/> GENERAL FURNISHING IRONMONGERY, <lb/> including Cullery, Nickel Silver, Plated, and Japanned Wares, Iron and Brass Bedsteads, so arranged and classified that purchasers may easily and at once make their selections.</p><p >Catalogues, with Engravings, sent (per post) free. The money returned for <lb/> every article not approved of.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisements"><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. XI.—JANUARY, 1853.</opener><head >BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head><opener >In the Press, to be completed in 21 Volumes 4to,</opener><head >THE EIGHTH EDITION OF THE <lb/> ENCYCLOPÆDIA BRITANNICA </head><p >EDITED BY THOMAS STEWART TRAILL, M.D., F.R.S.E., </p><p > Professor of Medical Jurisprudence in the University of Edinburgh.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">To be published in Parts, Monthly, at</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s., and in Volumes, Quarterly, at</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s., with upwards of</hi> 500 <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Engravings on Steel, and several thousands on Wood.</hi></p><p >THE FIRST VOLUME will consist of the Dissertations by DUGALD STEWART and SIR JAMES MACKINTOSH, on the Progress of Metaphysical and Ethical Philosophy: to which will be added a Preface by WM. WHEWELL, D.D., Professor of Moral Philosophy in the University of Cambridge; and by PROFESSOR PLAYFAIR and SIR JOHN LESLIE, on the Progress of Mathematical and Physical Science. To these will be added two new Dissertations, the first by the ARCHBISHOP OF DUBLIN, on the Rise, Progress, and Corruptions of Christianity; the second by JAMES D. FORBES, F.R.S., Professor of Natural Philosophy in the University of Edinburgh; being a continuation of the Dissertations on the Progress of Physical Science to the present time.</p><p >The whole work will undergo careful revision and extensive correction. Articles rendered imperfect by the lapse of time will be submitted for improvement to writers intimately conversant with the respective subjects, whilst other articles will be superseded by entirely new contributions, and subjects not formerly embraced in its pages will be added.</p><p >To secure regularity of publication, the work will be considerably advanced at press before the publication of the first part, which it is intended to issue on the 1st of March, 1853.</p><closer >ADAM AND CHARLES BLACK, EDINBURGH.</closer><closer >LONGMAN &amp; Co.; SIMPKIN &amp; Co.; HAMILTON &amp; Co.; and WHITTAKER &amp; Co., LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE LADY Of The LAKE</head><p >BY SIR WALTER SCOTT. New Edition, including all his latest Copyright Notes, Various Readings, and Additions. Exquisitely Illustrated by BIRKET FOSTER and JOHN GILBERT, uniform with the Illustrated Editions of Campbell, Rogers, Thomson, Goldsmith, and Longfellow's Poems, forming a beautiful and appropriate Gift-Book for Christmas.</p><p >The Illustrations of the Scenery are from Sketches drawn on the spot during the past Summer, by Mr. Foster, expressly for this Work, and comprise all the principal places alluded to in the Poem.</p><p >EXTRA CLOTH, GILT EDGES, 15s.; MOROCCO ELEGANT OR ANTIQUE, 21s.; MOROCCO ELEGANT, <hi rend="italics">bound by Hayday,</hi> 24s.</p><p >“Paper, type, and printing are of the highest order, and its elaborately ornamented cover is unique and most tasteful in design. Christmas books and new year gifts will soon be in request; we will venture to assert that the season will produce none worthier of a popular place among them than this edition of one of our most popular poems.”—<hi rend="italics">Art Journal,</hi> December, 1852.</p><closer >A. &amp; C. BLACK, EDINBURGH. HOULSTON &amp; STONEMAN, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><opener >NOTICE.</opener><head >RE-ISSUE OF LIVES OF THE QUEENS OF <lb/> ENGLAND.</head><docAuthor >BY AGNES STRICKLAND.</docAuthor><p >On the 1st of January, 1853, was published, the First Volume of a RE-ISSUE of this Interesting National Work, comprising the recent Important Additions, <lb/> PORTRAITS OF ALL THE QUEENS, ETC.</p><p >To be completed in 8 Monthly Volumes, Demy 8vo., handsomely bound, Price 10s. 6d. each.</p><p >“No one can be said to possess an accurate knowledge of the history of England who has not studied this truly national work.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p><p >PUBLISHED FOR HENRY COLBURN BY HIS SUCCESSORS, HURST &amp; BLACKETT, <lb/> 13, Great Marlborough Street. Orders received by all Booksellers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >APPROVED EDUCATIONAL WORKS FOR SCHOOLS and FAMILIES.</head><p >Twelfth Edition, price 3s. 6d., or with 30 Maps on Steel, 5s. 6d., <lb/> A SCHOOL GEOGRAPHY. By JAMES CORNWELL, Ph. D.</p><p >“We are qualified by ample trial of the books in our own classes to speak to their great efficiency and value. We have never known so much interest evinced, or so much progress made in the study of geography, as since we have employed these as our school books.”—<hi rend="italics">Educational Times.</hi></p><p >“Without exception, the best book of its class we have seen.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >Also, by the same Author, price 2s. 6d., or 4s. Coloured, <lb/> A SCHOOL ATLAS; consisting of 30 MAPS on Steel, containing every name <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>ound</sic><corr>found</corr></choice> in the School Geography, and a list of several hundred places, with their latitude and longitude, and the accentuation and pronunciation of all difficult names. The Maps of England and Scotland enlarged.</p><p >19th Edition, price 2s. Red, 1s. 9d. Cloth, <lb/> ALLEN and CORNWELL'S SCHOOL GRAMMAR; with very copious EXERCISES, and a Systematic View of the FORMATION and DERIVATION of Words, together with Anglo-Saxon, Latin, and Greek roots, which explain the Etymology of above 7000 English words.</p><p >“Written by those who are profoundly acquainted with the sources of our language, and who have brought this acquaintance to bear on its grammatical structure. This Grammar will make its way in Schools.”—<hi rend="italics">Church of England Quarterly.</hi></p><p >“A complete, well-arranged, and thoroughly scientific manual of the English language. The whole chapter on the formation and derivation of words is one of great interest, and is a valuable exposition of the modes of verbal development; to it are added ample lists of the roots of foreign words.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >20th Edition, price 1s. Cloth, 9d. Sewed, <lb/> GRAMMAR FOR BEGINNERS.</p><p >“We have never seen a more desirable elementary work.”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p><p >12th Edition, price 1s. 6d., <lb/> THE YOUNG COMPOSER; or, Progressive Exercises in English Composition. By JAMES CORNWELL, Ph. D.</p><p >“An invaluable little work for beginners. If they go through it steadily, they will not only learn how to write, but how to think.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“Dr. Cornwell has executed this work with great ability. We have seen no other of the kind so clear, so well arranged, so comprehensive, so thoroughly adapted to the practical business of tuition; or, in short, so fully entitled to be named ‘Progressive Exercises in English Composition.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">Scotsman.</hi></p><p >Also, price 3s., <lb/> A KEY TO THE YOUNG COMPOSER; with Suggestions as to the Mode of using the Book.</p><p >6th Edition, much improved, price 4s., <lb/> SELECT ENGLISH POETRY. Edited by the late Dr. ALLEN.</p><p >“We can confidently recommend it for young persons in general, as calculated to promote the cultivation of poetical taste, and an acquaintance with the different styles of many of our English poets.”—<hi rend="italics">English Journal of Education.</hi></p><p >New Edition, price 3s., Cloth, <lb/> DR. ALLEN'S EUTROPIUS; with a Complete Dictionary.</p><p >London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co.; HAMILTON, ADAMS, &amp; Co. Edinburgh: OLIVER &amp; BOYD; W. P. KENNEDY.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >APPROPRIATE LITERARY PRESENT.</head><p >Just published, tastefully bound in cloth, price 5s.</p><p >SPIRITS OF THE PAST.</p><p >AN HISTORICAL POEM, WITH COPIOUS BIOGRAPHICAL NOTES.</p><p >By NICHOLAS MICHELL, Author of “Ruins of many Lands,” &amp;c.</p><p >CONTENTS:—<hi rend="italics">Scripture Characters: Military Heroes: Celebrated Women.</hi></p><p >“He has evoked with great success the Illustrious Dead of all ages, gliding from epoch to epoch, and from character to character. The work has singular variety, fascinating grace, and thrilling power.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Michell is decidedly one of the most popular poets of the day.”—<hi rend="italics">New Monthly Magazine, Nov.</hi></p><p >“The character of Napoleon is most ably drawn.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p><p >“To delineate the history and character of the great leading spirits of ancient and modern times, was a task beset with difficulties, but he has effected his object in a manner scarcely to be expected. Indeed the truthfulness and beauty of some passages are beyond all praise—passages worthy to be ranked with the loftiest efforts of Coleridge and Wordsworth.”—<hi rend="italics">Oxford Chronicle,</hi> 23 <hi rend="italics">Oct.</hi></p><p >London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; CO., 85, Queen-street, Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><div type="section"><opener >Crown 8vo. cloth, 3s. 6d., uniform with the “Pickwick Papers,” &amp;c.,</opener><head > MR. DICKENS'S CHRISTMAS BOOKS,</head><p > Complete in One Volume; containing,</p><p >A Christmas Carol—The Chimes—The Cricket on the Hearth— </p><p >The Battle of Life—and, The Haunted Man.</p><p >WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY LEECH.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Second Edition, with Corrections and Additions, <lb/> 3 vols. 8vo, 42s., </opener><head >NIEBUHR'S LIFE AND <lb/> LETTERS.</head><p >Edited and Translated by SUSANNA WINKWORTH.</p><p >With Essays on his Character and Influence, by the Chevalier BUNSEN and Professors BRANDIS and LOEBELL.</p><p >“One of the most valuable contributions to our biographical literature which has been made in recent times.”—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >At all the Libraries, 3 vols, post 8vo.</opener><head >AGATHA'S HUSBAND.</head><p >A NOVEL.</p><p >By the Author of “OLIVE,” “THE HEAD OF THE <lb/> FAMILY,” &amp;c.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >2 vols. post 8vo, cloth, 21s.</opener><head >VILLAGE LIFE IN EGYPT.</head><p >By BAYLE ST. JOHN, <lb/> Author of “Adventures in the Libyan Desert.” “Two <lb/> Years Residence in a Levantine Family.”</p><p >“An attractive addition to the library of Eastern travel.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >2 vols. post 8vo,</opener><head >THE BLITHEDALE <lb/> ROMANCE.</head><p >By NATHANIEL HAWTHORNE, <lb/> Author of “The Scarlet Letter,” “The House of the <lb/> Seven Gables,” &amp;c.</p><p >“The ‘Blithedale Romance’ is the intellectual exercise of a true poet, of one who is eager to read whatever Nature has to teach, and who has the faculty of uttering in words the spiritual instruction derived from his royal mistress. . . . . The book is overflowing with energy and thought.”—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >n fcap. 8vo,</opener><head > READING for TRAVELLERS, <lb/><hi rend="italics">A New Library of Railway Literature.</hi></head><p >No. 1.—OLD ROADS AND NEW ROADS, 1s.</p><p >No. 2.—MAGIC AND WITCHCRAFT, 1s.</p></div><div><p >CHEAP EDITION OF THE <lb/> Works of Mr. Charles Dickens.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces by the Author.</hi></p><p >THE PICKWICK PAPERS.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by C. R. LESLIE, R. A. Cloth, 5s.</p><p >NICHOLAS NICKLEBY.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by T. WEBSTER, R.A. Cloth, 5s.</p><p >THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by GEORGE CATTERMOLE. Cloth 4s.</p><p >BARNABY RUDGE.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by H. K. BROWNE. Cloth, 4s.</p><p >MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by FRANK STONE. Cloth, 5s.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Cloth, 3s. 6d.</p><p >AMERICAN NOTES.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by CLARESON STANFIELD, R. A. Cloth, 2s. 6d.</p><p >SKETCHES BY BOZ.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Cloth, 3s. 6d.</p><p >CHRISTMAS BOOKS.</p><p >With a Frontispiece by JOHN LEECH. Cloth, 3s. 6d.</p></div><div><opener >NEW NOVEL. At all the Libraries,</opener><head >THE FORTUNES OF FRANCIS<lb/> CROFT.
</head><p >AN AUTOBIOGRAPHY.</p><p >In 3 vols. post 8vo.</p><p >“To recommend it to general perusal is at once a pleasure to the critic and a duty to the public.”—<hi rend="italics">Observer.</hi></p></div><div><opener >2 vols. post 8vo. cloth, 18s.</opener><head >THE LIFE OF BERNARD <lb/> PALISSY, OF SAINTES;</head><p >His Labours and Discoveries in Art and Science, with an Outline of his Philosophical Doctrines, and Illustrative Selections from his Works.</p><p >By HENRY MORLEY, <lb/> Author of “How to make Home unhealthy,” &amp;c.</p><p >“A Masterly full-length of the potter in his habit as he lived—the truth and vividness of actual existence animating every line of the portrait . . . We have not been more interested by a biography for many days.”—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p></div><div><head >RUTH. BY THE AUTHOR OF “MARY BARTON,” </head><p >Is published this day, in Three Vols. post 8vo, and may be had at all the Libraries.</p></div><closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><div><head >A Christmas Tale, by FRANK FAIRLEGH, <lb/> Just published, in 1 vol., price 5s. cloth gilt, illustrated by PHIZ, entitled </head><head >THE FORTUNES OF THE COLVILLE FAMILY; 
<lb/> OR, A CLOUD AND ITS SILVER LINING. BY FRANK E. SMEDLEY,</head><p >Author of “FRANK FAIRLEGH,” “LEWIS ARUNDEL, &amp;c.</p></div><div><head >A Christmas Tale, </head><docAuthor > BY THE AUTHOR OF “THE USE OF SUNSHINE,” “THE STORY OF A FAMILY,” &amp;c.
</docAuthor><opener >Just published, in 1 vol., price 6s. cloth gilt, entitled</opener><head > NINA: A TALE FOR THE TWILIGHT,</head><p >BY S. M.</p><p >LONDON: GEORGE HOBY, 123, MOUNT STREET, BERKLEY SQUARE.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW WORKS.</head><p >HISTORY OF EUROPE, <lb/> FROM THE FALL OF NAPOLEON IN 1815 <lb/> TO THE ACCESSION OF LOUIS NAPOLEON <lb/> IN 1852.</p><p >By SIR ARCHIBALD ALISON, Bart. Vol. 1., price 15s. To be completed in 5 vols. 8vo, uniform with the LIBRARY EDITION of the “History of Europe from 1792 to 1815,” by the same Author.</p><p >NEW WORK <lb/> BY SIR E. BULWER LYTTON, BART.</p><p >MY NOVEL; <lb/> Or, VARIETIES IN ENGLISH LIFE.</p><p >By PISISTRATUS CAXTON. In 4 vols. To be <lb/> published on 1st January.</p><p >KATIE STEWART; <lb/> A TRUE STORY.</p><p >(Originally published in <hi rend="italics">Blackwood's Magazine.</hi>) In small 8vo, with Frontispiece and Vignette. Elegantly <lb/> bound in gilt cloth, price 7s. 6d.</p><p >NOTES ON PARIS AFTER <lb/> WATERLOO.</p><p >Taken at the time and hitherto unpublished. By JAMES SIMPSON, Esq., Advocate, Author of “A Visit to Flanders and the Field of Waterloo.” Including a revised edition (the tenth) of the latter work. In small 8vo.</p><p >LIFE OF MARY QUEEN <lb/> OF SCOTS.</p><p >By AGNES STRICKLAND. Being Vol. III. of the “Lives of the Queens of Scotland and English Princesses connected with the Royal <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Successon</sic><corr>Succession</corr></choice>.” To be completed in 6 volumes, post 8vo, with Portraits and Historical Vignettes. Price 10s. 6d. each.</p><p >WILLIAM BLACKWOOD &amp; SONS, Edinburgh and <lb/> London.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Orders received by all Booksellers.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >THE TOILET OF BEAUTY furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy, and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.—“ROBERT SHAW, London,” is in white letters on the government stamp, without which none is genuine. Price 2s. 9d. and 5s, 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Christmas Present or New Year's Gift.</opener><head >EDGEWORTH'S NOVELS AND TALES.</head><p >A New Edition, in 9 vols., foolscap 8vo. £2 5s. <lb/> cloth lettered.</p><p >THIS EDITION contains all that was contained in the last edition of 18 vols., and is embellished with Engravings on Steel, by Goodall, Engleheart, J. W. Cook, Rolls, and other eminent Engravers, from Paintings by Harvey.</p><p >Also, separately, <lb/> MORAL TALES; with Three Engravings. Foolscap. 5s. cloth lettered.</p><p >POPULAR TALES; with Three Engravings. Foolscap. 5s. cloth lettered.</p><p >London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co.: H. WASHBOURNE; H. G. BOHN; E. HODOSON; WHITTAKER &amp; Co.; H. RENSHAW; J. BAIN; HOULSTON &amp; STONEMAN; R. MACKIE; ORR &amp; Co.; SMITH, ELDER, &amp; Co.; ROUTLEDGE &amp; Co.; TEGG &amp; Co.; Mrs. TEMPLEMAN; and G. &amp; J. ROBINSON, Liverpool.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MISS DOLBY'S NEW SONGS.—</head><p >“The Sunshine of our Home.” Poetry by J. E. Carpenter, music by Edward Land “Mary Astore.” Irish ballad. Poetry by Mr. Crawford, music by Stephen Glover. “My Mother's Gentle Words.” Poetry by J. E. Carpenter, music by J. Henry Griesbach, each 2s. Also, by Sir Henry Bishop, “Mourn for the Mighty Dead.” Poetry by Dr. Mackay. 2s. And on application, Gratis, Robert Cook &amp; Co.'s Musical Almanac for 1853. 32mo.</p><p >London: Robert Cocks &amp; Co., New Burlington Street, Publishers to the Queen.</p><p >N.B. Cocks's Musical Miscellany on the first of every month, 16 pp. 410, price 5d., postage free, 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALBANY LAMP AND CANDLE-MANUFACTORY —</head><p > CLARKE'S Russian Wax Candles, 1s. per lb., burn superior to all others. Best Albany Composite Candles, 8d. per lb., do not require snuffing; for ordinary purposes the Cheapest Candles that can be used, Moulds, 6d., Store Candles, 5d. per lb.; Express Pale Soap, very old and dry, 545. per cwt.; Good Yellow, 50s. and 44s.; Best Mottled, 56s.; Honey Soap, 1s.; Old Brown Windsor, 2s.; all other Scented Soaps, 1s. 6d. per lb.; Patent Albany Oil, 5s. 6d. per gallon, superior to Sperm; CLARKE'S Refined Oil for French Lamps, 4s. 6d. per gallon; Solar, 3s. 6d. Italian goods of the finest quality at the Wholesale Price; Lamps of every description manufactured on the premises, for cash only.</p><p >SAMUEL CLARKE, Albany Lamp and Candle Manufactory, 55, Albany-street, Regent's-park, London, within two minutes' walk of the Colosseum.</p><p >N.B. Country Orders, amounting to £10 or upwards, Carriage Free.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><opener >13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH-STREET, JAN. 1853.
</opener><opener >MESSRS. HURST AND BLACKETT, <lb/> SUCCESSORS TO MR. COLBURN, <lb/> WILL PUBLISH DURING THE PRESENT SEASON <lb/> THE FOLLOWING NEW WORKS.</opener><head >MEMOIRS OF THE COURT AND CABINETS <lb/> OF GEORGE THE THIRD.</head><p >FROM ORIGINAL FAMILY DOCUMENTS.</p><p >BY THE DUKE OF BUCKINGHAM AND CHANDOS, K.G., &amp;<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> 2 vols. 8vo.</p><p >A TOUR OF INQUIRY THROUGH FRANCE AND ITALY, Illustrating their present Political, Social, and Religious Condition. By EDMUND SPENCER, Esq., Author of “Travels in European Turkey,” “Circassia,” &amp;c. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s. (<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi>)</p><p >MILITARY LIFE IN ALGERIA. By the Count P. de CASTELLANE. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p><p >WISE SAWS AND MODERN INSTANCES. By the Author of “SAM SLICK,” &amp;c. 3 vols. post 8vo. 31s. 6d.</p><p >TRAVELS IN INDIA AND KASHMIR. By Baron SCHONBERG. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p><p >MEMOIRS OF JOHN ABERNETHY, F.R.S. With a view of his Writings, Lectures and Character. By GEORGE MACILWAIN, F.R.C.S. 2 vols. post 8vo.</p><p >A NEW WORK. By the Author of “EMILIA WYNDHAM,” &amp;c. In 1 volume.</p><p >AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF AN ENGLISH SOLDIER IN THE UNITED STATES' ARMY. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p><p >NARRATIVE OF A FIVE YEARS' JOURNEY ROUND THE WORLD, from 1847 to 1852. By F. GERSTAUKER. 3 vols. post 8vo.</p><p >FAMILY ROMANCE; or, Episodes in the Domestic Annals of the Aristocracy. By J. B. BURKE, Esq., Author of “The Peerage,” “Anecdotes of the Aristocracy,” &amp;c. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p><p >THE FOLLOWING ARE NOW READY.</p><p >THE RIGHT HONOURABLE B. DISRAELI'S BIOGRAPHY OF LORD GEORGE BENTINCK. New and cheaper Edition, Revised. 1 vol. post 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p><p >THE BARONESS D'OBERKIRCH'S MEMOIRS, Illustrative of the Secret History of the Courts of France, Russia, and Germany. 3 vols. post 8vo. 31s. 6d.</p><p >MISS PARDOE'S LIFE OF MARIE DE MEDICIS. Second Edition. 3 vols. 8vo. With fine Portraits. 42s.</p><p >AUSTRALIA AS IT IS; its Settlements, Farms, and Gold Fields. By F. LANCELOTT, Esq., Mineralogical Surveyor in the Australian Colonies. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p><p >THE MARVELS OF SCIENCE, AND THEIR TESTIMONY TO HOLY WRIT; a Popular Manual of the Sciences. By S. W. FULLOM, Esq. Dedicated by permission to the King of Hanover. Third Edition, Revised. Post 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p><p >REVELATIONS OF SIBERIA. By a BANISHED LADY. Second Edition. 2 vols. post 8vo. 21s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >New Novels by Distinguished Writers.</head><p >THE LIEUTENANT'S STORY. By Lady CATHARINE LONG. Author of “Sir Roland Ashton.” 3 vols. (<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi>)</p><p >THE DEAN'S DAUGHTER. By Mrs. GORE. 3 vols.</p><p >HARRY MUIR. A Story of Scottish Life. By the Author of “Margaret Maitland,” “Adam Graeme,” &amp;c. 3 vols.</p><p >THE JEALOUS WIFE. By Miss PARDOE. 3 vols.</p><p >CASTLE AVON. By the Author of “Emilia Wyndham,” &amp;c. 3 vols. (<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi>)</p><p >A NEW NOVEL. By Mrs. TROLLOPE. 3 vols.</p><p >THE LONGWOODS OF THE GRANGE. By the Author of “Adelaide Lindsay.” 3 vols.</p><p >BROOMHILL; or, the County Beauties. 3 vols. (<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi>)</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >GRACE AGUILAR'S WORKS.</head><p >I. <lb/> Fourth Edition, fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece, 6s. 6d.</p><p >HOME INFLUENCE: <lb/> A Tale for Mothers and Daughters.</p><p >II. <lb/> Second Edition, fcap. 8vo, Illustrated with Portrait, 7s.</p><p >THE <lb/> MOTHER'S RECOMPENSE: <lb/> A Sequel to “Home Influence.”</p><p >III. <lb/> Second Edition, fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece, 6s. 6d., <lb/> WOMAN'S FRIENDSHIP: <lb/> A Story of Domestic Life.</p><p >IV. <lb/> Second Edition, fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece, 6s.</p><p >THE VALE OF CEDARS: <lb/> A Story of Spain in the Fifteenth Century.</p><p >V. <lb/> Fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece and Vignette, 7s. 6d., <lb/> THE DAYS OF BRUCE: <lb/> A Story from Scottish History.</p><p >VI. <lb/> In fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece, 6s. 6d., <lb/> HOME SCENES AND HEART <lb/> STUDIES.</p><p >Tales.</p><p >VII. <lb/> Second Edition, in 2 vols., fcap. 8vo, 12s., <lb/> THE WOMEN OF ISRAEL;</p><p >Or, Characters and Sketches from the Holy Scriptures, illustrative of the Past History, Present Duties, and Future Destiny of Hebrew Females, as based on the Word of God.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> MRS. CROSSLAND'S NEW DOMESTIC STORY.</p><p >In 1 vol., fcap. 8vo, price 6s., <lb/> LYDIA; A WOMAN'S BOOK.</p><p >By Mrs. NEWTON CROSLAND (late CAMILLA TOULMIN.)</p><closer >GROOMBRIDGE &amp; SONS. 5, Paternoster-row.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >JUST PUBLISHED BY</opener><head >PARTRIDGE AND OAKEY.</head><p >LANG'S EMIGRANT'S MANUAL; or, A Guide to Australia and the Gold Regions of New South Wales and Port Philip. By <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>JGHN</sic><corr>JOHN</corr></choice> DUNMORE LANG, D.D., recently one of the Members of the Legislative Council of New South Wales for the City of Sydney, and formerly a Member for Port Philip. Fcap. 8vo, cloth, 1s.
</p><p >PARTRIDGE AND OAKEY'S STANDARD <lb/> PICTORIAL EDITIONS OF <lb/> “UNCLE TOM'S CABIN.”</p><p >ELEGANT GIFT BOOK.</p><list  type="simple"><item>I.—THE STANDARD ILLUSTRATED EDITION. Beautifully printed in demy 8vo, with Sixteen beautiful Engravings on Tinted Paper, from Designs by Anelay. With an Introduction by Elihu Burritt. Price 10s. 6d.</item><item>II.—PEOPLE'S ILLUSTRATED EDITION. Crown 8vo, printed upon Superior Paper, with Twelve Wood Engravings from Designs by Anelay. Strong cloth, 2s. 6d.</item><item>III.—PEOPLE'S SHILLING EDITION. Crown 8vo, uniform with the People's Edition of Dickens. In neat boards, with Frontispiece, Illustrated Title and Cover, by Anelay.</item></list><p >Order PARTRIDGE AND OAKEY'S Unabridged <lb/> Editions.</p><p >PRISONERS OF HOPE; being Letters from Florence, relative to the Persecution of Francisco and Rosa Madiai, sentenced to solitary confinement and hard labour for reading the Word of God and professing the Gospel of Christ. Edited, with an Introduction, by S. P. TREGELLES, LL.D. Second thousand, with additions. Royal 18mo, cloth boards 2s. 6d. (Profits to be devoted to the Madiai.)</p><p >THE PEARL OF DAYS; or, The Advantages of the Sabbath to the Working Classes. By a LABOURER'S DAUGHTER. Thirty-seventh Thousand. Crimson gilt, with Five Illustrations, 3s.</p><p >People's Edition, 16th thousand, 6d.; Welsh, 1s. 6d.; French, 1s. 6d.</p><closer >London: PARTRIDGE AND OAKEY, Paternoster-row, <lb/> wand 70, Edgware-road.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >New Fiction by the Author of “Jane Eyre,” &amp;c.
<lb/>In January will be published,</opener><head >VILLETTE. BY CURRER BELL,</head><p >Author of “JANE EYRE,” “SHIRLEY,” &amp;c., <lb/> In Three Volumes, post 8vo.
</p><closer >LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, &amp; CO, 65, CORNHILL.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 56<hi rend="italics">s. folio, half bound morocco, gilt,</hi></opener><head >BLACK'S GENERAL ATLAS OF THE <lb/> WORLD.
</head><p >With upwards of Sixty-five Maps, Engraved and Coloured in the first style of Art, embracing all the latest discoveries, including those of Captain INGLEFIELD, in the Arctic Regions, &amp;c., and a COMPLETE INDEX of 60,000 names.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">This Work is published on the plan of small impressions, and frequent new and corrected issues. The Publishers are thus enabled to take advantage of every discovery as it appears, and to offer the Public an Atlas that can be relied upon for accuracy, beauty, and comprehensiveness.</hi></p><closer >EDINBURGH: ADAM &amp; CHARLES BLACK; <lb/> And Sold by all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >Works by Charles Dickens.</head><div><opener >Now ready, price 3s. 6d., neatly bound in cloth, <lb/> THE SECOND VOLUME <lb/> OF </opener><head >A CHILD'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</head><p >BY CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >WITH FRONTISPIECE FROM A DRAWING BY F. W. TOPHAM.</p><p >CORRECTED AND REVISED FROM “HOUSEHOLD WORDS,” WITH A TABLE OF DATES.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The History will be completed in Three Volumes.</hi></p></div><div><p >BLEAK HOUSE. WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. Now publishing in Monthly Parts, price 1s. each. (To be completed in Twenty.)</p><p >DAVID COPPERFIELD. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21s. in cloth.</p><p >DOMBEY AND SON. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21s. in cloth.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST. With Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Price 11s. in cloth.</p><p >PICTURES FROM ITALY, In fcap. 8vo. Price 6s. in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound in cloth, gilt edges, the Illustrations by</hi> D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON <lb/> STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, JOHN TENNIEL, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> RICHARD DOYLE.</p><p >A CHRISTMAS CAROL, IN PROSE.</p><p >THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH. A fairy Tale of Home.</p><p >THE BATTLE OF LIFE. A LOVE STORY.</p><p >THE HAUNTED MAN AND THE GHOST'S BARGAIN. A Fancy for Christmas Time.</p><p >THE CHIMES. A GOBLIN STORY OF SOME BELLS THAT RANG AN OLD YEAR OUT AND A NEW YEAR IN.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Works by W. M. Thackeray.</head><p >VANITY FAIR. With Forty Steel Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts, by the Author. 8vo. Price 21s.</p><p >THE HISTORY OF PENDENNIS. Forty-eight Steel Engravings. and Numerous Woodcuts, by the Author. 2 Vols., 8vo. Price 26s.</p><p >THE HISTORY OF SAMUEL TITMARSH AND THE GREAT HOGGARTY DIAMOND. In One Volume, small 8vo, price 4s., in cloth. with Ten Illustrations on Steel. <hi rend="italics">A New Edition.</hi></p><p >THE BOOK OF SNOBS. With Sixty Illustrations by the Author. <hi rend="italics">A New Edition in the Press.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Works by G. A. A'Beckett.</head><p >THE COMIC HISTORY OF ROME. Illustrated with Ten Coloured Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts. by JOHN LEECH. Price 11s. in cloth.</p><p >THE COMIC BLACKSTONE. Price 5s.</p><p >THE COMIC HISTORY OF ENGLAND. Twenty Coloured Engravings and Numerous Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH. In Two Volumes, 8vo. Price 21s.</p><p >THE QUIZZIOLOGY OF THE BRITISH DRAMA. Price 2s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">To be completed in about Seven Volumes, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s. each,</hi> </opener><head >Collected Edition of the Writings of Douglas Jerrold.</head><p >VOL. 1.—MEN OF CHARACTER.</p><p >2.—ST. GILES AND ST. JAMES.</p><p >3.—MRS. CAUDLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES; STORY OF A FEATHER; AND THE SICK GIANT AND DOCTOR DWARF.</p><p >VOL. 4.—CAKES AND ALE.</p><p >5.—PUNCH'S LETTERS TO HIS SON; PUNCH'S COMPLETE LETTER-WRITER; SKETCHES OF THE ENGLISH.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Publishing also in Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d. each, and Monthly Parts, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">d. each.</hi></p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >Illustrated Works Suitable for Presents.</head><p >MR. SPONGE'S SPORTING TOUR. By the Author of “Handley Cross,” “Jorrocks's Jaunts,” &amp;c. Illustrated with Coloured Engravings and Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH. Complete in 1 Volume 8vo., handsomely bound in cloth, price 14s., or with gilt edges, price 15s.</p><p >THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF OLIVER GOLDSMITH. A BIOGRAPHY; IN FOUR BOOKS. By JOHN FORSTER. In one large volume. Forty Original Designs engraved on Wood. Price 21s.</p><p >THE STORY OF NELL GWYN AND THE SAYINGS OF CHARLES THE SECOND. Collected and related by PETER CUNNINGHAM. Plates. Crown 8vo. Price 6s.</p><p >PUNCH'S POCKET - BOOK FOR 1853. With a large Coloured Engraving by JOHN LEECH, and numerous Woodcuts by JOHN LEECH and JOHN TENNIEL. Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >THE RISING GENERATION. A Series of 12 large Coloured Plates, designed and engraved by JOHN LEECH. Price 10s. 6d.</p><p >YOUNG TROUBLESOME: Or, MASTER JACKEY'S HOLIDAYS. A Series of Plates. Price 5s. 6d. plain; 7s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >THE MAN MADE OF MONEY. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. With Illustrations by JOHN LEECH. Price 7s.</p><p >PUNCH'S COMPLETE LETTER-WRITER. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. With Fifty Illustrations. Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >PUNCH'S LETTERS TO HIS SON. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. With Twenty-four Illustrations. Price 5s.</p><p >PUNCH; OR, THE LONDON CHARIVARI. Volumes 1 to 20, elegantly bound in 10. Price 7<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p><p >MANNERS AND CUSTOMS OF THE ENGLISH IN 1849. Drawn from ye Quick, by RICHARD DOYLE. With some Extracts from Mr. Pips his Diary, by PERCIVAL LEIGH. Complete, price 15s.</p><p >THE LADIES' COMPANION. Embellished with large Coloured Plates, and Numerous Engravings on Wood. 3 vols., Imperial 8vo. Price 30s.</p><p >THE ENCHANTED DOLL. A FAIRY TALE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE. By MARK LEMON. Illustrated by RICHARD DOYLE. Price 3s. 6d., in Boards.</p><p >THE NATURAL HISTORY OF CAGE BIRDS. Their Management, Habits, Food, Diseases, Treatment, Breeding, and the Methods of Catching them. By J. M. BECHSTEIN, M. D. Price 6s. in cloth, gilt.</p><p >THE MONTH. A VIEW OF PASSING SUBJECTS AND MANNERS: HOME AND FOREIGN, SOCIAL AND GENERAL. By JOHN LEECH and ALBERT SMITH. Price 6s.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Miscellaneous Works.</head><p >PROSE AND VERSE. By MARK LEMON. Foolscap 8vo., price 4s., cloth.</p><p >A SHORT INQUIRY INTO THE HISTORY OF AGRICULTURE, in Ancient, Mediæval and Modern Times. By CHANDOS WEEN HOSKYNS, Esq. 5s., cloth.</p><p >THE MAGAZINE OF DOMESTIC ECONOMY. A Library of everything requisite for Household Economy. Seven Volumes, 8vo. Price 35s.</p><p >BARRACK SERMONS, preached in the Riding School of the Cavalry Barracks, at Dorchester. By the REV. HENRY MOULK, M.A., Vicar of Fordington, Dorset. Dedicated (by permission) to the QUEEN. Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >HOW TO SEE THE BRITISH MUSEUM. In Four Visits. By WILLIAM BLANCHARD JERROLD. 2s. 6d.</p><p >HAND-BOOK OF COOKERY. Intended for the Use of the Middle Classes. Price 2s. cloth.</p><p >WHAT SHALL WE HAVE FOR DINNER? By LADY CLUTTERBUCK. Price 1s.</p><p >HINTS TO RAILWAY TRAVELLERS, AND COUNTRY VISITORS TO LONDON. By AN OLD STAGER. Price 1s.</p><p >THE POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE. Edited by W. C. MACREADY. For Schools and Families. Price 4s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >THE SHIPMASTER'S GUIDE. By THE REGISTRAR-GENERAL OF SEAMEN. Containing ample Directions for Making the Returns, and otherwise complying with the provisions of the Mercantile Marine Act, the Merchant Seamens' Act, and the Seaman's Protection Act, &amp;c. &amp;c. Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >SCRIPTURAL CHURCH TEACHING. The Doctrinal, Experimental, and Practical Teaching of the Church of England. By the Rev. H. MOULK. Price 2s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><head >Works in Preparation.</head><div><opener >On 31st January will be published, price 1s., the First Number of</opener><head >HANDLEY CROSS; OR, MR. JORROCKS'S HUNT.</head><p >By the AUTHOR of “Mr. Sponge's Tour.”</p><p >Illustrated with Coloured Plates and Numerous Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH, <lb/> Uniformly with “Sponge's Tour.”</p></div><div><opener >NEW WORK BY RICHARD DOYLE.</opener><head >THE FOREIGN TOUR OF MESSRS. BROWN, <lb/> JONES, AND ROBINSON.</head><p >Showing some of the Adventures that befel those Gentlemen during their travels in Belgium, Germany, <lb/> and Italy.</p><p >BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p></div><div><opener >Early in January will be published</opener><head >A NEW EDITION OF VANITY FAIR.</head><p >BY W. M. THACKERAY. Price 6s. in Cloth.</p><p >The Original Edition, with 40 large Plates, and numerous Woodcuts, by the Author, may still be <lb/> had, price 21s.</p><p >“In forming our general estimate of this writer, we wish it to be understood as referring principally, if not exclusively, to ‘Vanity Fair,’ so immeasurably superior in our opinion is this to every other known production of his pen. The great charm of this work is its entire freedom from mannerism and affectation, both in style and sentiment,—the confiding frankness with which the reader is addressed,—the thoroughbred carelessness with which the author permits the thoughts and feelings suggested by the situations to flow in their natural channel, as if conscious that nothing mean or unworthy could fall from him. In a word, the book is the work of a gentleman—one touch of nature makes the whole world kin, and here are touches of nature by the dozen.”—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p></div><div><opener >Price 7s. in cloth, a New Edition of</opener><head >THE LADIES' COMPANION TO THE FLOWER-GARDEN.</head><p >Being an Alphabetical Arrangement of all the Ornamental Plants grown in Gardens and Shrubberies: <lb/> with full directions for their culture.</p><p >BY MRS. LOUDON.</p></div><div><opener >A New Edition, enlarged and improved, of</opener><head > THE VEGETABLE KINGDOM:</head><p >OR, THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS. Illustrated upon the Natural System.</p><p >BY DR. LINDLEY, Ph. D., F.R.S., &amp;c.</p></div><div><opener >A New Edition, brought down to the present time, of</opener><head >THE HANDBOOK OF BOTANY.</head><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><head >BRITISH COLLEGE of HEALTH,</head><p >  Hamilton-place, New-road, London.</p><p >FOREIGN GENERAL AGENTS <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>LOR</sic><corr>[FOR]</corr></choice> THE SALE <lb/> OF MORISON'S PILLS.</p><p >THE VEGETABLE UNIVERSAL MEDICINE.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Amsterdam </cell><cell> Mr. Jacob Meihuzen. </cell></row><row><cell> Baltimore (U.S.) </cell><cell> J. C. French and Son. </cell></row><row><cell> Barbadoes </cell><cell> J. Montensiore and Co. </cell></row><row><cell> Barcelona (Spain) </cell><cell> Messrs. Charles Sola, Miret, and Cuyas. </cell></row><row><cell> Basle (Switzerland) </cell><cell> Mr. Roderick Scholp. </cell></row><row><cell> Brody (Germany) </cell><cell> N. Kornfeld, Esq. </cell></row><row><cell> Buffalo (U.S.) </cell><cell> Mr. Czeicke. </cell></row><row><cell> Cadiz </cell><cell> Mr. J. Bensusan. </cell></row><row><cell> Calcutta </cell><cell> T. Gardner, Esq. </cell></row><row><cell> Cape Breton </cell><cell> Lieut. J. M'Kinnon. </cell></row><row><cell> Carthagena </cell><cell> Rafael Cauto, Muralla del Mar. </cell></row><row><cell> Constantinople </cell><cell> Mr. A. Stampa. </cell></row><row><cell> Copenhagen </cell><cell> Mr. C. S. Holm and Mr. Michaelsen. </cell></row><row><cell> Cracow </cell><cell> Mr. Muldner. </cell></row><row><cell> Curacoa (W.I.) </cell><cell> Messrs. Senior. </cell></row><row><cell> Douglas (I. of Man) </cell><cell> Mr. Johnson. </cell></row><row><cell> Elsinore </cell><cell> Mr. O. S. Steenburg. </cell></row><row><cell> Frankfort </cell><cell> Berck, Freres. </cell></row><row><cell> George Town City (Demerara) </cell><cell> Mr. John M'Douall. </cell></row><row><cell> Gibraltar </cell><cell> Mr. T. H. Roberts. </cell></row><row><cell> Guernsey </cell><cell> Mr. James Cochrane. </cell></row><row><cell> Halifax (N.S.) </cell><cell> Messrs. A. and W. Mackinlay. </cell></row><row><cell> Hamburgh </cell><cell> Messrs. Krauskopf and Co. </cell></row><row><cell> Kempton (Bavaria) </cell><cell> Mr. M. Gayrhos. </cell></row><row><cell> Kingston (Jamaica) </cell><cell> Miss Kington. </cell></row><row><cell> Melbourne (Port Philip) </cell><cell> Mr. A. Charlwood. </cell></row><row><cell> Madras </cell><cell> R. L. Periera, Esq. </cell></row><row><cell> Madrid </cell><cell> Messrs, Saavedra and Co. </cell></row><row><cell> Matanzas (Cuba) </cell><cell> Dr. Ambrosio C. Sauto, <foreign xml:lang="spa">Calle del Medio</foreign>, No. 13. </cell></row><row><cell> Mexico </cell><cell> Mr. Jean Togne. </cell></row><row><cell> Montreal </cell><cell> Mr. R. Trudeau. </cell></row><row><cell> New York (U.S.) </cell><cell> Messrs. Firth, Pond and Co. </cell></row><row><cell> Odessa (Russia) </cell><cell> Wm. Wagner. </cell></row><row><cell> Paris </cell><cell> M. Arthaud, 33, <foreign xml:lang="fre">Kue Louis-le Grand</foreign>. </cell></row><row><cell> Passau </cell><cell> Carl Herman. </cell></row><row><cell> Pernambuco (Brazils) </cell><cell> A. S. Corbett, Esq. </cell></row><row><cell> Valencia </cell><cell> Mr. Antonio Andrews. </cell></row><row><cell> Bishop's Auckland (New Zealand) </cell><cell> Mr. R. Parris. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT.</head><head >METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN.</head><p >BY ROYAL COMMAND.</p><p >JOSEPH GILLOTT most respectfully begs to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic Institutions, and the Public generally, that by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times, he has introduced a <hi rend="italics">new series</hi> of his useful productions, which for <hi rend="italics">excellence of temper, quality of material,</hi> and, above all, <hi rend="italics">cheapness in price,</hi> he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition. Each pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of Boxes, containing One Gross each, with Label outside, and fac-simile of his signature.</p><p >Victoria Works, Graham-street, Birmingham.</p><p >April 20th, 1852.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for the removal of superfluous hair on the arms, neck, and face, so inimical to beauty. The genuine is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed “G. H. Hogard” for the last forty years. Sold for the proprietor by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell-street, Covent Garden, and 43, London Bridge, City, and by all respectable Perfumers, in packets, price 4s.; double ditto, 7s.; or by post, free, for fifty or eighty-eight postage stamps.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Chubb's Fire-proof Safes and Locks.</head><p >CHUBB &amp; SON <lb/> Have now on Sale, at their Warehouses, an Assortment <lb/> of their <lb/> FIRE-PROOF SAFES, <lb/> WHICH GAINED THE PRIZE MEDAL, WITH <lb/> SPECIAL APPROBATION, <lb/> at the Great Exhibition, this distinction being awarded to them SOLELY by the Jurors of Class XXII., after a careful comparison with those of other makers from all parts of England.</p><p >These SAFES, undoubtedly the MOST SECURE FROM FORCE, FRAUD, and FIRE, are sold at moderate prices.</p><p >CHUBB'S LOCKS, with all the recent improvements, CASH BOXES and DEED BOXES of all sizes, may be inspected.</p><p >IRON DOORS and FRAMES for Strong Rooms.</p><p >Complete Lists, with Prices, will be sent on application.</p><p >CHUBB &amp; SON, 57, St. Paul's Churchyard, London; 28, Lord-street, Liverpool; 16, Market-street, Manchester; and Hornsley Fields, Wolverhampton.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.</head><p >HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS have effected another wonderful cure of a bad leg, of seven years standing.—Extract of a letter from Mr. E. Pollard, druggist, of 32, Catherine-street, Devonport, dated May, 19, 1852, to Professor Holloway:—“Sir,—Mr. Blanker, of Charlotte-street, Newpassage, near Devonport, suffered severely, for more than seven years, from a wound in his leg. He tried every remedy that medical aid could devise, but in vain, as it would not heal by their treatment. At length he had recourse to your ointment and pills, which in the course of a few weeks, perfectly cured it, and he is now in most excellent health.” Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRT.</head><p >No. 84.</p><p >31s. 6d. &amp; 37s. 6d. the Half-dozen.</p><p >THE most comfortable and perfect-fitting Shirts extant, combining the highest degree of excellence at the smallest coat. Satisfaction (as usual) guaranteed, or the money returned.</p><p >Superb Dress Shirts for evening wear, 6s. 6d., 7s, 6d., and 8s. 6d. each. Also, Fashionable Coloured Shirts, ready made, or made to order, 20s. 26s., and 31s. 6d. the half-dozen. A choice of 200 New Patterns.</p><p >The general Ready-made Stock is the best, the cheapest, and the largest assortment of Shirts in London, and embraces all the recent improvements in the art.</p><p >Illustrated Priced Lists, with directions for self-measurement, and full particulars, gratis and post-free.</p><p >Patterns of the new and elegant designs for Coloured Shirts sent post-paid on receipt of Four Stamps.</p><p >RODGERS &amp; CO., Shirt Makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing Cross, and No. 29, at the Corner of New-street, Covent-garden, London. Established Sixty Years.—N. B. Boys' Shirts in all Sizes.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><head >THE NEW YEAR.</head><p >AT the social re-unions of this festive period the fair and youthful are more than usually anxious to shine in PERSONAL ATTRACTION, under the gaze of many friends, and the following unrivalled discoveries for the TOILET are called into increased requisition, namely—</p><p >ROWLANDS' MACASSAR OIL, for creating and sustaining a luxuriant head of hair.</p><p >ROWLANDS' KALYDOR, for rendering the Skin soft, fair, and blooming.</p><p >ROWLANDS' ODONTO, OR PEARL DENTIFRICE, for imparting a pearl-like whiteness to the Teeth, and <lb/> ROWLANDS' AQUA D'ORO, a fragrant and spirituous Perfume, an essential accompaniment to places of public amusement, and crowded assemblies.</p><p >The Patronage of Royalty throughout Europe, and the high appreciation by Rank and Fashion, with the well-known infallible efficacy of these articles render them a peculiarly <lb/> ELEGANT AND SEASONABLE PRESENT.</p><p >BEWARE OF SPURIOUS IMITATIONS.—The only GENUINE of each bears the name of “ROWLANDS” preceding that of the Article on the Wrapper or Label.</p><p >Sold by A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS, 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.</head><p >Have immediate influence over the following cases:—Asthmatic and Consumptive Complaints, Coughs, Shortness of Breath, Hoarseness, &amp;<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> &amp;<hi rend="italics">c.</hi></p><p >Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1s. 1½d., and Tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's-churchyard, London, and sold Retail by all Druggists, &amp;c.</p><p >CURE OF ASTHMA OF SEVERAL YEARS' STANDING.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Cainscross, near Stroud, Gloucestershire, March 20, 1850.</hi></p><p >SIR,—Having been troubled with Asthma for several years, I could find no relief from any medicine whatever, until I was induced about two years ago to try a box of your valuable Lozenges, and found such relief from them that I am determined for the future never to be without a box of them in the house, and will do all in my power to recommend them to my friends.</p><p >If you consider the above testimonial of any advantage, you are quite at liberty to make what use of it you please.</p><p >I am, Sir, your most obliged Servant, <lb/> J. TRIGG.</p><p >THOS. KEATING, Esq.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >Under Royal Patronage.</p><p >PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES <lb/> AND INSTANT RELIEF AND A RAPID CURE OF <lb/> ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, COLDS, <lb/> AND ALL <lb/> DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS <lb/> ARE INSURED BY <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S <lb/> PULMONIC WAFERS</p><p > Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated testimonials may be had from <lb/> every agent.</p><div type="section"><head >Cures of Consumption.</head><p >GENTLEMEN,—I can myself speak of your Wafers with the greatest confidence, having recommended them in many cases of pulmonary consumption, and they have always afforded relief when everything else has failed, and the patients having been surfeited with medicine, are delighted to meet with so efficient a remedy, having such an agreeable taste.</p><p >J. MAWSON.</p><p >13, Moseley-street, Newcastle-on-Tyne.</p><p >From the Author of the “NARRATIVE OF THE SECOND SIKH WAR.”</p><p >June 25, 1851.</p><p >SIR,—I had long suffered from a deep-seated cough, when Providence placed in my way a box of your Pulmonic Wafers. I experienced instantaneous relief, and have such a high estimate of their efficacy that I firmly believe they would effect the cure of the most consumptive person. You may make any use you please of this letter.</p><p >(Signed) EDWARD JOSEPH THACKWELL,</p><p >Lieut. 3rd Light Dragoons, Union Club, London.</p><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >THEY HAVE A PLEASANT TASTE. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >Also, may be had, <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S FAMILY APERIENT AND ANTIBILIOUS WAFERS.</p><p >A mild and gentle Aperient and Stomach Medicine, having a most agreeable taste, and of great efficacy for regulating the Secretions and correcting the action of the Stomach and Liver. Sold at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box. Also, <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS,</p><p >The best Medicine for Females. They have a pleasant taste. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >Full directions are given with every box.</p><p >SOLD BY EVERY RESPECTABLE CHEMIST AND MEDICINE VENDOR.</p><p >ALL PILLS UNDER SIMILAR NAMES ARE COUNTERFEITS.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p12"/><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES </head><p > of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >IN FULL DRESS.</p><p >WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p><p >INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS, <lb/> BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >BABY LINEN IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p><p >TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p><p >An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information, sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE ROYAL TURKISH TOWELS.</head><p >UNDER the Patronage of Her Majesty the Queen, and which received the Prize Medal at the Great Exhibition. The brown Linen combines the advantages of a flesh-brush with the qualities most desirable in a Towel. The white cotton is the softest Towel ever made, and absorbs moisture without the necessity of using friction. To be had of all respectable Linendrapers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR (as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Disinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p><p >Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p><p >RIMMEL'S HAIR DYE imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.—Price 5s. 6d.</p><p >RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended.—Beware of counterfeits.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39, Gerard-street, Soho, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE  PERUKE.</head><p >—The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13"/><head >PRIZE MEDAL.</head><head >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S <lb/> GOLD CHAINS.</head><p >By Troy Weight, and Workmanship at Wholesale <lb/> Manufacturers' Prices.</p><p >THE Great Exhibition having established the advantage of Purchasing from the Wholesale Manufacturer, wherever it can be accomplished, and thereby dispensing with an intermediate profit, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to announce that, in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them, they have thrown open their Manufactory to the Public at the same prices they have been in the habit (for the last half century) of charging to the Trade in London, India, and the Colonies.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to caution the Public against the Electro Gold Chain and Polished Zinc Gold, so extensively put forth in the present day, under the titles of “Pure Gold” and “Fine Gold,” and to call attention to the genuine Gold Chains made from their own ingots, and sold by Troy Weight at its bullion or realisable value.</p><p >The system of Weighing Chains against Sovereigns being one of the greatest frauds ever practised on the Public, WATHERSTON AND BROGDEN guarantee the Gold in their Chains, and will re-purchase it at the price charged; the workmanship according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> EXAMPLE.—Intrinsic value of a Chain of 15-Carat Gold, weighing 1⅛ Ounces </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 7 </cell></row><row><cell> Supposing the workmanship to be </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Total </cell><cell> £5 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 7 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >By this arrangement, the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">Bullion</hi> in a Gold Chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">An extensive assortment of Jewellery, all of the first quality, made at their Manufactory,</hi> <lb/> 16, HENRIETTA STREET, COVENT GARDEN, LONDON.</p><p >ESTABLISHED A.D. 1798.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MOTHERS! MOTHERS!! MOTHERS!!!</head><p >THE BEST MEDICINE IN THE WORLD for INFANTS AND YOUNG CHILDREN IS ATKINSON AND BARKER'S ROYAL INFANTS' PRESERVATIVE.—Under the Patronage of the Queen.—The high and universal celebrity which this medicine continues to maintain for the prevention and cure of those disorders incident to infants; affording instant relief in convulsions, flatulency, affections of the bowels, difficult teething, the thrush, rickets, measles, hooping-cough, cow-pox, or vaccine inoculation, and may be given with safety immediately after birth. It is no misnomer cordial!—no stupefactive, deadly narcotic!—but a veritable preserver of infants! Mothers would do well in always keeping it in the nursery. Many thousands of children are annually saved by this much-esteemed medicine, which is an immediate remedy and the infants rather like it than otherwise.</p><p >Prepared only by ROBERT BARKER, Ollerenshaw Hall, Chapel-en-le-Firth, Derbyshire, late of Manchester, (Chemist to Her most Gracious Majesty Queen Victoria), in bottles at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 11s. each.</p><p >Sold by all druggists and medicine vendors throughout the United Kingdom.</p><p >CAUTION.—Observe the name of “ATKINSON &amp; BARKER,” on the Government Stamp. Established in the year 1793.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS</head><p >Differ from other Patterns, not merely in shape and design, but in their great superiority of Fit, quality of Material, and Workmanship.—<hi rend="italics">Globe, April</hi> 12, 1852. They are of two prices; viz. Six for 40s.; Second Quality Six for 30s. in both of which the principle is strictly carried out.</p><p >List of Prices, and mode of Self-measurement sent free per Post.</p><p >FORD'S REGISTERED SHIRT COLLARS, 11s. per dozen.</p><p >Patterns of the New Coloured Shirtings in every variety of Colours. Upwards of 200 different styles for making FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS sent to select from on the receipt of six postage stamps. Price 27s. the half dozen.</p><closer >RICHARD FORD, 38, POULTRY, <lb/> LONDON, (Late 185, Strand.)</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14"/><head >PULVERMACHER'S PATENT PORTABLE <lb/>HYDRO - ELECTRIC CHAIN</head><p >Exhibited with the greatest success before the <hi rend="italics">Royal Coll. of Physicians, Royal Coll. of Surgeons, Royal Brit. Association, Prov. Med. Chirurgical Association, <foreign xml:lang="fre">Académie de Médecine</foreign></hi> at Paris, (a vote of thanks to the Inventor.)</p><p >Highly favourable <hi rend="italics">Testimonials in Writing</hi> from the most distinguished Members of the Profession, and now extensively used and prescribed in the <hi rend="italics">Hospitals</hi> of London, Edinburgh, Manchester, Nottingham, Birmingham, Paris, &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Constructed to be worn on the body under the Garments.</hi></p><p >SUPPLYING MILD STREAMING ELECTRICITY, <lb/> OR VITAL ENERGY TO THE SYSTEM.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Immediate Relief</hi> from acute pains. <hi rend="italics">Radical Cure</hi> of RHEUMATIC, CATARRHAL, NEURALGIC, SPASMODIC, NERVOUS, and FUNCTIONAL DISORDERS, within an incredibly short space of time, by this simple and painless remedy, which can be freely tested <hi rend="italics">beforehand,</hi> at C. MEINIG'S Head Depots, 103, Leadenhall Street, and 71, Regent Street. 600 <hi rend="italics">Cases of Cures within the last Eight Months,</hi> signed by PHYSICIANS, NOBLEMEN, CLERGYMEN, MAGISTRATES, &amp;c.—<hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 22<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> <hi rend="italics">and</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> according to Power.</p><p >FULL DESCRIPTION GRATIS (<hi rend="italics">or per post for Two Stamps</hi>).</p><p >...“I can scarcely recommend Dr. P.'s ingenious invention too strongly to the notice of my Medical Brethren.” <hi rend="italics">From that eminent Physician of Guy's Hospital, DR. GOLDING BIRD, M.D., F.R.S., &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> FASTEN AT THE BACK,</head><p >WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><p >A most perfect and easy-fitting Shirt, and by a simple invention of the Patentee, adjusts itself to all movements of the body, both back and front, either walking, sitting, or riding. Price, including the REGISTERED ELLIPTIC WRISTBAND, 42s. the half-dozen. The Elliptic Collar, quite unique, in all shapes, with Patent Elastic Fastenings, 12s. the dozen. The Patent Elastic Collar Fastening can be attached to any Collar, opening back or front. Six sent by post on receipt of 13 Postage Stamps.</p><p >THE GORGET PATENT SELF ADJUSTING SHIRT.</p><p >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR: <lb/> TO FASTEN IN FRONT.</p><p >WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><list  type="simple"><head>Directions for Self Measurement.</head><item>1. Round the Chest, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>2. Round the Waist, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>3. Round the Neck, taken about the middle of the Throat.</item><item>4. Round the Wrist.</item><item>5. The length of Coat Sleeve, from the centre of Back, down the seam of Sleeve to bottom of cuff.</item><item>6. The length of Shirt.</item></list><p >Say if the Shirts are to open back or front If with Collars attached (3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> the half-dozen extra),</p><p >PATENTEES, <lb/> COOPER &amp; FRYER, <lb/> Removed next door to the <lb/> HAYMARKET THEATRE</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >“THE BEST IS THE CHEAPEST.”</head><p >
<table><row><cell> The Best Congou Tea </cell><cell> 3s. 8d. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Imperial Souchong Tea </cell><cell> 4s. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Moyune Gunpowder </cell><cell> 5s. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Plantation Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Mocha Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. 4d. per lb. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Tea or Coffee to the value of 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> or upwards sent, Carriage Free, to any part of England, by <lb/> PHILLIPS &amp; COMPANY, <lb/> TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> 8, KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY, LONDON.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOYER'S RELISH.</head><p >“To describe the Sauce would be to make our readers hungry,—rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poured.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p><p >THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents, <lb/> CROSSE AND BLACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen.</p><closer >GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15"/><head >CITY OF GLASGOW <lb/> LIFE ASSURANCE AND REVERSIONARY COMPANY.</head><p >ESTABLISHED IN 1838.—CONSTITUTED BY ACT OF PARLIAMENT, 1842.</p><p >LONDON—12, KING WILLIAM STREET.</p><p >GLASGOW—40, ST. VINCENT PLACE. EDINBURGH—19, ST. ANDREW SQUARE.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Governor</hi>—THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE EARL OF GLASGOW.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Deputy Governor</hi>—JAMES OSWALD, ESQ.</p><div type="section"><head >LONDON BOARD OF DIRECTORS.</head><p >Sir JOHN RIVETT CARNAC, Bart., M.P.</p><p >H. JEEFREYS BUSHBY, Esq., Figtree Court, Temple.</p><p >JOHN HAMMILL, Esq., Sussex Gardens, Hyde Park.</p><p >T. WINGATE HENDERSON, ESQ., Westbourne Terrace.</p><p >CHARLES TENNANT, Esq., 101, Upper Thames Street.</p><p >WM. GODFREY WHATMAN, Esq., 73, Lombard Street.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Secretary</hi>—G. A. THOMSON, Esq.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Medical Referee</hi>—JAMES R, MARTIN, Esq., F.R.S.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Bankers</hi>—Messrs. BOSANQUET, FRANKS, &amp; Co.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Solicitors</hi>—Messrs. THOMPSON, DEBENHAM, and BROWN, Salter's Hall.</p></div><div type="section"><head >GLASGOW BOARD OF DIRECTORS.</head><p >P. CLOUSTON, Esq., Insur. Broker.</p><p >JOHN TENNANT, Esq., St. Rollox.</p><p >G. BAIRD, Esq., Gartsherrie.</p><p >J. MUIRHEAD, Esq., Goldsmith.</p><p >W. BUCHANAN, Esq., Merchant.</p><p >JOHN J. GIBB, Esq., Merchant.</p><p >MUNGO CAMPBELL, Esq., Merchant.</p><p >W. WUYTE, Esq., of Kilmardinny.</p><p >AND. S. DALGLISH, Esq., Glasgow.</p><p >ALEX. WINGATE, Esq., Merchant.</p><p >JAMES JAMIESON, Esq., Merchant.</p><p >W. PATERSON, Esq., Merchant.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Manager</hi>—DANIEL WALKINGSHAW, Esq.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Actuary</hi>—ARCHIBALD BORTHWICK, Esq.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Medical Referee</hi>—JOHN MACFARLANE, M.D.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Bankers</hi>—The CLYDESDALE BANK.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Solicitor</hi>—ALEXANDER MORRISON, Esq.</p><p >THE COMPANY'S REVENUE from Premiums alone amounts to FORTY THOUSAND POUNDS PER ANNUM.</p><p >THE SUMS ASSURED WITH THE COMPANY amount to upwards of ONE MILLION TWO HUNDRED THOUSAND BOUNDS STERLING.</p><p >THE SUCCESS of this Company is attributable to the liberality and soundness of its rules, and particularly to the plain and rational system practised by it of distributing the Profits to the Assured Annually and Equally.</p><p >PROFITS WERE FIRST DECLARED by the Company in the year 1846.</p><p >THE FIRST BONUS ADDITION TO POLICIES was at the rate of One Pound per Annum on each £100. assured from date of Policy being opened.</p><p >BONUS ADDITIONS have been declared annually since the year 1846, at the increased rate of One Pound Ten Shillings on each £100. assured.</p><p >THE RESULT OF THESE ANNUAL DIVISIONS OF PROFITS WILL BE SEEN FROM THE FOLLOWING EXAMPLES <lb/> OF THE INCREASED AMOUNT ON POLICIES OF £1000., ACCORDING TO THEIR DATES.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Date of Policy. </cell><cell> Present Amount. </cell><cell> Date of Policy. </cell><cell> Present Amount. </cell><cell> Date of Policy. </cell><cell> Present Amount. </cell><cell> Date of Policy. </cell><cell> Present Amount. </cell></row><row><cell> 1839 </cell><cell> £1160 </cell><cell> 1843 </cell><cell> £1120 </cell><cell> 1847 </cell><cell> £1075 </cell><cell> 1851 </cell><cell> £1015 </cell></row><row><cell> 1840 </cell><cell> 1150 </cell><cell> 1844 </cell><cell> 1110 </cell><cell> 1848 </cell><cell> 1060 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 1841 </cell><cell> 1140 </cell><cell> 1845 </cell><cell> 1100 </cell><cell> 1849 </cell><cell> 1045 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 1842 </cell><cell> 1130 </cell><cell> 1846 </cell><cell> 1090 </cell><cell> 1850 </cell><cell> 1030 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >BONUS EXAMPLES are too generally the most favourable cases which can be selected, and the large amount so temptingly displayed prove that undue partiality is shown to favoured classes of Policy-holders, but certainly warrant no expectation of similar advantages to new Entrants.</p><p >THE EXAMPLES given above from this Company's Books, on the contrary, show the increase on <hi rend="italics">every one of the Company's Policies</hi> effected on the Participating Scale; the Assured of all ages Participating <hi rend="italics">Equally</hi> in the Annual Division of Profits.</p><p >ANNUAL CASH PAYMENTS, in lieu of Bonus Additions, payable at death, are given to parties who may prefer that plan, according to a regular Scale of Rates.</p></div><div type="section"><head >NON-FORFEITURE OF POLICIES.</head><p >It has been the practice of this Company, although not generally adopted as a part of the system of Life Assurance, to pay the surrender-value of all dropped Policies entitled thereto. No unfair advantage is taken of the non-payment of the Premium from over-sight or otherwise, by which forfeiture of a Policy, as well as its cash value, are usually involved; on the contrary, in all such cases, the holder of a Policy of this Company is made aware of his being entitled to surrender-value, and the same is immediately paid.</p></div><div type="section"><head >LIFE CONTINGENCIES OF ALL KINDS,</head><p >embracing Assurances, the Purchase and Sale of Annuities, the Purchase of Reversionary Interests, &amp;c. &amp;c., are undertaken by the Company on rates equitably calculated. Numerous Tables are given in the Company's more detailed Prospectus, which can be obtained gratis, with Forms of Proposal, on application at any of the Company's Offices.</p><p >THE BOOKS CLOSE ANNUALLY ON 20th JANUARY.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16"/><p >Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'s REGISTERED PARDESSUS, <lb/> OF FINE AUSTRALIAN and LLAMA WOOLS, (6TH &amp; 7TH VICTORIA, CAP. 65), <lb/> FOR WALKING OR RIDING.</p><p >THIS is an improved style of Coat, of a light convenient form, which admits of its being worn either over or without the ordinary coat. It is neatly and handsomely made, care being bestowed in its construction, to impart to it that graceful and appropriate character which, since its first introduction, has so greatly recommended it to public favour; it is produced in all colours with silk sleeve linings, at the very moderate price of TWO GUINEAS; and for Winter wear, richly lined and quilted, TWO-AND-A-HALF and THREE GUINEAS. The IMPROVED WINTER GUINEA TROUSERS are also ready for selection from a choice variety of patterns.</p><p >In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s, Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94 REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >GREAT EXHIBITION, JURY REPORT.</head><p >CLASS XXIX., p. 661.</p><p >“W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Prize Medal for Silk Parasols and Umbrellas of excellent quality, and for their application of Alpaca Cloth to the Coverings of Umbrellas and Parasols.”</p><p >As the merit in an Umbrella consists in its strength, combined with extreme lightness, W. &amp; J. S. beg to say that they are now prepared to offer for the first time an Umbrella made on Fox's Paragon Frames, possessing these requirements, and rendering it an article perfectly unique, whether in Silk or Alpaca.</p><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER, <lb/> 140, Regent Street.</p><p >94, Fleet Street.</p><p >10, Royal Exchange.</p><p >75, Cheapside.</p><p >AGENTS FOR THE UNITED STATES, <lb/> MESSRS. F. DERBY &amp; CO., 12, PARK PLACE, NEW YORK.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><pb  xml:id="pxxx3"/><p >On January 31st will be published, price One Shilling, the First Number of <lb/> HANDLEY CROSS; <lb/> OR, <lb/> MR. JORROCKS'S HUNT.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF <lb/> “MR. SPONGE'S TOUR.”</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Illustrated with Coloured Plates and Numerous Woodcuts by JOHN LEECH <lb/> UNIFORMLY WITH “SPONGE'S TOUR.”</hi></p><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pxxx4"/><p >
<figure><p><hi rend="italics">Mr. Smallweed breaks the pipe of peace.</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pxxx5"/><p >
<figure><p><hi rend="italics">The old man of the name of Tulkinghorn.</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><pb  xml:id="pxxx6"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price 2d., or stamped for post, 3d.; in Monthly Parts, and in Half-Yearly Volumes,</hi></opener><head >  HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p >A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST <lb/> IN THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p><p >FIVE VOLUMES are published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, in cloth boards, and are always on sale.</p><p >A ROUND OF STORIES BY THE CHRISTMAS FIRE.</p><p >Being the Extra Christmas Number of “HOUSEHOLD WORDS” for 1852, and containing the amount of one regular number and a half, price 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or stamped 4<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> has just been issued. The Christmas Numbers for the years 1850-51, price 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, may still be had.</p></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><p ><hi rend="italics">Also published at the end of every Month, at the same Office, price 2d., or stamped for post, 3d.</hi></p><p >THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS; <lb/> Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Exchequer, a Legal Publication, not coming within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved.</p><p >The First and Second Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of 1850-51, may always be had, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, neatly bound in cloth. The Third Volume, comprising a History of 1852, will be published on the 8th of January. Each Volume contains a copious Index.</p><p >OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p321"/><head >CHAPTER XXXIII. <lb/> INTERLOPERS.</head><p >Now do those two gentlemen not very neat about the cuffs and buttons who attended the last Coroner's Inquest at the Sol's Arms, reappear in the precincts with surprising swiftness (being, in fact, breathlessly fetched by the active and intelligent beadle), and institute perquisitions through the court, and dive into the Sol's parlour, and write with ravenous little pens on tissue-paper. Now do they note down, in the watches of the night, how the neighbourhood of Chancery Lane was yesterday, at about midnight, thrown into a state of the most intense agitation and excitement by the following alarming and horrible discovery. Now do they set forth how it will doubtless be remembered, that some time back a painful sensation was created in the public mind, by a case of mysterious death from opium occurring in the first floor of the house occupied as a rag, bottle, and general marine store-shop, by an eccentric individual of intemperate habits, far advanced in life, named Krook; and how, by a remarkable coincidence, Krook was examined at the inquest, which it may be recollected was held on that occasion at the Sol's Arms, a well-conducted tavern, immediately adjoining the premises in question, on the west side, and licensed to a highly respectable landlord, Mr. James George Bogsby. Now do they show (in as many words as possible), how during some hours of yesterday evening a very peculiar smell was observed by the inhabitants of the court, in which the tragical occurrence which forms the subject of that present account transpired; and which odour was at one time so powerful, that Mr. Swills, a comic vocalist, professionally engaged by Mr. J.G. Bogsby, has himself stated to our reporter that he mentioned to Miss M. Melvilleson, a lady of some pretensions to musical ability, likewise engaged by Mr<corr>.</corr> J. G. Bogsby to sing at a series of concerts called Harmonic Assemblies or Meetings, which it would appear are held at the Sol's Arms, under Mr. Bogsby's direction, pursuant to the Act of George the Second, that he (Mr. Swills) found his voice seriously affected by the impure state of the atmosphere; his jocose expression, at the time, being, “that he was like an empty post-office, for he hadn't a single note in him.” How this account of Mr. Swills is entirely corroborated by two intelligent married females residing in the same court, and known respectively by the names of Mrs. Piper and Mrs. Perkins; both of whom observed the fœtid effluvia, and regarded them as being emitted from the premises in the occupation of Krook, the unfortunate deceased. All this and a great deal more, the two gentlemen, who have formed an amicable partnership in the melancholy catastrophe, write down on the spot; and the boy population of the court (out of bed in a moment) swarm up the shutters of the Sol's Arm's parlor, to behold the tops of their heads while they are about it.</p><p >The whole court, adult as well as boy, is sleepless for that night, and can do nothing but wrap up its many heads, and talk of the ill-fated house, and look at it. Miss Flite has been bravely rescued from
<pb xml:id="p322"/>
her chamber, as if it were in flames, and accommodated with a bed at the Sol's Arms. The Sol neither turns off its gas nor shuts its door, all night; for any kind of public excitement makes good for the Sol, and causes the court to stand in need of comfort. The house has not done so much in the stomachic article of cloves, or in brandy and water warm, since the Inquest. The moment the potboy heard what had happened, he rolled up his shirt-sleeves tight to his shoulders, and said, “There'll be a run upon us!” In the first outcry, Young Piper dashed off for the fire-engines; and returned in triumph at a jolting gallop, perched up aloft on the Phœnix, and holding on to that fabulous creature with all his might, in the midst of helmets and torches. One helmet remains behind, after careful investigation of all chinks and crannies; and slowly paces up and down before the house, in company with one of the two policemen who have been likewise left in charge thereof. To this trio, everybody in the court, possessed of sixpence, has an insatiate desire to exhibit hospitality in a liquid form.</p><p >Mr. Weevle and his friend Mr. Guppy are within the bar at the Sol, and are worth anything to the Sol that the bar contains, if they will only stay there. “This is not a time,” says Mr. Bogsby, “to haggle about money,” though he looks something sharply after it, over the counter; “give your orders, you two gentlemen, and you're welcome to whatever you put a name to.”</p><p >Thus entreated, the two gentlemen (Mr. Weevle especially) put names to so many things, that in course of time they find it difficult to put a name to anything quite distinctly; though they still relate, to all new comers, some version of the night they have had of it, and of what they said, and what they thought, and what they saw. Meanwhile, one or other of the policemen often flits about the door, and pushing it open a little way at the full length of his arm, looks in from outer gloom. Not that he has any suspicions, but that he may as well know what they are up to, in there.</p><p >Thus, night pursues its leaden course; finding the court still out of bed through the unwonted hours, still treating and being treated, still conducting itself similarly to a court that has had a little money left it unexpectedly. Thus, night at length with slow-retreating steps departs, and the lamplighter going his rounds, like an executioner to a despotic king, strikes off the little heads of fire that have aspired to lessen the darkness. Thus, the day cometh, whether or no.</p><p >And the day may discern, even with its dim London eye, that the court has been up all night. Over and above the faces that have fallen drowsily on tables, and the heels that lie prone on hard floors instead of beds, the brick and mortar physiognomy of the very court itself looks worn and jaded. And now the neighbourhood waking up, and beginning to hear of what has happened, comes streaming in, half-dressed, to ask questions; and the two policemen and the helmet (who are far less impressible externally than the court) have enough to do to keep the door.</p><p >“Good gracious, gentlemen!” says Mr. Snagsby, coming up. “What's this I hear!”</p><p >“Why, it's true,” returns one of the policemen. “That's what it is. Now move on here, come!”</p><p >“Why, good gracious, gentlemen,” says Mr. Snagsby, somewhat
<pb xml:id="p323"/>
promptly backed away, “I was at this door last night betwixt ten and eleven o'clock, in conversation with the young man who lodges here.”</p><p >“Indeed?” returns the policeman. “You will find the young man next door then. Now move on here, some of you.”</p><p >“Not hurt, I hope?” says Mr. Snagsby.</p><p >“Hurt? No. What's to hurt him!”</p><p >Mr. Snagsby, wholly unable to answer this, or any other question, in his troubled mind, repairs to the Sol's Arms, and finds Mr. Weevle languishing over tea and toast; with a considerable expression on him of exhausted excitement, and exhausted tobacco-smoke.</p><p >“And Mr. Guppy likewise!” quoth Mr. Snagsby. “Dear, dear, dear! What a Fate there seems in all this! And my lit—”</p><p >Mr. Snagsby's power of speech deserts him in the formation of the words “my little woman.” For, to see that injured female walk into the Sol's Arms at that hour of the morning and stand before the beer-engine, with her eyes fixed upon him like an accusing spirit, strikes him dumb.</p><p >“My dear,” says Mr. Snagsby, when his tongue is loosened, “will you take anything? A little—not to put too fine a point upon it—drop of shrub?”</p><p >“No,” says Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >“My love, you know these two gentlemen?”</p><p >“Yes!” says Mrs. Snagsby; and in a rigid manner acknowledges their presence, still fixing Mr. Snagsby with her eye.</p><p >The devoted Mr. Snagsby cannot bear this treatment. He takes Mrs. Snagsby by the hand, and leads her aside to an adjacent cask.</p><p >“My little woman, why do you look at me in that way? Pray don't do it.”</p><p >“I can't help my looks,” says Mrs. Snagsby, “and if I could I wouldn't.”</p><p >Mr. Snagsby, with his cough of meekness, rejoins,—“Wouldn't you really, my dear?” and meditates. Then coughs his cough of trouble, and says, “This is a dreadful mystery, my love!” still fearfully disconcerted by Mrs. Snagsby's eye.</p><p >“It <hi rend="italics">is,</hi>” returns Mrs. Snagsby, shaking her head, “a dreadful mystery.”</p><p >“My little woman,” urges Mr. Snagsby, in a piteous manner, “don't, for goodness sake, speak to me with that bitter expression, and look at me in that searching way! I beg and entreat of you not to do it. Good lord, you don't suppose that I would go spontaneously combusting any person, my dear?”</p><p >“I can't say,” returns Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >On a hasty review of his unfortunate position, Mr. Snagsby “can't say,” either. He is not prepared positively to deny that he may have had something to do with it. He has had something—he don't know what—to do with so much in this connexion that is mysterious, that it is possible he may even be implicated, without knowing it, in the present transaction. He faintly wipes his forehead with his handkerchief, and gasps.</p><p >“My life,” says the unhappy stationer, “would you have any objections to mention why, being in general so delicately circumspect in your conduct, you come into a Wine Vaults before breakfast?”</p><pb  xml:id="p324"/><p >“Why do <hi rend="italics">you</hi> come here?” inquires Mrs. Snagsby.</p><p >“My dear, merely to know the rights of the fatal accident which has happened to the venerable party who has been—combusted.” Mr. Snagsby has made a pause to suppress a groan. “I should then have related them to you, my love, over your French roll.”</p><p >“I dare say you would! You relate everything to me, Mr. Snagsby.”</p><p >“Every—my lit—?”</p><p >“I should be glad,” says Mrs. Snagsby, after contemplating his increased confusion with a severe and sinister smile, “if you would come home with me; I think you may be safer there, Mr. Snagsby, than anywhere else.”</p><p >“My love, I don't know but what I may be, I am sure. I am ready to go.”</p><p >Mr. Snagsby casts his eyes forlornly round the bar, gives Messrs. Weevle and Guppy good morning, assures them of the satisfaction with which he sees them uninjured, and accompanies Mrs. Snagsby from the Sol's Arms. Before night, his doubt whether he may not be responsible for some inconceivable part in the catastrophe which is the talk of the whole neighbourhood, is almost resolved into certainty by Mrs. Snagsby's pertinacity in that fixed gaze. His mental sufferings are so great, that he entertains wandering ideas of delivering himself up to justice, and requiring to be cleared, if innocent, and punished with the utmost rigor of the law, if guilty.</p><p >Mr. Weevle and Mr. Guppy, having taken their breakfast, step into Lincoln's Inn to take a little walk about the square, and clear as many of the dark cobwebs out of their brains as a little walk may.</p><p >“There can be no more favorable time than the present, Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, after they have broodingly made out the four sides of the square, “for a word or two between us, upon a point on which we must, with very little delay, come to an understanding.”</p><p >“Now, I tell you what, William G!” returns the other, eyeing his companion with a bloodshot eye. “If it's a point of conspiracy, you needn't take the trouble to mention it. I have had enough of that, and I ain't going to have any more. We shall have <hi rend="italics">you</hi> taking fire next, or blowing up with a bang.”</p><p >This supposititious phenomenon is so very disagreeable to Mr. Guppy that his voice quakes, as he says in a moral way, “Tony, I should have thought that what we went through last night, would have been a lesson to you never to be personal any more as long as you lived.” To which Mr. Weevle returns, “William, I should have thought it would have been a lesson to <hi rend="italics">you</hi> never to conspire any more as long as you lived.” To which Mr. Guppy says, “Who's conspiring?” To which Mr. Jobling replies, “Why, <hi rend="italics">you</hi> are!” To which Mr. Guppy retorts, “No, I am not.” To which Mr. Jobling retorts again, “Yes, you are!” To which Mr. Guppy retorts, “Who says so?” To which Mr. Jobling retorts, “<hi rend="italics">I</hi> say so!” To which Mr. Guppy retorts, “Oh, indeed?” To which Mr. Jobling retorts, “Yes, indeed!” And both being now in a heated state, they walk on silently for a while, to cool down again.</p><p >“Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, then, “if you heard your friend out, instead of flying at him, you wouldn't fall into mistakes. But your temper is hasty, and you are not considerate. Possessing in yourself, Tony, all that is calculated to charm the eye—”</p><pb  xml:id="p325"/><p >“Oh! Blow the eye!” cries Mr. Weevle, cutting him short. “Say what you have got to say!”</p><p >Finding his friend in this morose and material condition, Mr. Guppy only expresses the finer feelings of his soul through the tone of injury in which he recommences:</p><p >“Tony, when I say there is a point on which we must come to an understanding pretty soon, I say so quite apart from any kind of conspiring, however innocent. You know it is professionally arranged beforehand, in all cases that are tried, what facts the witnesses are to prove. Is it, or is it not, desirable that we should know what facts we are to prove, on the inquiry into the death of this unfortunate old Mo— gentleman?” (Mr. Guppy was going to say, Mogul, but thinks gentleman better suited to the circumstances.)</p><p >“What facts? <hi rend="italics">The</hi> facts.”</p><p >“The facts bearing on that inquiry. Those are—” Mr. Guppy tells them off on his fingers.—“what we knew of his habits; when you saw him last; what his condition was then; the discovery that we made, and how we made it.”</p><p >“Yes,” says Mr. Weevle. “Those are about the facts.”</p><p >“We made the discovery, in consequence of his having, in his eccentric way, an appointment with you for twelve o'clock at night, when you were to explain some writing to him, as you had often done before, on account of his not being able to read. I, spending the evening with you, was called down—and so forth. The inquiry being only into the circumstances touching the death of the deceased, it's not necessary to go beyond these facts, I suppose you'll agree?”</p><p >“No!” returns Mr. Weevle. “I suppose not.”</p><p >“And this is not a conspiracy, perhaps?” says the injured Guppy.</p><p >“No,” returns his friend; “if it's nothing worse than this, I withdraw the observation.”</p><p >“Now, Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, taking his arm again, and walking him slowly on, “I should like to know, in a friendly way, whether you have yet thought over the many advantages of your continuing to live at that place?”</p><p >“What do you mean?” says Tony, stopping.</p><p >“Whether you have yet thought over the many advantages of your continuing to live at that place?” repeats Mr. Guppy, walking him on again.</p><p >“At what place? <hi rend="italics">That</hi> place?” pointing in the direction of the rag and bottle shop.</p><p >Mr. Guppy nods.</p><p >“Why, I wouldn't pass another night there, for any consideration that you could offer me,” says Mr. Weevle, haggardly staring.</p><p >“Do you mean it though, Tony?”</p><p >“Mean it! Do I look as if I mean it? I feel as if I do; I know that” says Mr. Weevle, with a very genuine shudder.</p><p >“Then the possibility, or probability—for such it must be considered—of your never being disturbed in possession of those effects, lately belonging to a lone old man who seemed to have no relation in the world; and the certainty of your being able to find out what he really had got stored up there; don't weigh with you at all against last night,
<pb xml:id="p326"/>
Tony, if I understand you?” says Mr. Guppy, biting his thumb with the appetite of vexation.</p><p >“Certainly not. Talk in that cool way of a fellow's living there?” cries Mr. Weevle, indignantly. “Go and live there yourself.”</p><p >“O! I, Tony!” says Mr. Guppy, soothing him. “I have never lived there, and couldn't get a lodging there now; whereas you have got one.”</p><p >“You are welcome to it,” rejoins his friend, “and—ugh!—you may make yourself at home in it.”</p><p >“Then you really and truly at this point,” says Mr. Guppy, “give up the whole thing, if I understand you, Tony?”</p><p >“You never,” returns Tony, with a most convincing stedfastness, “said a truer word in all your life. I do!”</p><p >While they are so conversing, a hackney-coach drives into the square, on the box of which vehicle a very tall hat makes itself manifest to the public. Inside the coach, and consequently not so manifest to the multitude, though sufficiently so to the two friends, for the coach stops almost at their feet, are the venerable Mr. Smallweed and Mrs. Smallweed, accompanied by their grand-daughter Judy. An air of haste and excitement pervades the party; and as the tall hat (surmounting Mr. Smallweed the younger) alights, Mr. Smallweed the elder pokes his head out of window, and bawls to Mr. Guppy, “How de do, sir! How de do!”</p><p >“What do Chick and his family want here at this time of the morning, I wonder!” says Mr. Guppy, nodding to his familiar.</p><p >“My dear sir,” cries Grandfather Smallweed, “would you do me a favor? Would you and your friend be so very obleeging as to carry me into the public-house in the court, while Bart and his sister bring their grandmother along? Would you do an old man that good turn, sir?”</p><p >Mr. Guppy looks at his friend, repeating inquiringly, “the public-house in the court?” And they prepare to bear the venerable burden to the Sol's Arms.</p><p >“There's your fare!” says the Patriarch to the coachman with a fierce grin, and shaking his incapable fist at him. “Ask me for a penny more, and I'll have my lawful revenge upon you. My dear young men, be easy with me, if you please. Allow me to catch you round the neck. I won't squeeze you tighter than I can help. O Lord! O dear me! O my bones!”</p><p >It is well that the Sol is not far off, for Mr. Weevle presents an apoplectic appearance before half the distance is accomplished. With no worse aggravation of his symptoms, however, than the utterance of divers croaking sounds, expressive of obstructed respiration, he fulfils his share of the porterage, and the benevolent old gentleman is deposited by his own desire in the parlor of the Sol's Arms.</p><p >“O Lord!” gasps Mr. Smallweed, looking about him, breathless, from an arm-chair. “O dear me! O my bones and back! O my aches and pains! Sit down, you dancing, prancing, shambling, scrambling poll parrot! Sit down!”</p><p >This little apostrophe to Mrs. Smallweed is occasioned by a propensity on the part of that unlucky old lady, whenever she finds herself on her feet, to amble about, and “set” to inanimate objects, accompanying herself with a chattering noise, as in a witch dance. A nervous affection has probably as much to do with these demonstrations, as any imbecile
<pb xml:id="p327"/>
intention in the poor old woman; but on the present occasion they are so particularly lively in connexion with a Windsor arm-chair, fellow to that in which Mr. Smallweed is seated, that she only quite desists when her grandchildren have held her down in it: her lord in the meanwhile bestowing upon her, with great volubility, the endearing epithet of “a pig-headed Jackdaw,” repeated a surprising number of times.</p><p >“My dear sir,” Grandfather Smallweed then proceeds, addressing Mr. Guppy, “there has been a calamity here. Have you heard of it, either of you?”</p><p >“Heard of it, sir! Why we discovered it.”</p><p >“You discovered it. You two discovered it! Bart, <hi rend="italics">they</hi> discovered it!” The two discoverers stare at the Smallweeds, who return the compliment.</p><p >“My dear friends,” whines Grandfather Smallweed, putting out both his hands, “I owe you a thousand thanks for discharging the melancholy office of discovering the ashes of Mrs. Smallweed's brother.”</p><p >“Eh?” says Mr. Guppy.</p><p >“Mrs. Smallweed's brother, my dear friend—her only relation. We were not on terms, which is to be deplored now, but he never <hi rend="italics">would</hi> be on terms. He was not fond of us. He was eccentric—he was very eccentric. Unless he has left a will (which is not at all likely) I shall take out letters of administration. I have come down to look after the property; it must be sealed up, it must be protected. I have come down,” repeats Grandfather Smallweed, hooking the air towards him with all his ten fingers at once, “to look after the property.”</p><p >“I think, Small,” says the disconsolate Mr. Guppy, “you might have mentioned that the old man was your uncle.”</p><p >“You two were so close about him that I thought you would like me to be the same,” returns that old bird, with a secretly glistening eye. “Besides, I wasn't proud of him.”</p><p >“Besides which, it was nothing to you, you know, whether he was or not,” says Judy. Also with a secretly glistening eye.</p><p >“He never saw me in his life, to know me,” observes Small; “I don't know why I should introduce <hi rend="italics">him,</hi> I am sure!”</p><p >“No, he never communicated with us—which is to be deplored,” the old gentleman strikes in; “but I have come to look after the property—to look over the papers, and to look after the property. We shall make good our title. It is in the hands of my solicitor. Mr. Tulkinghorn, of Lincoln's Inn Fields, over the way there, is so good as to act as my solicitor; and grass don't grow under <hi rend="italics">his</hi> feet, I can tell ye. Krook was Mrs. Smallweed's only brother; she had no relation but Krook, and Krook had no relation but Mrs. Smallweed. I am speaking of your brother, you brimstone black-beetle, that was seventy-six years of age.”</p><p >Mrs. Smallweed instantly begins to shake her head, and pipe up, “Seventy-six pound seven and sevenpence! Seventy-six thousand bags of money! Seventy-six hundred thousand million of parcels of bank notes!”</p><p >“Will somebody give me a quart pot?” exclaims her exasperated husband, looking helplessly about him, and finding no missile within his reach. “Will somebody obleege me with a spittoon? Will somebody hand
<pb xml:id="p328"/>
me anything hard and bruising to pelt at her? You hag, you cat, you dog, you brimstone barker!” Here Mr. Smallweed, wrought up to the highest pitch by his own eloquence, actually throws Judy at her grandmother in default of anything else, by butting that young virgin at the old lady with such force as he can muster, and then dropping into his chair in a heap.</p><p >“Shake me up, somebody, if you'll be so good,” says the voice from within the faintly struggling bundle into which he has collapsed. “I have come to look after the property. Shake me up; and call in the police on duty at the next house, to be explained to about the property. My solicitor will be here presently to protect the property. Transportation or the gallows for anybody who shall touch the property!” As his dutiful grandchildren set him up, panting, and put him through the usual restorative process of shaking and punching, he still repeats like an echo, “the—the property! The property!—property!”</p><p >Mr. Weevle and Mr. Guppy look at each other; the former as having relinquished the whole affair; the latter with a discomfited countenance, as having entertained some lingering expectations yet. But there is nothing to be done in opposition to the Smallweed interest. Mr. Tulkinghorn's clerk comes down from his official pew in the chambers, to mention to the police that Mr. Tulkinghorn is answerable for its being all correct about the next of kin, and that the papers and effects will be formally taken possession of in due time and course. Mr. Smallweed is at once permitted so far to assert his supremacy as to be carried on a visit of sentiment into the next house, and upstairs into Miss Flite's deserted room, where he looks like a hideous bird of prey newly added to her aviary.</p><p >The arrival of this unexpected heir soon taking wind in the court, still makes good for the Sol, and keeps the court upon its mettle. Mrs. Piper and Mrs. Perkins think it hard upon the young man if there really is no will, and consider that a handsome present ought to be made him out of the estate. Young Piper and Young Perkins, as members of that restless juvenile circle which is the terror of the foot-passengers in Chancery Lane, crumble into ashes behind the pump and under the archway, all day long; where wild yells and hootings take place over their remains. Little Swills and Miss M. Melvilleson enter into affable conversation with their patrons, feeling that these unusual occurrences level the barriers between professionals and non-professionals. Mr. Bogsby puts up “The popular song of KING DEATH! with chorus by the whole strength of the company,” as the great Harmonic feature of the week; and announces in the bill that “J. G. B. is induced to do so at a considerable extra expense, in consequence of a wish which has been very generally expressed at the bar by a large body of respectable individuals and in homage to a late melancholy event which has aroused so much sensation.” There is one point connected with the deceased, upon which the court is particularly anxious; namely that the fiction of a full-sized coffin should be preserved, though there is so little to put in it. Upon the undertaker's stating in the Sol's bar in the course of the day, that he has received orders to construct “a six-footer,” the general solicitude is much relieved, and it is considered that Mr. Smallweed's conduct does him great honour.</p><p >Out of the court, and a long way out of it, there is considerable
<pb xml:id="p329"/>
excitement too; for men of science and philosophy come to look, and carriages set down doctors at the corner who arrive with the same intent, and there is more learned talk about inflammable gases and phosphuretted hydrogen than the court has ever imagined. Some of these authorities (of course the wisest) hold with indignation that the deceased had no business to die in the alleged manner; and being reminded by other authorities of a certain inquiry into the evidence for such deaths, reprinted in the sixth volume of the Philosophical Transactions; and also of a book not quite unknown, on English Medical Jurisprudence; and likewise of the Italian case of the Countess Cornelia Baudi as set forth in detail by one Bianchini, prebendary of Verona, who wrote a scholarly work or so, and was occasionally heard of in his time as having gleams of reason in him; and also of the testimony of Messrs. Foderé and Mere, two pestilent Frenchmen who <hi rend="italics">would</hi> investigate the subject; and further, of the corroborative testimony of Monsieur Le Cat, a rather celebrated French surgeon once upon a time, who had the unpoliteness to live in a house where such a case occurred, and even to write an account of it;—still they regard the late Mr. Krook's obstinacy, in going out of the world by any such byeway, as wholly unjustifiable and personally offensive. The less the court understands of all this, the more the court likes it; and the greater enjoyment it has in the stock in trade of the Sol's Arms. Then, there comes the artist of a picture newspaper, with a foreground and figures ready drawn for anything, from a wreck on the Cornish coast to a review in Hyde Park, or a meeting at Manchester,—and in Mrs. Perkins's own room, memorable evermore, he then and there throws in upon the block, Mr. Krook's house, as large as life; in fact, considerably larger, making a very Temple of it. Similarly, being permitted to look in at the door of the fatal chamber, he depicts that apartment as three quarters of a mile long, by fifty yards high; at which the court is particularly charmed. All this time, the two gentlemen before mentioned pop in and out of every house, and assist at the philosophical disputations,—go everywhere, and listen to everybody,—and yet are always diving into the Sol's parlour, and writing with the ravenous little pens on the tissue-paper.</p><p >At last come the coroner and his inquiry, like as before, except that the coroner cherishes this case as being out of the common way, and tells the gentlemen of the Jury, in his private capacity, that “that would seem to be an unlucky house next door, gentlemen, a destined house; but so we sometimes find it, and these are mysteries we can't account for!” After which the six-footer comes into action, and is much admired.</p><p >In all these proceedings Mr. Guppy has so slight a part, except when he gives his evidence, that he is moved on like a private individual, and can only haunt the secret house on the outside; where he has the mortification of seeing Mr. Smallweed padlocking the door, and of bitterly knowing himself to be shut out. But before these proceedings draw to a close, that is to say, on the night next after the catastrophe, Mr. Guppy has a thing to say that must be said to Lady Dedlock.</p><p >For which reason, with a sinking heart, and with that hangdog sense of guilt upon him, which dread and watching, enfolded in the Sol's Arms, have produced, the young man of the name of Guppy presents himself at the town mansion at about seven o'clock in the evening, and requests
<pb xml:id="p330"/>
to see her ladyship. Mercury replies that she is going out to dinner; don't he see the carriage at the door? Yes, he does see the carriage at the door; but he wants to see my lady too.</p><p >Mercury is disposed, as he will presently declare to a fellow gentleman in waiting, “to pitch into the young man;” but his instructions are positive. Therefore he sulkily supposes that the young man must come up into the library. There he leaves the young man in a large room, not over-light, while he makes report of him.</p><p >Mr. Guppy looks into the shade in all directions, discovering everywhere a certain charred and whitened little heap of coal or wood. Presently he hears a rustling. Is it—? No, it's no ghost; but fair flesh and blood, most brilliantly dressed.</p><p >“I have to beg your ladyship's pardon,” Mr. Guppy stammers, very downcast. “This is an inconvenient time——”</p><p >“I told you, you could come at any time.” She takes a chair, looking straight at him as on the last occasion.</p><p >“Thank your ladyship. Your ladyship is very affable.”</p><p >“You can sit down.” There is not much affability in her tone.</p><p >“I don't know, your ladyship, that it's worth while my sitting down and detaining you, for I—I have not got the letters that I mentioned when I had the honor of waiting on your ladyship.”</p><p >“Have you come merely to say so?”</p><p >“Merely to say so, your ladyship.” Mr. Guppy, besides being depressed, disappointed, and uneasy, is put at a further disadvantage by the splendour and beauty of her appearance. She knows its influence perfectly; has studied it too well to miss a grain of its effect on any one. As she looks at him so steadily and coldly, he not only feels conscious that he has no guide, in the least perception of what is really the complexion of her thoughts; but also that he is being every moment, as it were, removed further and further from her.</p><p >She will not speak, it is plain. So he must.</p><p >“In short, your ladyship,” says Mr. Guppy, like a meanly penitent thief, “the person I was to have had the letters of, has come to a sudden end, and——” He stops. Lady Dedlock calmly finishes the sentence.</p><p >“And the letters are destroyed with the person?”</p><p >Mr. Guppy would say no, if he could—as he is unable to hide.</p><p >“I believe so, your ladyship.”</p><p >If he could see the least sparkle of relief in her face now? No, he could see no such thing, even if that brave outside did not utterly put him away, and he were not looking beyond it and about it.</p><p >He falters an awkward excuse or two for his failure.</p><p >“Is this all you have to say?” inquires Lady Dedlock, having heard him out—or as nearly out as he can stumble.</p><p >Mr. Guppy thinks that's all.</p><p >“You had better be sure that you wish to say nothing more to me; this being the last time you will have the opportunity.”</p><p >Mr. Guppy is quite sure. And indeed he has no such wish at present, by any means.</p><p >“That is enough. I will dispense with excuses. Good evening to you!” and she rings for Mercury to show the young man of the name of Guppy out.</p><pb  xml:id="p331"/><p >But in that house, in that same moment, there happens to be an old man of the name of Tulkinghorn. And that old man, coming with his quiet footstep to the library, has his hand at that moment on the handle of the door—comes in—and comes face to face with the young man as he is leaving the room.</p><p >One glance between the old man and the lady; and for an instant the blind that is always down flies up. Suspicion, eager and sharp, looks out. Another instant; close again.</p><p >“I beg your pardon, Lady Dedlock. I beg your pardon a thousand times. It is so very unusual to find you here at this hour. I supposed the room was empty. I beg your pardon!”</p><p >“Stay!” She negligently calls him back. “Remain here, I beg. I am going out to dinner. I have nothing more to say to this young man!”</p><p >The disconcerted young man bows, as he goes out, and cringingly hopes that Mr. Tulkinghorn of the Fields is well. </p><p >“Aye, aye?” says the lawyer, looking at him from under his bent brows; though he has no need to look again—not he. “From Kenge and Carboy's, surely?”</p><p >“Kenge and Carboy's, Mr. Tulkinghorn. Name of Guppy, sir.”</p><p >“To be sure. Why, thank you, Mr. Guppy, I am very well!”</p><p >“Happy to hear it, sir. You can't be too well, sir, for the credit of the profession.”</p><p >“Thank you, Mr. Guppy!”</p><p >Mr. Guppy sneaks away. Mr. Tulkinghorn, such a foil in his old-fashioned rusty black to Lady Dedlock's brightness, hands her down the staircase to her carriage. He returns rubbing his chin, and rubs it a good deal in the course of the evening.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXIV. <lb/> A TURN OF THE SCREW.</head><p >“Now, what,” says Mr. George, “may this be? Is it blank cartridge, or ball? A flash in the pan, or a shot?”</p><p >An open letter is the subject of the trooper's speculations, and it seems to perplex him mightily. He looks at it at arm's length, brings it close to him, holds it in his right hand, holds it in his left hand, reads it with his head on this side, with his head on that side, contracts his eyebrows, elevates them; still, cannot satisfy himself. He smooths it out upon the table with his heavy palm, and thoughtfully walking up and down the gallery, makes a halt before it every now and then, to come upon it with a fresh eye. Even that won't do. “Is it,” Mr. George still muses, “blank cartridge or ball?”</p><p >Phil Squod, with the aid of a brush and paint-pot, is employed in the distance whitening the targets; softly whistling, in quick-march time, and in drum-and-fife manner, that he must and he will go back again to the girl he left behind him.</p><pb  xml:id="p332"/><p >“Phil!” The trooper beckons as he calls him.</p><p >Phil approaches in his usual way; sidling off at first as if he were going anywhere else, and then bearing down upon his commander like a bayonet-charge. Certain splashes of white show in high relief upon his dirty face, and he scrapes his one eyebrow with the handle of his brush.</p><p >“Attention, Phil! Listen to this.”</p><p >“Steady, commander, steady.”</p><p >“ ‘Sir. Allow me to remind you (though there is no legal necessity for my doing so, as you are aware) that the bill at two months’ date, drawn on yourself by Mr. Matthew Bagnet, and by you accepted, for the sum of ninety-seven pounds four shillings and ninepence, will become due tomorrow, when you will please be prepared to take up the same on presentation. Yours, JOSHUA SMALLWEED.’ — What do you make of that, Phil?”</p><p >“Mischief, guv'ner.”</p><p >“Why?”</p><p >“I think,” replies Phil, after pensively tracing out a cross-wrinkle in his forehead with the brush-handle, “that mischeevious consequences is always meant when money's asked for.”</p><p >“Lookye, Phil,” says the trooper, sitting on the table. “First and last, I have paid, I may say, half as much again as this principal, in interest and one thing and another.”</p><p >Phil intimates, by sidling back a pace or two, with a very unaccountable wrench of his wry face, that he does not regard the transaction as being made more promising by this incident.</p><p >“And lookye further, Phil,” says the trooper, staying his premature conclusions with a wave of his hand. “There has always been an understanding that this bill was to be what they call Renewed. And it has been renewed, no end of times. What do you say now?”</p><p >“I say that I think the times is come to a end at last.”</p><p >“You do? Humph! I am much of the same mind myself.”</p><p >“Joshua Smallweed is him that was brought here in a chair?”</p><p >“The same.”</p><p >“Guv'ner,” says Phil, with exceeding gravity, “he's a leech in his dispositions, he's a screw and a wice in his actions, a snake in his twistings, and a lobster in his claws.”</p><p >Having thus expressively uttered his sentiments, Mr. Squod, after waiting a little to ascertain if any further remark be expected of him, gets back, by his usual series of movements, to the target he has in hand; and vigorously signifies, through his former musical medium, that he must and he will return to that ideal young lady. George having folded the letter walks in that direction.</p><p >“There <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a way, commander,” says Phil, looking cunningly at him, “of settling this.”</p><p >“Paying the money, I suppose? I wish I could.”</p><p >Phil shakes his head. “No, guv'ner, no; not so bad as that. There <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a way,” says Phil, with a highly artistic turn of his brush—“what I'm a doing at present.”</p><p >“Whitewashing?”</p><p >Phil nods.</p><p >“A pretty way that would be! Do you know what would become
<pb xml:id="p333"/>
of the Bagnets in that case? Do you know they would be ruined to pay off my old scores? <hi rend="italics">You're</hi> a moral character,” says the trooper, eyeing him in his large way with no small indignation, “upon my life you are, Phil!”</p><p >Phil, on one knee at the target, is in course of protesting earnestly, though not without many allegorical scoops of his brush, and smoothings of the white surface round the rim with his thumb, that he had forgotten the Bagnet responsibility, and would not so much as injure a hair of the head of any member of that worthy family, when steps are audible in the long passage without, and a cheerful voice is heard to wonder whether George is at home. Phil, with a look at his master, hobbles up, saying, “Here's the guv'ner, Mrs. Bagnet! Here he is!” and the old girl herself, accompanied by Mr. Bagnet, appears.</p><p >The old girl never appears in walking trim, in any season of the year, without a grey cloth cloak, coarse and much worn but very clean, which is, undoubtedly, the identical garment rendered so interesting to Mr. Bagnet by having made its way home to Europe from another quarter of the globe, in company with Mrs. Bagnet and an umbrella. The latter faithful appendage is also invariably a part of the old girl's presence out of doors. It is of no color known in this life, and has a corrugated wooden crook for a handle, with a metallic object let into its prow or beak, resembling a little model of a fan-light over a street door, or one of the oval glasses out of a pair of spectacles: which ornamental object has not that tenacious capacity of sticking to its post that might be desired in an article long associated with the British army. The old girl's umbrella is of a flabby habit of waist, and seems to be in need of stays—an appearance that is possibly referable to its having served, through a series of years, at home as a cupboard, and on journeys as a carpet bag. She never puts it up, having the greatest reliance on her well-proved cloak with its capacious hood; but generally uses the instrument as a wand with which to point out joints of meat or bunches of greens in marketing, or to arrest the attention of tradesmen by a friendly poke. Without her market-basket, which is a sort of wicker well with two flapping lids, she never stirs abroad. Attended by these her trusty companions, therefore, her honest sunburnt face looking cheerily out of a rough straw bonnet, Mrs. Bagnet now arrives, fresh-colored and bright, in George's Shooting Gallery.</p><p >“Well, George, old fellow,” says she, “and how do <hi rend="italics">you</hi> do, this sunshiny morning?”</p><p >Giving him a friendly shake of the hand, Mrs. Bagnet draws a long breath after her walk, and sits down to enjoy a rest. Having a faculty, matured on the tops of baggage-wagons, and in other such positions, of resting easily anywhere, she perches on a rough bench, unties her bonnet-strings, pushes back her bonnet, crosses her arms, and looks perfectly comfortable.</p><p >Mr. Bagnet, in the mean time, has shaken hands with his old comrade, and with Phil: on whom Mrs. Bagnet likewise bestows a good-humoured nod and smile.</p><p >“Now, George,” says Mrs. Bagnet, briskly, “here we are, Lignum and myself;” she often speaks of her husband by this appellation, on account, as it is supposed, of Lignum Vitæ having been his old regimental
<pb xml:id="p334"/>
nickname when they first became acquainted, in compliment to the extreme hardness and toughness of his physiognomy; “just looked in, we have, to make it all correct as usual about that security. Give him the new bill to sign, George, and he'll sign it like a man.”</p><p >“I was coming to you this morning,” observes the trooper, reluctantly.</p><p >“Yes, we thought you'd come to us this morning, but we turned out early, and left Woolwich, the best of boys, to mind his sisters, and came to you instead—as you see! For Lignum, he's tied so close now, and gets so little exercise, that a walk does him good. But what's the matter, George?” asks Mrs. Bagnet, stopping in her cheerful talk. “You don't look yourself.”</p><p >“I am not quite myself,” returns the trooper; “I have been a little put out, Mrs. Bagnet.”</p><p >Her quick bright eye catches the truth directly. “George!” holding up her forefinger. “Don't tell me there's anything wrong about that security of Lignum's! Don't do it, George, on account of the children!”</p><p >The trooper looks at her with a troubled visage.</p><p >“George,” says Mrs. Bagnet, using both her arms for emphasis, and occasionally bringing down her open hands upon her knees. “If you have allowed anything wrong to come to that security of Lignum's, and if you have let him in for it, and if you have put us in danger of being sold up—and I see sold up in your face, George, as plain as print—you have done a shameful action, and have deceived us cruelly. I tell you, cruelly, George. There!”</p><p >Mr. Bagnet, otherwise as immoveable as a pump or a lamp-post, puts his large right hand on the top of his bald head, as if to defend it from a shower-bath, and looks with great uneasiness at Mrs. Bagnet.</p><p >“George!” says that old girl. “I wonder at you! George, I am ashamed of you! George, I couldn't have believed you would have done it! I always knew you to be a rolling stone that gathered no moss; but I never thought you would have taken away what little moss there was for Bagnet and the children to lie upon. You know what a hardworking, steady-going chap he is. You know what Quebec and Malta and Woolwich are—and I never did think you would, or could, have had the heart to serve us so. O George!” Mrs. Bagnet gathers up her cloak to wipe her eyes on, in a very genuine manner, “How could you do it?”</p><p >Mrs. Bagnet ceasing, Mr. Bagnet removes his hand from his head as if the shower-bath were over, and looks disconsolately at Mr. George; who has turned quite white, and looks distressfully at the grey cloak and straw bonnet.</p><p >“Mat,” says the trooper, in a subdued voice, addressing him, but still looking at his wife; “I am sorry you take it so much to heart, because I do hope it's not so bad as that comes to. I certainly have, this morning, received this letter;” which he reads aloud; “but I hope it may be set right yet. As to a rolling stone, why, what you say is true. I <hi rend="italics">am</hi> a rolling stone; and I never rolled in anybody's way, I fully believe, that I rolled the least good to. But it's impossible for an old vagabond comrade to like your wife and family better than <hi rend="italics">I</hi> like 'em, Mat, and I trust you'll look upon me as forgivingly as you can. Don't think I've kept anything from you. I haven't had the letter more than a quarter of an hour.”</p><pb  xml:id="p335"/><p >“Old girl!” murmurs Mr. Bagnet, after a short silence, “will you tell him my opinion?”</p><p >“Oh! Why didn't he marry,” Mrs. Bagnet answers, half laughing and half crying, “Joe Pouch's widder in North America? Then he wouldn't have got himself into these troubles.”</p><p >“The old girl,” says Mr. Bagnet, “puts it correct—why didn't you?”</p><p >“Well, she has a better husband by this time, I hope,” returns the trooper. “Anyhow, here I stand, this present day, <hi rend="italics">not</hi> married to Joe Pouch's widder. What shall I do? You see all I have got about me. It's not mine; it's yours. Give the word, and I'll sell off every morsel. If I could have hoped it would have brought in nearly the sum wanted, I'd have sold all long ago. Don't believe that I'll leave you or yours in the lurch, Mat. I'd sell myself first. I only wish,” says the trooper, giving himself a disparaging blow in the chest, “that I knew of anyone who'd buy such a second-hand piece of old stores.”</p><p >“Old girl,” murmurs Mr. Bagnet, “give him another bit of my mind.”</p><p >“George,” says the old girl, “you are not so much to be blamed, on full consideration, except for ever taking this business without the means.”</p><p >“And that was like me!” observes the penitent trooper, shaking his head. “Like me, I know.”</p><p >“Silence! The old girl,” says Mr. Bagnet, “is correct—in her way of giving my opinions—hear me out!”</p><p >“That was when you never ought to have asked for the security, George, and when you never ought to have got it, all things considered. But what's done can't be undone. You are always an honourable and straight-forward fellow, as far as lays in your power, though a little flighty. On the other hand, you can't admit but what it's natural in us to be anxious, with such a thing hanging over our heads. So forget and forgive all round, George. Come! Forget and forgive all round!”</p><p >Mrs. Bagnet giving him one of her honest hands, and giving her husband the other, Mr. George gives each of them one of his, and holds them while he speaks.</p><p >“I do assure you both, there's nothing I wouldn't do to discharge this obligation. But whatever I have been able to scrape together, has gone every two months in keeping it up. We have lived plainly enough here, Phil and I. But the Gallery don't quite do what was expected of it, and it's not—in short, it's not the Mint. It was wrong in me to take it? Well, so it was. But I was in a manner drawn into that step, and I thought it might steady me, and set me up, and you'll try to overlook my having such expectations, and upon my soul, I am very much obliged to you, and very much ashamed of myself.” With these concluding words, Mr. George gives a shake to each of the hands he holds, and, relinquishing them, backs a pace or two, in a broad-chested upright attitude, as if he had made a final confession, and were immediately going to be shot with all military honours.</p><p >“George, hear me out!” says Mr. Bagnet, glancing at his wife. “Old girl, go on!”</p><p >Mr. Bagnet, being in this singular manner heard out, has merely to observe that the letter must be attended to without any delay; that it is advisable that George and he should immediately wait on Mr. Smallweed in person; and that the primary object is to save and hold harmless
<pb xml:id="p336"/>
Mr. Bagnet, who had none of the money. Mr. George entirely assenting, puts on his hat, and prepares to march with Mr. Bagnet to the enemy's camp.</p><p >“Don't you mind a woman's hasty word, George,” says Mrs. Bagnet, patting him on the shoulder. “I trust my old Lignum to you, and I am sure you'll bring him through it.”</p><p >The trooper returns, that this is kindly said, and that he <hi rend="italics">will</hi> bring Lignum through it somehow. Upon which Mrs. Bagnet, with her cloak, basket, and umbrella, goes home, bright-eyed again, to the rest of her family; and the comrades sally forth on the hopeful errand of mollifying Mr. Smallweed.</p><p >Whether there are two people in England less likely to come satisfactorily out of any negotiation with Mr. Smallweed than Mr. George and Mr. Matthew Bagnet, may be very reasonably questioned. Also, notwithstanding their martial appearance, broad square shoulders, and heavy tread, whether there are, within the same limits, two more simple and unaccustomed children, in all the Smallweedy affairs of life. As they proceed with great gravity through the streets towards the region of Mount Pleasant, Mr. Bagnet, observing his companion to be thoughtful, considers it a friendly part to refer to Mrs. Bagnet's late sally.</p><p >“George, you know the old girl—she's as sweet and as mild as milk. But touch her on the children—or myself—and she's off like gunpowder.”</p><p >“It does her credit, Mat!”</p><p >“George,” says Mr. Bagnet, looking straight before him, “the old girl—can't do anything—that don't do her credit. More or less. I never say so. Discipline must be maintained.”</p><p >“She's worth her weight in gold,” returns the trooper.</p><p >“In gold?” says Mr. Bagnet. “I'll tell you what. The old girl's weight—is twelve stone six. Would I take that weight—in any metal—<hi rend="italics">for</hi> the old girl? No. Why not? Because the old girl's metal is far more precious—than the preciousest metal. And she's <hi rend="italics">all</hi> metal!”</p><p >“You are right, Mat!”</p><p >“When she took me—and accepted of the ring—she 'listed under me and the children—heart and head; for life. She's that earnest,” says Mr. Bagnet, “and that true to her colours—that, touch us with a finger—and she turns out—and stands to her arms. If the old girl fires wide—once in a way—at the call of duty—look over it, George. For she's loyal!”</p><p >“Why bless her, Mat!” returns the trooper, “I think the higher of her for it!”</p><p >“You are right!” says Mr. Bagnet, with the warmest enthusiasm, though without relaxing the rigidity of a single muscle. “Think as high of the old girl—as the rock of Gibraltar—and still you'll be thinking low—of such merits. But I never own to it before her. Discipline must be maintained.”</p><p >These encomiums bring them to Mount Pleasant, and to Grandfather Smallweed's house. The door is opened by the perennial Judy, who, having surveyed them from top to toe with no particular favor, but indeed with a malignant sneer, leaves them standing there, while she consults the oracle as to their admission. The oracle may be inferred to
<pb xml:id="p337"/>
give consent, from the circumstance of her returning with the words on her honey lips “that they can come in if they want to it.” Thus privileged they come in, and find Mr. Smallweed with his feet in the drawer of his chair as if it were a paper footbath, and Mrs. Smallweed obscured with the cushion like a bird that is not to sing.</p><p >“My dear friend,” says Grandfather Smallweed, with those two lean, affectionate arms of his stretched forth. “How de do? How de do? Who is our friend, my dear friend?”</p><p >“Why this,” returns George, not able to be very conciliatory at first, “is Matthew Bagnet, who has obliged me in that matter of ours, you know.”</p><p >“Oh! Mr. Bagnet? Surely!” The old man looks at him under his hand. “Hope you're well, Mr. Bagnet? Fine man, Mr. George! Military air, sir!”</p><p >No chairs being offered, Mr. George brings one forward for Bagnet, and one for himself. They sit down; Mr. Bagnet as if he had no power of bending himself, except at the hips for that purpose.</p><p >“Judy,” says Mr. Smallweed, “bring the pipe.”</p><p >“Why, I don't know,” Mr. George interposes, “that the young woman need give herself that trouble, for, to tell you the truth, I am not inclined to smoke it to-day.”</p><p >“Ain't you?” returns the old man. “Judy, bring the pipe.”</p><p >“The fact is, Mr. Smallweed,” proceeds George, “that I find myself in rather an unpleasant state of mind. It appears to me, sir, that your friend in the city has been playing tricks.”</p><p >“O dear no!” says Grandfather Smallweed. “He never does that!”</p><p >“Don't he? Well, I am glad to hear it, because I thought it might be <hi rend="italics">his</hi> doing. This, you know, I am speaking of. This letter.”</p><p >Grandfather Smallweed smiles in a very ugly way, in recognition of the letter.</p><p >“What does it mean?” asks Mr. George.</p><p >“Judy,” says the old man. “Have you got the pipe? Give it to me. Did you say what does it mean, my good friend?”</p><p >“Aye! Now, come, come, you know, Mr. Smallweed,” urges the trooper, constraining himself to speak as smoothly and confidentially as he can, holding the open letter in one hand, and resting the broad knuckles of the other on his thigh; “a good lot of money has passed between us, and we are face to face at the present moment, and are both well aware of the understanding there has always been. I am prepared to do the usual thing which I have done regularly, and to keep this matter going. I never got a letter like this from you before, and I have been a little put about by it this morning; because here's my friend Matthew Bagnet, who, you know, had none of the money—”</p><p >“I <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> know it, you know,” says the old man, quietly.</p><p >“Why, con-found you—it, I mean—I tell you so; don't I?”</p><p >“Oh, yes, you tell me so,” returns Grandfather Smallweed. “But I don't know it.”</p><p >“Well!” says the trooper, swallowing his fire. “<hi rend="italics">I</hi> know it.”</p><p >Mr. Smallweed replies with excellent temper, “Ah! that's quite another thing!” And adds, “but it don't matter. Mr. Bagnet's situation is all one, whether or no.”</p><pb  xml:id="p338"/><p >The unfortunate George makes a great effort to arrange the affair comfortably, and to propitiate Mr. Smallweed by taking him upon his own terms.</p><p >“That's just what I mean. As you say, Mr. Smallweed, here's Matthew Bagnet liable to be fixed whether or no. Now, you see, that makes his good lady very uneasy in her mind, and me too; for, whereas I'm a harum-scarum sort of a good-for-nought, that more kicks than half-pence come natural to, why he's a steady family man, don't you see? Now, Mr. Smallweed,” says the trooper, gaining confidence as he proceeds in this soldierly mode of doing business; “although you and I are good friends enough in a certain sort of a way, I am well aware that I can't ask you to let my friend Bagnet off entirely.”</p><p >“O dear, you are too modest. You can <hi rend="italics">ask</hi> me anything, Mr. George.” (There is an Ogreish kind of jocularity in Grandfather Smallweed to-day.)</p><p >“And you can refuse, you mean, eh? Or not you so much, perhaps, as your friend in the city? Ha ha ha!”</p><p >“Ha ha ha!” echoes Grandfather Smallweed. In such a very hard manner, and with eyes so particularly green, that Mr. Bagnet's natural gravity is much deepened by the contemplation of that venerable man.</p><p >“Come!” says the sanguine George, “I am glad to find we can be pleasant, because I want to arrange this pleasantly. Here's my friend Bagnet, and here am I. We'll settle the matter on the spot, if you please, Mr. Smallweed, in the usual way. And you'll ease my friend Bagnet's mind, and his family's mind, a good deal, if you'll just mention to him what our understanding is.”</p><p >Here some shrill spectre cries out in a mocking manner, “O good gracious! O!”—unless, indeed, it be the sportive Judy, who is found to be silent when the startled visitors look round, but whose chin has received a recent toss, expressive of derision and contempt. Mr. Bagnet's gravity becomes yet more profound.</p><p >“But I think you asked me, Mr. George;” old Smallweed, who all this time has had the pipe in his hand, is the speaker now; “I think you asked me, what did the letter mean?”</p><p >“Why, yes, I did,” returns the trooper, in his off-hand way: “but I don't care to know particularly, if it's all correct and pleasant.”</p><p >Mr. Smallweed, purposely balking himself in an aim at the trooper's head, throws the pipe on the ground and breaks it to pieces.</p><p >“That's what it means, my dear friend. I'll smash you. I'll crumble you. I'll powder you. Go to the devil!”</p><p >The two friends rise and look at one another. Mr. Bagnet's gravity has now attained its profoundest point.</p><p >“Go to the devil!” repeats the old man. “I'll have no more of your pipe-smokings and swaggerings. What? You're an independent dragoon, too! Go to my lawyer (you remember where; you have been there before), and show your independence now, will you? Come, my dear friend, there's a chance for you. Open the street door, Judy; put these blusterers out! Call in help if they don't go. Put 'em out!”</p><p >He vociferates this so loudly, that Mr. Bagnet, laying his hands on the shoulders of his comrade, before the latter can recover from his amazement, gets him on the outside of the street door; which is instantly slammed by the triumphant Judy. Utterly confounded, Mr. George
<pb xml:id="p339"/>
awhile stands looking at the knocker. Mr. Bagnet, in a perfect abyss of gravity, walks up and down before the little parlor window, like a sentry, and looks in, every time he passes; apparently revolving something in his mind.</p><p >“Come, Mat!” says Mr. George, when he has recovered himself, “we must try the lawyer. Now, what do you think of this rascal?”</p><p >Mr. Bagnet, stopping to take a farewell look into the parlor, replies, with one shake of his head directed at the interior, “If my old girl had been here—I'd have told him!” Having so discharged himself of the subject of his cogitations, he falls into step, and marches off with the trooper, shoulder to shoulder.</p><p >When they present themselves in Lincoln's Inn Fields, Mr. Tulkinghorn is engaged, and not to be seen. He is not at all willing to see them; for when they have waited a full hour, and the clerk, on his bell being rung, takes the opportunity of mentioning as much, he brings forth no more encouraging message than that Mr. Tulkinghorn has nothing to say to them, and they had better not wait. They do wait, however, with the perseverance of military tactics; and at last the bell rings again, and the client in possession comes out of Mr. Tulkinghorn's room.</p><p >The client is a handsome old lady; no other than Mrs. Rouncewell, housekeeper at Chesney Wold. She comes out of the sanctuary with a fair old-fashioned curtsey, and softly shuts the door. She is treated with some distinction there; for the clerk steps out of his pew to show her through the outer office, and to let her out. The old lady is thanking him for his attention, when she observes the comrades in waiting.</p><p >“I beg your pardon, sir, but I think those gentlemen are military?”</p><p >The clerk referring the question to them with his eye, and Mr. George not turning round from the almanack over the fire-place, Mr. Bagnet takes upon himself to reply, “Yes, ma'am. Formerly.”</p><p >“I thought so. I was sure of it. My heart warms, gentlemen, at the sight of you. It always does at the sight of such. God bless you, gentlemen! You'll excuse an old woman; but I had a son once who went for a soldier. A fine handsome youth he was, and good in his bold way, though some people did disparage him to his poor mother. I ask your pardon for troubling you, sir. God bless you, gentlemen!”</p><p >“Same to you, ma'am!” returns Mr. Bagnet, with right good will.</p><p >There is something very touching in the earnestness of the old lady's voice, and in the tremble that goes through her quaint old figure. But Mr. George is so occupied with the almanack over the fire-place (calculating the coming months by it perhaps), that he does not look round until she has gone away, and the door is closed upon her.</p><p >“George,” Mr. Bagnet gruffly whispers, when he does turn from there almanack at last. “Don't be cast down! ‘Why soldiers, why—should we be melancholly boys?’ Cheer up, my hearty!”</p><p >The clerk having now again gone in to say that they are still there and Mr. Tulkinghorn being heard to return with some irascibility, “Let 'em come in then!” they pass into the great room with the painted ceiling, and find him standing before the fire.</p><p >“Now, you men, what do you want? Serjeant, I told you the last time I saw you that I don't desire your company here.”</p><p >Serjeant replies—dashed within the last few minutes as to his usual
<pb xml:id="p340"/>
manner of speech, and even as to his usual carriage—that he has received this letter, has been to Mr. Smallweed about it, and has been referred there.</p><p >“I have nothing to say to you,” rejoins Mr. Tulkinghorn. “If you get into debt, you must pay your debts, or take the consequences. You have no occasion to come here to learn that, I suppose?”</p><p >Serjeant is sorry to say that he is not prepared with the money.</p><p >“Very well! Then the other man—this man, if this is he—must pay it for you.”</p><p >Serjeant is sorry to add that the other man is not prepared with the money either.</p><p >“Very well! Then you must pay it between you, or you must both be sued for it, and both suffer. You have had the money and must refund it. You are not to pocket other people's pounds, shillings, and pence, and escape scot free.”</p><p >The lawyer sits down in his easy chair and stirs the fire. Mr. George hopes he will have the goodness to—</p><p >“I tell you, Serjeant, I have nothing to say to you. I don't like your associates, and don't want you here. This matter is not at all in my course of practice, and is not in my office. Mr. Smallweed is good enough to offer these affairs to me, but they are not in my way. You must go to Melchisedech's in Clifford's Inn.”</p><p >“I must make an apology to you, sir,” says Mr. George, “for pressing myself upon you with so little encouragement—which is almost as unpleasant to me as it can be to you; but would you let me say a private word to you?”</p><p >Mr. Tulkinghorn rises with his hands in his pockets, and walks into one of the window recesses. “Now! I have no time to waste.” In the midst of his perfect assumption of indifference, he directs a sharp look at the trooper; taking care to stand with his own back to the light, and to have the other with his face towards it.</p><p >“Well, sir,” says Mr. George, “this man with me is the other party implicated in this unfortunate affair—nominally, only nominally—and my sole object is to prevent his getting into trouble on my account. He is a most respectable man with a wife and family; formerly in the Royal Artillery—.”</p><p >“My friend, I don't care a pinch of snuff for the whole Royal Artillery establishment—officers, men, tumbrils, wagons, horses, guns, and ammunition.”</p><p >“ 'Tis likely, sir. But I care a good deal for Bagnet and his wife and family being injured on my account. And if I could bring them through this matter, I should have no help for it but to give up without any other consideration, what you wanted of me the other day.”</p><p >“Have you got it here?”</p><p >“I have got it here, sir.”</p><p >“Serjeant,” the lawyer proceeds in his dry, passionless manner, far more hopeless in the dealing with, than any amount of vehemence, “make up your mind while I speak to you, for this is final. After I have finished speaking I have closed the subject, and I won't re-open it. Understand that. You can leave here, for a few days, what you say you have brought here, if you choose; you can take it away at once, if you choose. In case you choose to leave it here, I can do this for you—I can replace this
<pb xml:id="p341"/>
matter on its old footing, and I can go so far besides as to give you a written undertaking that this man Bagnet shall never be troubled in any way until you have been proceeded against to the utmost—that your means shall be exhausted before the creditor looks to his. This is in fact all but freeing him. Have you decided?”</p><p >The trooper puts his hand into his breast, and answers with a long breath, “I must do it, sir.”</p><p >So Mr. Tulkinghorn, putting on his spectacles, sits down and writes the undertaking; which he slowly reads and explains to Bagnet, who has all this time been staring at the ceiling, and who puts his hand on his bald head again, under this new verbal shower-bath, and seems exceedingly in need of the old girl through whom to express his sentiments. The trooper then takes from his breast-pocket a folded paper, which he lays with an unwilling hand at the lawyer's elbow. “ 'Tis only a letter of instructions, sir. The last I ever had from him.”</p><p >Look at a millstone, Mr. George, for some change in its expression, and you will find it quite as soon as in the face of Mr. Tulkinghorn when he opens and reads the letter! He re-folds it, and lays it in his desk, with a countenance as imperturbable as Death.</p><p >Nor has he anything more to say or do, but to nod once in the same frigid and discourteous manner, and to say briefly, “You can go. Show these men out, there!” Being shown out, they repair to Mr. Bagnet's residence to dine.</p><p >Boiled beef and greens constitute the day's variety on the former repast of boiled pork and greens; and Mrs. Bagnet serves out the meal in the same way, and seasons it with the best of temper: being that rare sort of old girl that she receives Good to her arms without a hint that it might be Better; and catches light from any little spot of darkness near her. The spot on this occasion is the darkened brow of Mr. George; he is unusually thoughtful and depressed. At first Mrs. Bagnet trusts to the combined endearments of Quebec and Malta to restore him; but finding those young ladies sensible that their existing Bluffy is not the Bluffy of their usual frolicsome acquaintance, she winks off the light infantry, and leaves him to deploy at leisure on the open ground of the domestic hearth.</p><p >But he does not. He remains in close order, clouded and depressed. During the lengthy cleaning up and pattening process, when he and Mr. Bagnet are supplied with their pipes, he is no better than he was at dinner. He forgets to smoke, looks at the fire and ponders, lets his pipe out, fills the breast of Mr. Bagnet with perturbation and dismay, by showing that he has no enjoyment of tobacco.</p><p >Therefore when Mrs. Bagnet at last appears, rosy from the invigorating pail, and sits down to her work, Mr. Bagnet growls “Old girl!” and winks monitions to her to find out what's the matter.</p><p >“Why, George!” says Mrs. Bagnet, quietly threading her needle. “How low you are!”</p><p >“Am I? Not good company? Well, I am afraid I am not.”</p><p >“He ain't at all like Bluffy, mother!” cries little Malta.</p><p >“Because he ain't well, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> think, mother!” adds Quebec.</p><p >“Sure that's a bad sign not to be like Bluffy, too!” returns the trooper, kissing the young damsels. “But it's true,” with a sigh—“true, I am afraid. These little ones are always right!”</p><pb  xml:id="p342"/><p >“George,” says Mrs. Bagnet, working busily, “if I thought you cross enough to think of anything that a shrill old soldier's wife—who could have bitten her tongue off afterwards, and ought to have done it almost—said this morning, I don't know what I shouldn't say to you now.”</p><p >“My kind soul of a darling,” returns the trooper. “Not a morsel of it.”</p><p >“Because really and truly, George, what I said and meant to say, was that I trusted Lignum to you, and was sure you'd bring him through it. And you <hi rend="italics">have</hi> brought him through it, noble!”</p><p >“Thank'ee, my dear,” says George. “I am glad of your good opinion.”</p><p >In giving Mrs. Bagnet's hand, with her work in it, a friendly shake—for she took her seat beside him—the trooper's attention is attracted to her face. After looking at it for a little while as she plies her needle, he looks to young Woolwich, sitting on his stool in the corner, and beckons that fifer to him.</p><p >“See there, my boy,” says George, very gently smoothing the mother's hair with his hand, “there's a good loving forehead for you! All bright with love of you, my boy. A little touched by the sun and the weather through following your father about and taking care of you, but as fresh and wholesome as a ripe apple on a tree.”</p><p >Mr. Bagnet's face expresses, so far as in its wooden material lies, the highest approbation and acquiescence.</p><p >“The time will come, my boy,” pursues the trooper, “when this hair of your mother's will be grey, and this forehead all crossed and re-crossed with wrinkles—and a fine old lady she'll be then. Take care, while you are young, that you can think in those days, ‘<hi rend="italics">I</hi> never whitened a hair of her dear head, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> never marked a sorrowful line in her face!’ For of all the many things that you can think of when you are a man, you had better have <hi rend="italics">that</hi> by you, Woolwich!”</p><p >Mr. George concludes by rising from his chair, seating the boy beside his mother in it, and saying, with something of a hurry about him, that he'll smoke his pipe in the street a bit.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXV. <lb/> ESTHER'S NARRATIVE.</head><p >I LAY ill through several weeks, and the usual tenor of my life became like an old remembrance. But, this was not the effect of time, so much as of the change in all my habits, made by the helplessness and inaction of a sick room. Before I had been confined to it many days, everything else seemed to have retired into a remote distance, where there was little or no separation between the various stages of my life which had been really divided by years. In falling ill, I seemed to have crossed a dark lake, and to have left all my experiences, mingled together by the great distance, on the healthy shore.</p><p >My housekeeping duties, though at first it caused me great anxiety to think that they were unperformed, were soon as far off as the oldest of the old duties at Greenleaf, or the summer afternoons when I went home from school with my portfolio under my arm, and my childish shadow at
<pb xml:id="p343"/>
my side, to my godmother's house. I had never known before how short life really was, and into how small a space the mind could put it.</p><p >While I was very ill, the way in which these divisions of time became confused with one another, distressed my mind exceedingly. At once a child, an elder girl, and the little woman I had been so happy as, I was not only oppressed by cares and difficulties adapted to each station, but by the great perplexity of endlessly trying to reconcile them. I suppose that few who have not been in such a condition can quite understand what I mean, or what painful unrest arose from this source.</p><p >For the same reason I am almost afraid to hint at that time in my disorder—it seemed one long night, but I believe there were both nights and days in it—when I laboured up colossal staircases, ever striving to reach the top, and ever turned, as I have seen a worm in a garden path, by some obstruction, and labouring again. I knew perfectly at intervals, and I think vaguely at most times, that I was in my bed; and I talked with Charley, and felt her touch, and knew her very well; yet I would find myself complaining “O more of these never-ending stairs, Charley,—more and more—piled up to the sky, I think!” and labouring on again.</p><p >Dare I hint at that worse time when, strung together somewhere in great black space, there was a flaming necklace, or ring, or starry circle of some kind, of which <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was one of the beads! And when my only prayer was to be taken off from the rest, and when it was such inexplicable agony and misery to be a part of the dreadful thing?</p><p >Perhaps the less I say of these sick experiences, the less tedious and the more intelligible I shall be. I do not recal them to make others unhappy, or because I am now the least unhappy in remembering them. It may be that if we knew more of such strange afflictions, we might be better able to alleviate their intensity.</p><p >The repose that succeeded, the long delicious sleep, the blissful rest, when in my weakness I was too calm to have any care for myself, and could have heard (or so I think now) that I was dying; with no other emotion than with a pitying love for those I left behind—this state can be perhaps more widely understood. I was in this state when I first shrunk from the light as it twinkled on me once more, and knew with a boundless joy for which no words are rapturous enough, that I should see again.</p><p >I had heard my Ada crying at the door, day and night; I had heard her calling to me that I was cruel and did not love her; I had heard her praying and imploring to be let in to nurse and comfort me, and to leave my bedside no more; but I had only said, when I could speak, “Never, my sweet girl, never!” and I had over and over again reminded Charley that she was to keep my darling from the room, whether I lived or died. Charley had been true to me in that time of need, and with her little hand and her great heart had kept the door fast.</p><p >But now, my sight strengthening, and the glorious light coming every day more fully and brightly on me, I could read the letters that my dear wrote to me every morning and evening, and could put them to my lips and lay my cheek upon them with no fear of hurting her. I could see my little maid, so tender and so careful, going about the two rooms setting every thing in order, and speaking cheerfully to Ada from the open window again. I could understand the stillness in the house, and the thoughtfulness
<pb xml:id="p344"/>
it expressed on the part of all those who had always been so good to me. I could weep in the exquisite felicity of my heart, and be as happy in my weakness as ever I had been in my strength.</p><p >By and by, my strength began to be restored. Instead of lying, with so strange a calmness, watching what was done for me, as if it were done for some one else whom I was quietly sorry for, I helped it a little, and so on to a little more and much more, until I became useful to myself, and interested, and attached to life again.</p><p >How well I remember the pleasant afternoon when I was raised in bed with pillows for the first time, to enjoy a great tea-drinking with Charley! The little creature—sent into the world, surely, to minister to the weak and sick—was so happy, and so busy, and stopped so often in her preparations to lay her head upon my bosom, and fondle me, and cry with joyful tears she was so glad, she was so glad! that I was obliged to say, “Charley, if you go on in this way, I must lie down again, my darling, for I am weaker than I thought I was!” So Charley became as quiet as a mouse, and took her bright face here and there, across and across the two rooms, out of the shade into the divine sunshine, and out of the sunshine into the shade, while I watched her peacefully. When all her preparations were concluded and the pretty tea-table with its little delicacies to tempt me, and its white cloth, and its flowers, and everything so lovingly and beautifully arranged for me by Ada down-stairs, was ready at the bed-side, I felt sure I was steady enough to say something to Charley that was not new to my thoughts.</p><p >First, I complimented Charley on the room; and indeed, it was so fresh and airy, so spotless and neat, that I could scarce believe I had been lying there so long. This delighted Charley, and her face was brighter than before.</p><p >“Yet, Charley,” said I looking round, “I miss something, surely, that I am accustomed to?”</p><p >Poor little Charley looked round too, and pretended to shake her head, as if there were nothing absent.</p><p >“Are the pictures all as they used to be?” I asked her.</p><p >“Every one of them, miss,” said Charley.</p><p >“And the furniture, Charley?”</p><p >“Except where I have moved it about, to make more room, miss.”</p><p >“And yet,” said I, “I miss some familiar object. Ah, I know what it is, Charley! It's the looking-glass.”</p><p >Charley got up from the table, making as if she had forgotten something, and went into the next room; and I heard her sob there.</p><p >I had thought of this very often. I was now certain of it. I could thank God that it was not a shock to me now. I called Charley back; and when she came—at first pretending to smile, but as she drew nearer to me, looking grieved—I took her in my arms, and said, “It matters very little, Charley. I hope I can do without my old face very well.</p><p >I was presently so far advanced as to be able to sit up in a great chair, and even giddily to walk into the adjoining room, leaning on Charley. The mirror was gone from its usual place in that room too; but what I had to bear, was none the harder to bear for that.</p><p >My guardian had throughout been earnest to visit me, and there was now
<pb xml:id="p345"/>
no good reason why I should deny myself that happiness. He came one morning; and when he first came in, could only hold me in his embrace, and say, “My dear, dear girl!” I had long known—who could know better!—what a deep fountain of affection and generosity his heart was; and was it not worth my trivial suffering and change to fill such a place in it? “O yes!” I thought. “He has seen me, and he loves me better than he did; he has seen me, and is even fonder of me than he was before; and what have I to mourn for!”</p><p >He sat down by me on the sofa, supporting me with his arm. For a little while he sat with his hand over his face, but when he removed it, fell into his usual manner. There never can have been, there never can be, a pleasanter manner.</p><p >“My little woman,” said he, “what a sad time this has been. Such an inflexible little woman, too, through all!”</p><p >“Only for the best, guardian,” said I.</p><p >“For the best?” he repeated, tenderly. “Of course, for the best. But here have Ada and I been perfectly forlorn and miserable; here has your friend Caddy been coming and going late and early; here has everyone about the house been utterly lost and dejected; here has even poor Rick been writing—to <hi rend="italics">me</hi> too—in his anxiety for you!”</p><p >I had read of Caddy in Ada's letters, but not of Richard. I told him so.</p><p >“Why no, my dear,” he replied. “I have thought it better not to mention it to her.”</p><p >“And you speak of his writing to <hi rend="italics">you,</hi>” said I, repeating his emphasis. “As if it were not natural for him to do so, guardian; as if he could write to a better friend!”</p><p >“He thinks he could, my love,” returned my guardian, “and to many a better. The truth is, he wrote to me under a sort of protest, while unable to write to you with any hope of an answer—wrote coldly, haughtily, distantly, resentfully. Well, dearest little woman, we must look forbearingly on it. He is not to blame. Jarndyce and Jarndyce has warped him out of himself, and perverted me in his eyes. I have known it do as bad deeds, and worse, many a time. If two angels could be concerned in it, I believe it would change their nature.”</p><p >“It has not changed yours, guardian.”</p><p >“Oh yes, it has, my dear,” he said, laughingly. “It has made the south wind easterly, I don't know how often. Rick mistrusts and suspects me—goes to lawyers, and is taught to mistrust and suspect me. Hears I have conflicting interests; claims clashing against his, and what not. Whereas, Heaven knows, that if I could get out of the mountains of Wiglomeration on which my unfortunate name has been so long bestowed (which I can't), or could level them by the extinction of my own original right (which I can't, either, and no human power ever can, anyhow, I believe, to such a pass have we got), I would do it this hour. I would rather restore to poor Rick his proper nature, than be endowed with all the money that dead suitors, broken, heart and soul, upon the wheel of Chancery, have left unclaimed with the Accountant-General—and that's money enough, my dear, to be cast into a pyramid, in memory of Chancery's transcendant wickedness.”</p><p >“Is it possible, guardian,” I asked, amazed, “that Richard can be suspicious of you?”</p><pb  xml:id="p346"/><p >“Ah, my love, my love,” he said, “it is in the subtle poison of such abuses to breed such diseases. His blood is infected, and objects lose their natural aspects in his sight. It is not <hi rend="italics">his</hi> fault.”</p><p >“But it is a terrible misfortune, guardian.”</p><p >“It is a terrible misfortune, little woman, to be ever drawn within the influences of Jarndyce and Jarndyce. I know none greater. By little and little he has been induced to trust in that rotten reed, and it communicates some portion of its rottenness to everything around him. But again, I say, with all my soul, we must be patient with poor Rick, and not blame him. What a troop of fine fresh hearts, like his, have I seen in my time turned by the same means!”</p><p >I could not help expressing something of my wonder and regret that his benevolent disinterested intentions had prospered so little.</p><p >“We must not say so, Dame Durden,” he cheerfully replied; “Ada is the happier, I hope; and that is much. I did think that I and both these young creatures might be friends, instead of distrustful foes, and that we might so far counteract the suit, and prove too strong for it. But it was too much to expect. Jarndyce and Jarndyce was the curtain of Rick's cradle.”</p><p >“But, guardian, may we not hope that a little experience will teach him what a false and wretched thing it is?”</p><p >“We <hi rend="italics">will</hi> hope so, my Esther,” said Mr. Jarndyce, “and that it may not teach him so too late. In any case we must not be hard on him. There are not many grown and matured men living while we speak, good men too, who, if they were thrown into this same court as suitors, would not be vitally changed and depreciated within three years—within two—within one. How can we stand amazed at poor Rick? A young man so unfortunate,” here he fell into a lower tone, as if he were thinking aloud, “cannot at first believe (who could?) that Chancery is what it is. He looks to it, flushed and fitfully, to do something with his interests, and bring them to some settlement. It procrastinates, disappoints, tries, tortures him; wears out his sanguine hopes and patience, thread by thread; but he still looks to it, and hankers after it, and finds his whole world treacherous and hollow. Well, well, well! Enough of this, my dear!”</p><p >He had supported me, as at first, all this time; and his tenderness was so precious to me, that I leaned my head upon his shoulder and loved him as if he had been my father. I resolved in my own mind in this little pause, by some means, to see Richard when I grew strong, and try to set him right.</p><p >“There are better subjects than these,” said my guardian, “for such a joyful time as the time of our dear girl's recovery. And I had a commission to broach one of them, as soon as I should begin to talk. When shall Ada come to see you, my love?”</p><p >I had been thinking of that too. A little in connexion with the absent mirrors, but not much; for I knew my loving girl would be changed by no change in my looks.</p><p >“Dear guardian,” said I, “as I have shut her out so long—though indeed, indeed, she is like the light to me——”</p><p >“I know it well, Dame Durden, well.”</p><p >He was so good, his touch expressed such endearing compassion and affection, and the tone of his voice carried such comfort into my heart,
<pb xml:id="p347"/>
that I stopped for a little while, quite unable to go on. “Yes, yes, you are tired,” said he. “Rest a little.”</p><p >“As I have kept Ada out so long,” I began afresh after a short while, “I think I should like to have my own way a little longer, guardian. It would be best to be away from here before I see her. If Charley and I were to go to some country lodging as soon as I can move, and if I had a week there, in which to grow stronger and to be revived by the sweet air, and to look forward to the happiness of having Ada with me again, I think it would be better for us.”</p><p >I hope it was not a poor thing in me to wish to be a little more used to my altered self, before I met the eyes of the dear girl I longed so ardently to see; but it is the truth. I did. He understood me, I was sure; but I was not afraid of that. If it were a poor thing, I knew he would pass it over.</p><p >“Our spoilt little woman,” said my guardian, “shall have her own way even in her inflexibility, though at the price, I know, of tears down-stairs. And see here! Here is Boythorn, heart of chivalry, breathing such ferocious vows as never were breathed on paper before, that if you don't go and occupy his whole house, he having already turned out of it expressly for that purpose, by Heaven and by earth he'll pull it down, and not leave one brick standing on another!”</p><p >And my guardian put a letter in my hand; without any ordinary beginning such as “My dear Jarndyce,” but rushing at once into the words, “I swear if Miss Summerson do not come down and take possession of my house, which I vacate for her this day at one o'clock, p.m.,” and then with the utmost seriousness, and in the most emphatic terms, going on to make the extraordinary declaration he had quoted. We did not appreciate the writer the less, for laughing heartily over it; and we settled that I should send him a letter of thanks on the morrow, and accept his offer. It was a most agreeable one to me; for of all the places I could have thought of, I should have liked to go to none so well as Chesney Wold.</p><p >“Now, little housewife,” said my guardian, looking at his watch, “I was strictly timed before I came up-stairs, for you must not be tired too soon; and my time has waned away to the last minute. I have one other petition. Little Miss Flite, hearing a rumour that you were ill, made nothing of walking down here—twenty miles, poor soul, in a pair of dancing shoes—to inquire. It was Heaven's mercy we were at home, or she would have walked back again.”</p><p >The old conspiracy to make me happy! Everybody seemed to be in it!</p><p >“Now, pet,” said my guardian, “if it would not be irksome to you to admit the harmless little creature one afternoon, before you save Boythorn's otherwise devoted house from demolition, I believe you would make her prouder and better pleased with herself than I—though my eminent name <hi rend="italics">is</hi> Jarndyce—could do in a lifetime.”</p><p >I have no doubt he knew there would be something in the simple image of the poor afflicted creature, that would fall like a gentle lesson on my mind at that time. I felt it as he spoke to me. I could not tell him heartily enough how ready I was to receive her. I had always pitied her; never so much as now. I had always been glad of my
<pb xml:id="p348"/>
little power to soothe her under her calamity; but never, never, half so glad before.</p><p >We arranged a time for Miss Flite to come out by the coach, and share my early dinner. When my guardian left me, I turned my face away upon my couch, and prayed to be forgiven if I, surrounded by such blessings, had magnified to myself the little trial that I had to undergo. The childish prayer of that old birthday, when I had aspired to be industrious, contented, and true-hearted, and to do some good to some one, and win some love to myself if I could, came back into my mind with a reproachful sense of all the happiness I had since enjoyed, and all the affectionate hearts that had been turned towards me. If I were weak now, what had I profited by those mercies? I repeated the old childish prayer in its old childish words, and found that its old peace had not departed from it.</p><p >My guardian now came every day. In a week or so more, I could walk about our rooms, and hold long talks with Ada from behind the window-curtain. Yet I never saw her; for I had not as yet the courage to look at the dear face, though I could have done so easily without her seeing me.</p><p >On the appointed day Miss Flite arrived. The poor little creature ran into my room quite forgetful of her usual dignity, and, crying from her very heart of hearts, “My dear Fitz Jarndyce!” fell upon my neck and kissed me twenty times.</p><p >“Dear me!” said she, putting her hand into her reticule, “I have nothing here but documents, my dear Fitz Jarndyce; I must borrow a pocket-handkerchief.”</p><p >Charley gave her one, and the good creature certainly made use of it, for she held it to her eyes with both hands, and sat so shedding tears for the next ten minutes.</p><p >“With pleasure, my dear Fitz Jarndyce,” she was careful to explain. “Not the least pain. Pleasure to see you well again. Pleasure at having the honor of being admitted to see you. I am so much fonder of you, my love, than of the Chancellor. Though I <hi rend="italics">do</hi> attend court regularly. By the by, my dear, mentioning pocket-handkerchiefs——”</p><p >Miss Flite here looked at Charley, who had been to meet her at the place where the coach stopped. Charley glanced at me, and looked unwilling to pursue the suggestion.</p><p >“Ve-ry right!” said Miss Flite, “ve-ry correct. Truly! Highly indiscreet of me to mention it; but my dear Miss Fitz Jarndyce, I am afraid I am at times (between ourselves, you wouldn't think it) a little—rambling you know,” said Miss Flite, touching her forehead. “Nothing more.”</p><p >“What were you going to tell me?” said I, smiling, for I saw she wanted to go on. “You have roused my curiosity, and now you must gratify it.”</p><p >Miss Flite looked to Charley for advice in this important crisis, who said, “If you please, ma'am, you had better tell then,” and therein gratified Miss Flite beyond measure.</p><p >“So sagacious, our young friend,” said she to me, in her mysterious way. “Diminutive. But ve-ry sagacious! Well, my dear, it's a pretty anecdote. Nothing more. Still I think it charming. Who should follow us down
<pb xml:id="p349"/>
the road from the coach, my dear, but a poor person in a very ungenteel bonnet——”</p><p >“Jenny, if you please, miss,” said Charley.</p><p >“Just so!” Miss Flite acquiesced with the greatest suavity. “Jenny. Ye-es! And what does she tell our young friend, but that there has been a lady with a veil inquiring at her cottage after my dear Fitz Jarndyce's health, and taking a handkerchief away with her as a little keepsake, merely because it was my amiable Fitz Jarndyce's! Now, you know, so very prepossessing in the lady with the veil!”</p><p >“If you please, miss,” said Charley, to whom I looked in some astonishment, “Jenny says that when her baby died, you left a handkerchief there, and that she put it away and kept it with the baby's little things. I think, if you please, partly because it was yours, miss, and partly because it had covered the baby.”</p><p >“Diminutive,” whispered Miss Flite, making a variety of motions about her own forehead to express intellect in Charley. “But ex-ceedingly sagacious! And so clear! My love, she's clearer than any Counsel I ever heard!”</p><p >“Yes, Charley,” I returned. “I remember it. Well?”</p><p >“Well, miss,” said Charley, “and that's the handkerchief the lady took. And Jenny wants you to know that she wouldn't have made away with it herself for a heap of money, but that the lady took it, and left some money instead. Jenny don't know her at all, if you please, miss?”</p><p >“Why, who can she be?” said I.</p><p >“My love,” Miss Flite suggested, advancing her lips to my ear, with her most mysterious look, “in <hi rend="italics">my</hi> opinion—don't mention this to our diminutive friend—she's the Lord Chancellor's wife. He's married, you know. And I understand she leads him a terrible life. Throws his lordship's papers into the fire, my dear, if he won't pay the jeweller!”</p><p >I did not think very much about this lady then, for I had an impression that it might be Caddy. Besides, my attention was diverted by my visitor, who was cold after her ride, and looked hungry; and who, our dinner being brought in, required some little assistance in arraying herself with great satisfaction in a pitiable old scarf and a much-worn and often-mended pair of gloves, which she had brought down in a paper parcel. I had to preside, too, over the entertainment, consisting of a dish of fish, a roast fowl, a sweetbread, vegetables, pudding, and Madeira; and it was so pleasant to see how she enjoyed it, and with what state and ceremony she did honor to it, that I was soon thinking of nothing else.</p><p >When we had finished, and had our little dessert before us, embellished by the hands of my dear, who would yield the superintendence of everything prepared for me to no one; Miss Flite was so very chatty and happy, that I thought I would lead her to her own history, as she was always pleased to talk about herself. I began by saying “You have attended on the Lord Chancellor many years, Miss Flite?”</p><p >“O many, many, many years, my dear. But I expect a judgment. Shortly.”</p><p >There was an anxiety even in her hopefulness, that made me doubtful if I had done right in approaching the subject. I thought I would say no more about it.</p><p >“My father expected a Judgment,” said Miss Flite. “My brother. My sister. They all expected a Judgment. The same that I expect.”</p><pb  xml:id="p350"/><p >“They are all——”</p><p >“Ye-es. Dead of course, my dear,” said she.</p><p >As I saw she would go on, I thought it best to try to be serviceable to her by meeting the theme, rather than avoiding it.</p><p >“Would it not be wiser,” said I, “to expect this Judgment no more?”</p><p >“Why, my dear,” she answered promptly, “of course it would!”</p><p >“And to attend the court no more?”</p><p >“Equally of course,” said she. “Very wearing to be always in expectation of what never comes, my dear Fitz Jarndyce! Wearing, I assure you, to the bone!”</p><p >She slightly showed me her arm, and it was fearfully thin indeed.</p><p >“But, my dear,” she went on, in her mysterious way, “there's a dreadful attraction in the place. Hush! Don't mention it to our diminutive friend, when she comes in. Or it may frighten her. With good reason. There's a cruel attraction in the place. You <hi rend="italics">can't</hi> leave it. And you <hi rend="italics">must</hi> expect.”</p><p >I tried to assure her that this was not so. She heard me patiently and smilingly, but was ready with her own answer.</p><p >“Aye, aye, aye! You think so, because I am a little rambling. Ve-ry absurd, to be a little rambling, is it not? Ve-ry confusing, too. To the head. I find it so. But, my dear, I have been there many years, and I have noticed. It's the Mace and Seal upon the table.”</p><p >What could they do, did she think? I mildly asked her.</p><p >“Draw,” returned Miss Flite. “Draw people on, my dear. Draw peace out of them. Sense out of them. Good looks out of them. Good qualities out of them. I have felt them even drawing my rest away in the night. Cold and glittering devils!”</p><p >She tapped me several times upon the arm, and nodded good-humouredly, as if she were anxious I should understand that I had no cause to fear her, though she spoke so gloomily, and confided these awful secrets to me.</p><p >“Let me see,” said she. “I'll tell you my own case. Before they ever drew me—before I had ever seen them—what was it I used to do? Tambourine playing? No. Tambour work. I and my sister worked at tambour work. Our father and our brother had a builder's business. We all lived together. Ve-ry respectably, my dear! First, our father was drawn—slowly. Home was drawn with him. In a few years, he was a fierce, sour, angry bankrupt, without a kind word or a kind look for any one. He had been so different, Fitz Jarndyce. He was drawn to a debtor's prison. There he died. Then our brother was drawn—swiftly—to drunkenness. And rags. And death. Then my sister was drawn. Hush! Never ask to what! Then I was ill, and in misery; and heard, as I had often heard before, that this was all the work of Chancery. When I got better, I went to look at the Monster. And then I found out how it was, and I was drawn to stay there.”</p><p >Having got over her own short narrative, in the delivery of which she had spoken in a low, strained voice, as if the shock were fresh upon her, she gradually resumed her usual air of amiable importance.</p><p >“You don't quite credit me, my dear! Well well! You will, some day. I am a little rambling. But I have noticed. I have seen many new faces come, unsuspicious, within the influence of the Mace and
<pb xml:id="p351"/>
Seal, in these many years. As my father's came there. As my brother's. As my sister's. As my own. I hear Conversation Kenge, and the rest of them, say to the new faces, ‘Here's little Miss Flite. O you are new here; and you must come and be presented to little Miss Flite!’ Ve-ry good. Proud I am sure to have the honor! And we all laugh. But, Fitz Jarndyce, I know what will happen. I know, far better than they do, when the attraction has begun. I know the signs, my dear. I saw them begin in Gridley. And I saw them end. Fitz Jarndyce, my love,” speaking low again, “I saw them beginning in our friend the Ward in Jarndyce. Let some one hold him back. Or he'll be drawn to ruin.”</p><p >She looked at me in silence for some moments, with her face gradually softening into a smile. Seeming to fear that she had been too gloomy, and seeming also to lose the connexion in her mind, she said, politely, as she sipped her glass of wine, “Yes, my dear, as I was saying, I expect a Judgment. Shortly. Then I shall release my birds, you know, and confer estates.”</p><p >I was much impressed by her allusion to Richard, and by the sad meaning, so sadly illustrated in her poor pinched form, that made its way through all her incoherence. But happily for her, she was quite complacent again now, and beamed with nods and smiles.</p><p >“But, my dear,” she said, gaily, reaching another hand to put it upon mine. “You have not congratulated me on my physician. Positively not once, yet!”</p><p >I was obliged to confess that I did not quite know what she meant.</p><p >“My physician, Mr. Woodcourt, my dear, who was so exceedingly attentive to me. Though his services were rendered quite gratuitously. Until the Day of Judgment. I mean <hi rend="italics">the</hi> judgment that will dissolve the spell upon me of the Mace and Seal.”</p><p >“Mr. Woodcourt is so far away, now,” said I, “that I thought the time for such congratulation was past, Miss Flite.”</p><p >“But, my child,” she returned, “is it possible that you don't know what has happened?”</p><p >“No,” said I.</p><p >“Not what everybody has been talking of, my beloved Fitz Jarndyce?”</p><p >“No,” said I. “You forget how long I have been here.”</p><p >“True! My dear, for the moment—true. I blame myself. But my memory has been drawn out of me, with everything else, by what I mentioned. Ve-ry strong influence, is it not? Well, my dear, there has been a terrible shipwreck over in those East-Indian seas.”</p><p >“Mr. Woodcourt shipwrecked!”</p><p >“Don't be agitated, my dear. He is safe. An awful scene. Death in all shapes. Hundreds of dead and dying. Fire, storm, and darkness. Numbers of the drowning thrown upon a rock. There, and through it all, my dear physician was a hero. Calm and brave, through everything. Saved many lives, never complained in hunger and thirst, wrapped naked people in his spare clothes, took the lead, showed them what to do, governed them, tended the sick, buried the dead, and brought the poor survivors safely off at last! My dear, the poor emaciated creatures all but worshipped him. They fell down at his feet, when they got to the land, and blessed him. The whole country rings with it. Stay! Where's my bag of documents? I have got it there, and you shall read it, you shall read it!”</p><pb  xml:id="p352"/><p >And I <hi rend="italics">did</hi> read all the noble history; though very slowly and imperfectly then, for my eyes were so dimmed that I could not see the words, and I cried so much that I was many times obliged to lay down the long account she had cut out of the newspaper. I felt so triumphant ever to have known the man who had done such generous and gallant deeds; I felt such glowing exultation in his renown; I so admired and loved what he had done; that I envied the storm-worn people who had fallen at his feet and blessed him as their preserver. I could myself have kneeled down then, so far away, and blessed him, in my rapture that he should be so truly good and brave. I felt that no one—mother, sister, wife—could honor him more than I. I did, indeed!</p><p >My poor little visitor made me a present of the account, and when, as the evening began to close in, she rose to take her leave, lest she should miss the coach by which she was to return, she was still full of the ship-wreck, which I had not yet sufficiently composed myself to understand in all its details.</p><p >“My dear,” said she, as she carefully folded up her scarf and gloves, “my brave physician ought to have a Title bestowed upon him. And no doubt he will. You are of that opinion?”</p><p >That he well deserved one, yes. That he would ever have one, no.</p><p >“Why not, Fitz Jarndyce?” she asked, rather sharply.</p><p >I said it was not the custom in England to confer titles on men distinguished by peaceful services, however good and great; unless occasionally, when they consisted of the accumulation of some very large amount of money.</p><p >“Why, good gracious,” said Miss Flite, “how can you say that? Surely you know, my dear, that all the greatest ornaments of England, in knowledge, imagination, active humanity, and improvement of every sort, are added to its nobility! Look round you, my dear, and consider. <hi rend="italics">You</hi> must be rambling a little now, I think, if you don't know that this is the great reason why titles will always last in the land!”</p><p >I am afraid she believed what she said; for there were moments when she was very mad indeed.</p><p >And now I must part with the little secret I have thus far tried to keep. I had thought, sometimes, that Mr. Woodcourt loved me; and that if he had been richer, he would perhaps have told me that he loved me, before he went away. I had thought, sometimes, that if he had done so, I should have been glad of it. But, how much better it was now, that this had never happened! What should I have suffered, if I had had to write to him, and tell him that the poor face he had known as mine was quite gone from me, and that I freely released him from his bondage to one whom he had never seen!</p><p >O, it was so much better as it was! With a great pang mercifully spared me, I could take back to my heart my childish prayer to be all he had so brightly shown himself; and there was nothing to be undone: no chain for me to break, or for him to drag; and I could go, please God, my lowly way along the path of duty, and he could go his nobler way upon its broader road; and though we were apart upon the journey, I might aspire to meet him, unselfishly, innocently, better far than he had thought me when I found some favor in his eyes, at the journey's end.</p></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><pb  xml:id="pxxx7"/><head >NEW SPORTING NEWSPAPER.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st of</hi> JANUARY <hi rend="italics">will be published, price Sixpence, to be continued Weekly,</hi>
<lb/> The First Number of <lb/> THE FIELD, <lb/> OR, <lb/> COUNTRY GENTLEMAN'S NEWSPAPER.</p><p
>With occasional Illustrations; <lb/> DEVOTED ESPECIALLY TO <lb/> HUNTING, <lb/> RACING, <lb/> FISHING, <lb/> SHOOTING, <lb/> COURSING, <lb/> ARCHERY, <lb/> YACHTING, <lb/> CRICKETING, <lb/> FARMING, <lb/> GARDENING, AND POULTRY KEEPING; <lb/> Agricultural and Health-giving pursuits generally. With a COMPREHENSIVE SUMMARY OF THE WEEK'S NEWS; Law and Police Reports, Lists of Markets, Theatricals, Fashionable Intelligence, Reviews of Books, Veterinary Information, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Paper may be obtained through all respectable News Agents throughout the kingdom.</hi></p><p >PUBLISHING OFFICE, 4, BRYDGES STREET, COVENT GARDEN, <lb/> Where Advertisements and Communications to the Editor can be addressed.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb  xml:id="pxxx8"/><head >NEW WORKS <lb/> PUBLISHED THIS SEASON.</head><p >MR. BARTLETT'S NEW CHRISTMAS BOOK.</p><p >On November 15th, in super-royal 8vo, uniform with the “Nile Boat,” <lb/> PICTURES FROM SICILY.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “FORTY DAYS IN THE DESERT,” ETC.</p><p >This work will contain Thirty-one beautiful Vignette Illustrations engraved on Steel, several Woodcuts, and upwards of 200 pages of Letter-press, handsomely printed and bound.</p><p >II. <lb/> NEW WORK BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D.</p><p >EXPOSITORY READINGS on the BOOK of REVELATION.</p><p >EXPOSITIONS OF THE CHAPTER READ, ON SABBATH EVENINGS, IN THE SCOTTISH NATIONAL CHURCH, <lb/> CROWN COURT, COVENT GARDEN.</p><p >Forming a Continuous and Complete Commentary on the Apocalypse.</p><p >III. <lb/> MEMORIALS OF EARLY CHRISTIANITY.</p><p >PRESENTING IN A GRAPHIC, COMPACT, AND POPULAR FORM SOME OF THE MEMORABLE EVENTS OF EARLY <lb/> ECCLESIASTICAL HISTORY.</p><p >By the Rev. J. G. MIALL, author of “Footsteps of our Forefathers.” <lb/> In post 8vo, with Illustrations.</p><p >IV. <lb/> A Second Series <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>o</sic><corr>of</corr></choice> <lb/> PILGRIMAGES TO ENGLISH SHRINES.</p><p >BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >With Notes and Illustrations by F. W. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A.</p><p >In 8vo, handsomely bound and gilt.</p><p >V. <lb/> NEW WORK BY THE AUTHOR OF “MARY POWELL.”</p><p >Y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> COLLOQUIES OF EDWARD OSBORNE.</p><p >CITIZEN AND CLOTH WORKER OF LONDON.</p><p >Uniform with “The Household of Sir Thomas More,” &amp;c. In post 8vo, with Frontispiece, &amp;c., <lb/> cloth antique.</p><p >VI. <lb/> THE OLD FOREST RANGER; <lb/> OR, <lb/> WILD SPORTS OF INDIA ON THE NEILGHERRY HILLS, IN THE JUNGLES, AND ON THE PLAINS <lb/> BY MAJOR WALTER CAMPBELL, OF SKIPNESS.</p><p >New Edition, in post 8vo, with Illustrations on Steel.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx9"/><head >NEW WORKS RECENTLY PUBLISHED.</head><p >VII. <lb/> THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF WILLIAM JERDAN; <lb/> With his Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences and Correspondence, during the last Forty Years, as Editor of the “Sun” Newspaper, 1812-17, and of the “Literary Gazette,” 1817-50, in connexion with most of the Eminent Persons who have been distinguished in the past half-century as Statesmen, Poets, Authors, Men of Science, Artists. &amp;c. Three Volumes are now published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, post 8vo, cloth gilt, embellished with Portraits of the Author, George Canning, and L.E.L., with other Illustrations.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> Y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> MAIDEN and MARRIED LIFE of MARY POWELL, afterwards <lb/> MISTRESS MILTON.</p><p >New Edition, with Portrait. Post 8vo, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> antique.</p><p >“This is a charming little book; and whether we regard its subject, cleverness, or delicacy of sentiment and expression—to say nothing of its type and orthography—it is likely to be a most acceptable present to young or old, be their peculiar taste for religion, morals, poetry, history, or romance.”—<hi rend="italics">Christian Observer.</hi></p><p >“Unquestionably the production of an able hand, and a refined mind. We recommend it to all who love pure healthy, literary fare.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p><p >“This quaint narrative, presented in ancient binding, and in the type of bygone days, is a most acceptable addition to the literature of the times.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >IX. <lb/> Y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Household of SIR THOS. MORE.</p><p ><foreign xml:lang="lat">Libellus a Margareta More, quindecim annos nata, Chelseiæ inceptus.</foreign></p><p >Second Edition, with Portrait, &amp;c., uniform with above.</p><p >“Clever and agreeable reading. . . . We can give the book unqualified praise for the pleasant, and tolerably accurate pictures which it affords of the domestic manners of the period; and the characters of some of the personages represented are drawn with distinctness, and with the features of nature.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p><p >“It ends with musical melancholy, a strain of exquisitely simple beauty, referring to the judicial slaying of one of England's worthiest sons. There are some fine portraits ably limned herein. There are family pictures so graphically described that they possess the mind for ever.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p><p >X. <lb/> BALLADS FOR THE TIMES, AND OTHER POEMS.</p><p >By MARTIN FARQUHAR TUPPER, Esq., D.C.L., F.R.S., &amp;c.</p><p >Third Complete Edition, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> with Vignette and Frontispiece, uniform with “PROVERBIAL <lb/> PHILOSOPHY.”</p><p >“With smoothness of measure, Mr. Tupper's design is always excellent, and his versification is brought to bear upon things of no transient interest. It is one of the best characteristics of his labours, that he does not write for praise, but for the benefit of his fellow-men—not merely for time, but for eternity.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >XI. <lb/> THE CELT, THE ROMAN, AND THE SAXON.</p><p >A History of the Early Inhabitants of Britain, down to the Conversion of the Anglo-Saxons to Christianity.</p><p >By THOMAS WRIGHT, Esq., M.A., F.S.A. With numerous Engravings. Price 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> post 8vo, cloth.</p><p >XII. <lb/> NINEVEH AND PERSEPOLIS.</p><p >An Historical Sketch of Ancient Assyria and Persia, with an Account of the recent researches in those <lb/> Countries. By W. S. W. VAUX, M.A.</p><p >Third Edition, with numerous Illustrations, price 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth; or 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco, antique.</p><p >XIII. <lb/> SELECT POETRY FOR CHILDREN.</p><p >WITH BRIEF EXPLANATORY NOTES.</p><p >Arranged for the Use of Schools and Families, by JOSEPH PAYNE. Tenth Edition, in 18mo, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> <lb/> scarlet cloth, gilt edges,</p><p >XIV. <lb/> STUDIES IN ENGLISH POETRY.</p><p >With short Biographical Sketches, and Notes Explanatory and Critical. By JOSEPH PAYNE. <lb/> Second Edition, in 12mo, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> bound in cloth.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx10"/><head >MR. BARTLETT'S ILLUSTRATED WORKS.</head><p >FOOTSTEPS OF OUR LORD AND HIS APOSTLES</p><p >In Syria, Greece, and Italy, a Succession of Visits to the Scenes of the New Testament Narrative Third Edition in super-royal 8vo, with Twenty-three Engravings on Steel, and several Woodcuts, price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth, gilt edges; or 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco elegant.</p><p >“If beauty of design and execution, combined with elegance of narrative and trustworthy description, can be any recommendation to a book, it is sufficient to say that this excellent volume possesses every one of these features, and establishes its own character without the need of any further praise.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Bartlett has with success brought together in an effective and attractive volume, a series of written and engraved memorials of the early days of our faith, which cannot but find a welcome in many a domestic circle, and cheer with its recollections every Christian heart, whilst it pleases with its artistic beauty the most careless inspectors. We close the book with regret,’ and recommend it without fear.”—<hi rend="italics">Britannia</hi></p><p >“This is one of the happiest of the many happy Christmas ventures that their publishers have put forth, It is got up in excellent taste, and written in a pleasing and attractive style.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> GLEANINGS, ANTIQUARIAN AND PICTORIAL, <lb/> ON THE OVERLAND ROUTE.</p><p >Illustrated with Twenty-eight Steel Plates and Maps, and Twenty-three Woodcuts. Second Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> handsomely bound in cloth gilt; or 28s. morocco, elegant.</p><p >“The present work is as excellent as his former productions, for its lively and picturesque narrative, and for the exquisite engravings by which it is illustrated.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >“It is unquestionably one of the most elegant volumes ever published. The letter-press gives an excellent historical account of Malta, with graphic sketches of travelling adventures, both at that place and at Gibraltar.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >“Should be in the hands of every person travelling by the Overland Route, as <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>wellasin</sic><corr>well as in</corr></choice> every library in the kingdom, with the least pretensions to completeness.”—<hi rend="italics">Observer.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> THE NILE BOAT; <lb/> OR, GLIMPSES OF THE LAND OF EGYPT.</p><p >Illustrated by Thirty-five Steel Engravings and Maps, with numerous Cuts. Third Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt; 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco gilt.</p><p >“Of Mr. Bartlett's merits as a pictorial traveller we have frequently had occasion to speak in terms of high commendation. In the present work he has been eminently successful.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >IV. <lb/> FORTY DAYS IN THE DESERT, <lb/> ON THE TRACK OF THE ISRAELITES; <lb/> Or, a JOURNEY from CAIRO by WADY FEIRAN to MOUNT SINAI and PETRA.</p><p >With Twenty-seven Engravings on Steel, a Map, and numerous Woodcuts, Fourth Edition in super-royal 8vo, price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt; 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco gilt.</p><p >“The author presents, in this volume, one of the most picturesque accounts of the route across the wilderness of sand we have ever read.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Bartlett has made a book, pleasant in letter-press, as well as attractive in its illustrations—delicately finished line engravings of subjects particularly well chosen.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >“A very handsome volume, copiously and cleverly illustrated in the vignette style; an elegant table-book or most acceptable present.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >V. <lb/> WALKS ABOUT JERUSALEM AND ITS ENVIRONS.</p><p >Illustrated by Twenty-four Steel Engravings, Two Maps, and many superior Woodcuts. New Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt; 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco gilt,</p><p >“We have at length, in this attractive volume, the <hi rend="italics">desideratum</hi> of a complete picturesque guide to the topography of Jerusalem.”—<hi rend="italics">Patriot.</hi></p><p >“The volume is well got up in point of embellishments, and contains much valuable matter, with illustrations beautifully executed.”—<hi rend="italics">Church of England Magazine.</hi></p><p >“It is very elegantly got up, and will be richly ornamental to the table of any drawing-room, library, or boudoir.”—<hi rend="italics">Wesleyan Association Magazine.</hi></p><p >“Our impression is, that Jerusalem was never before so successfully delineated.”—<hi rend="italics">Evangelical Magazine.</hi></p><p >VI. <lb/> SCRIPTURE SITES AND SCENES, <lb/> FROM ACTUAL SURVEY, IN EGYPT, ARABIA, AND PALESTINE.</p><p >Illustrated by Seventeen Steel Engravings, Three Maps, and Thirty-seven Woodcuts. Price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><head >WORKS BY THE REV. DR. CUMMING.</head><p >NEW SERIES OF LECTURES ON THE PENTATEUCH.</p><p >THE CHURCH BEFORE THE FLOOD; <lb/> A SERIES OF LECTURES ON THE BOOK OF GENESIS.</p><p >Uniform with “APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES.”</p><p >FORESHADOWS; <lb/> OR, LECTURES ON OUR LORD'S MIRACLES AND PARABLES, <lb/> AS EARNESTS OF THE AGE TO COME.</p><p >Fifth Thousand, in Two Vols., price 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, bound and gilt.</p><p >“It has been the design of the Author, in these Lectures, to set forth as fully as possible the redemptive character of the miracles of our Lord; in other words, to show that they were not mere feats of power, or proofs of Divine beneficence, but installations of the future age;—specimens on a smaller scale of what will be realized when the predictions of the two last chapters of the Apocalypse shall have become actualized in full and lasting fact.”</p><p >APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES; <lb/> OR, LECTURES ON THE BOOK OF REVELATION.</p><p >Delivered in Exeter Hall, and at Crown Court Church.</p><p >Twelfth Thousand, in Two Vols., price 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, cloth gilt; or 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco elegant.</p><p >Uniform with the above, Ninth Thousand, <lb/> LECTURES ON THE SEVEN CHURCHES OF ASIA MINOR.</p><p >Forming a Third Series of “APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES.”</p><p >ILLUSTRATED BY WOOD ENGRAVINGS, representing the present state of the Apostolic Churches.</p><p >New EDITIONS, revised and corrected, with Index, &amp;c.</p><p >These Lectures were begun in Exeter Hall, during the period occupied in the enlargement of the Church of which the Lecturer is the Minister. Not a few were then afraid that the Author might be led into rash and questionable theories in investigating a subject confessedly beset with difficulties; but, by the blessing of God, and the exercise of caution and prayerful study, all has ended more than satisfactorily. The unprecedentedly large masses of persons of every denomination, and of no denomination at all, who overflowed the spacious hall in which they were delivered, and the growing attention excited in the minds of these audiences, and the saving and very striking impressions made on unconverted minds. by the means of the solemn truths they heard, are all signs and tokens that call for humble gratitude to God.</p><p >Numerous requests were made for their publication. A short-hand writer was therefore engaged, who took a <hi rend="italics">verbatim</hi> report of every Lecture. These reports the Author has now corrected; and trusts that the work will be found a substantial summary of the Discourses on the Apocalypse. It is his earnest prayer that these, and all his labours, may redound to the glory of God, and to the good of souls.</p><p >PROPHETIC STUDIES; <lb/> OR, LECTURES ON THE BOOK OF DANIEL.</p><p >Sixth Thousand, in foolscap 8vo, 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth, elegantly gilt; or 13s. morocco extra.</p><p >LECTURES FOR THE TIMES; <lb/> OR, ILLUSTRATIONS AND REFUTATIONS OF THE ERRORS OF ROMANISM AND <lb/> TRACTARIANISM.</p><p >New Edition, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Revised and Corrected, with Additions.</p><p >“In these Lectures, Dr. Cumming gives the fullest scope to all his high powers. Careful research, acute argument, brilliant illustration, graphic description, eloquent appeal, all unite in enriching and embellishing his pages, alluring the most indifferent to read, and compelling the most prejudiced against his views to pause and consider.”—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Ecclesiastical Review.</hi></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx12"/><head >WORKS BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D. —CONTINUED</head><p >THE CELEBRATED PROTESTANT DISCUSSION <lb/> Between the Rev. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., and DANIEL FRENCH, ESQ., held at HAMMERSMITH, <lb/> in 1839. Cheap Edition. Tenth Thousand. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth lettered.</p><p >“No clergyman's library can be complete without it.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p><p >“A compendium of argument.”—<hi rend="italics">Gentleman's Magazine.</hi></p><p >“The subject (<hi rend="italics">pro</hi> and <hi rend="italics">con</hi>) is all but exhausted.”—<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p><p >ST. BONAVENTURE'S PSALTER; <lb/> OR, THE PSALMS OF DAVID ADDRESSED TO THE VIRGIN MARY.</p><p >Translated from the last French edition of 1852.</p><p >This work ought to be in the hand of every Protestant, as the most conclusive proof of the idolatry of the Church of Rome. Published this day. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >“IS CHRISTIANITY FROM GOD?”</p><p >A Popular Manual of Christian Evidences. Ninth Edition. Fcap. 8vo, cloth, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >OUR FATHER; <lb/> A Manual of Family Prayers for General and Special Occasions. Fifth Edition. Fcap, 8vo, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt edges.</p><p >THE COMMUNION TABLE; <lb/> Or, Communicant's Manual. A Plain and Practical Exposition of the Lord's Supper. New Edition. Fcap. 8vo, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p><p >INFANT SALVATION; <lb/> Or, All Saved who Die in Infancy. Specially addressed to Mothers mourning the loss of Infants and Children. Fourth Edition. Fcap. 8vo. gilt edges, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE BAPTISMAL FONT; <lb/> An Exposition of the Nature and Obligations of Christian Baptism. With an Appendix. Third Edition. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Uniform with the above.</p><p >A MESSAGE FROM GOD: <lb/> Or, Thoughts on Religion, for Thinking Men. Also uniform. Third Edition. Fcap. 8vo, cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >SALVATION: <lb/> A Sermon preached in the Parish Church of Crathie, Balmoral, before her Majesty the Queen, on Sunday, September 22, 1850. Eighteenth Thousand. Price Sixpence.</p><p >OCCASIONAL DISCOURSES.</p><p >New Edition, in Two Volumes, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, cloth gilt.</p><p >EDITED BY DR. CUMMING.</p><p >HEROINES OF THE MISSIONARY ENTERPRISE; <lb/> OR, SKETCHES OF PROMINENT FEMALE MISSIONARIES <lb/> BY DANIEL C. EDDY.</p><p >Second Edition, in Fcap. 8vo, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth, gilt edges.</p><p >“This is a book for the many, and cannot fail to be a great favourite, especially with the sex whose virtues and labours it records.”—<hi rend="italics">British Banner.</hi></p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, AND PATON AND RITCHIE, EDINBURGH; J. ROBERTSON, AND J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx13"/><head >ILLUSTRATED WORKS FOR THE YOUNG.</head><div type="section"><head >CANADIAN CRUSOES, <lb/> A TALE OF THE RICE LAKE PLAINS.</head><docAuthor >By MRS. TRAILL, Authoress of “The Backwoods of Canada,” &amp;c.</docAuthor><p >Edited by AGNES STRICKLAND. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s</hi> bound and gilt. Illustrated by HARVEY.</p><p >“This is an extremely pleasing and not very improbable fiction. The object of the writer has been to inculcate the virtues of energy and self reliance under circumstances of difficulty and danger. The book is exceedingly well calculated for children, to whom its interesting contents, its handsome appearance and beautiful illustrations will render it an acceptable present.”—<hi rend="italics">Tait's Magazine, Sept.</hi> 1852.</p><p >“A very delightful book for young readers. The interest is deep and well sustained, the style uniformly agreeable and lively, and the knowledge of the writer, who has lived for some time on the Rice Lake Plains, the scene of the story, adds a value to the book for readers of all ages. Mr. Harvey has contributed some excellent woodcuts, and the book is altogether a pretty and interesting one.”—<hi rend="italics">Guardian.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >LOVE: A REALITY, NOT ROMANCE, </head><docAuthor > By Mrs. THOMAS GELDART, author of “Truth is Everything,” &amp;c.</docAuthor><p >In foolscap. (CUTS BY GILBERT,) price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> handsomely bound, with gilt edges.</p><p >“Few writers are more indefatigable in their offices of benevolence than the authoress of this elegant little volume, who has once more done herself infinite credit by a transcript of the realities of life, so fairly and truly made, as to go home to the heart of every one, who follows the tale to the conclusion. It is a high gift to be able to write well; but it is a far higher and nobler privilege to be known to write usefully, and to the best of purposes; and this Mrs. Geldart has never more effectually done than in ‘Love; a Reality, not Romance.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >THE HOFLAND LIBRARY.</head><head >FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF YOUTH.</head><p >Illustrated with Plates. Each Volume handsomely bound in embossed scarlet cloth, with gilt edges, &amp;c.</p><list  type="simple"><head>First Class, in 12mo, price 2s. 6d. each,</head><item>1. ALFRED CAMPBELL; or Travels of a Young Pilgrim.</item><item>2. DECISION.</item><item>3. ENERGY,</item><item>4. FAREWELL TALES.</item><item>5. FORTITUDE.</item><item>6. HUMILITY.</item><item>7. INTEGRITY.</item><item>8. MODERATION.</item><item>9. PATIENCE.</item><item>10. REFLECTION.</item><item>11. SELF-DENIAL.</item><item>12. YOUNG CADET; or, Travels in Hindostan.</item><item>13. YOUNG PILGRIM; or, Alfred Campbell's Return.</item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Second Class, in 18mo, price 1s. 6d each.</head><item>1. Adelaide.</item><item>2. Affectionate Brothers.</item><item>3. Alicia and her Aunt.</item><item>4. Barbadoes Girl.</item><item>5. Blind Farmer.</item><item>6. Clergyman's Widow.</item><item>7. Daughter-in-law.</item><item>8. Elizabeth.</item><item>9. Godmother's Tales.</item><item>10. Good Grandmother.</item><item>11. Merchant's Widow.</item><item>12. Rich Boys and Poor Boys.</item><item>13. The Sisters.</item><item>14. Stolen Boy.</item><item>15. William and his Uncle Ben.</item><item>16. Young Northern Traveller.</item><item>17. Young Crusoe.</item></list><p >Uniformly printed in square 16mo. handsomely bound in cloth, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p><p >HOW TO WIN LOVE; <lb/> Or, Rhoda's Lesson. Second Edition, with Plates <lb/> on Steel.</p><p >“Truthfulness, descriptive talent, and pure morality in every line.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >PIPPLE'S WARNING; <lb/> Or, Mind your Temper. By Catherine Crowe, <lb/> Author of “Susan Hopley,’ &amp;c.</p><p >STRATAGEMS.</p><p >By Mrs. Newton Crosland.</p><p >MY OLD PUPILS.</p><p >With Four Illustrations.</p><p >PLEASANT PASTIME; <lb/> Or, Drawing-room Dramas for Private Representation <lb/> by the Young.</p></div><div type="section"><head >THE DOCTOR'S LITTLE DAUGHTER.</head><docAuthor >BY ELIZA METEYARD.</docAuthor><p >Fcap 8vo,, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> elegantly bound and gilt, with numerous Illustrations by HARVEY.</p><p >“This is a very delightful book, especially calculated for the amusement and instruction of our young friends, and is evidently the production of a right-thinking and accomplished mind.”—<hi rend="italics">Church of England Review.</hi></p><p >“An elegant, interesting, and unobjectionable present for young ladies. The moral of the book turns on benevolence.”—<hi rend="italics">Christian Times.</hi></p><p >“This Story of a Child's Life is so full of beauty and meekness, that we can hardly express our sense of its worth in the words of common praise.”—<hi rend="italics">Nonconformist.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >RECOLLECTIONS OF MRS. ANDERSON'S SCHOOL.</head><docAuthor >By JANE WINNARD HOOPER. Illustrated by FRANKLIN. In fcap. 8vo, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth, gilt edges.</docAuthor><p >“A pretty unpretentious volume, neatly embellished, and gay in its livery of green and gold. Outside and in 'tis precisely the <hi rend="italics">beau ideal</hi> of a present or a prize-book for a young lady. More fresh and more delightful reading than this book it has rarely been our fortune to meet.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser.</hi></p></div><closer >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer><closer >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx14"/><opener >In One handsome Volume, price One Guinea, cloth gilt, </opener><head > THE ART-JOURNAL <lb/> ILLUSTRATED CATALOGUE <lb/> OF THE <lb/> GREAT INDUSTRIAL EXHIBITION OF 1851, </head><p >CONTAINING <lb/> UPWARDS OF FOURTEEN HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD, <lb/> AND A FRONTISPIECE ON STEEL.
</p><p >This volume includes the Prize Essays, for which the Proprietors of the ART JOURNAL paid one hundred guineas to R. N. Wornum, Esq.; also an Essay on the Science of the Exhibition, by Professor Robert Hunt; an Essay on the Harmony of Colours, by Mrs. Merrifield; another on the Vegetable Productions of the Exhibition, by Professor Forbes, F.R.S; and concludes with an Essay on the Machinery, by Professor Gordon. These are accompanied by appropriate engravings, and must at all times give to the work a permanent and enduring value, wholly independent of its merits as a Catalogue.</p><p >The Work will be soon OUT OF PRINT: it cannot be reprinted: and there is no question of its largely augmenting in value when classed among Scarce Books: those by whom it is required will therefore do well to obtain copies early.</p><p >“It is at once interesting, useful and beautiful;” “a valuable reminder of the Exhibition to those by whom it was visited, and equally valuable to those to whom the enjoyment was denied.” “A beautiful book for the drawing-room, and a useful instructor for all classes.”</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >In Parts at 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and in Vols. at 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> morocco cloth gilt, </opener><head > A CYCLOPEDIA OF USEFUL ARTS, </head><p > Mechanics, Manufactures, Mining, and Civil Engineering.</p><p >EDITED BY CHARLES TOMLINSON.</p><p >WITH NEARLY TWO THOUSAND ENGRAVINGS.</p><p >This Work, in addition to its general information on every topic connected with the Mechanical Arts and Manufacturing Ingenuity, contains beautifully executed Views of the Exterior and Interior of THE GREAT INDUSTRIAL EXHIBITION of 1852, as well as Engravings, and Descriptions of the most important Mechanical Inventions and Machines submitted to public inspection on that occasion; thus rendering the Work a permanent record of the most valuable productions of the Mechanical and Scientific genius of every country in the civilized world.</p><p >“We recommend this book to all, for, though not quite divested of technicalities, there is still a vast amount of general information to be derived from it; and especially to practical men in every branch of handicraft and engineering.”—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Citizen.</hi></p><p >Each Shilling Part contains an average of Seventy Engravings.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx15"/><opener >In Two Vols, imperial 8vo, price 1l. 5s. each, </opener><head >THE CASTLES AND ABBEYS <lb/> OF ENGLAND.
</head><p >A SUPERBLY ILLUSTRATED HISTORICAL WORK</p><p >By W. BEATTIE, M.D., Member of the Institute of France, and author of “Switzerland <lb/> Illustrated,” &amp;c.</p><p >This work presents Engravings of whatever is most interesting or least known in the Scenery, Style, or Decoration of each subject, and is embellished with Vignette specimens of the Castles, Abbeys, Cathedrals, Chapels, Tombs, Altars, Halls, Galleries, Armouries, Portraits and Medallions, Sculptures, Arches, Gateways, Antique Furniture and Inscriptions, Statues and fragments of Art, Festive, Military, and Rural Scenes, Battle-fields, Banquet Halls, National Sports and Athletic Games, and whatever illustrates most forcibly the minds, habits, and pursuits of our baronial ancestors; the whole so distributed throughout the work, that the Engravings and the Literary Matter mutually illustrate each other, and bring the Edifices and their Inhabitants once more before the eye of the reader.</p><p >The Second Volume may be had separately, if required.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >In 1 vol. 8vo, price 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, <lb/> WITH FORTY-TWO ILLUSTRATIONS BY “PHIZ,” </opener><head > LEWIS ARUNDEL: <lb/> OR, <lb/> THE RAILROAD OF LIFE.
</head><p >BY FRANK E. SMEDLEY, (FRANK FAIRLEGH.)</p><p >“The task of the reviewer becomes a pleasant one when such works as the one before us is forced upon his perusal. We must once more commend the taste and talent of the author of ‘Lewis Arundel.’”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Times.</hi></p><p >“The best tale going is ‘Lewis Arundel,’ by the author of ‘Frank Fairlegh.’ It displays a great deal of that sort of feeling for which we can find no better term than gentlemanly.”—<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Chronicle.</hi></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “LEWIS ARUNDEL.”</p><p >Complete in 1 vol. 8vo, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, <lb/> FRANK FAIRLEGH; <lb/> OR, <lb/> SCENES FROM THE LIFE OF A PRIVATE PUPIL.</p><p >With Thirty Illustrations by George Cruikshank.</p><p >“Its fame is very likely to be more durable than that of the majority of works of the kind.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life in London.</hi></p><p >“There is no writer of fiction since Sir Walter Scott who has so well deserved popularity as the author of this story.”—<hi rend="italics">Exeter Gazette.</hi></p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx16"/><opener >EDITED BY S. C. HALL, ESQ.</opener><head >THE NATIONAL GALLERY <lb/> OF <lb/> BRITISH PICTURES, </head><p >(PRESENTED TO THE NATION BY ROBERT VERNON, ESQ.)</p><p >AND OF MODERN SCULPTURE.</p><p >In Monthly Parts, containing Three Line-Engravings from the Pictures in the Vernon Gallery, and One Engraving of Modern Sculpture. With accompanying Letter-press from the pens of several eminent Authors. Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each Part.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >UNDER THE PATRONAGE OF HER MOST GRACIOUS MAJESTY, AND HIS ROYAL <lb/> HIGHNESS PRINCE ALBERT, K.G.</opener><head >PROOF IMPRESSIONS OF THE ENGRAVINGS <lb/> OF <lb/> THE VERNON COLLECTION.</head><p >The Proofs of the above Collection will be all printed on India Paper, and published in Monthly Parts, each part to consist of Three Plates. With the First Part will be delivered a handsome Portfolio, made to contain the Series of Proofs for Twelve Months; and a similar Portfolio will be given to the Subscribers annually. Explanatory letter-press pages will accompany each volume.</p><p >
<table><head>TERMS OF SUBSCRIPTION.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> s. </cell><cell> d. </cell></row><row><cell> ARTISTS' PROOFS, of which only 150 will be printed. The Part </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> PROOFS BEFORE LETTERS, of which only 200 will be printed. The Part </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> LETTERED PROOFS, of which only 150 will be printed. The Part </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >Completed in One Volume, splendidly printed on Elephant Quarto, Price £3 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >THE WILKIE GALLERY, </head><p > A SERIES OF 66 LINE ENGRAVINGS <lb/> FROM THE <lb/> BEST PAINTINGS OF THE LATE SIR DAVID WILKIE, R.A., <lb/> with notices Biographical and Critical.</p><p >The Work comprises an ample Biography of the Painter, written expressly for the Wilkie Gallery. A Portrait of Wilkie and a View of his Birth-place form part of the Illustrations.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx17"/><opener >Beautifully Illustrated, embellished, and bound in fancy cloth, 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> gilt edges, </opener><head >MIDSUMMER EVE.</head><p >A Fairy Tale of Lobe.</p><p >BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >Embellished with upwards of Two Hundred Engravings on Wood.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> <hi rend="italics">The Designs by</hi> </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">The Engravings by</hi> </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> D. MACLISE, R.A. </cell><cell> W. FROST, A.R.A. </cell><cell> W. T. GREEN, </cell><cell> H. LINTON. </cell></row><row><cell> C. STANFIELD, RA. </cell><cell> F. W. TOPHAM. </cell><cell> G. DALZIEL. </cell><cell> G. MEASOM </cell></row><row><cell> T. CRESWICK, A.R.A. </cell><cell> KENNY MEADOWS. </cell><cell> E. DALZIEL. </cell><cell> W. MEASOM. </cell></row><row><cell> E. M. WARD, A.R.A. </cell><cell> E. W. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A. </cell><cell> J. BASTIN. </cell><cell> A. S. MASON. </cell></row><row><cell> A. ELMORE, A.R.A. </cell><cell> &amp;C. &amp;C. </cell><cell> J. WILLIAMS. </cell><cell> &amp;C. &amp;C. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >New Edition, in 3 vols. super-royal 8vo, price 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, </opener><head > IRELAND.</head><p >ITS SCENERY, CHARACTER, &amp;c.</p><p >BY MR. AND MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >Illustrated with Forty-Eight Steel Engravings, after drawings by T. Creswick, A.R.A., <lb/> Five Hundred exquisite Wood Engravings, and Eighteen Maps of the Counties.</p><p >The Authors of this Work have laboured with zeal and industry to obtain such topographical and statistical information as may be useful to those who visit Ireland, or who desire the means of judging correctly as to its capabilities and condition. But their especial duty has been to associate with more important details such incidents, descriptions, legends, traditions, and personal sketches, as may excite interest in those who might be deterred from the perusal of mere facts, if communicated in a less popular form.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >Now Publishing, in Parts at 1<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> each illustrated with Two Steel Engravings, </opener><head > THE PICTORIAL <lb/> HISTORY OF SCOTLAND,</head><docAuthor >BY THE REV. JAMES TAYLOR, D.D., GLASGOW.</docAuthor><p >With Illustrations on Steel, from Drawings by W. H. Bartlett, and other Artists.</p><p >The Steel Engravings comprise, in addition to authentic Portraits of eminent Scotchmen, a series of accurate and highly finished Views of those localities which are identified with the most important events in the annals of the country.</p><p >It is also intended to group together, on carefully engraved plates, fac-similes of the coins, seals, armorial bearings, &amp;c., of the different eras, as well as specimens of the weapons, dress, domestic implements, and other minor objects illustrative of the social condition of the nation.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">To be completed in two large Octavo Volumes.</hi></p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx18"/><opener >In super-royal 8vo, price 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</opener><head >THE HISTORY OF WALES.</head><p >BY B. B. WOODWARD, B.A.</p><p >From the Earliest Times to its Final Incorporation with England; <lb/> WITH NOTICES OF ITS PHYSICAL GEOGRAPHY, <lb/> And the Poetry, Traditions, Religion, Acts, Manners, and Laws of the Welsh. Illustrated <lb/> by Fifteen Original Views of remarkable Places, Antiquities and Scenery.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >In Two super-royal 8vo. vols., price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, </opener><head >THE DECLINE AND <lb/> FALL OF THE ROMAN EMPIRE.</head><p >BY EDWARD GIBBON.</p><p >Illustrated Edition, with Memoir of the Author, and additional Notes, principally <lb/> referring to Christianity. From the French of M. GUIZOT.</p><p >The Illustrations comprise—1. Maps of the Roman Empire, and of the Cities of Rome and Constantinople—2. Architectural Monuments of the different periods, from the Augustan period to the time of Leo X.—3. Views of celebrated Cities and important sites, with topographical references—4. A series of Coins, with Portraits of some of the most remarkable personages mentioned in the History.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >DAILY FAMILY DEVOTION; <lb/> OR, GUIDE TO FAMILY WORSHIP.</head><p >BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., <lb/> Minister of the Scottish National Church, Crown Court, Russell Street, Covent Garden, London.</p><p >This work, consisting of a Hymn a portion of Scripture, and an appropriate Prayer for the Morning and Evening of every day in the year, is designed to introduce or facilitate the practice of Family Worship; and by constructing the daily prayers on the passage of Scripture selected for reading, greater variety, interest, and practical use are associated with the exercise.</p><p >The Work will be published in Monthly Parts, price One Shilling each. Every Part will contain four sheets, or 32 Quarto pages It will be completed in about 23 Parts, forming One Volume. The printing and paper will be of a superior character.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >Complete in 1 handsome vol., cloth, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >BUNYAN'S PILGRIM'S PROGRESS</head><p >A splendidly Illustrated Edition, in super-royal octavo, comprising 120 fine Engravings on Wood, by the Messrs. WHIMPER, from Designs made expressly for the purpose by Artists of the highest celebrity. Also Nine elegant Engravings on Steel, a Portrait, and a Fac-simile of John Bunyan's Will.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx19"/><opener >In Two Volumes, music folio, elegantly bound and gilt, 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, </opener><head ><lb/> THE ILLUSTRATED <lb/> BOOK OF BRITISH SONG.</head><p >Comprising above One Hundred of the best Songs, by those famous composers, Purcell, Arne, Handel, Shield, Jackson, Storace, Linley, and others; with Accompaniments for the Pianoforte, newly arranged from the figured basses of the Composers, and Notes, Biographical and Historical, by GEORGE HOGARTH, Esq. Each Song is illustrated by some eminent Artist: amongst others, are drawings by Townsend, Meadows, Pickersgill, Franklin, Hamerton, Crowquill, Warren Topham, Hook, Dodgson, Weigall, Fahey, Anelay, Absolon, and Weir; engraved by Linton, Gray, Dalziel, Mason, Green, Landells, Nicholls, Measom, &amp;c.</p><p >The Work contains the whole of the Music and Poetry introduced in the Tragedy of Macbeth, composed by MATTHEW LOCK. The Illustrations etched in Glyphography by H. WEIR.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >In One Vol., super-royal 8vo, cloth extra, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >THE WORKS OF BURNS.</head><p >PEOPLE'S EDITION.</p><p >Embellished with Thirty-three Plates (after Wright and other Artists), illustrative of the Principal subjects of his Poems. With a NEW LIFE OF BURNS, and Explanatory Notes preceding each Poem, by ALLAN CUNNINGHAM.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >Complete in Two handsome Volumes, cloth gilt, 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></opener><head >ROYAL GEMS <lb/> FROM THE GALLERIES OF EUROPE.</head><p >ENGRAVED AFTER PICTURES OF THE GREAT MASTERS,</p><p >WITH NOTICES BIOGRAPHICAL, HISTORICAL, AND DESCRIPTIVE.</p><p >BY S. C. HALL, F.S.A.</p><p >Containing 90 highly-finished Plates, engraved in the first style of art by W. Greatbach, C. Rolls, L. Stocks, Cousen, and others. Size of the Engravings, 6½ by 9½ inches.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >Two neat Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >VIEWS OF THE <lb/> PORTS, HARBOURS, &amp; WATERING-PLACES <lb/> OF GREAT BRITAIN.</head><p >Forming a complete Series of Views of all the points of interest round the entire Coast, whether noted for their commercial importance, or as places of pleasurable resort. The Plates, 125 in number, are executed in the Messrs. FINDEN'S best style.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx20"/><opener >Neatly printed on fcap. 8vo, and specially adapted for the Pocket of the Traveller.</opener><head >AN UNIFORM SERIES OF <lb/> STANDARD THEOLOGICAL WORKS </head><docAuthor > EDITED BY <lb/> THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., DR. PYE SMITH, DR. CROLY, <lb/> DR. STEBBING, JAMES MONTGOMERY, ESQ., &amp;c.
</docAuthor><p >This collection comprises TREATISES on the DOCTRINES, MORALITY, and EVIDENCES OF
CHRISTIANITY, which have received the permanent stamp of general approbation;—SELECT SERMONS of the most eminent DIVINES;—the most interesting Specimens of RELIGIOUS BIOGRAPHY;—and the choicest examples of DEVOTIONAL and SACRED POETRY.</p><p >To the productions of each Author, or to each separate production, as the case may seem to require, is prefixed AN INTRODUCTORY ESSAY, pointing out their characteristic excellences; and, in some instances, comprehending a Biographical Sketch of the Author, with remarks on the State of Religion in his times.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Each Work is published without abridgment, and most carefully revised and collated.</hi></p><p >The Analogy of Religion, Natural and Revealed, to the Constitution and Course of Nature: to which are added, Two Brief Dissertations—1. On Personal Identity. 2. On the Nature of Virtue. By JOSEPH BUTLER, D.C.L., late Lord Bishop of Durham. With a Memoir of the Author, by the Rev. GEORGE CROLY, LL.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Bishop Beveridge's Private Thoughts: to which is added, THE NECESSITY OF FREQUENT COMMUNION; with Introductory Essays, by the Rev. H. STEBBING, D.D. In 2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each vol. cloth.</p><p >Baxter's Dying Thoughts; with an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. HENRY STEBBING, D.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Jeremy Taylor's Holy Living; together with Prayers, containing the whole Duty of a Christian. With a Life of the Author, by Dr. CROLY. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Jeremy Taylor's Rule and Exercises of Holy Dying. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Jeremy Taylor's Select Sermons; viz.: The Miracles of the Divine Mercy;—of the Spirit of Grace;—the Deceitfulness of the Heart;—the Marriage Ring;—the Righteousness Evangelical Described;—the Christian's Conquest over the Body of Sin;—Fides Formata; or, Faith working by Love. With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. R. CATTERMOLE, B.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Jeremy Taylor's Life of Christ. With an Introductory Essay to each Part, by the Rev. HENRY STEBBING, D.D. Illustrated by a Portrait. In 3 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each vol.</p><p >The Liberty of Prophesying; showing the Unreasonableness of Prescribing to other Men's Faith; and the Iniquity of Persecuting differing Opinions. By JEREMY TAYLOR, D.D.; with an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. RICHARD CATTERMOLE, B.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="x14"/><head >STANDARD THEOLOGICAL WORKS</head><p >Cave's Lives of the Apostles; to which are added Selections from the Lives of the Apostolic Fathers: with Notes, and an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. HENRY STEBBING, D.D. In 2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, cloth.</p><p >Cave's Primitive Christianity; or, the Religion of the Ancient Christians in the First Ages of the Gospel: to which are added, an Historical Account of Paganism under the first Christian Emperors; and the Lives of Justin Martyr and St. Cyprian. With an Introductory Essay, and Notes, by the Rev. W. TROLLOPE, M.A.; Vicar of Great Wigston. In 2 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each vol. cloth.</p><p >Bates's Spiritual Perfection Unfolded and Enforced; with an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. J. PYE SMITH, D.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Bishop Hall's Treatises, Devotional and Practical. With an Essay and Notes, by the Rev. RICHARD CATTERMOLE, B.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Archbishop Leighton's Expositions of the Creed, the LORD'S PRAYER, and the TEN COMMANDMENTS, &amp;c. &amp;c. With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. J. PYE SMITH, D.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Dr. Watts's Lyric Poems; with a Biographical Essay, by the late ROBERT SOUTHEY, Esq., LL.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Fifteen Sermons on Retirement, Self-Denial, Resignation, &amp;c. &amp;c. With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. RICHARD CATTERMOLE, B.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Fourteen Sermons on the Resurrection, &amp;c. &amp;c. With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. HENRY STEBBING, D.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Fourteen Sermons on the Divinity and Operation of the Holy Spirit. With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. RICHARD CATTERMOLE, B.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >The Hon. Robert Boyle on the Veneration due to God; On Things above Reason; and on the Style of the Holy Scriptures. With an Essay, by HENRY ROGERS. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Vicesimus Knox's Christian Philosophy. With an Essay, by the Rev. H. STEBBING, D.D. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Locke on the Reasonableness of Christianity as delivered in the Scriptures. With a Biographical Essay, Notes, and an Appendix. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >Bishop Horne's Commentary on the Psalms. With a Life of the Author, by the Rev. W. JONES, of Nayland, and an Introductory Essay, by JAMES MONTGOMERY, Esq. In 3 vols., price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each vol. cloth.</p><p >Bishop Butler's Fifteen Sermons, preached at the Rolls' Chapel, and a Charge to the Clergy of Durham, with an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. R. CATTERMOLE, B.D., and an Appendix, by BISHOP HALIFAX. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx22"/><head >SHARPE'S LONDON MAGAZINE.</head><docAuthor >CONDUCTED BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</docAuthor><p >THIS Monthly Journal has been recently placed under the Editorship of Mrs. S. C. HALL. Aided by a large number of accomplished and popular authors, her efforts are directed to give to the Publication such a tone and character as—while insuring its welcome into English homes—may render it a work of high literary distinction and value. It consists of the united contributions of the best writers of Tales, Essays, Personal Adventures, Sketches of Character, Results of Travel, Visits to Remarkable Places, Popular Statistics, Poems, Reviews, Translations from the purest French, German, and Italian authors; concluded each month by an article entitled “Books and their Authors,” which combines much that is valuable in the literature of the current month, with much that is interesting in personal history.</p><p >The Work is printed on fine paper, with new type; <hi rend="italics">two interesting Engravingss</hi> are given with each part; the part consists of 64 pages of letter-press, imperial octavo.</p><p >The price of One Shilling monthly places it within reach of all classes; and the active zeal of Editor, Authors, and Publishers is combined to obtain for the Work extensive circulation, and consequent utility.</p><p >The first volume of the New Series for 1852, price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> containing 384 pages of imperial 8vo. letter-press, and twelve Engravings on steel, is now ready.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Among the principal contents of the Volumes for</hi> 1852, <hi rend="italics">will be found the following:</hi>—</p><p >“Impressions of England,” by Miss BREMER; “The Chronicle of Ethelfled,” by the Author of “Mary Powell;” “The Mysteries of a Flower,” by Professor R. HUNT; “The Marrying Man,” by the Author of “Frank Fairlegh;” ‘Fragments of a Young Wife's Diary,” by the Author of “Olive,” &amp;c.; “A Day in a French Criminal Court,” by Miss PARDOE; “Annie Orme,” by the Author of “Margaret Maitland;” “Blind Rosa,” by MARY HOWITT; “My Mission to Egypt in 1841,” by Lieut.-Col. NAPIER; “The Treatment of Birds in Captivity,” by a distinguished Naturalist; “Italy and her Foremost Men;” “A Lady's Captivity among Algerine Pirates;” “The Lucky Penny,” by Mrs. S. C. HALL; “Nelly Nowlan's Experience,” communicated by Mrs. S. C. HALL, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Among the principal Engravings on Steel will be found the following:</hi>—</p><p >“Egyptian Dancing Girls,” from the picture by H. WARREN; “The Maiden's Tower at Constantinople;” “The Coast of Genoa;” “Glengariffe,” by T. CRESWICK, R.A.; “Chepstow Castle and Bridge,” by W. H. BARTLETT; “St. Mawes,” by T. CRESWICK, R.A.; “Campagna di Roma,” by W. CROUCH; “Innocence,” by — GREUZE; “The Vale of Tintern,” by W. H. BARTLETT.</p><p >Vols. I. to IX. may now be had, elegantly bound in scarlet cloth, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p><p >Vols. X. to XV. (each containing Six Monthly Parts,) price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> are also ready.</p><p >Cloth Cases, for Binding the Parts, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> may be had through any Bookseller.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx23"/><head >THE ART-JOURNAL; <lb/> Record of the Fine Arts, the Arts Industrial, &amp;r.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Monthly: Price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >IN announcing the completion of the Fourth Volume of the New Series of his Work, and the commencement of the Fifth Volume, the Editor and Publishers desire to direct attention to its claims to patronage and support.</p><p >The arrangements for the coming year—1853—are of such a nature as cannot fail to maintain its popularity, by extending its useful character, and by increasing the interest as well as value of its literary and artistic contents.</p><p >The Engravings from the VERNON GALLERY—a series now approaching completion—will include a large number of the choicest Pictures of the collection: these have been necessarily postponed until towards the close, in consequence of the greater extent of time required for the finish of the more elaborate works—as, for examples, the “Hamlet,” by Maclise; the “Peace and War,” by Landseer; the “Dr. Johnson and Chesterfield” by Ward; the “South Sea Bubble” by Ward; the “Hall of Combray,” by Haghe; the “Grape Gatherers,” by Uwins; the “Saviour on the Mount,” by Eastlake, &amp;c.</p><p >Engravings of these rare and beautiful Pictures (THE GEMS OF THE NATIONAL GALLERY) will appear in due course; and in order to complete the series, and to carry out the pledge given to Mr. VERNON, to engrave “the whole of his collection presented to the Nation,” <hi rend="italics">eight of the twelve monthly parts for the year</hi> 1853 <hi rend="italics">will contain, in each part, three of the Vernon Series;</hi> the other four parts containing two of the Vernon Pictures, and one Engraving of a work in Sculpture.</p><p >With regard to other arrangements for the conduct of the “ART-JOURNAL,” the Editor feels it only necessary to refer to the past. The best aids he can obtain in Europe, for the Literature and Art of the Journal, shall be resorted to, as heretofore, in order to continue and secure to that Publication the high character it has obtained in every country of the world.</p><p >The Four Volumes, which the present year will complete, and which are issued each at the price of 31<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> contain no fewer than 148 Engravings on Steel, and about 2000 Engravings on Wood: the former consist of the noblest productions of British Art—the works of the most renowned Painters and Sculptors of the age and country—engraved in the most perfect style of which the Art is capable, by the most accomplished of English Engravers.</p><p >The Engravings on Wood comprise copies of famous Pictures, illustrating the lives of celebrated Painters; the finest and most suggestive of the works of Mediæval Art; Illustrations of Costumes of several epochs; outlines from the Portfolio of Moritz Retzsch; Illustrated Reports of the Progress of British Industrial Art, Illustrated Visits to Historic Sites, &amp;c. &amp;c.; all illustrative of subjects generally interesting, and widely instructive.</p><p >These Four Volumes—procurable at comparatively small cost—supply, in so far, A COMPLETE SERIES OF ENGRAVINGS OF THE VERNON GALLERY, numerous examples of admirable works in Sculpture, and an immense number of fine and useful Wood Engravings, associated with letter-press, contributed by the best writers of England, Germany, and France.</p><p >The Volumes are, therefore, recommended to all classes who derive enjoyment from Art, and desire instruction from its salutary influences.</p><p >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p><p >SOLD BY J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</p><p >Reed and Pardon, Printers, Paternoster, London.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx24"/><head >KAYE'S WORSDELL'S PILLS, <lb/> THE BEST FAMILY MEDICINE.</head><p >A REMEDY FOR PAIN AND DISEASE so effectual as the <hi rend="italics">Vegetable Restorative Pills,</hi> prepared solely by JOHN KAYE, Esq., of Dalton Hall, near Huddersfield, and St. John's Wood Park, London, has never been presented to the public. It is daily effecting the most astonishing cures of diseases differing materially in their symptoms and consequences. Thousands who had suffered greatly, some of whose cases had long been given up by eminent medical practitioners, and considered hopeless by themselves, have been speedily and thoroughly cured. The unprecedented popularity which these Pills have acquired may be readily accounted for. In the first place, they are purely vegetable, and are free from everything that can possibly injure the most delicate constitution. The infant, the mature, the aged, and even the most delicate female, may take them with perfect safety. Secondly, they are compounded upon philosophical principles, and go at once to the root of all disease. All diseases owe their origin to one primary cause—namely, the impurity of the blood; and no medicine, in whatever quantities taken, can be effectual, unless it becomes assimilated with the blood, and assist that principle or vitality to pursue its course through the system, charged with the power of exterminating every unhealthy obstruction. This is precisely the office of these Pills; they have power speedily to remove all obstructions, to purify the blood, and to promote the healthy circulation of all the fluids. Another remarkable excellence in these Pills is, that while they operate thus readily to remove what is injurious, while they are invaluable as <hi rend="italics">aperients,</hi> they also prove admirable <hi rend="italics">tonics.</hi> So far from weakening by their operation, as is common with ordinary active medicines, they materially strengthen the whole system. Those who have given them a fair trial bear grateful testimony to the fact, that by the use of these Pills, their appetites have been quickened, their digestion assisted, all their bodily powers braced and invigorated; at the same time that a pleasing serenity has been imparted to their minds, so that they could engage in the various duties of life with cheerfulness and satisfaction.</p><p >And these testimonials have been borne, not by a few individuals, placed in very peculiar circumstances, or whose veracity is questionable, but by thousands of persons, of both sexes, moving in various ranks, whose integrity is unimpeachable, and the majority of whom have requested the publication of their cases, in order that the afflicted might indulge the confident hope of receiving the <hi rend="italics">relief,</hi> the CURE, which is so earnestly desired.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >ASTHMA, RHEUMATISM, GOUT, TIC DOLOREUX.</head><p >Mr. NICHOLAS TAYLOR, Lichdon-street, Barnstaple, was for many years afflicted with rheumatism, attended with excruciating pains in the nerves and muscles, and could scarcely even dress himself without assistance. After taking one box of Kaye's Wersdell's Pills he was freed from pain and by occasionally using them he has continued so ever since.
</p><pb  xml:id="pxxx25"/><p >CATHERINE CLARK, of Littletown, Durham, was cured by the use of these Pills, after being so afflicted with rheumatic fever as to be rendered quite helpless.</p><p >

ELIZA DICKINSON, of Lockington, was dreadfully afflicted for four years with tic doloreux, and applied to several medical gentlemen without effect. She was completely cured by the use of Kaye's Pills.</p></div><div type="section"><head >DROPSY, INDIGESTION, LIVER, AND OTHER STOMACH COMPLAINTS.</head><p >DANIEL GOODMAN, 14, Snowden-street, North Liverpool, was dreadfully swollen with dropsy, and unable to attend to his business. Professional aid was tried, without any relief. A friend recommended Kaye's Worsdell's Pills to him, and by the time he had taken one boxful he was astonished to find himself quite well. He has since been able to attend to his employment with great comfort.</p><p >
MARY, the Wife of JOHN TETLOW, carrier, of Delph, Saddleworth, was afflicted with dropsy till she became almost twice her usual size, and her condition was truly deplorable. Whilst in this state she took a few of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills. She expresses her thankfulness for being completely restored to health by using them; and as she believes that under Providence she owes her life to them, she will cheerfully answer any inquiries for the satisfaction of others.</p><p >
Mr. LUSCOMBE, of Deptford, near Totness, was so swollen with, dropsy, as almost to have lost the human form. But, though he was given up by the doctors and his friends as incurable, to the astonishment of all be was completely cured by taking one box of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills.
</p><p >
Mrs. MARIA SLEEP, of Parson-street, Teignmouth, was for a long time afflicted with dropsy, and though under medical care she received no benefit. She tried Kaye's Pills, and, after taking two boxes, she was able to attend as formerly to her household employment.</p><p >
ALEXANDER MITCHELL, residing near Swansea, says:— “For twelve months I was a great sufferer from that severe malady, the liver complaint, and had the advice of a number of  medical men, but all to no purpose; at length, hearing of your Pills, I commenced taking them, and the effect produced was truly magical, for the use of one box and a half wrought a complete cure in me.”</p><p >
JOHN MANLOVE, gardener; St. Alban's, has suffered very long with a liver complaint. After taking two boxes of  Kaye's Worsdell's Pills he was quite restored to health.</p><p >
Mr. M'WHA, 16, Hanley-street, Liverpool, after having suffered from jaundice and an affection of the liver, was severely attacked by dropsy; and, upon application to his medical adviser, was told that his case was hopeless; but a friend induced him to try Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, and after taking two boxes he was perfectly restored to health.</p><p >
JONATHAN GOOD, tailor, residing in Winchester, suffered for years from indigestion. Kaye's Worsdell's Pills were recommended to him, and he is thankful that ever he used them, as he has been better in health since that than he had been for years previously. He strongly recommends the Pills to all who are similarly afflicted.</p><p >
ISAAC BAILEY, 26, Regent-street, Oldfield-road, Salford, suffered severely from indigestion for twelve months, and though under treatment by two medical men, he received no benefit. He procured one box of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, by taking which a complete cure was effected.
</p><p >
JOSEPH JUGGINS, of Market-street, Beds, had been labouring for thirty years under a complaint in the stomach, which he attributed to lying on the damp ground whilst serving in the army under the <hi rend="italics">Duke of Wellington at the battle of Waterloo</hi>. He had taken medicines in abundance, and incurred great expense in hope of relief; but the pain and sickness gradually increased, and he had given up all hope of a cure expecting his disease would carry him to the grave. After taking two boxes of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, he was so greatly relieved, that, buoyed up by hope, he persevered until he had taken
<pb xml:id="pxxx26"/>
six boxes, which effected a complete cure; and, although now far advanced in life, enjoys a state of health to which he had been a stranger for the last thirty years.</p><p >
Mr. JAMES GAMMAGE, Cumberland-street, Woodbridge, states that for some years he was greatly troubled with a redundancy of bile, foulness of stomach, and outer unpleasant symptoms. He had almost given up all hope of cure; but he tried Kaye's Pills, and found them a speedy and efficacious remedy.</p><p >
Mr. J. K. UPTON, of Banbury, declares that he found his life a burden to him in consequence of dizziness, constant head-ache, loss of appetite, and great weakness and nervous debility; but, by taking three pills' regularly every night for some time, he was completely restored to health, and is now comfortable and happy.
</p><p >
Mr. THOMAS SHARPE, of Barrowby, near Grantham, had suffered for twenty-two years from indigestion, accompanied by constant sickness and vomiting. Many physicians had been applied to in vain; but a very few doses of Kaye's Pills effectually relieved him, and he continues to enjoy a good state of health.
</p></div><div type="section"><head >TO FEMALES OF ALL AGES.</head><p >
SIR,—I can confidently recommend Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, especially to <hi rend="italics">Females</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Mothers</hi>, having used them myself for several years with success, and having witnessed their salutary and invigorating effects upon many whom I have had the honour of nursing.—M. A. TAPLEY, Nurse, Woodbridge, Suffolk.</p><p >
JANE TURNER, of Mansfield, Notts, about nineteen years of age, had all the symptoms of decline and the usual operations of nature were obstructed. She made trial of  Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, and is restored to all the bloom of health and strength.
</p><p >
Mrs. PAGE of Bexhill, who has been afflicted with a complication of diseases for many years. She suffered greatly from dropsy, liver complaint, and spasms; and though she employed many doctors, at a great expense, she
obtained little or no relief, and began to despair of a cure. After taking a few boxes of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills, she was so far recovered as to be able to walk four miles and back. The water has been driven from her chest; and she enjoys better health than she had before done for years.
</p><p >
Mrs. GRACE VENNING, wife of Mr. G. Venning, farmer, Linkenhorne, near Callington, Cornwall, was afflicted with erysipelas, of which she has been perfectly cured by persevering for a short time in the use of Kaye's Worsdell's Pills. She has had no return of the complaint.
 </p></div><div type="section"><head >TO EMIGRANTS GOING TO ALL PARTS OF THE WORLD</head><p >
Every Emigrant ought to provide himself with a supply, as by their mild yet efficacious properties, they speedily prevent or remove the various diseases produced by a sea voyage and change of diet. They will also be found of immense value after their arrival, as appears from a public statement, that amongst the articles in greatest demand at the Gold Regions were really good Patent Medicines,—the limited supply to be there met with being charged at a most exorbitant price.</p></div><div type="section"><head >IMPORTANT CAUTION.</head><p >
Be careful that you are not imposed upon by spurious imitations.  The genuine have these words; "WORSDELL'S PILLS, by JOHN KAYE," engraved on the Government Stamp; and, as a further protection, Mr. Kaye's coat-of-arms and a fac-simile of his signature are printed on the directions, wrapped round each Box, and to imitate which is felony.</p><p >
Sold in Boxes, at 1s. 1 1/2d., 2s. 9d., and 4s. 6d. each, at the Wholesale Depot, 80, Fleet-street, London; and by every respectable Medicine Vender throughout the United Kingdom.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><pb  xml:id="pxxx27"/><head >KAYE'S INFANT'S RESTORATIVE.</head><p >THE MOTHER'S BLESSING—THE NURSE'S FRIEND.</p><p >There is scarcely a more interesting sight upon earth than an affectionate mother bending with anxiety over a beloved babe, upon whose tender and delicate frame disease has laid its withering hand. It may be her first or the last born, or it may be one of many; it may be well proportioned, or it may be deformed; no matter—it is <hi rend="italics">her</hi> child; and the ordinary pleasures of life become burdensome, and the customary duties of the household are neglected: and all her thoughts and anxieties are directed to this one object, the recovery—the health of her child. With what eagerness does she listen to every piece of advice that is given her by those who are supposed to have experience, and how readily does she apply every remedy that may be recommended, in the earnest hope that her darling may be saved!</p><p >A REMEDY, however, <hi rend="italics">has been devised,</hi> which is well worthy the attention of all who desire the health of children. A remedy which, while it is singularly <hi rend="italics">efficacious,</hi> is perfectly free from all those stupefying and dangerous ingredients which are so freely dispensed under the name of <hi rend="italics">soothing cordials,</hi> and by the use of which many a mistaken mother extinguishes the feeble flame of infant life, while she fondly imagines that she is cherishing and strengthening it.</p><p >This remedy, <hi rend="italics">efficacious, palatable,</hi> and even <hi rend="italics">pleasant,</hi> to infants and young children, is KAYE'S INFANT'S RESTORATIVE. It contains a combination of agents which cannot fail to remove the <hi rend="italics">causes</hi> of all the complaints to which children are subject. It corrects acidity in the stomach, cools and purifies the blood, allays griping or irritation in the bowels, and removes every obstruction from the system. It is peculiarly serviceable during the trying period of <hi rend="italics">teething,</hi> in all eruptions of the skin, <hi rend="italics">measles,</hi> nettle-rash, chicken-pock, and other diseases of that class; as also <hi rend="italics">hooping-cough,</hi> frog, thrush, <hi rend="italics">croup,</hi> rickets, slight fevers, <hi rend="italics">convulsions, fits,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p >As a proof of its perfect efficacy in obstinate cases of HOOPING-COUGH, the following has just been received:—“A respectable person residing in <hi rend="italics">Worthing,</hi> had her children ill with the hooping-cough. After trying several things without doing them any good, she was strongly recommended to try KAYE'S INFANT'S RESTORATIVE. She did so; and, after giving them only three doses, they were quite cured. She is willing that reference should be made to her by any person similarly afflicted.” What mother, that can obtain such a remedy, will endure to see a beloved child torn and tormented by this distressing malady!</p><p >Mothers and attendants are filled with alarm whenever an infant or young child utters the frightful noise peculiar to <hi rend="italics">the</hi> CROUP. It is a dangerous symptom. But <hi rend="italics">Mr. James Banns,</hi> of Bosbury, Herefordshire, writing to Mr. Kaye on another subject, says, “Having been told of your <hi rend="italics">Infant's Restorative,</hi> and having at the same time a child ill <hi rend="italics">with the croup,</hi> I purchased a bottle and administered a dose. In the course of an hour afterwards, the child was greatly revived, and at length recovered. In many other families to which I had recommended your medicine, great good has resulted.”</p><p >The period of <hi rend="italics">teething</hi> is, generally, one of great pain to infants, and of much anxiety to mothers. In many instances the whole body is disordered, and frightfully convulsed. But <hi rend="italics">Mr. John Freeman,</hi> City Missionary, residing in Somers Town, London, writes—“Having given your <hi rend="italics">Infant's Restorative</hi> a fair trial, I can confidently recommend it as a most invaluable remedy, especially for the pain to which children are subject <hi rend="italics">during the period of teething.</hi> It soothes them, and relieves them from the many irregularities which almost invariably accompany that critical period.”</p><p >Numerous other cases might be given, but as our limited space precludes the possibility, we beg to refer to the number of cases accompanying each bottle.</p><p >Parents and nurses know well how difficult it is to administer medicine to infants in the form of pills or powder; but <hi rend="italics">Kaye's Infant's Restorative</hi> is in a convenient form, and may be given with case and perfect safety to the most tender and delicate babe.</p><p >Prepared by JOHN KAYE, Esq., of Dalton-hall, near Huddersfield, and St. John's Wood Park, London; and sold in bottles at 1s. 1½d, 2s. 9d., and 4s. 6d. each, with ample directions for use; in London, at the Wholesale Depot, No. 80, Fleet-street; and by all respectable Medicine Vendors throughout the United Kingdom.</p><p >N.B.—A considerable saving will be effected by purchasing the larger-sized bottles.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx28"/><head >WATERLOW'S <lb/> PATENT IMPROVED AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, </head><p >OR PORTABLE <lb/> PRINTING MACHINE, <lb/> FOR THE COUNTING-HOUSE, OFFICE, OR LIBRARY, <lb/> BY MEANS OF WHICH <lb/> EVERY PERSON MAY BECOME HIS OWN PRINTER.
</p><p >The process is simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing, piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.</p><p >Many hundreds of these Presses have now been sold, and are being successfully used by Railway and Public Companies, Bankers, Merchants, Amateurs, &amp;c., &amp;c.; also in Public and Private Schools, for the production of Lessons in Music, Drawing, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >The Press may be seen at work at the Patentees,’ and specimens of its production will be forwarded free, upon application.</p><p >
<table><head>PRICES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> On Mahogany Stand. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 11 × 9 </cell><cell> £7 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 16½ × 10½ </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 18 × 13½ </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >PATENT AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS FOR TRAVELLERS, <lb/> WHICH FROM ITS COMPACT FROM IS RECOMMENDED FOR USE ON <lb/> VOYAGES AND FOREIGN MISSIONS.</p><p >To Print a Subject 11 × 9 Price complete £9 9 0.</p><p >PATENTEES—WATERLOW AND SONS, 65 TO 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</p><p >From the City Article of “The Times.”</p><p >A very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, which will be productive of great convenience to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared paper, with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly valuable.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx29"/><head >PATENT LETTER COPYING PRESSES.</head><p >Lever Press.</p><p >Screw Press.</p><p >First quality Screw Press.</p><p >Wrought Iron Beam <lb/> Screw Press.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press, wrt. iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell></row><row><cell> Large 4to </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 11s. </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12s. </cell></row><row><cell> Post Folio </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MAHOGANY STANDS FOR COPYING PRESSES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Quarto. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Foolscap. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Folio. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 2 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 </cell><cell> drawer </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 2 </cell><cell> drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 </cell><cell> drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>COPYING BOOKS, OF BLUE OR CREAM-WOVE COPYING PAPER, OF FIRST QUALITY, TYPE-PAGED BY STEAM POWER.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> QUARTER BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> HALF BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell></row><row><cell> 500 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 8s. </cell><cell> 84s. </cell><cell> 500 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 102s. </cell></row><row><cell> 750 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 105s. </cell><cell> 750 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 13s. </cell><cell> 138s. </cell></row><row><cell> 1000 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 12s. </cell><cell> 126s. </cell><cell> 1000 </cell><cell> LEAVES </cell><cell> 15s. </cell><cell> 156s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink, <lb/> FOR COPYING LETTERS.</p><p >The only <hi rend="italics">really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="italics">used</hi> in many of the <hi rend="italics">Principal Establishments in London,</hi> <lb/> and is universally admitted the best yet produced.</p><p >Per PINT, 2s. Per QUART, 3s. Per DOZEN QUARTS, 30s. Per GALLON, 10s. Per HALF-GALLON, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per GALLON, do., do., 12s.</p><p >AN ECONOMICAL COPYING PRESS, <lb/> FITTED ON POLISHED MAHOGANY STAND, <lb/> WITH DAMPING BOX, COPYING BOOK, INK, AND <lb/> EVERY REQUISITE.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Large Letter Size </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio Size </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing, Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65 to 68, London Wall, London.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx30"/><opener >12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> NEW SILVER ELECTRO PLATE, </head><p > Possessing in a pre-eminent degree the qualities of Sterling Silver.</p><p >A table may be elegantly furnished with this beautiful manufacture at a <lb/> fifth of the cost of Silver, from which it cannot be distinguished.</p><p >W. MOTT invites particular attention to his very extensive stock of all articles of Plate required for the Sideboard, Dinner and Breakfast Tables, now manufactured in this elegant material, comprising superb Epergnes, Candelabra, Salad Stands, Wine Coolers, Waiters, Corner Dishes, Meat and Venison Dishes, Dish Covers, Cruet Frames, Liqueur Stands, Spoons, and Forks, Tea and Coffee Services, Tea Kettles, Toast Racks, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> TEA POTS from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 each </cell></row><row><cell> CRUET FRAMES, great variety from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 each </cell></row><row><cell> LIQUEUR FRAMES, elegant designs from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 each </cell></row><row><cell> WAITERS, of every size, from 8 to 24 inches, commencing at </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 each </cell></row><row><cell> FLOWER VASES, with glass linings from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 each </cell></row><row><cell> DISH COVERS, 12 to 20 Guineas the set. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SPOONS AND FORKS.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Fiddle. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Threaded. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> King's. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Table Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Table Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Tea Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gravy Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Sauce Ladles </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Soup Ladles </cell><cell> each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Salt Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLETS OF PRICES GRATIS.</p><p >W. MOTT. 12. CHEAPSIDE. CITY.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx31"/><opener >Manufactory, 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON.<lb/>
English Watches that may be relied upon for <lb/> Accuracy and Durability.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> English Patent Levers in Gold Cases and <lb/> Gold Dial.—Ten Guineas.</head><p >In order to assimilate as nearly as possible the cost of his best English Watches to the price of Foreign, over which they possess an immeasurable superiority in the grand requirements of correct performance and durability, W. MOTT has made a considerable reduction in the scale of prices, at the same time maintaining the high character by which, for so many years, they have been distinguished.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> GOLD CASES. </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, double back and gold dial </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, with engraved back </cell><cell> 11 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, full size, highly finished </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, engraved back </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, enamel dial </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial engraved back </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, very flat construction </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> SILVER CASES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, double back, jewelled </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, to go while winding </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, very flat construction </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, Hunting cases </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >WATCHES REPAIRED, AND ONE LENT GRATIS DURING THE TIME, <lb/> AT THE <lb/> MANUFACTORY, <lb/> No. 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, <lb/> CORNER OF FRIDAY STREET.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><pb  xml:id="pxxx32"/><opener >ON JANUARY 1ST, 1853, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Will be Published, in Foolscap Folio Sheets, price 6d each, No. 1 (to be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">continued weekly) of</hi></opener><head >MARSLAND'S <lb/> NEW AND ELEGANT <lb/> REGISTERED DESIGNS,</head><p > IN <lb/> CROCHET, GUIPURE, <lb/> LACÊT, AND EMBROIDERY WORK.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="insert"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Also, on the 1st of JANUARY, 1853, in Demy Quarto, (to be continued</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">on the 1st of every subsequent month) Part I. price 1s. of</hi> </opener><head > MARSLAND'S MANUAL <lb/> OF <lb/> CROCHET, GUIPURE, <lb/> LACÊT AND EMBROIDERY DESIGNS.
</head><p >MARSLAND, SON and Co., have been induced to publish the above works, for the purpose of supplying THE VERY BEST PATTERNS, AT THE LOWEST POSSIBLE PRICE.</p><p >Each Part of their “MANUAL” will contain TWELVE NEW AND ORIGINAL DESIGNS, with NOTES and EXPLANATIONS, by Artists of acknowledged talent, PRACTICALLY acquainted with the various branches of work illustrated and who have been engaged by them for this special purpose.</p><p >The various Designs which will appear in the above Works, are secured by MARSLAND, SON and CO., under the “Registration of Designs Act,” 5 and 6 Vict., Cap. 65.</p><p >May be had at ALL BERLIN WOOL DEALERS THROUGHOUT THE KINGDOM; and at <lb/> BRIDGE MILLS, BLACKFRIARS, MANCHESTER.</p><p >A LIBERAL ALLOWANCE TO THE TRADE</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx33"/><head >USE MARSLAND, SON, &amp; CO'S <lb/>UNRIVALLED AND REGISTERED <lb/> GRIFFIN CROCHET COTTON.</head><p >CROCHET WORK.</p><p >To such a high degree of perfection has Crochet Work been brought, in consequence of the important improvements effected by MARSLAND, SON, and Co., in their CROCHET and SEWING COTTON, that it is now generally worn by the Nobility and Gentry in preference to real lace, and thereby employment has been afforded during the past year to thousands, who would, otherwise, have been in a state of the utmost poverty.</p><p >MARSLAND, SON, and Co., having devoted the most minute attention to the various requirements of Crochet Workers, as well as to those points in the production of THEIR COTTON, which constitute the great beauty and excellence of Crochet Work; being themselves extensive manufacturers of it, beg to inform all those who take an interest in the Crochet Manufacture, whether for their own amusement, or as a matter of business, that they guarantee every article made from their cotton, will not only <hi rend="italics">retain its colour,</hi> but <hi rend="italics">wear and wash</hi> to the satisfaction of the most fastidious.</p><p >LADIES will do well to ENQUIRE in making their purchases, <hi rend="italics">whether the work has been made from Marsland, Son, and Co.'s Cotton.</hi></p><p >From the many advantages which MARSLAND, SON, and Co. enjoy, not only in the newest and most improved machinery, but also in their great manufacturing skill, and extensive experience in this particular branch of business, they are enabled to produce both Crochet and Sewing Cotton which defies all competition!</p><p >To their CROCHET COTTON they would especially call attention, not only for the peculiarity of the material itself, but for the IMPORTANT DISCOVERY made and adopted by MARSLAND, SON and Co., in the MODE OF FINISH which gives to their Cotton a soft and pulpy appearance, and a complete, freedom from fibre. It is warranted not to twist or curl in the working, or to shrink in the washing; and from its extraordinary silkiness, the Crochet Work has a beautiful pearly appearance, adding immensely to its value</p><p >MARSLAND, SON, and Co., having brought their SIX CORD COTTON to the high degree of perfection of their Crochet Cotton, so as to render it peculiarly suitable for GUIPURE and LACET WORK, beg to call the attention of Ladies, who are engaged in this branch of Crochet Work, and request they will give their Cotton A TRIAL, if they have not hitherto done so, in order to prove that the OBJECTIONS, so important as regards other Cottons, ARE NOW COMPLETELY OVERCOME.</p><p >TO PUBLISHERS OF CROCHET BOOKS.</p><p >MARSLAND, SON, and Co.'s Crochet Cotton has now so fully established its character, that all the leading publishers of the present day are bringing out their books to suit the numbers of their Cottons.</p><p >Sold wholesale by all the principal wholesale houses, and retail by all the Berlin wool venders, Drapers, Haberdashers, and Smallware Dealers throughout the Kingdom.</p><p >Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p><p >LONDON AGENTS; WRIGHT and TURNBULL, 4½, LAWRENCE LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx34"/><head >THE STORY OF THE SEASON.</head><p >CHRISTMAS has passed: the mental banquet has been less profuse than formerly, but has been supplied with differently dressed Dishes of Goblins and other strange creatures of insidious genealogy served up with Bottles of Elfins whose principal kingdom is the memory of Young People before they go to School, and which they very much improve by reading Arabian Nights and other classical productions, such as Blue Beards and Giant-Killers—but a reparation has been fully made by a story less fabulous but more entertaining. The points of the story are relative to a person known as the subject of fortune's reverses, who employed the last few pounds of his patrimony in preparing for Australia. Procuring his OUTFIT at E. MOSES &amp; SON'S, he proceeded to the “Diggings,” where his adventures and success were equally surprising, and having returned with an abundance of the “needful,” has furnished a very affecting narrative for all classes. It is only justice to suppose, that the Establishment where he took his first step toward <hi rend="italics">wealth</hi> should form a prominent part in his story; and it is equally right to observe, that E. MOSES &amp; SON, as OUTFITTERS, MERCHANT TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HOSIERS, HATTENS, BOOT and SHOEMAKERS, HATTERS, &amp;c. &amp;c., are always prepared to furnish GOODS for EMIGRANTS, for LADIES or GENTLEMEN, for FAMILIES, for Mechanics, or for any and every class in the City, Country, or throughout the World. JUVENILE CLOTHING, superior to any which can be obtained elsewhere, <hi rend="italics">made</hi> and <hi rend="italics">cut</hi> by a distinct class of artists, on a plan which never fails to ensure a correct and comfortable <hi rend="italics">fit.</hi> SPORTING DRESS, the most novel and easy styles. Materials without a parallel. OVERCOATS and WINTER DRESS in every respect excelling. All articles charged at prices so low that competition is impossible.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><p >
<table><head>E. MOSES &amp; SON'S AUTUMN AND WINTER LIST OF PRICES.</head><row><cell> MEN'S WINTER COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> The New BEQUEME Over-Coat, designed by E. MOSES &amp; SON from 25<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Pea Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Chesterfields and Codringtons, various materials </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Witney Wrapper </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Derby Coat, made to wear as an Over or Surtout Coat from 21<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The MELTON MOWBRAY, a new and elegant Overcoat from 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Wellington Sac, made to form Coat, Cloak, and Traveller's Companion, designed by and only to be had of E. MOSES &amp; Son, from 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> BOYS' WINTER COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Byron Coat from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Chesterfield from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Bulwer, in cloth of all colours, and the new Melton Mowbray material, a neat gentlemanly style of Coat 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> WALKING, FISHING &amp; SHOOTING COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Plaid Shooting Coats from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Melton Mowbray Cambridge Coat, quite a new material 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Fishing Coats in endless variety, suited either for Sporting, Gardening, or House Coat, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> AUTUMN AND WINTER WAISTCOATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> White Quilting (for Dress) 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Kerseymere 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Doeskins, Tweeds, &amp;c. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Embroidered Cloth from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> A large assortment of Fancy Thibets, and a variety of Fancy Materials from 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> AUTUMN AND WINTER TROUSERS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Tweeds from 4s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Kerseymere, for Dress from 9s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Doeskin, for Dress 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> A large assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskins 18s., 22s. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> DRESS COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Dress Coat from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best quality from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 9 </cell></row><row><cell> FROCK COATS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Frock Coat from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Coat from </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> JUVENILE CLOTHING. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Tunic and Hussar Suit from 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Polka Jacket, handsomely trimmed 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Spanish Dress from 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> LIVERIES. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> Page's suit from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Footman's </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Groom's </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Coachman's </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p ><hi rend="italics">All the above materials are made into Suits to match, and form a very comfortable dress, either for Travelling, Walking, or Office.</hi></p><p >LADIES' AND GENTLEMEN'S HOSIERY.</p><p >The Largest Stock in the Kingdom, LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Summer Cloth Habits, with 1 train from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superior Cloth Habits </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine quality </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >HATS AND CARS, THE NEWEST STYLES AT THE LOWEST PRICES.</p><p >A large Assortment of HUNTING and SHOOTING BOOTS, including the celebrated GROUSE BOOT.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the Public against imposition, having learned that the <hi rend="italics">untradesmanlike falsehood</hi> of “being connected with their Establishment,” or “It's the same concern,” has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons. They beg to state they have NO CONNECTION WITH ANY OTHER HOUSE IN OR OUT OF LONDON, EXCEPT THEIR OWN ESTABLISHMENTS, as follows:—</p><p >London City Establishments:—154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories: 83, 84, 85, and 86, Alagate, (opposite the Church) all communicating.</p><p >London West End Branch:—506, 507, and 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, and 3, Hart-street, all communicating.</p><p >Bradford, “Yorkshire” Branch, 19 and 20, Bridge-street.</p><p >Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p><p >The FUR and SHAWL DEPARTMENT is now replete with every Novelty of the Season.</p><p >IMPORTANT.—Should any article not give satisfaction, it will be exchanged, if desired, or, if preferred, the money will be returned without hesitation. All Goods are marked, in plain figures, the lowest prices, from which no abatement can be made.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed from sunset on Fridays till sunset on Saturdays, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</hi></p><p >A New Book, entitled “The World's Pharos,” containing the “Emigrant's Assistant,” full Lists of Prices, and directions for self-measurement, may be had on application, or post free to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >E. MOSES &amp; SON, <lb/> MERCHANT TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS. FURRIERS, BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pxxx35"/><head >HEAL &amp; SON'S EIDER DOWN QUILT, </head><p >The most luxurious Covering for the Bed, the Couch, or the Carriage.</p><p >PRICED LIST SENT POST-FREE.</p><p >The Catalogue contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, Mahogany, Rosewood, &amp; Walnut Tree Woods.</p><p >HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS <lb/> AND <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING, <lb/> SENT FREE BY POST FROM THEIR <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTORY, <lb/> 196, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</p><p >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS</p></div></back></text></TEI>