<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>Bleak House, No. X:</emph> Electronic Edition.</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Maura McKee</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.  300 K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_page Bleak House</title><author>Charles Dickens</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>  81 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">London:Bradbury &amp; Evans, Bouverie Street.</publisher><date>1852</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number RBC Dickens 21 c. 2 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><projectDesc><p/></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords><list type="simple"><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002">Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther  revised TEIHeader and created catalog record for the electronic edition.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-14"> Natalia Smith, project manager, finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-11">Matthew Kern finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="title_page_image"><p ><figure xml:id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"> No. X. </titlePart></docTitle><docDate>DECEMBER.
</docDate><docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE </titlePart></docTitle><byline>BY</byline><docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor><docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
<lb/>The Author of this Work notifies that it is his intention to reserve the <lb/> right of translating it.</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><head >TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</head><head >EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT.</head><p >WEIGHT 10 OZ.</p><p >Sole Manufacturers of the celebrated Pocket Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on Saddle; the most <hi rend="italics">important</hi> feature in this <hi rend="italics">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.—Price according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat.</p><p >NOTICE—NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p><p >EDMISTON &amp; SON, WATERPROOFERS, 416, STRAND, <lb/> Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >THE VERSATIO, <lb/> OR REVERSIBLE COAT.</head><p >WORTHY THE ATTENTION OF THE NOBLEMAN, MERCHANT, OR TRADESMAN.</p><p >The importance of this <hi rend="italics">patented</hi> invention consists in the novelty of the material and its application, viz., the double purpose of forming two in one without trouble, one side presenting a gentlemanly morning coat, the other a riding, shooting, or hunting coat, in any texturo or colour desired.</p><p >In over-garments or paletots this happy discovery offers still more useful advantages to the wearer, one surface exhibiting a graceful and elegant walking coat, while its counterpart is conveniently adapted for the rougher purposes of travelling, skilfully designed in each, and perfect in both their capacities. In these varying properties the public must recognise an union of novelty and usefulness not hitherto accomplished. Gentlemen supplied sending their height and size round the chest over the waistcoat. Price from 50s. to 70s.</p><closer >LONDON: EDMISTON &amp; SON, TAILORS, 69, STRAND, opposite the Adelphi Theatre.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >No. X.—December, 1852.</opener><head >BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head><head >THE LADY of The LAKE</head><p >BY SIR WALTER SCOTT. New Edition, including all his latest Copyright Notes, Various Readings, and Additions. Exquisitely Illustrated by BIRKET FOSTER and JOHN GILBERT, uniform with the Illustrated Editions of Campbell, Rogers, Thomson, Goldsmith, and Longfellow's Poems, forming a beautiful and appropriate Gift-Book for Christmas.</p><p >EXTRA CLOTH, GILT EDGES, 15s.; MOROCCO ANTIQUE, 21s.; MOROCCO ELEGANT, <hi rend="italics">bound by Hayday,</hi> 24s.</p><p >The Illustrations of the Scenery are from Sketches drawn on the spot during the past Summer, by Mr. Foster, expressly for this Work, and comprise all the principal places alluded to in the Poem.</p><closer >A. &amp; C. BLACK, EDINBURGH. HOULSTON &amp; STONEMAN, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >In the Press, to be completed in 21 Volumes 4to, <lb/> THE EIGHTH EDITION OF THE</opener><head >ENCYCLOPÆDIA BRITANNICA,</head><p >EDITED BY THOMAS STEWART TRAILL, M.D., F.R.S.E., <lb/> Professor of Medical Jurisprudence in the University of Edinburgh.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">To be published in Parts, Monthly, at</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s., and in Volumes, Quarterly, at</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s., with upwards of</hi> 500 <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Engravings on Steel, and several thousands on Wood. Part First in March,</hi> 1853.</p><p >THE FIRST VOLUME will consist of the Dissertations by DUGALD STEWART and SIR JAMES MACKINTOSH, on the Progress of Metaphysical and Ethical Philosophy; and by PROFESSOR PLAYFAIR and SIR JOHN LESLIE, on the Progress of Mathematical and Physical Science. To these will be added two new Dissertations, the first by the ARCHBISHOP OF DUBLIN, on the Rise, Progress, and Corruptions of Christianity; the second on the Progress of Physical Science, being a continuation of those by PLAYFAIR and LESLIE to the present time.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">For a limited time the Publishers will take Copies of the Seventh Edition in exchange for the Eighth, to be supplied as published, on receiving Five Pounds with each copy of the book.</hi></p><p >The whole work will undergo careful revision and extensive correction. Articles rendered imperfect by the lapse of time will be submitted for improvement to writers intimately conversant with the respective subjects, whilst other articles will be superseded by entirely new contributions, and subjects not formerly embraced in its pages will be added.</p><closer >ADAM AND CHARLES BLACK, EDINBURGH.</closer><closer >LONGMAN &amp; Co.; SIMPKING &amp; Co.; HAMILTON &amp; Co.; and WHITTAKER &amp; Co., LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >SECOND EDITION OF “ESMOND.”</head><p >By the Author of “VANITY FAIR,” “PENDENNIS,” &amp;c.</p><p >Mr. Thackeray's Novel, <lb/> ENTITLED <lb/> The History of Henry Esmond, Esq., <lb/> A Colonel in the service of Her Majesty Q. Anne, <lb/> WRITTEN BY HIMSELF, <lb/> Is being reprinted, and the New Edition will be ready in a few days, <lb/> in Three Volumes, crown 8vo, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, &amp; CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >I.<lb/><hi rend="italics">Second Edition, with Corrections and Additions,</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics">vols.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo.,</hi> 42<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> THE LIFE AND LETTERS OF BARTHOLD <lb/> GEORGE NIEBUHR.</p><p >EDITED AND TRANSLATED BY SUSANNA WINKWORTH.</p><p >WITH ESSAYS ON HIS CHARACTER AND INFLUENCE, BY THE CHEVALIER BUNSEN AND PROFESSORS <lb/> BRANDIS AND LOBELL.</p><p >The Third Volume, which will consist entirely of new matter, and comprise a Letter on Niebuhr's Political Conduct, by Chevalier Bunsen, and Selections from Niebuhr's Letters from Holland and minor writings, can be procured separately by the purchasers of the first edition.</p><p >“One of the most valuable contributions to our biographical literature which has been made in recent times.”—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p><p >II.<lb/>New Novel by the Author of “Mary Barton.”</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In December will be published,</hi>
<lb/> RUTH.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF “MARY BARTON.”</p><p >In Three Volumes, post 8vo.</p><p >III.<lb/>New Novel by the Author of “Olive,” &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In December will be published,</hi>
<lb/> AGATHA'S HUSBAND.</p><p >BY THE AUTHOR OF THE “HEAD OF THE FAMILY,” &amp;c.</p><p >In Three Volumes, post 8vo.</p><closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><head >NEW AND POPULAR BOOKS <lb/> FOR THE YOUNG.</head><p >PUBLISHED BY <lb/> GRANT AND GRIFFITH, <lb/> SUCCESSORS TO <lb/> NEWBERY AND HARRIS, <lb/> THE CORNER OF ST. PAUL'S CHURCH <lb/> YARD.</p><p >THE HISTORY OF AN ADOPTED CHILD. By JERALDINE E. JEWSBURY. With an Illustration, by JOHN ABSOLON. Fcap. 8vo, 5s. cloth.</p><p >THE FAMILY BIBLE NEWLY OPENED: with UNCLE GOODWIN'S ACCOUNT OF IT. By JEFFERYS TAYLOR, Author of “A Glance at the Globe,” “The Young Islanders,” &amp;c. Frontispiece by J. GILBERT. Fcap. 8vo, 5s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >KATE AND ROSALIND; or, Early Experiences. With an Illustration by J. GILBERT. Fcap. 8vo, 5s. cloth.</p><p >MANCO; or, An Englishman's Adventures in the Country of the Incas. A Peruvian Tale. By W. H. G. KINSTON, Esq., Author of “Peter the Whaler,” “Mark Seaworth,” &amp;c. With Illustrations by CARL SCHMOLZE. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >ANECDOTES OF THE HABITS AND INSTINCTS OF BIRDS—REPTILES and FISHES. By Mrs. R. LEE, Author of “Anecdotes of Animals,” “The African Wanderers,” &amp;c. With Illustrations by HARRISON WEIR. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >HIDDEN TREASURES; or, The Heir of Hohenberg. Edited by FREDERICK HARDMAN, Author of “Peninsular Scenes and Sketches,” “The Student of Salamanca,” &amp;c. With Engravings. Fcap. 8vo, 4s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >TWELVE STORIES OF THE SAYINGS AND DOINGS OF ANIMALS. By Mrs. R. LEE. With Illustrations by J. W. ARCHEE. Super-royal 16mo, price 2s. 6d. plain; 3s. 6d. coloured, gilt edges.</p><p >FUNNY LEAVES FOR THE YOUNGER BRANCHES. By the BARON KRAKENSIDES. Illustrated by ALFRED CROWQUILL. Coloured Plates, Price 2s. 6d.</p><p >FAMILIAR NATURAL HISTORY. With Forty-two Illustrations, from Original Drawings, by HARRISON WEIR, and Descriptions by Mrs. R. LEE. Super-royal 16mo, price 3s. 6d. cloth, plain; 6s. coloured, gilt edges.</p><p >MARK SEAWORTH: a Tale of the Indian Ocean. By W. H. G. KINGSTON, Esq., Author of “Peter the Whaler.” With Engravings. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >ANECDOTES OF THE HABITS AND INSTINCT OF ANIMALS. By Mrs. LEE, Author of “The African Wanderers.” “Adventures in Australia,” &amp;c. With Illustrations by H. WEIR. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >GOOD IN EVERYTHING; or, The Early History of Gilbert Harland. By Mrs. BARWELL. With Engravings. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. cloth; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >THE DOLL AND HER FRIENDS. By the Author of “Letters from Madras,” &amp;c. With Illustrations by PHIZ. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. cloth; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >STORIES OF JULIAN AND HIS PLAYFELLOWS. Written by his MAMMA. With Illustrations by ABSOLON. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. cloth; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >TALES FROM CATLAND, written for LITTLE KITTENS. By an OLD TABBY. With Illustrations by H. WEIR. Second Edition. Small 4to, 2s. 6d. cloth; 3s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >PETER THE WHALER: his Early Life and Adventures in the Arctic Regions. By W. H. G. KINGSTON, Esq. With Illustrations. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >ADVENTURES IN AUSTRALIA; or, the Wanderings of Captain Spencer, in the Bush and the Wilds. By Mrs. LEE. With Engravings. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth.</p><p >TALES OF SCHOOL LIFE. By AGNES LOUDON. Second Edition. With Illustrations. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. cloth; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >THE WONDERS OF HOME: in Eleven Stories. By GRANDFATHER GREY. With Engravings. Second Edition. Royal 16mo, 3s. 6d. cloth; 4s. 6d. coloured.</p><p >HOME AMUSEMENTS: a Choice Collection of Riddles, Charades, Conundrums, Parlour Games, Forfeits, &amp;c. By PETER PUZZLEWELL, Esq. Price 2s. 6d. cloth.</p><closer >GRANT &amp; GRIFFITH, CORNER OF ST. PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><opener >21, OLD BOND STREET, DECEMBER, 1852.</opener><head >MESSRS. ADDEY AND CO.<lb/>HAVE JUST PUBLISHED THE FOLLOWING <lb/> BOOKS FOR THE COMING CHRISTMAS.</head><p >I. <lb/> THE DIARY and HOURES of the LADY ADOLIE, a Faythfulle Childe, 1552. Edited by the Lady CHARLOTTE PEPYS. Quarto uniform with the First Edition of Lady Willoughby's Diary. [<hi rend="italics">Early in December.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> AUSTRALIA VISITED AND RE-VISITED. A narrative of recent Travels and Old Experiences in the Golden, Pastoral, and Agricultural Districts of Victoria and New South Wales. By SAMUEL MOSSMAN, Author of the “Gold Regions of Australia,” &amp;c., and THOMAS BANISTER, Author of “England and her Dependencies.” Post 8vo., with Maps, by A. K. Johnston. [<hi rend="italics">Early in December.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> BY THE AUTHOR OF “CHILD'S PLAY.”</p><p >A CHILDREN'S SUMMER. Eleven Etchings on Steel by E. V. B. With Prose and Poetical Illustrations. In imperial 4to., price 15s., half-bound in morocco.</p><p >A few sets of the Plates are printed on India paper, large size, price £1 11s. 6d. in Portfolio.</p><p >IV. <lb/> A NEW EDITION OF</p><p >CHILD'S PLAY. Seventeen Drawings by E. V. B. Imperial 8vo. 8s., handsomely bound; £1 11s. 6d., with Coloured Plates.</p><p >V. <lb/> A fac-simile on copper of a large Drawing by E. V. B., entitled</p><p >THE BURIAL SERVICE. Engraved by G. WENZEL, of Rome. Size of Plate, 24 inches wide by 18⅛ inches high.</p><p >Proofs before Letters, on India Paper, with the Artist's Name, (100 printed) £1 1s.; Prints, 10s. 6d.</p><p >“The accomplished and talented authoress of ‘Child's Play,’ whose designs are distinguished no less for grace and delicacy than for artistic facility and copious invention, has produced a large composition, descriptive of ‘The Burial Service in the Protestant Church.’ The same qualities that distinguish the drawings in the work above mentioned, are repeated in this instance, and a feminine sympathy of feeling softens the asperities of what might else be severe in the solemn attitudes, aspects, and costumes of grief. The contrast to the mournful scene in front, produced by the children and wreaths of flowers behind, is an effect ever welcome, however frequent it be, in the conceptions of art.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >VI. <lb/> POETICAL WORKS of EDGAR ALLAN POE. With a Notice of his Life and Genius. By JAMES HANNAY, Esq. And Twenty Illustrations by E. H. Wehnert, J. Godwin, H. Weir, and F. W. Hulme. In a handsome foolscap 8vo. volume, price 3s. 6d. cloth.</p><p >VII. <lb/> A NEW AND CHEAPER EDITION OF</p><p >THE VILLAGE QUEEN; or, Summer in the Country. By THOMAS MILLER, Author of “A Day in the Woods,” “The Country Year Book,” &amp;c. &amp;c. With watercolour Pictures by Absolon, Wehnert, Harrison Weir, and William Lee. 4to., handsomely bound in gilt cloth, 10s. 6d.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> LANDSCAPE SKETCHES from NATURE. Drawn on Stone by CHARLES SIMMS. Oblong 4to., 2s. 6d.</p><p >IX. <lb/> WATER COLOUR PICTURES. By MEMBERS of the NEW SOCIETY OF PAINTERS IN WATER COLOURS.</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. The VILLAGE DANCE, by John Absolon.</item><item>2. The GLEANERS, by William Lec.</item><item>3. The COTTAGE DOOR, by John Absolon.</item><item>4. The NUT GATHERERS, by E. H. Wehnert.</item><item>5. CATTLE at the STREAM, by Harrison Weir.</item></list><p >Mounted on Cardboard, 1s. each.</p><p >X. <lb/> SACRED PICTURES. By the OLD MASTERS. Beautifully engraved on Wood, and printed with tints in the best style.</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. The HOLY FAMILY, by Raphael D'Urbino.</item><item>2. The LAST SUPPER, by Leonardo da Vinci.</item><item>3. ADORATION of the SHEPHERDS, by Rembrandt.</item><item>4. The DESCENT from the CROSS, by Rubens.</item></list><p >Imperial folio, 1s. each.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><opener >Messrs. Addey and Co.'s New Works continued.</opener><head >BOOKS FOR YOUNG PEOPLE.</head><p >I. <lb/> THE CHARM:</p><p >A Book for Boys and Girls. The Contributions by Mrs. HARRIET MYRTLE, ALFRED ELWES, J. H. PEPPER, FREDERICA GRAHAM, CLARA DE CHATELAIN, &amp;c., &amp;c. Embellished with more than 100 Illustrations by Lejeune, Kaulbach, Weir, Wehnert. Absolon, Skill, &amp;c. &amp;c. Octavo, price 5s., bound in gilt cloth.</p><p >II. <lb/> THE CHARM ALMANACK</p><p >for BOYS and GIRLS. By the Editor of “The Charm.” With Twenty large Engravings. Post 8vo, 6d.</p><p >III. <lb/> THE ADVENTURES of a BEAR, and a GREAT BEAR TOO. By ALFRED ELWES. With Nine Illustrations by Harrison Weir. Facp. 4to, 3s. 6d. cloth; 6s. with coloured Plates.</p><p >IV. <lb/> THE PICTURE PLEASURE BOOK. Five Hundred Illustrations by the most eminent Artists. Large 4to, 6s., in elegant coloured Picture Binding by Luke Limner.</p><p >An Edition is also published mounted on cloth, price 12s.</p><p >V. <lb/> GRIMM'S HOUSEHOLD STORIES. The celebrated Stories of the Brothers GRIMM. Embellished with Two Hundred small, and Thirty-six full-page Illustrations, by E. H. Wehnert, 2 vols. crown 8vo, 10s. 6d. cloth gilt. (Complete Edition.)</p><p >VI. <lb/> A LIFE OF WELLINGTON for BOYS. By W. K. KELLY, Author of “Syria and the Holy Land,” “History of 1848,” &amp;c. &amp;c. With Eight Illustrations by John Absolon. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth gilt.</p><p >VII. <lb/> A HERO: Philip's Book; a Tale for Young People. By the Author of “Olive,” “The Head of the Family,” “Cola Monti,” &amp;c. Illustrated by James Godwin. Fcap. 8vo, 3s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> ARBELL: A Tale for Young People. By JANE WINNARD HOOPER, Author of “Recollections of Mrs. Anderson's School,” &amp;c. Illustrated by James Godwin. Fcap. 8vo, 6s. cloth gilt.</p><p >IX. <lb/> THE LITTLE DRUMMER; or, Filial Affection: a Story of the Russian Campaign. By GUSTAV NIERITZ. Translated by H. W. DULCKEN. Illustrated by John Gilbert. Fcap. 8vo, 2s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p><p >X. <lb/> WONDER CASTLE: A Structure of Seven Stories. By A. F. FRERE. Illustrated by E. H. Wehnert. Imperial 16mo, cloth gilt, 6s.</p><p >XI. <lb/> A DAY OF PLEASURE. A Simple Story for Young Children. By Mrs. HARRIET MYRTLE. Eight Illustrations by Hablot K. BROWNE. Fcap. 4to, 3s. 6d. cloth; 6s. with coloured Plates.</p><p >XII. <lb/> A NEW AND CHEAPER EDITION OF DANISH FAIRY TALES and LEGENDS. By HANS CHRISTIAN ANDERSEN. The Genuine Edition, translated direct from the Danish. With 20 Illustrations and a Portrait. Fcap. 8vo, 5s. cloth gilt.</p><p >XIII. <lb/> A NEW EDITION OF A LAUGHTER BOOK for LITTLE FOLK. Translated from the German by Madame DE CHATELAIN. With Eighteen large coloured Comic Illustrations by Thos. Hoseman. Post 4to, 2s. 6d. in coloured Picture Binding by Kenny Meadows.</p><p >XIV. <lb/> A NEW EDITION OF NAUGHTY BOYS and GIRLS. Comic Tales and Coloured Pictures. A Companion to the “English Struwwelpeter,” and “Laughter Book for Little Folk.” Post 4to, 2s. 6d. in coloured Picture Binding.</p><p >XV. <lb/> COTTAGE LIFE. Tales at Dame Barbara's Tea-Table. By MADAMS DE CHATELAIN. With Six Water-colour Pictures. 4to, 6s. cloth.</p><p >XVI. <lb/> THE GREEN BIRD: A Fairy Tale. With numerous Illustrations. 4to, 5s. cloth; coloured Plates, 7s. 6d.</p><p >XVII. <lb/> LITTLE FOLKS' BOOKS—New Volumes.</p><list  type="simple"><item>5. FAR-FAMED TALES. With 40 Illustrations.</item><item>6. ALADDIN and SINBAD. With 40 Illustrations.</item><item>7. NEW NURSERY SONGS. By Mrs. Follen. With 40 Illustrations.</item><item>8. THE LITTLE FORTUNE-TELLER: a Pastime in Poetry. Illustrated by Kenny Meadows.</item></list><p >In boards. One Shilling each.</p><p >XVIII. <lb/> WATTS'S DIVINE and MORAL SONGS. Printed on Indestructible Cloth. With 20 Illustrations. Crown 8vo, 1s. cloth.</p><p >XIX. <lb/> A NEW AND CHEAPER EDITION OF THE ILLUMINATED CHURCH CATECHISM. With Ten richly-Illuminated Borders from an Italian Missal. Small 4to, 3s. extra boards, gilt edges.</p><p >XX. <lb/> A NEW AND CHEAPER EDITION OF THE PEACOCK AT HOME. By Mrs. DORSET. Illustrated with Twelve Illuminated Borders, printed by M. and N. Hanhart. New Edition, 16mo, extra boards, gilt edges, 3s.</p><p >XXI. <lb/> NEW EDITIONS OF INDESTRUCTIBLE BOOKS for CHILDREN. Printed on cloth expressly prepared. One Shilling each.</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. INDESTRUCTIBLE ALPHABET, 26 pictures.</item><item>2. — PRIMER, 40 pictures.</item><item>3. — SPELLING-BOOK, 12 large pictures.</item><item>4. — READING-BOOK, 12 large pictures.</item></list><p >Also, price Five Shillings,</p><p >THE INDESTRUCTIBLE LESSON-BOOK, Comprising the Four Parts strongly bound in One Volume, with 90 Pictures.</p><p >XXII. <lb/> INDESTRUCTIBLE PLEASURE BOOKS. Printed in Colours on prepared cloth:—</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. DEATH OF COCK ROBIN. With 13 pictures.</item><item>2. OLD MOTHER HUBBARD. With 14 pictures.</item></list><p >Illustrated by Harrison Weir and John Absolon. Price One Shilling each, in Ornamental Binding. Registered pursuant to 5 and 6 Vict., c. 100.</p><closer >LONDON: ADDEY AND CO., 21, OLD BOND STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><opener >Sure Guide to Domestic Happiness.<lb/><hi rend="italics">This day, a New and Improved Edition, in a neat Volume, elegantly bound in cloth gilt, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >HOME TRUTHS FOR HOME PEACE; <lb/> OR, MUDDLE DEFEATED.</head><p >A Practical Inquiry into what chiefly Mars or Makes the Comfort of Domestic Life. Especially addressed to <lb/> Young Housewives.</p><p >“With all our heart we recommend this book to ladies, married or unmarried, charging their several husbands or lovers to present it to them, either as a proper reward, or as a warning caution.”—<hi rend="italics">The Critic.</hi></p><p >“Benevolent in design as it is, the authoress has produced a work which is calculated to cause an amount of good, which both young men and maidens, old men and children, will heartily thank her for.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Weekly Messenger.</hi></p><p >“Many useful hints will here be found, both for securing good, and avoiding evil in the home circle. A tone of good feeling, as well as good sense, pervades the whole book.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“We heartily recommend its sage advice and serious warnings to our fair friends. It is practical, sensible, and amusing.—Altogether, this is the very best book of the kind we have met with.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >“We have rarely met a work better calculated to diffuse practical Christianity amongst the middle class social circles of this country; and we have no doubt, that the labours of this lady will give rise to a cheerful and healthy moral tone in many a home.”—<hi rend="italics">The Observer.</hi></p><p >“Sound sense abounds on almost every page, mingled with touches of sly humour. Muddle is treated to a sharp analysis, and the means of putting an end to its empire in the family are clearly and closely pointed out. We have been much pleased with this little volume.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >“One of the best blessings that a young housewife can possibly have, if she will only read it attentively, and act by the wisdom it inculcates.”—<hi rend="italics">Lady's Newspaper.</hi></p><p >“Full of golden truths, which ought to be read and pondered upon by every housewife.”—<hi rend="italics">Eliza Cook's Journal.</hi></p><closer >LONDON: EFFINGHAM WILSON, PUBLISHER, No. 11, ROYAL EXCHANGE.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >EARLY IN DECEMBER, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Small Quarto, handsomely bound, price 21. 2s.,</hi></opener><head > POETRY OF THE YEAR: <lb/> SELECTIONS FROM THE POETS</head><p >DESCRIPTIVE OF THE SEASONS.</p><p >WITH TWENTY-TWO COLOURED ILLUSTRATIONS AFTER DRAWINGS <lb/> BY THE FOLLOWING EMINENT ARTISTS.</p><list  type="simple"><item>T. CRESWICK, R.A.</item><item>H. LE JEUNE.</item><item>C. DAVIDSON.</item><item>W. HELMSLEY,</item><item>W. LEE.</item><item>C. BRANWHITE.</item><item>J. MULLER.</item><item>E. WOLF.</item><item>E. DUNCAN.</item><item>C. WEIGALL.</item><item>BIRKET FOSTER.</item><item>HARRISON WEIR.</item><item>D. COX.</item><item>E. V. B.</item><item>LUCETTE E. BARKER.</item></list><closer >GEORGE BELL, 186, FLEET STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >A CHRISTMAS TALE, BY FRANK FAIRLEGH,  <lb/> Will appear early in DECEMBER, in 1 vol., price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, illustrated by PHIZ, entitled</opener><head >THE FORTUNES OF THE COLVILLE FAMILY;</head><p >OR, A CLOUD AND ITS SILVER LINING. BY FRANK E. SMEDLEY, <lb/>Author of “FRANK FAIRLEGH,” “LEWIS ARUNDEL,” &amp;c.</p><p >A CHRISTMAS TALE, <lb/> BY THE AUTHOR OF “THE USE OF SUNSHINE,” “THE STORY OF A FAMILY,” &amp;c.</p><p >Will be published early in DECEMBER, in 1 vol., price 6s. cloth gilt, entitled <lb/> NINA: A TALE FOR THE TWILIGHT, <lb/> BY S. M.</p><closer >LONDON: GEORGE HOBY, 123, MOUNT STREET, BERKLEY SQUARE.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7"/><head >NEW WORKS THIS SEASON.</head><p >I. <lb/> Pictures from Sicily. By W. H. Bartlett, author of “Walks about Jerusalem,” “Forty Days in the Desert,” &amp;c. With Thirty-three steel engravings, and numerous woodcuts. In super royal 8vo, handsomely bound and gilt, uniform with the “Nile Boat,” &amp;c.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">In a few days.</hi></p><p >II. <lb/> The Church before the Flood; a series of Lectures on the Book of Genesis, by REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., uniform with “Apocalyptic Sketches.”</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">At Christmas.</hi></p><p >III. <lb/> Scripture Readings on the New Testament. To be published in Monthly Numbers, price 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each. Commencing with the New Year.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">January</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st.</hi></p><p >IV. <lb/> Memorials of Early Christianity. Presenting, in a graphic, compact, and popular form, some of the memorable events of Early Ecclesiastical History. By the Rev. J. G. MIALL, author of “Footsteps of our Forefathers,” in post 8vo., with illustrations.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p><p >V. <lb/> Bases of Belief; an Examination of Christianity as a Divine Revelation by the Light of Recognised Facts and Principles. In Four Parts, 8vo. By EDWARD MIALL, M.P.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p><p >VI. <lb/> Homes in the New World; Impressions of America. By Frederika BREMER.</p><p >VII. <lb/> The Farth and its Inhabitants. By Margaret E. Darton. In crow 8vo, with coloured Frontispiece. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth lettered.</p><p >VIII. <lb/> True Stories by an Old Woman. In small 8vo.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">At Christmas.</hi></p><p >IX. <lb/> Rosalie: or “The Truth shall make you Free.” An authentic Narrative. Edited by Rev. Jos. RIDGWAY, A.M. of Sydenham. With Recommendatory Preface by M. ADOLPH MONOD, In fcap. 8vo, with Frontispiece.</p><p >[<hi rend="italics">At Christmas.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >JUST PUBLISHED.</head><p >X. <lb/> The Old Forest Ranger; or Wild Sports of India in the Neilgherry Hills, in the Jungles and on the Plains. By MAJOR W. CAMPBELL. New Edition. With illustrations on steel. In post 8vo. Price 8<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth gilt.</p><p >XI. <lb/> Ye Colloquies of Edward Osborne, Citizen and Cloth Worker of London. reported by the Author of “Mary Powell.” In post 8vo., with Frontispiece, &amp;c. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth, gift.</p><p >XII. <lb/> Pilgrimages to English Shrines. By Mrs. S. C. Hall. With notes and illustrations, by F. W. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A. Now complete in 2 vols., price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, cloth gilt.</p><p >XIII. <lb/> Autobiography of William Jerdan. Vol. 3. With a Portrait of L. E. L., after PICKERSGILL. In post 8vo, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The Fourth Volume, completing the Work, will appear on February 1st.</p><p >XIV. <lb/> Ballads for the Times and other Poems. By M. F. Tupper, Esq., D.C.L. Fourth edition, with many omissions and additions. In fcap. 8vo, with vignette and frontispiece. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 uniform with “Proverbial Philosophy.”</p><p >XV. <lb/> Thoughts and Reflections on Sickness and Affliction. By A. R. SANDERSON M.D. Second Edition, in fcap. 8vo., 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth lettered.</p><p >XVI. <lb/> Expository Readings from the Book of Revelation. Forming a continuous commentary on the Apocalypse. By the Rev. JOHN CUMMING, D.D. In one Volume. price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> cloth lettered.</p><closer >ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><head >CHRISTMAS GIFTS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">The Lady of the Lake,</hi> BY SIR WALTER SCOTT. NEW EDITION. Extra cloth, gilt edges, 15s.; morocco elegant or antique, 21s.; morocco elegant, bound by Hayday, 24s.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Life of Sir Walter Scott,</hi> By J. G. LOCKHART, ESQ. NEW EDITION, in One Vol. (Narrative Portion), 12 Engravings, cloth, 7s. 6d.; extra, gilt edges, 8s. 6d.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Poetical Works of Sir Walter Scott,</hi> AUTHOR'S EDITION. Cloth, gilt edges, 5s.; morocco antique, 10s. Large paper, cloth, gilt edges; 6s.; mirocco antique, 10s. 6d.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Illustrations to Sir Walter Scott's Poetry,</hi> by J. M. W. TURNER. <hi rend="italics">Original Proofs after Letters,</hi> royal 4to cloth, £1 15s.; imperial 4to, £2 6s.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Tales of a Grandfather (History of Scotland),</hi> by SIR WALTER SCOTT. Numerous Illustrations, 3 vols. cloth, 12s.; extra, gilt edges, 15s.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Tales of a Grandfather (History of France),</hi> by SIR WALTER SCOTT. Numerous Illustrations, cloth, 4s.; extra, gilt edges, 5s.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Beauties of Sir Walter Scott.</hi> (SELECTIONS FROM HIS WRITINGS.) Two Engravings, cloth, gilt edges, 5s.; extra, gilt sides and edges, 6s.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Readings for the Young,</hi> FROM THE WORKS OF SIR WALTER SCOTT. Numerous Illustrations, 3 vols. in one, cloth, gilt edges, 7s.; separate vols. 2s. 6d.</p><closer >ADAM &amp; CHARLES BLACK, EDINBURGH. HOULSTON &amp; STONEMAN	 LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Just published, crown 8vo, (pp. 390), price 5s. cloth,</opener><head >SPIRITS OF THE PAST.</head><p >AN HISTORICAL POEM; by the Author of “Ruins of many Lands,” &amp;c.</p><p >CONTENTS:—<hi rend="italics">Scripture Characters; Military Heroes: Celebrated Women.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Mitchell is decidedly one of the most popular poets of the day. The field now embraced declares its own deep interest—its <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>bonndless</sic><corr>bondless</corr></choice> poetic resources.”—<hi rend="italics">New Monthly Magazine.</hi></p><p >“The historical and biographical Tableaux are numerous, and most admirably delineated.”—<hi rend="italics">Tait's Edinburgh Magazine.</hi></p><p >“He has evoked with great success the Illustrious Dead of all ages, gliding from epoch to epoch, and from character to character. The work has singular variety, fascinating grace, and thrilling power.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“His style is remarkably lucid and strong; his thoughts flow easily and majestically; this respect he may be compared to Byron.”—<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><p >“The truthfulness and beauty of some of the passages are beyond all praise. The numerous Notes are full of interest and valuable information.”—<hi rend="italics">Oxford Chronicle.</hi></p><closer >London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; CO., 85, Queen street, Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >FUNERAL OF THE DUKE OF WELLINGTON.</head><p >MR. HOGARTH, PRINTSELLER, 5, HAYMARKET, <lb/> HAS THE HONOUR TO ANNOUNCE THAT HE IS PREPARING FOR PUBLICATION AN IMPORTANT <lb/> VIEW OF ST. PAUL'S CATHEDRAL <lb/> DURING THE FUNERAL CEREMONY OF THE DUKE OF WELLINGTON, <lb/> the size of which will be 27¼ by 24½ inches, exclusive of margin. The picture is painting by E. T. PARRIS, Esq., <lb/> and is so far advanced that the first etching proof may be seen at 5, HAYMARKET.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><opener >13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</opener><head >COLBURN &amp; Co.'S <lb/> NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head><p >THE RIGHT HON. B. DISRAELI'S POLITICAL BIOGRAPHY OF LORD GEORGE BENTINCK.</p><p >Fifth and Cheaper Edition. 1 vol., 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> bound.</p><p >MEMOIRS OF THE BARONESS D'OBERKIRCH;</p><p >Illustrative of the Secret History of the Courts of France, Russia, and Germany. 3 vols., 31<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> “We commend these charming volumes most heartily to every reader. They will entertain the most fastidious, and instruct the most informed.”—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p><p >THE LIFE OF MARIE DE' MEDICIS.</p><p >By MISS PARDOE. SECOND EDITION. 3 vols. Portraits. 42<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A valuable, well-written, and elaborate biography, displaying an unusual amount of research.”—<hi rend="italics">Chronicle.</hi></p><p >AUSTRALIA AS IT IS:</p><p >ITS SETTLEMENTS, FARMS, AND GOLD FIELDS. By F. LANCELOTT, Esq., Mineralogical Surveyor in the Australian Colonies. 2 Vols. 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE ROMANCE OF THE FORUM;</p><p >or, NARRATIVES, SCENES, AND ANECDOTES FROM COURTS OF JUSTICE. By PETER BURKE, Esq. Barrister-at-Law. 2 vols., 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE MARVELS OF SCIENCE; AND</p><p >THEIR TESTIMONY TO HOLY WRIT. A Popular Manual of the Sciences, By F. W. FULLOM, Esq. Dedicated by permission to the King of Hanover. SECOND EDITION. <hi rend="italics">Revised.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >ADVENTURES OF THE CONNAUGHT</p><p >RANGERS. By WILLIAM GRATTAN, Esq., late Lieutenant Connaught Rangers. SECOND SERIES. 2 Vols. 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >REVELATIONS OF SIBERIA.</p><p >By A BANISHED LADY. 2 Vols. 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“This interesting work, by a lady of quality, who for a political offence was exiled to Siberia, contains a lively and graphic picture of the country and the people, their manners, customs, &amp;c., and gives a most important and valuable insight into the economy of what has been hitherto the <hi rend="italics">terra incognita</hi> of Russian Despotism.”—<hi rend="italics">Daily News.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE NEW NOVELS.</head><p >CASTLE AVON.</p><p >By the Author of “Emilia Wyndham,” “Ravenscliffe,” &amp;c. 3 Vols.</p><p >UNCLE WALTER.</p><p >By MRS. TROLLOPE. Author of “Father Eustace,” &amp;c. 3 Vols.</p><p >“ ‘Uncle Walter’ is an admirably constructed and exceedingly entertaining novel. It assures Mrs. Trollope, more than ever, in her position as one of the ablest fiction writers of the day.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p><p >THE LIEUTENANTS STORY.</p><p >By LADY CATHERINE LONG. Author of “Sir Roland Ashton,” &amp;c. 3 Vols. <hi rend="italics">Just Ready.</hi></p><p >BROOMHILL; OR, THE COUNTY</p><p >BEAUTIES. 3 Vols. <hi rend="italics">Just Ready.</hi></p><p >THE KINNEARS.</p><p >A Scottish Story. 3 Vols.</p><p >“One of the best Scottish stories we have read for many years. That it will be universally popular is unquestionable.”—<hi rend="italics">Messenger.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >AUTHENTICATED TARTANS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> CLANS AND FAMILIES OF SCOTLAND.</head><p >WITH HISTORICAL AND TRADITIONAL <lb/> ACCOUNTS.</p><p >Just published, a New Edition of this work, the only one in which the Scottish Tartans are painted in a style worthy of their national importance. In a work of this kind the beauty of the paintings must form one of its chief qualities, as nothing can be more incongruous than to see these ancient setts disfigured in the pages of those very works which profess to bequeath their beauties to posterity. The care with which the selection of the setts has been made, is evidenced by the fact that the work has received the approval of the Antiquarian Society of Scotland.</p><closer >W. &amp; A. SMITH, Mauchline, Ayrshire; A. &amp; C. BLACK, <lb/> Edinburgh.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >Chubb's Fire-proof Safes and Locks.</head><p >CHUBB &amp; SON <lb/> Have now on Sale, at their Warehouses, an Assortment <lb/> of their <lb/> FIRE-PROOF SAFES, <lb/> WHICH GAINED THE PRIZE MEDAL, WITH <lb/> SPECIAL APPROBATION, <lb/> at the Great Exhibition, this distinction being awarded to them SOLELY by the Jurors of Class XXII., after a careful comparison with those of other makers from all parts of England.</p><p >These SAFES, undoubtedly the MOST SECURE FROM FORCE, FRAUD, and FIRE, are sold at moderate prices.</p><p >CHUBB'S LOCKS, with all the recent improvements, CASH BOXES and DEED BOXES of all sizes, may be inspected.</p><p >IRON DOORS and FRAMES for Strong Rooms.</p><p >Complete Lists, with Prices, will be sent on application.</p><p >CHUBB &amp; SON, 57. St. Paul's Churchyard, London; 28, Lord-street, Liverpool; 16, Market-street, Manchester; and Hornsley Fields, Wolverhampton.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT!</head><p >METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN.</p><p >BY ROYAL COMMAND.</p><p >JOSEPH GILLOTT most respectfully begs to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic Institutions, and the Public generally, that by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times, he has introduced a <hi rend="italics">new series</hi> of his useful productions, which for <hi rend="italics">excellence of temper, quality of material,</hi> and, above all, <hi rend="italics">cheapness in price,</hi> he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition. Each pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of Boxes, containing One Gross each, with Label outside, and fac-simile of his signature.</p><p >Victoria Works, Graham-street, Birmingham.</p><p >April 20th, 1852.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE PATENT CONCERTINA.—</head><p >Messrs. WHEATSTONE &amp; CO., the Inventors and Patentees, have now for inspection, CONCERTINAS of a new description; comprising various qualities of tone, adapted so as to be alike suitable to the drawing-room or orchestra, the latter sort being the same as those supplied to Signor Giulio Regondi, Mr. Richard Blagrove, and other eminent professors of this fashionable instrument. Full compass double-action concertinas may be had from 6 guineas each new; or secondhand as low as 4 guineas. Mssrs. WHEATSTONE &amp; Co., 20, Conduit-street, Regent-street.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><p >Punch's Almanack <lb/> for 1853 will be published <lb/> early in December.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE ROYAL TURKISH TOWELS.</head><p >UNDER the Patronage of Her Majesty the Queen, and which received the Prize Medal at the Great Exhibition. The brown Linen combines the advantages of a flesh-brush with the qualities most desirable in a Towel. The white cotton is the softest Towel ever made, and absorbs moisture without the necessity of using friction. To be had of all respectable Linendrapers.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GORGET PATENT SELF ADJUSTING SHIRT</head><p >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> TO FASTEN AT THE BACK, <lb/> WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><p >A most perfect and easy-fitting Shirt, and by a simple invention of the Patentee, adjusts itself to all movements of the body, both back and front, either walking, sitting, or riding. Price, including the REGISTERED ELLIPTIC WRISTBAND, 42s. the half-dozen. The Elliptic Collar, quite unique, in all shapes, with Patent Elastic Fastenings, 12s. the dozen. The Patent Elastic Collar Fastening can be attached to any Collar, opening back or front. Six sent by post on receipt of 13 Postage Stamps.</p><p >THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> TO FASTEN IN FRONT. <lb/> WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p><list  type="simple"><head>Directions for Self Measurement.</head><item>1. Round the Chest, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>2. Round the Waist, tight over the Shirt.</item><item>3. Round the Neck, taken about the middle of the Throat.</item><item>4. Round the Wrist.</item><item>5. The length of Coat Sleeve, from the center of Back, down the seam of Sleeve to bottom of cuff.</item><item>6. The length of Shirt.</item></list><p >Say if the Shirts are to open back or front. If with Collars attached (3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> the half-dozen extra), <lb/> PATENTEE, <lb/> GEO. P. COOPER, <lb/> TAILOR TO HER MAJESTY &amp; PRINCE <lb/> ALBERT, <lb/> 6, Suffolk-street, Pall Mall East, <lb/> London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><p >“THE BEST IS THE CHEAPEST.”</p><p >
<table><row><cell> The Best Congou Tea </cell><cell> 3s.  </cell><cell> 8d. </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Imperial Souchong Tea </cell><cell> 4s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Moyune Gunpowder </cell><cell> 5s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Plantation Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row><row><cell> The Best Mocha Coffee </cell><cell> 1s. </cell><cell>  4d. </cell><cell> per lb. </cell></row></table>
</p><closer >Tea or Coffee to the value of 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> or upwards sent, Carriage Free, to any part of England, by <lb/> PHILLIPS &amp; COMPANY, <lb/> TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> 8, KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY, LONDON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11"/><head >WORKING TAILORS' JOINT <lb/> STOCK COMPANY,</head><p >314, OXFORD STREET, near Hanover Square, <lb/> Registered according to 7 &amp; 8 Vict., cap. 110.</p><p >THE WORKING TAILORS' JOINT STOCK COMPANY return their sincere thanks to their numerous patrons for past favours, and respectfully solicit a continuance of their patronage and recommendation.</p><p >They warrant every article manufactured by them to be of the best material and workmanship; they can, with safety, do this, as all their workmen are shareholders in the Company, and thus specially interested in the success of the undertaking.</p><p >They earnestly appeal for support to those who desire to benefit the working-classes for the additional reason that this Company affords them an opportunity of doing so without cost to themselves, and without sacrificing the independence of the workman.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE EMPRESS OF CHINA'S TEA.</head><p >IMPORTED this Season for the first time, and containing all the choice sorts of the First Picking, packed in air-tight tins of various sizes at 4s. 8d. per lb. This fine Tea has been carefully analysed and examined, and submitted to numerous chemical tests by ROBERT WARINGTON, Esq., Chemical Operator to the Society of Apothecaries, and pronounced by him to be <hi rend="italics">“genuine.”</hi> J. C. L. MARSH, Esq., M.R.C.S.E. &amp; L.A.C., has also analysed it, and affirmed that “he could find no trace of copper, logwood, or any chemical dye, and recommends it as a <hi rend="italics">most wholesome</hi> article of diet.” A London Tea Inspector of 30 years' experience, has also certified “that it consists of many sorts of <hi rend="italics">really fine Tea,</hi> well matured and so judiciously blended, that great flavour and strength are most happily combined.” As a further proof of its superior quality, hundreds of the chief Tea Dealers in the country have become Agents for the sale of it. Applications for Agencies may be addressed, by first-class Tea Dealers, to Messrs. MOORE &amp; COMPANY, Sole Wholesale Agents, 38, Fenchurch Street, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p >furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy, and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.—“ROBERT SHAW, London,” is in white letters on the government stamp, without which none is genuine. Price 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.</head><p >HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS have effected another wonderful cure of a bad leg, of seven years standing.—Extract of a letter from Mr. E. Pollard, druggist, of 32, Catherine-street, Devonport, dated May, 19, 1852, to Professor Holloway:—“Sir,—Mr. Blanker, of Charlotte-street, Newpassage, near Devonport, suffered severely, for more than seven years, from a wound in his leg. He tried every remedy that medical aid could devise, but in vain, as it would not heal by their treatment. At length he had recourse to your ointment and pills, which in the course of a few weeks, perfectly cured it, and he is now in most excellent health.” Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ALBANY LAMP AND CANDLE-MANUFACTORY —</head><p >CLARKE's Russian Wax Candles, 1s. per 1b., burn superior to all others. Best Albany Composite Candles, 8d. per 1b., do not require snuffing; for ordinary purposes the Cheapest Candles that can be used, Moulds, 6d., Store Candles, 5d. per 1b.; Express Pale Soap, very old and dry, 54s. per cwt.; Good Yellow, 50s. and 44s.; Best Mottled, 56s.; Honey Soap, 1s.; Old Brown Windsor, 2s.; all other Scented Soaps, 1s. 6d. per 1b.; Patent Albany Oil, 5s. 6d. per gallon, superior to Sperm; CLARKE's Refined Oil for French Lamps, 4s. 6d. per gallon; Solar, 3s. 6d. Italian goods of the finest quality at the Wholesale Price; Lamps of every description manufactured on the premises, for cash only.</p><p >SAMUEL CLARKE, Albany Lamp and Candle Manufactory, 55, Albany-street, Regent's-park, London, within two minutes' walk of the Colosseum.</p><p >N.B. Country Orders, amounting to £10 or upwards, Carriage Free.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >CONSUMPTION AND ASTHMA CURABLE.</head><p >The invaluable Apparatus constructed upon approved scientific principles for the cure of the above diseases. Sold by W. E. LOWE, Chemist, &amp;c., S, Stafford-street, Old Bond-Street, London.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRT.</head><p >No. 84.</p><p >31s. 6d. &amp; 37s. 6d. the Half-dozen.</p><p >THE most comfortable and perfect-fitting Shirts extant, combining the highest degree of excellence at the smallest cost. Satisfaction (as usual) guaranteed, or the money returned.</p><p >Superb Dress Shirts for evening wear, 6s. 6d., 7s, 6d., and 8s. 6d. each. Also, Fashionable Coloured Shirts, ready made, or made to order, 20s. 26s., and 31s. 6d. the half-dozen. A choice of 200 New Patterns.</p><p >The general Ready-made Stock is the best, the cheapest, and the largest assortment of Shirts in London, and embraces all the recent improvements in the art.</p><p >Illustrated Priced Lists, with directions for self-measurement, and full particulars, gratis and post-free.</p><p >Patterns of the new and elegant designs for Coloured Shirts sent post-paid on receipt of Four Stamps.</p><p >RODGERS &amp; CO., Shirt Makers, 59. St. Martin's-lane, Charing Cross, and No. 29, at the Corner of New-street, Covent-garden, London. Established Sixty Years.—N.B. Boy's Shirts in all Sizes.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >SOYER'S RELISH.</head><p >“To describe the Sauce would be to make our readers hungry,—rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poured.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p><p >THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents, <lb/> CROSSE AND BLACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen.</p><closer >GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p12"/><head >CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES</head><p >of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY. </p><p >IN FULL DRESS.</p><p >WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p><p >SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p><p >INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS, <lb/> BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p><p >BABY LINEN IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p><p >TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p><p >An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information, sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >PROFESSOR LIEBIG'S OPINION OF ALLSOPP'S <lb/> PALE ALE.</head><p >“The specimens of your Pale Ale, sent to me, afforded me another opportunity of confirming its valuable qualities. I am myself an admirer of this beverage, <hi rend="italics">and my own experience enables me to recommend it,</hi> in accordance with the opinion of the most eminent English physicians, as a very agreeable and efficient tonic, and as a general beverage both for the invalid and the robust.</p><p >“Giessen, May 6, 1852.”</p><p >“JUSTUS LIEBIG.”</p><p >BARON LIEBIG ON CERTAIN RECENT ANONYMOUS ADVERTISEMENTS</p><p >Messrs. ALLSOPP &amp; SONS have great satisfaction in being enabled to publish the following extract of a Letter just received, dated Munich, 12th, September, 1852, from BARON LIEBIG to Mr. HENRY ALLSOPP, Brewery, Burton-on-Trent.</p><p >“To my great astonishment and concern, my attention has lately been called to several anonymous articles and advertisements headed by my name, such as in the —, whose author altogether misrepresents the motives of my remarks, and even goes so far as to say ‘that I had never analysed your beer, nor perhaps ever tasted it in my life,’ and to allege a retraction on my part of the original statement.</p><p >“I emphatically declare that I had not the slightest knowledge of these anonymous articles, the contents of which I entirely disapprove of; and that in every respect I adhere to the statement made in my letter to you, which certainly you were, and are at perfect liberty to publish.</p><p >“Munich, 12th September, 1852.”</p><p >“JUSTUS LIEBIG.”</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >JUSTUS LIEBIG ON PALE ALES.</head><p >“If I wished to associate with any individual brewery my remarks on the alleged adulteration of bitter beer with strychnine, it would have been only natural to have mentioned another brewery in which alone, and not in Mr. ALLSOPP'S I was engaged in investigating the Burton mode of brewing; and it was also in that brewery, and NOT IN MR. ALLSOPP'S, that the Bavarian brewers acquired all the instructions they obtained at Burton. The admiration I expressed of this beverage in my letter to Mr. ALLSOPP is advertised in such a manner as to lead to the inference that my praise was exclusively confined to Mr. ALLSOPP'S beer; THIS WAS NOT THE CASE: my remarks referred to that CLASS of beer.</p><p >“Giessen, July 24, 1852.”</p><p >“JUSTUS LIEBIG.”</p><p >N.B. The Baron's original letter is in the hands of Mr. Miller, at the Jerusalem Coffee House, Cornhill, where it may be seen by any one taking an interest in the matter.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >BARON LIEBIG ON PALE ALES.</head><p >MESSRS. ALLSOPP AND SONS <lb/> Recommend parties applying to Mr. MILLER of the Jerusalem Coffee House, Cornhill, London, for any information on the above subject, to ask to see a letter from BARON LIEBIG addressed to Mr. BASS, and dated GIESSRN, 23rd August, 1852. Copies of which letter are already in the possession of all the Brewers at Burton-upon-Trent.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13"/><head >PRIZE MEDAL.</head><head >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S <lb/> GOLD CHAINS.</head><p >By Troy Weight, and Workmanship at Wholesale <lb/> Manufacturers' Prices.</p><p >THE Great Exhibition having established the Advantage of Purchasing from the Wholesale Manufacturer, wherever it can be accomplished, and thereby dispensing with an intermediate profit, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to announce that, in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them, they have thrown open their Manufactory to the Public at the same prices they have been in the habit (for the last half century) of charging to the Trade in London, India, and the Colonies.</p><p >WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to caution the Public against the Electro Gold Chain and Polished Zinc Gold, so extensively put forth in the present day, under the titles of “Pure Gold” and “Fine Gold,” and to call attention to the genuine Gold Chains made from their own ingots, and sold by Troy Weight at its bullion or realisable value.</p><p >The system of Weighing Chains against Sovereigns being one of the greatest frauds ever practised on the Public, WATHERSTON AND BROGDEN guarantee the Gold in their Chains, and will re-purchase it at the price charged; the workmanship according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern.</p><p >EXAMPLE.—Intrinsic value of a Chain of 15-Carat</p><p >
<table><row><cell> Gold, weighing 1⅛ Ounces </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 7 </cell></row><row><cell> Supposing the workmanship to be </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Total </cell><cell> £5 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 7 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >By this arrangement, the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">Bullion</hi> in a Gold Chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">An extensive assortment of Jewellery, all of the first quality, made at their Manufactory.</hi></p><closer >16, HENRIETTA STREET, COVENT GARDEN, LONDON.</closer><closer >ESTABLISHED A.D. 1798.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><head >MOTHERS! MOTHERS!! MOTHERS!!!</head><p >THE BEST MEDICINE IN THE WORLD for INFANTS AND YOUNG CHILDREN IS ATKINSON AND BARKER'S ROYAL INFANTS' PRESERVATIVE.—Under the Patronage of the Queen.—The high and universal celebrity which this medicine continues to maintain for the prevention and cure of those disorders incident to infants; affording instant relief in convulsions, flatulency, affections of the bowels, difficult teething, the thrush, rickets, measles, hooping-cough, cow-pox, or vaccine inoculation, and may be given with safety immediately after birth. It is no misnomer cordial !—no stupefactive, deadly narcotic!—but a veritable preserver of infants! Mothers would do well in always keeping it in the nursery. Many thousands of children are annually saved by this much-esteemed medicine, which is an immediate remedy, and the infants rather like it than otherwise.</p><p >Prepared only by ROBERT BARKER. Ollerenshaw Hall, Chapel-en-le-Frith, Derbyshire, late of Manchester, (Chemist to Her most Gracious Majesty Queen Victoria), in bottles at ls. 1½d., 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 11s. each.</p><p >Sold by all druggists and medicine vendors throughout the United Kingdom.</p><p >CAUTION.—Observe the name of “ATKINSON &amp; BARKER,” on the Government Stamp. Established in the year 1793.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS</head><p >Differ from other Patterns, not merely in shape and design, but in their great superiority of Fit, quality of Material, and Workmanship.—<hi rend="italics">Globe, April</hi> 12, 1852. They are of two prices ; viz. Six for 40s.; Second Quality Six for 30s. in both of which the principle is strictly carried out.</p><p >List of Prices, and mode of Self-measurement sent free per Post.</p><p >FORD'S REGISTERED SHIRT COLLARS, 11s. per dozen.</p><p >Patterns of the New Coloured Shirtings in every variety of Colours. Upwards of 200 different styles for making FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS sent to select from on the receipt of six postage stamps. Price 27s. the half dozen.</p><closer >RICHARD FORD, 38, POULTRY, <lb/> LONDON, (Late 185, Strand.)</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14"/><opener >PULVERMACHER'S PATENT PORTABLE</opener><head >HYDRO-ELECTRIC CHAIN</head><p >Exhibited with the greatest success before the <hi rend="italics">Royal Coll. of Physicians, Royal Coll. of Surgeons, Royal Brit. Association, Prov. Med. Chirurgical Association, Académic de Medicine</hi> at Paris, (a vote of thanks to the Inventor.)</p><p >Highly favourable</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Testimonials in Writing</hi> from the most distinguished Members of the Profession, and now extensively used and prescribed in the <hi rend="italics">Hospitals</hi> of London, Edinburgh, Manchester, Nottingham, Birmingham, Paris, &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Constructed to be worn on the body under the Garments,</hi>
<lb/> SUPPLYING MILD STREAMING ELECTRICITY.</p><p >OR VITAL ENERGY TO THE SYSTEM.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Immediate Relief</hi> from acute pains. <hi rend="italics">Radical Cure</hi> of RHEUMATIC, CATARRHAL, NEURALGIC, SPASMODIC, NERVOUS, and FUNCTIONAL DISORDERS, within an incredibly short space of time, by this simple and painless remedy, which can be freely tested <hi rend="italics">beforehand,</hi> at C. MEINIG'S Head Depots, 103, Leadenhall Street, and 71, Regent Street. 600 <hi rend="italics">Cases of Cures within the last Eight Months,</hi> signed by PHYSICIANS, NOBLEMEN, CLERGYMEN, MAGISTRATES, &amp;c.—<hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 22<hi rend="italics">s., and</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> according to Power.</p><p >FULL DESCRIPTION GRATIS (<hi rend="italics">or per post for Two Stamps</hi>).</p><p >...“I can scarcely recommend Dr. P.'s ingenious invention too strongly to the notice of my Medical Brethren.” <hi rend="italics">From that eminent Physician of Guy's Hospital, DR. GOLDING BIRD, M.D., F.R.S., &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><opener >Winter Royal Patronage.<lb/>PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES <lb/> AND INSTANT RELIEF AND A RAPID CURE OF <lb/> ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, COLDS, <lb/> AND ALL <lb/> DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS <lb/> ARE INSURED BY </opener><head >DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS</head><p >Another Testimonial.</p><p >From Mr. A. Scott, 42, Trongate, Glasgow, October 20, 1852.—“I am glad to say that the demand for Dr. Locock's Pulmonic Wafers has commenced this season very briskly. I believe I keep in stock every Cough Medicine which has been advertised, either in times past or present, but there is not one of them which has gained the same popularity as your Wafers. In severe Coughs, Asthma, and where there is a tendency to Consumption, the working classes and others who cannot well afford it, prefer to pay 2s. 9d. for a box of Pulmonic Wafers, to boxes of similar size which can be got for a much smaller sum. I think this is an unmistakeable proof of their efficacy. “42, Trongate, Glasgow. A. SCOTT.”</p><p >Cures of Consumption in Newcastle.</p><p >“13, Mosley Street, Newcastle-on-Tyne.</p><p >“Gentlemen,—I can myself speak of your Wafers with the greatest confidence, having recommended them in many cases of Pulmonary Consumption, and they have always afforded relief when everything else has failed, and the patients having been surfeited with medicine, and delighted to meet with so efficient a remedy, having such an agreeable taste.</p><p >“J. MAWSON.”</p><p >TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p><p >THEY HAVE A PLEASANT TASTE. Price 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >Also, may be had, <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S FAMILY APERIENT AND ANTIBILIOUS WAFERS.</p><p >A mild and gentle Aperient and Stomach Medicine, having a most agreeable taste, and of great efficacy for regulating the Secretions and correcting the action of Stomach and Liver. Sold at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box. Also, <lb/> LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS, <lb/> The best Medicine for Females. They have a pleasant taste. Price 18. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p><p >Full directions are given with every box.</p><p >SOLD BY ALL RESPECTABLE CHEMISTS.</p><p >ALL PILLS UNDER SIMILAR NAMES ARE COUNTERFEITS.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.</head><p >UPWARDS OF FORTY YEARS' experience has fully confirmed the superior reputation of these Lozenges, in the cure of Asthma, Winter Cough, Hoarseness, Shortness of Breath, and other Pulmonary Maladies.</p><p >They have deservedly obtained the high patronage of their Majesties the KING OF PRUSSIA, and the KING OF HANOVER; very many also of the NOBILITY and CLERGY, and of the public generally, use them, <hi rend="italics">under the recommendation of some of the most eminent of the Faculty.</hi></p><p >Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1s. 1½d., and Tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Church-yard, London.</p><p >Sold Retail by all Druggists and Patent Medicine Venders in the Kingdom.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15"/><head >CHRISTMAS.</head><p >THE Yule-Log will soon burn ruddily on the hearth; the tables be spread with luxurious cheer; merry guests will assemble; the toast go round; the song enchant all hearers; the cheek of beauty will glow; the heart of youth will palpitate with love and joy; and finally—</p><p >“A MEASURE—A MEASURE—FOR FAIR DAMES AND GENTLEMEN!” will resound through the glorious halls.</p><p >It is at this period of festivity and mirth that the fair and youthful are more than usually desirous of shining in<lb/>PERSONAL ATTRACTION,<lb/>under the gaze of many friends, and the following unrivalled discoveries for the TOILET are necessarily called into increased requisition.</p><p >The Patronage of Royalty and the Aristocracy throughout Europe, and their well-known infallible efficacy, render them a peculiarly<lb/>ELEGANT AND SEASONABLE PRESENT.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ROWLANDS' MACASSAR OIL,</head><p >IS A DELIGHTFULLY FRAGRANT AND TRANSPARENT PREPARATION FOR THE HAIR; and as an <hi rend="italics">invigorator and beautifier</hi> beyond all precedent. In dressing the hair nothing can equal its effect, rendering it so admirably soft that it will lie in any direction, and imparting a transcendent lustre. Price 3s. 6d.; 7s. Family Bottles (equal to four small), 10s. 6d; and double that size, 21s.</p><div type="advertisement"><head >ROWLANDS' KALYDOR,</head><p >FOR THE SKIN AND COMPLEXION, <lb/> Is unequalled <hi rend="italics">for its rare and inestimable qualities.</hi> The radiant bloom it imparts to the CHEEK; the softness and delicacy which it induces of the HANDS and ARMS; its capability of soothing Irritations, and removing CUTANEOUS DEFECTS, DISCOLOURATIONS, and all unsightly appearances, render it indispensable to every Toilet. Price 4s. 6d. and 8s. 6d. per bottle.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ROWLANDS' ODONTO,</head><p >OR PEARL DENTIFRICE, <lb/> Prepared from Oriental Herbs with unusual care, transmitted to this country at great expense, this unique compound will be found of inestimable value in <hi rend="italics">preserving and beautifying the Teeth, strengthening the Gums,</hi> and in giving sweetness and perfume to the breath. Price 2s. 9d. per box.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >ROWLANDS' AQUA D'ORO.</head><p >A fragrant and refreshing perfume, combining the spirituous essences and essential properties of the most esteemed and valuable exotic flowers and plants, without any one being in the ascendant. Price 3s. 6d. per bottle.</p><p >BEWARE OF SPURIOUS IMITATIONS!!!</p><p >The only GENUINE of each bears the name of “ROWLANDS”’ preceding that of the Article on the <lb/> Wrapper or Label.</p><p >Sold by A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS, 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><head >THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.—</head><p >The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p><p >
<table><head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head><row><cell> Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell><cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell><cell> Inches. </cell><cell> Eighths. </cell></row><row><cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell><cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows </cell><cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY £1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p >(as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Disinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p><p >Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p><div><head >RIMMEL'S HAIR DYE</head><p >imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.—Price 5s. 6d.</p><p >RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended.—Beware of counterfeits.</p><p >Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39, Gerard-street, Soho, London.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16"/><head >Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'S REGISTERED PARDESSUS,</head><p >OF FINE AUSTRALIAN and LLAMA WOOLS, (6TH &amp; 7TH VICTORIA, CAP. 65), <lb/> FOR WALKING OR RIDING.</p><p >THIS is an improved style of Coat, of a light convenient form, which admits of its being worn either over or without the ordinary coat. It is neatly and handsomely made, care being bestowed in its construction, to impart to it that graceful and appropriate character which, since its first introduction, has so greatly recommended it to public favour; it is produced in all colours with silk sleeve linings, at the very moderate price of TWO GUINEAS; and for Winter wear, richly lined and quilted, TWO-AND-A-HALF and THREE GUINEAS. The IMPROVED WINTER GUINEA TROUSERS are also ready for selection from a choice variety of patterns.</p><p >In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s, Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94 REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p></div><div type="advertisement"><head >GREAT EXHIBITION, JURY REPORT.</head><p >CLASS XXIX., p. 661.</p><p >“W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Prize Medal for Silk Parasols and Umbrellas of excellent quality, and for their application of Alpaca Cloth to the Coverings of Umbrellas and Parasols.”</p><p >As the merit in an Umbrella consists in its strength, combined with extreme lightness, W. &amp; J. S. beg to say that they are now prepared to offer for the first time an Umbrella made on Fox's Paragon Frames, possessing these requirements, and rendering it an article perfectly unique, whether in Silk or Alpaca.</p><p >W. AND J. SANGSTER,</p><list  type="simple"><item>140, Regent Street.</item><item>94, Fleet Street.</item><item>10, Royal Exchange.</item><item>75, Cheapside.</item></list><closer >AGENTS FOR THE UNITED STATES, <lb/> MESSRS. F. DERBY &amp; CO., 12, PARK PLACE, NEW YORK.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p17"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., neatly bound in cloth,</hi></opener><head > THE SECOND VOLUME <lb/> OF <lb/> A CHILD'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</head><p >BY CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >WITH FRONTISPIECE FROM A DRAWING BY F. W. TOPHAM.</p><p >CORRECTED AND REVISED FROM “HOUSEHOLD WORDS,” WITH A TABLE OF DATES.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The History will be completed in Three Volumes.</hi></p><div type="advertisement"><head >Works by the same Author.</head><p >BLEAK HOUSE. WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY LABLOT K. BROWNE. Now publishing in Monthly Parts, price 1s. each. (To be completed in Twenty).</p><p >DAVID COPPERFIELD. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >DOMBEY AND SON. With Forty Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >OLIVER TWIST. With Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Price 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p >PICTURES FROM ITALY. In fep. 8vo. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price 5s., each, bound in cloth, gilt edges, the Illustrations by</hi> D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., <lb/> FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, JOHN TENNIEL, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> RICHARD DOYLE.</p><p >A CHRISTMAS CAROL, IN PROSE.</p><p >THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH.<lb/>A Fairy Tale of Home.</p><p >THE BATTLE OF LIFE. A LOVE STORY.</p><p >THE HAUNTED MAN AND THE GHOST'S BARGAIN. A Fancy for Christmas Time.</p><p >THE CHIMES. A GOBLIN STORY OF SOME BELLS THAT RANG AN OLD YEAR OUT AND A NEW YEAR IN.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><opener ><hi rend="italics">To be completed in about Seven Volumes, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each,</opener><head >COLLECTED EDITION of the WORKS of DOUGLAS JERROLD.</head><list  type="simple"><item>VOL.1.—MEN OF CHARACTER.</item><item>3.—MRS. CAUDLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES; STORY OF A FEATHER; AND THE SICK GIANT AND DOCTOR DWARF.</item><item>VOL.2.—ST. GILES AND ST. JAMES.</item><item>4.—CAKES AND ALE.</item><item>5.—IN PROGRESS.</item></list><p ><hi rend="italics">Publishing also in Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 1½<hi rend="italics">d. each, and Monthly Parts, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">d. each.</hi></p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p18"/><head >Illustrated Works Suitable for Christmas Presents.</head><p >PUNCH'S POCKET-BOOK FOR 1853.</p><p >With a large Coloured Engraving by JOHN LEECH, and Numerous Woodcuts by JOHN LEECH <lb/> and JOHN TENNIEL. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >THE LIFE AND <lb/> ADVENTURES OF OLIVER GOLDSMITH.</p><p >A BIOGRAPHY; IN FOUR BOOKS. BY JOHN FORSTER, ESQ.</p><p >In one large volume. Forty Original Designs, engraved on Wood. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE STORY OF NELL GWYN <lb/> AND THE SAYINGS OF CHARLES THE SECOND.</p><p >Collected and Related by PETER CUNNINGHAM. Plates. Crown 8vo. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >MANNERS AND CUSTOMS OF THE ENGLISH <lb/> IN 1849.</p><p >Drawn from ye Quick, by RICHARD DOYLE. With some Extracts from Mr. Pips his Diary, <lb/> by PERCIVAL LEIGH. Complete, price 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >YOUNG TROUBLESOME; <lb/> OR, MASTER JACKY'S HOLIDAYS.</p><p >A Series of Plates by JOHN LEECH. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> plain; 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured.</p><p >VANITY FAIR.</p><p >BY W. M. THACKERAY.</p><p >With Forty Steel Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts, by the Author. 8vo. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p ><hi rend="italics">By the same Author.</hi></p><p >THE HISTORY OF PENDENNIS.</p><p >Forty-eight Steel Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts, by the Author. 2 Vols. 8vo. Price 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE COMIC HISTORY OF ROME.</p><p >BY GILBERT ABBOTT A'BECKETT.</p><p >Illustrated with Ten Coloured Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH. Price 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">By the same Author.</hi></p><p >THE COMIC HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</p><p >Twenty Coloured Engravings, and Numerous Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH. In 2 Vols. 8vo. Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</p><p >A FAIRY TALE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE. BY MARK LEMON.</p><p >Illustrated by RICHARD DOYLE. Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in boards.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p19"/><head >MISCELLANEOUS WORKS.</head><p >THE BRITISH WINTER GARDEN; <lb/> A PRACTICAL TREATISE ON EVERGREENS: <lb/> Showing their general utility in the Formation of Garden and Landscape Scenery, and their mode of Propagating, <lb/> Planting, and Removal, from one to fifty feet in height, as Practised at Elvaston Castle.</p><p >BY WILLIAM BARRON, HEAD GARDENER.</p><p >Price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth. With Illustrations.</p><p >HOW TO LAY OUT A SMALL GARDEN.</p><p >Intended as a Guide to Amateurs in Choosing, Forming, or Improving a Place (from a Quarter of an <lb/> Acre to Thirty Acres in extent), with reference to both Design and Execution.</p><p >BY EDWARD KEMP, LANDSCAPE GARDENER, BIRKENHEAD PARK.</p><p >Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> bound in cloth.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">By the same Author, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE HAND-BOOK OF GARDENING.</p><p >For the use of all persons who possess a Garden of limited extent. The Tenth Edition, enlarged and improved.</p><p >PROSE AND VERSE.</p><p >BY MARK LEMON.</p><p >Foolscap 8vo. price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p><p >HOW TO SEE THE BRITISH MUSEUM.</p><p >In Four Visits.</p><p >BY WILLIAM BLANCHARD JERROLD.</p><p >Complete in One Volume, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >WHAT SHALL WE HAVE FOR DINNER?</p><p >BY LADY CLUTTERBUCK. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</p><p >EDITED BY W. C. MACREADY.</p><p >For Schools and Families. Price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Cloth.</p><p >THE SHIPMASTER'S GUIDE.</p><p >BY THE REGISTRAR-GENERAL OF SEAMEN.</p><p >Containing ample Directions for Making the Returns, and otherwise complying with the provisions of the <lb/> Mercantile Marine Act, the Merchant Seaman's Act, and the Seaman's Protection Act, &amp;c. &amp;c. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >THE NATURAL HISTORY OF CAGE BIRDS.</p><p >Their Management, Habits, Food, Diseases, Treatment, Breeding, and the Methods of Catching them.</p><p >BY J. M. BECHSTEIN, M.D. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth, gilt.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p20"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s., handsomely bound in cloth,</hi></opener><head > Mr. SPONGE'S <lb/> SPORTING TOUR</head><p >By the Author of “Handley Cross,” &amp;c.&amp;c. <lb/> With Coloured Illustrations and Woodcuts by John Leech. </p><closer > BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Nurse and Patient</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">The appointed time.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pv"/><p ><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Visitors at the Shooting Gallery.</hi></p></figure></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pvi"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">th of December will be published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> AN EXTRA NUMBER <lb/> OF</opener><head >HOUSEHOLD WORDS;</head><p >A WEEKLY JOURNAL</p><p >CONDUCTED BY CHARLES DICKENS.</p><p >BEING THE <lb/> ANNUAL CHRISTMAS NUMBER.</p><p >OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH.</p><p >SOLD BY ALL BOOKSELLERS AND NEWSMEN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p289"/><head >CHAPTER XXX. <lb/> ESTHER'S NARRATIVE.</head><p >RICHARD had been gone away some time, when a visitor came to pass a few days with us. It was an elderly lady. It was Mrs. Woodcourt, who, having come from Wales to stay with Mrs. Bayham Badger, and having written to my guardian, “by her son Allan's desire,” to report that she had heard from him and that he was well, “and sent his kind remembrances to all of us,” had been invited by my guardian to make a visit to Bleak House. She stayed with us nearly three weeks. She took very kindly to me, and was extremely confidential: so much so that sometimes she almost made me uncomfortable. I had no right, I knew very well, to be uncomfortable because she confided in me, and I felt it was unreasonable; still, with all I could do, I could not quite help it.</p><p >She was such a sharp little lady, and used to sit with her hands folded in each other, looking so very watchful while she talked to me, that perhaps I found that rather irksome. Or perhaps it was her being so upright and trim; though I don't think it was that, because I thought that quaintly pleasant. Nor can it have been the general expression of her face, which was very sparkling and pretty for an old lady. I don't know what it was. Or at least if I do, now, I thought I did not then. Or at least—but it don't matter.</p><p >Of a night when I was going up-stairs to bed, she would invite me into her room, where she sat before the fire in a great chair; and, dear me, she would tell me about Morgan ap Kerrig until I was quite low-spirited! Sometimes she recited a few verses from Crumlinwallinwer and the Mewlinwillinwodd, (if those are the right names, which I dare say they are not), and would become quite fiery with the sentiments they expressed. Though I never knew what they were (being in Welsh), further than that they were highly eulogistic of the lineage of Morgan ap Kerrig.</p><p >“So, Miss Summerson,” she would say to me with stately triumph, “this, you see, is the fortune inherited by my son. Wherever my son goes, he can claim kindred with Ap Kerrig. He may not have money, but he always has what is much better—family, my dear.”</p><p >I had my doubts of their caring so very much for Morgan ap Kerrig, in India and China; but of course I never expressed them. I used to say it was a great thing to be so highly connected.</p><p >“It <hi rend="italics">is,</hi> my dear, a great thing,” Mrs. Woodcourt would reply. “It has its disadvantages; my son's choice of a wife, for instance, is limited by it; but the matrimonial choice of the Royal family is limited, in much the same manner.”</p><p >Then she would pat me on the arm and smooth my dress, as much as to assure me that she had a good opinion of me, the distance between us notwithstanding.</p><p >“Poor Mr. Woodcourt, my dear,” she would say, and always with some emotion, for with her lofty pedigree she had a very affectionate heart, “was descended from a great Highland family, the Mac Coorts of Mac
<pb xml:id="p290"/>
Coort. He served his king and country as an officer in the Royal Highlanders, and he died on the field. My son is one of the last representatives of two old families. With the blessing of Heaven he will set them up again, and unite them with another old family.”</p><p >It was in vain for me to try to change the subject, as I used to try—only for the sake of novelty—or perhaps because—but I need not be so particular. Mrs. Woodcourt never would let me change it.</p><p >“My dear,” she said one night, “you have so much sense, and you look at the world in a quiet manner so superior to your time of life, that it is a comfort to me to talk to you about these family matters of mine. You don't know much of my son, my dear; but you know enough of him, I dare say, to recollect him?”</p><p >“Yes, ma'am. I recollect him.”</p><p >“Yes, my dear. Now, my dear, I think you are a judge of character, and I should like to have your opinion of him?”</p><p >“O, Mrs. Woodcourt!” said I, “that is so difficult.”</p><p >“Why is it so difficult, my dear?” she returned. “I don't see it myself.”</p><p >“To give an opinion —”</p><p >“On so slight an acquaintance, my dear. <hi rend="italics">That's</hi> true.”</p><p >I didn't mean that; because Mr. Woodcourt had been at our house a good deal altogether, and had become quite intimate with my guardian. I said so, and added that he seemed to be very clever in his profession—we thought—and that his kindness and gentleness to Miss Flite were above all praise.</p><p >“You do him justice!” said Mrs. Woodcourt, pressing my hand. “You define him exactly. Allan is a dear fellow, and in his profession faultless. I say it, though I am his mother. Still, I must confess he is not without faults, love.”</p><p >“None of us are,” said I.</p><p >“Ah! But his really are faults that he might correct, and ought to correct,” returned the sharp old lady, sharply shaking her head. “I am so much attached to you, that I may confide in you, my dear, as a third party wholly disinterested, that he is fickleness itself.”</p><p >I said, I should have thought it hardly possible that he could have been otherwise than constant to his profession, and zealous in the pursuit of it, judging from the reputation he had earned.</p><p >“You are right again, my dear,” the old lady retorted; “but I don't refer to his profession, look you.”</p><p >“O!” said I.</p><p >“No,” said she. “I refer, my dear, to his social conduct. He is always paying trivial attentions to young ladies, and always has been, ever since he was eighteen. Now, my dear, he has never really cared for any one of them, and has never meant in doing this to do any harm, or to express anything but politeness and good nature. Still, it's not right, you know; is it?”</p><p >“No,” said I, as she seemed to wait for me.</p><p >“And it might lead to mistaken notions, you see, my dear.”</p><p >I supposed it might.</p><p >“Therefore I have told him, many times, that he really should be more careful, both in justice to himself and in justice to others. And he
<pb xml:id="p291"/>
has always said, ‘Mother, I will be; but you know me better than anybody else does, and you know I mean no harm—in short, mean nothing.’ All of which is very true, my dear, but is no justification. However, as he is now gone so far away, and for an indefinite time, and as he will have good opportunities and introductions, we may consider this past and gone. And you, my dear,” said the old lady, who was now all nods and smiles; “regarding your dear self, my love?”</p><p >“Me, Mrs. Woodcourt?”</p><p >“Not to be always selfish, talking of my son, who has gone to seek his fortune, and to find a wife—when do you mean to seek <hi rend="italics">your</hi> fortune and to find a husband, Miss Summerson? Hey, look you! Now you blush!”</p><p >I don't think I did blush—at all events, it was not important if I did—and I said, my present fortune perfectly contented me, and I had no wish to change it.</p><p >“Shall I tell you what I always think of you, and the fortune yet to come for you, my love?” said Mrs. Woodcourt.</p><p >“If you believe you are a good prophet,” said I.</p><p >“Why, then, it is that you will marry some one, very rich and very worthy, much older—five and twenty years, perhaps—than yourself. And you will be an excellent wife, and much beloved, and very happy.”</p><p >“That is a good fortune,” said I. “But, why is it to be mine?”</p><p >“My dear,” she returned, there's suitability in it—you are so busy, and so neat, and so peculiarly situated altogether, that there's suitability in it, and it will come to pass. And nobody, my love, will congratulate you more sincerely on such a marriage than I shall.”</p><p >It was curious that this should make me uncomfortable, but I think it did. I know it did. It made me for some part of that night quite uncomfortable. I was so ashamed of my folly, that I did not like to confess it even to Ada; and that made me more uncomfortable still. I would have given anything not to have been so much in the bright old lady's confidence, if I could have possibly declined it. It gave me the most inconsistent opinions of her. At one time I thought she was a storyteller, and at another time that she was the pink of truth. Now, I suspected that she was very cunning; next moment, I believed her honest Welsh heart to be perfectly innocent and simple. And, after all, what did it matter to me, and why did it matter to me? Why could not I, going up to bed with my basket of keys, stop to sit down by her fire, and accommodate myself for a little while to her, at least as well as to anybody else; and not trouble myself about the harmless things she said to me? Impelled towards her, as I certainly was, for I was very anxious that she should like me, and was very glad indeed that she did, why should I harp afterwards, with actual distress and pain, on every word she said, and weigh it over and over again in twenty scales? Why was it so worrying to me to have her in our house, and confidential to me every night, when I yet felt that it was better and safer, somehow, that she should be there than anywhere else? These were perplexities and contradictions that I could not account for. At least, if I could—but I shall come to all that by and by, and it is mere idleness to go on about it now.</p><p >So, when Mrs. Woodcourt went away, I was sorry to lose her, but was
<pb xml:id="p292"/>
relieved too. And then Caddy Jellyby came down; and Caddy brought such a packet of domestic news, that it gave us abundant occupation.</p><p >First, Caddy declared (and would at first declare nothing else) that I was the best adviser that ever was known. This, my pet said, was no news at all; and this, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> said, of course, was nonsense. Then Caddy told us that she was going to be married in a month; and that if Ada and I would be her bridesmaids, she was the happiest girl in the world. To be sure, this was news indeed; and I thought we never should have done talking about it, we had so much to say to Caddy, and Caddy had so much to say to us.</p><p >It seemed that Caddy's unfortunate papa had got over his bankruptcy—“gone through the Gazette,” was the expression Caddy used, as if it were a tunnel,—with the general clemency and commiseration of his creditors; and had got rid of his affairs in some blessed manner, without succeeding in understanding them; and had given up everything he possessed (which was not worth much I should think, to judge from the state of the furniture), and had satisfied every one concerned that he could do no more, poor man. So, he had been honourably dismissed to “the office,” to begin the world again. What he did at the office, I never knew: Caddy said he was a “Custom-House and General Agent,” and the only thing I ever understood about that business was, that when he wanted money more than usual he went to the Docks to look for it, and hardly ever found it.</p><p >As soon as her papa had tranquillised his mind by becoming this shorn lamb, and they had removed to a furnished lodging in Hatton Garden (where I found the children, when I afterwards went there, cutting the horsehair out of the seats of the chairs, and choking themselves with it), Caddy had brought about a meeting between him and old Mr. Turveydrop; and poor Mr. Jellyby, being very humble and meek, had deferred to Mr. Turveydrop's Deportment so submissively, that they had become excellent friends. By degrees, old Mr. Turveydrop, thus familiarised with the idea of his son's marriage, had worked up his parental feelings to the height of contemplating that event as being near at hand; and had given his gracious consent to the young couple commencing housekeeping, at the Academy in Newman Street, when they would.</p><p >“And your papa, Caddy. What did he say?”</p><p >“O! poor Pa,” said Caddy, “only cried, and said he hoped we might get on better than he and Ma had got on. He didn't say so before Prince; he only said so to me. And he said, ‘My poor girl, you have not been very well taught how to make a home for your husband; but unless you mean with all your heart to strive to do it, you had better murder him than marry him—if you really love him.’ ”</p><p >“And how did you reassure him, Caddy?”</p><p >“Why, it was very distressing, you know, to see poor Pa so low, and hear him say such terrible things, and I couldn't help crying myself. But I told him that I <hi rend="italics">did</hi> mean it, with all my heart; and that I hoped our house would be a place for him to come and find some comfort in, of an evening; and that I hoped and thought I could be a better daughter to him there, than at home. Then I mentioned Peepy's coming to stay with me; and then Pa began to cry again, and said the children were Indians.”</p><pb  xml:id="p293"/><p >“Indians, Caddy?”</p><p >“Yes,” said Caddy, “Wild Indians. And Pa said,”—(here she began to sob, poor girl, not at all like the happiest girl in the world)—“that he was sensible the best thing that could happen to them was, their being all Tomahawked together.”</p><p >Ada suggested that it was comfortable to know that Mr. Jellyby did not mean these destructive sentiments.</p><p >“No, of course I know Pa wouldn't like his family to be weltering in their blood,” said Caddy; “but he means that they are very unfortunate in being Ma's children, and that he is very unfortunate in being Ma's husband; and I am sure that's true, though it seems unnatural to say so.”</p><p >I asked Caddy if Mrs. Jellyby knew that her wedding-day was fixed.</p><p >“O! you know what Ma is, Esther,” she returned. “It's impossible to say whether she knows it or not. She has been told it often enough; and when she <hi rend="italics">is</hi> told it, she only gives me a placid look, as if I was I don't know what—a steeple in the distance,” said Caddy, with a sudden idea; “and then she shakes her head, and says ‘O Caddy, Caddy, what a teaze you are!’ and goes on with the Borrioboola letters.”</p><p >“And about your wardrobe, Caddy?” said I. For she was under no restraint with us.</p><p >“Well, my dear Esther,” she returned, drying her eyes, “I must do the best I can, and trust to my dear Prince never to have an unkind remembrance of my coming so shabbily to him. If the question concerned an outfit for Borrioboola, Ma would know all about it, and would be quite excited. Being what it is, she neither knows nor cares.”</p><p >Caddy was not at all deficient in natural affection for her mother, but mentioned this with tears, as an undeniable fact: which I am afraid it was. We were so sorry for the poor dear girl, and found so much to admire in the good disposition which had survived under such discouragement, that we both at once (I mean Ada and I) proposed a little scheme, that made her perfectly joyful. This was, her staying with us for three weeks; my staying with her for one; and our all three contriving and cutting out, and repairing, and sewing, and saving, and doing the very best we could think of, to make the most of her stock. My guardian being as pleased with the idea as Caddy was, we took her home next day to arrange the matter; and brought her out again in triumph, with her boxes, and all the purchases that could be squeezed out of a ten-pound note, which Mr. Jellyby had found in the Docks I suppose, but which he at all events gave her. What my guardian would not have given her, if we had encouraged him, it would be difficult to say; but we thought it right to compound for no more than her wedding-dress and bonnet. He agreed to this compromise; and if Caddy had ever been happy in her life, she was happy when we sat down to work.</p><p >She was clumsy enough with her needle, poor girl, and pricked her fingers as much as she had been used to ink them. She could not help reddening a little, now and then: partly with the smart, and partly with vexation at being able to do no better: but she soon got over that, and began to improve rapidly. So, day after day, she, and my darling, and my little maid Charley, and a milliner out of the town, and I, sat hard at work, as pleasantly as possible.</p><pb  xml:id="p294"/><p >Over and above this, Caddy was very anxious “to learn housekeeping,” as she said. Now, Mercy upon us! the idea of her learning housekeeping of a person of my vast experience was such a joke, that I laughed, and coloured up, and fell into a comical confusion when she proposed it. However, I said, “Caddy, I am sure you are very welcome to learn anything that you can learn of <hi rend="italics">me,</hi> my dear;” and I showed her all my books and methods, and all my fidgetty ways. You would have supposed that I was showing her some wonderful inventions, by her study of them; and if you had seen her, whenever I jingled my housekeeping keys, get up and attend me, certainly you might have thought that there never was a greater impostor than I, with a blinder follower than Caddy Jellyby.</p><p >So, what with working and housekeeping, and lessons to Charley, and backgammon in the evening with my guardian, and duets with Ada, the three weeks slipped fast away. Then I went home, with Caddy, to see what could be done there; and Ada and Charley remained behind, to take care of my guardian.</p><p >When I say I went home with Caddy, I mean to the furnished lodging in Hatton Garden. We went to Newman Street two or three times, where preparations were in progress too; a good many, I observed, for enhancing the comforts of old Mr. Turveydrop, and a few for putting the newly-married couple away cheaply at the top of the house; but our great point was to make the furnished lodging decent for the wedding breakfast, and to imbue Mrs. Jellyby beforehand with some faint sense of the occasion.</p><p >The latter was the more difficult thing of the two, because Mrs. Jellyby and an unwholesome boy occupied the front sitting-room (the back one was a mere closet), and it was littered down with waste paper and Borrioboolan documents, as an untidy stable might be littered with straw. Mrs. Jellyby sat there all day, drinking strong coffee, dictating, and holding Borrioboolan interviews by appointment. The unwholesome boy, who seemed to me to be going into a decline, took his meals out of the house. When Mr. Jellyby came home, he usually groaned and went down into the kitchen. There he got something to eat, if the servant would give him anything; and then, feeling that he was in the way, went out and walked about Hatton Garden in the wet. The poor children scrambled up and tumbled down the house, as they had always been accustomed to do.</p><p >The production of these devoted little sacrifices, in any presentable condition, being quite out of the question at a week's notice, I proposed to Caddy that we should make them as happy as we could, on her marriage morning, in the attic where they all slept; and should confine our greatest efforts to her mama and her mama's room, and a clean breakfast. In truth Mrs. Jellyby required a good deal of attention, the lattice-work up her back having widened considerably since I first knew her, and her hair looking like the mane of a dustman's horse.</p><p >Thinking that the display of Caddy's wardrobe would be the best means of approaching the subject, I invited Mrs. Jellyby to come and look at it spread out on Caddy's bed, in the evening after the unwholesome boy was gone.</p><p >“My dear Miss Summerson,” said she, rising from her desk, with her usual sweetness of temper, “these are really ridiculous preparations, though your assisting them is a proof of your kindness. There is
<pb xml:id="p295"/>
something so inexpressibly absurd to me, in the idea of Caddy being married! O Caddy, you silly, silly, silly puss!”</p><p >She came up-stairs with us notwithstanding, and looked at the clothes in her customary far-off manner. They suggested one distinct idea to her; for she said, with her placid smile, and shaking her head, “My good Miss Summerson, at half the cost, this weak child might have been equipped for Africa!”</p><p >On our going down-stairs again, Mrs. Jellyby asked me whether this troublesome business was really to take place next Wednesday? And on my replying yes, she said, “Will my room be required, my dear Miss Summerson? For it's quite impossible that I can put my papers away.”</p><p >I took the liberty of saying that the room would certainly be wanted, and that I thought we must put the papers away somewhere. “Well, my dear Miss Summerson,” said Mrs. Jellyby, “you know best, I dare say. But by obliging me to employ a boy, Caddy has embarrassed me to that extent, overwhelmed as I am with public business, that I don't know which way to turn. We have a Ramification meeting, too, on Wednesday afternoon, and the inconvenience is very serious.”</p><p >“It is not likely to occur again,” said I, smiling. “Caddy will be married but once, probably.”</p><p >“That's true,” Mrs. Jellyby replied, “that's true, my dear. I suppose we must make the best of it!”</p><p >The next question was, how Mrs. Jellyby should be dressed on the occasion. I thought it very curious to see her looking on serenely from her writing-table, while Caddy and I discussed it; occasionally shaking her head at us with a half-reproachful smile, like a superior spirit who could just bear with our trifling.</p><p >The state in which her dresses were, and the extraordinary confusion in which she kept them, added not a little to our difficulty; but at length we devised something not very unlike what a common-place mother might wear on such an occasion. The abstracted manner in which Mrs. Jellyby would deliver herself up to having this attire tried on by the dress-maker, and the sweetness with which she would then observe to me how sorry she was that I had not turned my thoughts to Africa, were consistent with the rest of her behaviour.</p><p >The lodging was rather confined as to space, but I fancied that if Mrs. Jellyby's household had been the only lodgers in Saint Paul's or Saint Peter's, the sole advantage they would have found in the size of the building would have been its affording a great deal of room to be dirty in. I believe that nothing belonging to the family, which it had been possible to break, was unbroken at the time of those preparations for Caddy's marriage; that nothing which it had been possible to spoil in any way, was unspoilt; and that no domestic object which was capable of collecting dirt, from a dear child's knee to the door-plate, was without as much dirt as could well accumulate upon it.</p><p >Poor Mr. Jellyby, who very seldom spoke, and almost always sat when he was at home with his head against the wall, became interested when he saw that Caddy and I were attempting to establish some order among all this waste and ruin, and took off his coat to help. But such wonderful things came tumbling out of the closets when they were opened—bits
<pb xml:id="p296"/>
of mouldy pie, sour bottles, Mrs. Jellyby's caps, letters, tea, forks, odd boots and shoes of children, firewood, wafers, saucepan-lids, damp sugar in odds and ends of paper bags, footstools, black-lead brushes, bread, Mrs. Jellyby's bonnets, books with butter sticking to the binding, guttered candle-ends put out by being turned upside down in broken candle-sticks, nutshells, heads and tails of shrimps, dinner-mats, gloves, coffee-grounds, umbrellas—that he looked frightened, and left off again. But he came in regularly every evening, and sat without his coat, with his head against the wall; as though he would have helped us, if he had known how.</p><p >“Poor Pa!” said Caddy to me, on the night before the great day, when we really had got things a little to rights. “It seems unkind to leave him, Esther. But what could I do, if I stayed! Since I first knew you, I have tidied and tidied over and over again; but it's useless. Ma and Africa, together, upset the whole house directly. We never have a servant who don't drink. Ma's ruinous to everything.”</p><p >Mr. Jellyby could not hear what she said, but he seemed very low indeed, and shed tears, I thought.</p><p >“My heart aches for him; that it does!” sobbed Caddy. “I can't help thinking, to-night, Esther, how dearly I hope to be happy with Prince, and how dearly Pa hoped, I dare say, to be happy with Ma. What a disappointed life!”</p><p >“My dear Caddy!” said Mr. Jellyby, looking slowly round from the wall. It was the first time, I think, I ever heard him say three words together.</p><p >“Yes, Pa!” cried Caddy, going to him and embracing him affectionately.</p><p >“My dear Caddy, “said Mr. Jellyby. “Never have——”</p><p >“Not Prince, Pa?” faltered Caddy. “Not have Prince?”</p><p >“Yes, my dear,” said Mr. Jellyby. “Have him, certainly. But, never have——”</p><p >I mentioned, in my account of our first visit in Thavies' Inn, that Richard described Mr. Jellyby as frequently opening his mouth after dinner without saying anything. It was a habit of his. He opened his mouth now, a great many times, and shook his head in a melancholy manner.</p><p >“What do you wish me not to have? Don't have what, dear Pa?” asked Caddy, coaxing him, with her arms round his neck.</p><p >“Never have a Mission, my dear child.”</p><p >Mr. Jellyby groaned, and laid his head against the wall again; and this was the only time I ever heard him make any approach to expressing his sentiments on the Borrioboolan question. I suppose he had been more talkative and lively, once; but he seemed to have been completely exhausted long before I knew him.</p><p >I thought Mrs. Jellyby never would have left off serenely looking over her papers, and drinking coffee, that night. It was twelve o'clock before we could obtain possession of the room; and the clearance it required then, was so discouraging, that Caddy, who was almost tired out, sat down in the middle of the dust, and cried. But she soon cheered up, and we did wonders with it before we went to bed.</p><p >In the morning it looked, by the aid of a few flowers and a quantity of
<pb xml:id="p297"/>
soap and water, and a little arrangement, quite gay. The plain breakfast made a cheerful show, and Caddy was perfectly charming. But when my darling came, I thought—and I think now—that I never had seen such a dear face as my beautiful pet's.</p><p >We made a little feast for the children up-stairs, and we put Peepy at the head of the table, and we showed them Caddy in her bridal dress, and they clapped their hands and hurrahed, and Caddy cried to think that she was going away from them, and hugged them over and over again, until we brought Prince up to fetch her away—when, I am sorry to say, Peepy bit him. Then there was old Mr. Turveydrop down-stairs, in a state of Deportment not to be expressed, benignly blessing Caddy, and giving my guardian to understand, that his son's happiness was his own parental work, and that he sacrificed personal considerations to ensure it. “My dear sir,” said Mr. Turveydrop, “these young people will live with me; my house is large enough for their accommodation, and they shall not want the shelter of my roof. I could have wished—you will understand the allusion, Mr. Jarndyce, for you remember my illustrious patron the Prince Regent—I could have wished that my son had married into a family where there was more Deportment; but the will of Heaven be done!”</p><p >Mr. and Mrs. Pardiggle were of the party—Mr. Pardiggle, an obstinate-looking man with a large waistcoat and stubbly hair, who was always talking in a loud bass voice about his mite, or Mrs. Pardiggle's mite, or their five boys' mites. Mr. Gusher, with his hair brushed back as usual, and his knobs of temples shining very much, was also there; not in the character of a disappointed lover, but as the Accepted of a young—at least, an unmarried—lady, a Miss Wisk, who was also there. Miss Wisk's mission, my guardian said, was to show the world that woman's mission was man's mission; and that the only genuine mission, of both man and woman, was to be always moving declaratory resolutions about things in general at public meetings. The guests were few; but were, as one might expect at Mrs. Jellyby's, all devoted to public objects only. Besides those I have mentioned, there was an extremely dirty lady, with her bonnet all awry, and the ticketed price of her dress still sticking on it, whose neglected home, Caddy told me, was like a filthy wilderness, but whose church was like a fancy fair. A very contentious gentleman, who said it was his mission to be everybody's brother, but who appeared to be on terms of coolness with the whole of his large family, completed the party.</p><p >A party, having less in common with such an occasion, could hardly have been got together by any ingenuity. Such a mean mission as the domestic mission, was the very last thing to be endured among them; indeed, Miss Wisk informed us, with great indignation, before we sat down to breakfast, that the idea of woman's mission lying chiefly in the narrow sphere of Home was an outrageous slander on the part of her Tyrant, Man. One other singularity was, that nobody with a mission—except Mr. Gusher, whose mission, as I think I have formerly said, was to be in ecstacies with everybody's mission—cared at all for anybody's mission. Mrs. Pardiggle being as clear that the only one infallible course was her course of pouncing upon the poor, and applying benevolence to them like a strait-waistcoat; as Miss Wisk was that the only practical thing for the world was the emancipation of Woman from the thraldom of her Tyrant,
<pb xml:id="p298"/>
Man. Mrs. Jellyby, all the while, sat smiling at the limited vision that could see anything but Borrioboola-Gha.</p><p >But I am anticipating now the purport of our conversation on the ride home, instead of first marrying Caddy. We all went to church, and Mr. Jellyby gave her away. Of the air with which old Mr. Turveydrop, with his hat under his left arm, (the inside presented at the clergyman like a cannon,) and his eyes creasing themselves up into his wig, stood, stiff and high-shouldered, behind us bridesmaids during the ceremony, and afterwards saluted us, I could never say enough to do it justice. Miss Wisk, whom I cannot report as prepossessing in appearance, and whose manner was grim, listened to the proceedings, as part of Woman's wrongs, with a disdainful face. Mrs. Jellyby, with her calm smile and her bright eyes, looked the least concerned of all the company.</p><p >We duly came back to breakfast, and Mrs. Jellyby sat at the head of the table, and Mr. Jellyby at the foot. Caddy had previously stolen upstairs, to hug the children again, and tell them that her name was Turveydrop. But this piece of information, instead of being an agreeable surprise to Peepy, threw him on his back in such transports of kicking grief, that I could do nothing on being sent for, but accede to the proposal that he should be admitted to the breakfast table. So he came down, and sat in my lap; and Mrs. Jellyby, after saying, in reference to the state of his pinafore, “O you naughty Peepy, what a shocking little pig you are!” was not at all discomposed. He was very good, except that he brought down Noah with him (out of an ark I had given him before we went to church), and <hi rend="italics">would</hi> dip him head first into the wine-glasses, and then put him in his mouth.</p><p >My guardian, with his sweet temper and his quick perception and his amiable face, made something agreeable even out of the ungenial company. None of them seemed able to talk about anything but his, or her, own one subject, and none of them seemed able to talk about even that, as part of a world in which there was anything else; but my guardian turned it all to the merry encouragement of Caddy, and the honour of the occasion, and brought us through the breakfast nobly. What we should have done without him, I am afraid to think; for, all the company despising the bride and bridegroom, and old Mr. Turveydrop—and old Mr. Turveydrop, in virtue of his Deportment, considering himself vastly superior to all the company—it was a very unpromising case.</p><p >At last the time came when poor Caddy was to go, and when all her property was packed on the hired coach and pair that was to take her and her husband to Gravesend. It affected us to see Caddy clinging, then, to her deplorable home, and hanging on her mother's neck with the greatest tenderness.</p><p >“I am very sorry I couldn't go on writing from dictation, Ma,” sobbed Caddy. “I hope you forgive me, now?”</p><p >“O Caddy, Caddy!” said Mrs. Jellyby, “I have told you over and over again that I have engaged a boy, and there's an end of it.”</p><p >“You are sure you are not in the least angry with me, Ma? Say you are sure, before I go away, Ma?”</p><p >“You foolish Caddy,” returned Mrs. Jellyby, “do I look angry, or have I inclination to be angry, or time to be angry? How <hi rend="italics">can</hi> you?”</p><pb  xml:id="p299"/><p >“Take a little care of Pa while I am gone, mama!”</p><p >Mrs. Jellyby positively laughed at the fancy. “You romantic child,” said she, lightly patting Caddy's back. “Go along. I am excellent friends with you. Now, good bye, Caddy, and be very happy!”</p><p >Then Caddy hung upon her father, and nursed his cheek against hers as if he were some poor dull child in pain. All this took place in the hall. Her father released her, took out his pocket-handkerchief, and sat down on the stairs with his head against the wall. I hope he found some consolation in walls. I almost think he did.</p><p >And then Prince took her arm in his, and turned with great emotion and respect to his father, whose Deportment at that moment was overwhelming.</p><p >“Thank you over and over again, father!” said Prince, kissing his hand. “I am very grateful for all your kindness and consideration regarding our marriage, and so, I can assure you, is Caddy.”</p><p >“Very,” sobbed Caddy. “Ve-ry!”</p><p >“My dear son,” said Mr. Turveydrop, “and dear daughter, I have done my duty. If the spirit of a sainted Wooman hovers above us, and looks down on the occasion, that, and your constant affection, will be my recompence. You will not fail in <hi rend="italics">your</hi> duty, my son and daughter, I believe?”</p><p >“Dear father, never!” cried Prince.</p><p >“Never, never, dear Mr. Turveydrop!” said Caddy.</p><p >“This,” returned Mr. Turveydrop, “is as it should be. My children, my home is yours, my heart is yours, my all is yours. I will never leave you; nothing but Death shall part us. My dear son, you contemplate an absence of a week, I think?”</p><p >“A week, dear father. We shall return home this day week.”</p><p >“My dear child,” said Mr. Turveydrop, “let me, even under the present exceptional circumstances, recommend strict punctuality. It is highly important to keep the connexion together; and schools, if at all neglected, are apt to take offence.”</p><p >“This day week, father, we shall be sure to be home to dinner.”</p><p >“Good!” said Mr. Turveydrop. “You will find fires, my dear Caroline, in your own room, and dinner prepared in my apartment. Yes, yes, Prince!” anticipating some self-denying objection on his son's part with a great air. “You and our Caroline will be strange in the upper part of the premises, and will, therefore, dine that day in my apartment. Now, bless ye!”</p><p >They drove away; and whether I wondered most at Mrs. Jellyby, or at Mr. Turveydrop, I did not know. Ada and my guardian were in the same condition when we came to talk it over. But before we drove away, too, I received a most unexpected and eloquent compliment from Mr. Jellyby. He came up to me in the hall, took both my hands, pressed them earnestly, and opened his mouth twice. I was so sure of his meaning that I said, quite flurried, “You are very welcome, sir. Pray don't mention it!”</p><p >“I hope this marriage is for the best, guardian?” said I, when we three were on our road home.</p><p >“I hope it is, little woman. Patience. We shall see.”</p><p >“Is the wind in the East to-day?” I ventured to ask him.</p><p >He laughed heartily, and answered “No.”</p><pb  xml:id="p300"/><p >“But it must have been this morning, I think,” said I.</p><p >He answered “No,” again; and this time my dear girl confidently answered “No,” too, and shook the lovely head which, with its blooming flowers against the golden hair, was like the very Spring. “Much <hi rend="italics">you</hi> know of East winds, my ugly darling,” said I, kissing her in my admiration—I couldn't help it.</p><p >Well! It was only their love for me, I know very well, and it is a long time ago. I must write it, even if I rub it out again, because it gives me so much pleasure. They said there could be no East wind where Somebody was; they said that wherever Dame Durden went, there was sunshine and summer air.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXI. <lb/> NURSE AND PATIENT.</head><p >I HAD not been at home again many days, when one evening I went up-stairs into my own room to take a peep over Charley's shoulder, and see how she was getting on with her copy-book. Writing was a trying business to Charley, who seemed to have no natural power over a pen, but in whose hand every pen appeared to become perversely animated, and to go wrong and crooked, and to stop, and splash, and sidle into corners, like a saddle-donkey. It was very odd, to see what old letters Charley's young hand made; they, so wrinkled, and shrivelled, and tottering; it, so plump and round. Yet Charley was uncommonly expert at other things, and had as nimble little fingers as I ever watched.</p><p >“Well, Charley,” said I, looking over a copy of the letter O in which it was represented as square, triangular, pear-shaped, and collapsed in all kinds of ways, “we are improving. If we only get to make it round, we shall be perfect, Charley.”</p><p >Then I made one, and Charley made one, and the pen wouldn't join Charley's neatly, but twisted it up into a knot.</p><p >“Never mind, Charley. We shall do it in time.”</p><p >Charley laid down her pen, the copy being finished; opened and shut her cramped little hand; looked gravely at the page, half in pride and half in doubt; and got up, and dropped me a curtsey.</p><p >“Thank you, miss. If you please, miss, did you know a poor person of the name of Jenny?”</p><p >“A brickmaker's wife, Charley? Yes.”</p><p >“She came and spoke to me when I was out a little while ago, and said you knew her, miss. She asked me if I wasn't the young lady's little maid—meaning you for the young lady, miss—and I said yes, miss.”</p><p >“I thought she had left this neighbourhood altogether, Charley.”</p><p >“So she had, miss, but she's come back again to where she used to live—she and Liz. Did you know another poor person of the name of Liz, miss?”</p><p >“I think I do, Charley, though not by name.”</p><p >“That's what she said!” returned Charley. “They have both come back, miss, and have been tramping high and low.”</p><pb  xml:id="p301"/><p >“Tramping high and low, have they, Charley?”</p><p >“Yes, miss.” If Charley could only have made the letters in her copy as round as the eyes with which she looked into my face, they would have been excellent. “And this poor person came about the house three or four days, hoping to get a glimpse of you, miss—all she wanted, she said—but you were away. That was when she saw me. She saw me a going about, miss,” said Charley, with a short laugh of the greatest delight and pride, “and she thought I looked like your maid!”</p><p >“Did she though, really, Charley?”</p><p >“Yes, miss!” said Charley, “really and truly.” And Charley, with another short laugh of the purest glee, made her eyes very round again, and looked as serious as became my maid. I was never tired of seeing Charley in the full enjoyment of that great dignity, standing before me with her youthful face and figure, and her steady manner, and her childish exultation breaking through it now and then in the pleasantest way.</p><p >“And where did you see her, Charley?” said I.</p><p >My little maid's countenance fell, as she replied, “By the doctor's shop, miss.” For Charley wore her black frock yet.</p><p >I asked if the brickmaker's wife were ill, but Charley said No. It was some one else. Some one in her cottage who had tramped down to Saint Alban's, and was tramping he didn't know where. A poor boy, Charley said. No father, no mother, no any one. “Like as Tom might have been, miss, if Emma and me had died after father,” said Charley, her round eyes filling with tears.</p><p >“And she was getting medicine for him, Charley?”</p><p >“She said, miss,” returned Charley, “how that he had once done as much for her.”</p><p >My little maid's face was so eager, and her quiet hands were folded so closely in one another as she stood looking at me, that I had no great difficulty in reading her thoughts. “Well, Charley,” said I, “it appears to me that you and I can do no better than go round to Jenny's, and see what's the matter.”</p><p >The alacrity with which Charley brought my bonnet and veil, and, having dressed me, quaintly pinned herself into her warm shawl and made herself look like a little old woman, sufficiently expressed her readiness. So Charley and I, without saying anything to any one, went out.</p><p >It was a cold, wild night, and the trees shuddered in the wind. The rain had been thick and heavy all day, and with little intermission for many days. None was falling just then, however. The sky had partly cleared, but was very gloomy—even above us, where a few stars were shining. In the north and north-west, where the sun had set three hours before, there was a pale dead light both beautiful and awful; and into it long sullen lines of cloud waved up, like a sea stricken immoveable as it was heaving. Towards London, a lurid glare overhung the whole dark waste; and the contrast between these two lights, and the fancy which the redder light engendered of an unearthly fire, gleaming on all the unseen buildings of the city, and on all the faces of its many thousands of wondering inhabitants, was as solemn as might be.</p><p >I had no thought, that night—none, I am quite sure—of what was soon to happen to me. But I have always remembered since, that when we had stopped at the garden gate to look up at the sky,
<pb xml:id="p302"/>
and when we went upon our way, I had for a moment an undefinable impression of myself as being something different from what I then was. I know it was then, and there, that I had it. I have ever since connected the feeling with that spot and time, and with everything associated with that spot and time, to the distant voices in the town, the barking of a dog, and the sound of wheels coming down the miry hill.</p><p >It was Saturday night; and most of the people belonging to the place where we were going, were drinking elsewhere. We found it quieter than I had previously seen it, though quite as miserable. The kilns were burning, and a stifling vapour set towards us with a pale blue glare.</p><p >We came to the cottage, where there was a feeble candle in the patched window. We tapped at the door, and went in. The mother of the little child who had died, was sitting in a chair on one side of the poor fire by the bed; and opposite to her, a wretched boy, supported by the chimney-piece, was cowering on the floor. He held under his arm, like a little bundle, a fragment of a fur cap; and as he tried to warm himself, he shook until the crazy door and window shook. The place was closer than before, and had an unhealthy, and a very peculiar smell.</p><p >I had not lifted my veil when I first spoke to the woman, which was at the moment of our going in. The boy staggered up instantly, and stared at me with a remarkable expression of surprise and terror.</p><p >His action was so quick, and my being the cause of it was so evident, that I stood still, instead of advancing nearer.</p><p >“I won't go no more to the berryin ground,” muttered the boy; “I ain't a going there, so I tell you!”</p><p >I lifted my veil and spoke to the woman. She said to me in a low voice, “Don't mind him, ma'am. He'll soon come back to his head:” and said to him, “Jo, Jo, what's the matter?”</p><p >“I know wot she's come for!” cried the boy.</p><p >“Who?”</p><p >“The lady there. She's come to get me to go along with her to the berryin ground. I won't go to the berrying ground. I don't like the name on it. She might go a berryin <hi rend="italics">me.</hi>” His shivering came on again, and as he leaned against the wall, he shook the hovel.</p><p >“He has been talking off and on about such like, all day, ma'am,” said Jenny, softly. “Why, how you stare! This is <hi rend="italics">my</hi> lady, Jo.”</p><p >“Is it?” returned the boy doubtfully, and surveying me with his arm held out above his burning eyes. “She looks to me the t'other one. It ain't the bonnet, nor yet it ain't the gownd, but she looks to me the t'other one.”</p><p >My little Charley, with her premature experience of illness and trouble, had pulled off her bonnet and shawl, and now went quietly up to him with a chair, and sat him down in it, like an old sick nurse. Except that no such attendant could have shown him Charley's youthful face, which seemed to engage his confidence.</p><p >“I say!” said the boy. “<hi rend="italics">You</hi> tell me. Ain't the lady the t'other lady?”</p><p >Charley shook her head, as she methodically drew his rags about him and made him as warm as she could.</p><p >“O!” the boy muttered. “Then I 'spose she ain't.”</p><pb  xml:id="p303"/><p >“I came to see if I could do you any good,” said I. “What is the matter with you?”</p><p >“I'm a being froze,” returned the boy hoarsely, with his haggard gaze wandering about me, “and then burnt up, and then froze, and then burnt up, ever so many times in a hour. And my head's all sleepy, and all a going mad-like—and I'm so dry—and my bones isn't half so much bones as pain.</p><p >“When did he come here?” I asked the woman.</p><p >“This morning, ma'am, I found him at the corner of the town. I had known him up in London yonder. Hadn't I, Jo?”</p><p >“Tom-all-Alone's,” the boy replied.</p><p >Whenever he fixed his attention or his eyes, it was only for a very little while. He soon began to droop his head again, and roll it heavily, and speak as if he were half awake.</p><p >“When did he come from London?” I asked,</p><p >“I come from London yes'day,” said the boy himself, now flushed and hot. “I'm a going somewheres.”</p><p >“Where is he going?” I asked.</p><p >“Somewheres,” repeated the boy, in a louder tone. “I have been moved on, and moved on, more nor ever I was afore, since the t'other one giv' me the sov'ring. Mrs. Sangsby, she's always a watching, and a driving of me—what have I done to her?—and they're all a watching and a driving of me. Everyone of 'em's doing of it, from the time when I don't get up, to the time when I don't go to bed. And I'm a going somewheres. That's where I'm a going. She told me, down in Tom-all-Alone's, as she come from Stolbuns, and so I took the Stolbuns Road. It's as good as another.”</p><p >He always concluded by addressing Charley.</p><p >“What is to be done with him?” said I, taking the woman aside. “He could not travel in this state, even if he had a purpose, and knew where he was going!”</p><p >“I know no more, ma'am, than the dead,” she replied, glancing compassionately at him. “Perhaps the dead know better, if they could only tell us. I've kept him here all day for pity's sake, and I've given him broth and physic, and Liz has gone to try if any one will take him in (here's my pretty in the bed—her child, but I call it mine); but I can't keep him long, for if my husband was to come home and find him here, he'd be rough in putting him out, and might do him a hurt. Hark! Here comes Liz back!”</p><p >The other woman came hurriedly in as she spoke, and the boy got up with a half obscured sense that he was expected to be going. When the little child awoke, and when and how Charley got at it, took it out of bed, and began to walk about hushing it, I don't know. There she was, doing all this, in a quiet motherly manner, as if she were living in Mrs. Blinder's attic with Tom and Emma again.</p><p >The friend had been here and there, and had been played about from hand to hand, and had come back as she went. At first it was too early for the boy to be received into the proper refuge, and at last it was too late. One official sent her to another, and the other sent her back again to the first, and so backward and forward; until it appeared to me as if both must have been appointed for their skill in evading their duties, instead of performing them. And now, after all, she said, breathing quickly, for she had been running, and was frightened too, “Jenny,
<pb xml:id="p304"/>
your master's on the road home, and mine's not far behind, and the Lord help the boy, for we can do no more for him!” They put a few halfpence together and hurried them into his hand, and so, in an oblivious, half-thankful, half-insensible way, he shuffled out of the house.</p><p >“Give me the child, my dear!” said its mother to Charley, “and thank you kindly too! Jenny, woman dear, good night! Young lady, if my master don't fall out with me, I'll look down by the kiln by and by, where the boy will be most like, and again in the morning!” She hurried off; and presently we passed her hushing and singing to her child at her own door, and looking anxiously along the road for her drunken husband.</p><p >I was afraid of staying them, to speak to either woman, lest I should bring her into trouble. But I said to Charley that we must not leave the boy to die. Charley, who knew what to do much better than I did, and whose quickness equalled her presence of mind, glided on before me, and presently we came up with Jo, just short of the brick-kiln.</p><p >I think he must have begun his journey with some small bundle under his arm, and must have had it stolen, or lost it. For he still carried his wretched fragment of fur cap like a bundle, though he went bare-headed through the rain, which now fell fast. He stopped when we called to him, and again showed a dread of me when I came up; standing with his lustrous eyes fixed upon me, and even arrested in his shivering fit.</p><p >I asked him to come with us, and we would take care that he had some shelter for the night.</p><p >“I don't want no shelter,” he said; “I can lay amongst the warm bricks.”</p><p >“But don't you know that people die there?” returned Charley.</p><p >“They dies everywheres,” said the boy. “They dies in their lodgings—she knows where; I showed her—and they dies down in Tom-all-Alone's in heaps. They dies more than they lives, according to what <hi rend="italics">I</hi> see.” Then he hoarsely whispered Charley. “If she ain't the t'other one, she ain't the forrenner. Is there <hi rend="italics">three</hi> of 'em then?”</p><p >Charley looked at me a little frightened. I felt half frightened at myself when the boy glared on me so.</p><p >But he turned and followed, when I beckoned to him; and finding that he acknowledged that influence in me, I led the way straight home. It was not far; only at the summit of the hill. We passed but one man. I doubted if we should have got home without assistance; the boy's steps were so uncertain and tremulous. He made no complaint, however, and was strangely unconcerned about himself, if I may say so strange a thing.</p><p >Leaving him in the hall for a moment, shrunk into a corner of the window-seat, and staring with an indifference that could scarcely be called wonder, at the comfort and brightness about him, I went into the drawing-room to speak to my guardian. There I found Mr. Skimpole, who had come down by the coach, as he frequently did without notice, and never bringing any clothes with him, but always borrowing everything he wanted.</p><p >They came out with me directly, to look at the boy. The servants had gathered in the hall, too; and he shivered in the window-seat with Charley standing by him, like some wounded animal that had been found in a ditch.</p><pb  xml:id="p305"/><p >“This is a sorrowful case,” said my guardian, after asking him a question or two, and touching him, and examining his eyes. “What do you say, Leonard?”</p><p >“You had better turn him out,” said Mr. Skimpole.</p><p >“What do you mean?” enquired my guardian, almost sternly.</p><p >“My dear Jarndyce,” said Mr. Skimpole, “you know what I am: I am a child. Be cross to me, if I deserve it. But I have a constitutional objection to this sort of thing. I always had, when I was a medical man. He's not safe, you know. There's a very bad sort of fever about him.”</p><p >Mr. Skimpole had retreated from the hall to the drawing-room again, and said this in his airy way, seated on the music-stool as we stood by.</p><p >“You'll say it's childish,” observed Mr. Skimpole, looking gaily at us. “Well, I dare say it may be; but I <hi rend="italics">am</hi> a child, and I never pretend to be anything else. If you put him out in the road, you only put him where he was before. He will be no worse off than he was, you know. Even make him better off, if you like. Give him sixpence, or five shillings, or five pound ten—you are arithmeticians, and I am not—and get rid of him!”</p><p >“And what is he to do then?” asked my guardian.</p><p >“Upon my life,” said Mr. Skimpole, shrugging his shoulders with his engaging smile, “I have not the least idea what he is to do then. But I have no doubt he'll do it.”</p><p >“Now, is it not a horrible reflection,” said my guardian, to whom I had hastily explained the unavailing efforts of the two women, “is it not a horrible reflection,” walking up and down and rumpling his hair, “that if this wretched creature were a convicted prisoner, his hospital would be wide open to him, and he would be as well taken care of as any sick boy in the kingdom?”</p><p >“My dear Jarndyce,” returned Mr. Skimpole, “you'll pardon the simplicity of the question, coming as it does from a creature who is perfectly simple in worldly matters—but, why <hi rend="italics">isn't</hi> he a prisoner then?”</p><p >My guardian stopped and looked at him with a whimsical mixture of amusement and indignation in his face.</p><p >“Our young friend is not to be suspected of any delicacy, I should imagine,” said Mr. Skimpole, unabashed and candid. “It seems to me that it would be wiser, as well as in a certain kind of way more respectable, if he showed some misdirected energy that got him into prison. There would be more of an adventurous spirit in it, and consequently more of a certain sort of poetry.”</p><p >“I believe,” returned my guardian, resuming his uneasy walk, “that there is not such another child on earth as yourself.”</p><p >“Do you really?” said Mr. Skimpole; “I dare say! But, I confess I don't see why our young friend, in his degree, should not seek to invest himself with such poetry as is open to him. He is no doubt born with an appetite—probably, when he is in a safer state of health, he has an excellent appetite. Very well. At our young friend's natural dinner-hour, most likely about noon, our young friend says in effect to society, ‘I am hungry; will you have the goodness to produce your spoon, and feed me?’ Society, which has taken upon itself the general arrangement of the whole system of spoons, and professes to have a spoon for our young friend, does
<pb xml:id="p306"/>
<hi rend="italics">not</hi> produce that spoon; and our young friend, therefore, says ‘You really must excuse me if I seize it.’ Now, this appears to me a case of misdirected energy, which has a certain amount of reason in it, and a certain amount of romance; and I don't know but what I should be more interested in our young friend, as an illustration of such a case, than merely as a poor vagabond—which any one can be.”</p><p >“In the meantime,” I ventured to observe, “he is getting worse.”</p><p >“In the meantime,” said Mr. Skimpole cheerfully, “as Miss Summerson, with her practical good sense, observes, he is getting worse. Therefore I recommend your turning him out before he gets still worse.”</p><p >The amiable face with which he said it, I think I shall never forget.</p><p >“Of course, little woman,” observed my guardian, turning to me, “I can ensure his admission into the proper place by merely going there to enforce it, though it's a bad state of things when, in his condition, that is necessary. But it's growing late, and is a very bad night, and the boy is worn out already. There is a bed in the wholesome loft-room by the stable; we had better keep him there till morning, when he can be wrapped up and removed. We'll do that.”</p><p >“O!” said Mr. Skimpole, with his hands upon the keys of the piano, as we moved away. “Are you going back to our young friend?”</p><p >“Yes,” said my guardian.</p><p >“How I envy you your constitution, Jarndyee!” returned Mr. Skimpole, with playful admiration. “You don't mind these things, neither does Miss Summerson. You are ready at all times to go anywhere, and do anything. Such is Will! I have no Will at all—and no Won't —simply Can't.”</p><p >“You can't recommend anything for the boy, I suppose?” said my guardian, looking back over his shoulder, half angrily; only half angrily, for he never seemed to consider Mr. Skimpole an accountable being.</p><p >“My dear Jarndyce, I observed a bottle of cooling medicine in his pocket, and it's impossible for him to do better than take it. You can tell them to sprinkle a little vinegar about the place where he sleeps, and to keep it moderately cool, and him moderately warm. But it is mere impertinence in me to offer any recommendation. Miss Summerson has such a knowledge of detail, and such a capacity for the administration of detail, that she knows all about it.”</p><p >We went back into the hall, and explained to Jo what we proposed to do, which Charley explained to him again, and which he received with the languid unconcern I had already noticed, wearily looking on at what was done, as if it were for somebody else. The servants compassionating his miserable state, and being very anxious to help, we soon get the loft-room ready; and some of the men about the house carried him across the wet yard, well wrapped up. It was pleasant to observe how kind they were to him, and how there appeared to be a general impression among them that frequently calling him “Old Chap” was likely to revive his spirits. Charley directed the operations, and went to and fro between the loft-room and the house with such little stimulants and comforts as we thought it safe to give him. My guardian himself saw him before he was left for the night, and reported to me, when he returned to the Growlery to write a letter on the boy's behalf, which a messenger was charged to deliver at daylight in the morning, that he seemed easier, and inclined to sleep. They had
<pb xml:id="p307"/>
fastened his door on the outside, he said, in case of his being delirious; but had so arranged that he could not make any noise without being heard.</p><p >Ada being in our room with a cold, Mr. Skimpole was left alone all this time, and entertained himself by playing snatches of pathetic airs, and sometimes singing to them (as we heard at a distance) with great expression and feeling. When we rejoined him in the drawing-room he said he would give us a little ballad, which had come into his head, “apropos of our young friend;” and he sang one about a Peasant boy,</p><lg  type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">“Thrown on the wide world, doom'd to wander and roam,</l><l part="N">Bereft of his parents, bereft of a home.”</l></lg><p >—quite exquisitely. It was a song that always made him cry, he told us.</p><p >He was extremely gay all the rest of the evening: “for he absolutely chirped,” those were his delighted words; “when he thought by what a happy talent for business he was surrounded.” He gave us, in his glass of negus, “Better health to our young friend!” and supposed, and gaily pursued, the case of his being reserved like Whittington to become Lord Mayor of London. In that event, no doubt, he would establish the Jarndyce Institution and the Summerson Alms-houses, and a little annual Corporation Pilgrimage to St. Albans. He had no doubt, he said, that our young friend was an excellent boy in his way, but his way was not the Leonard Skimpole way; what Leonard Skimpole was, Leonard Skimpole had found himself, to his considerable surprise, when he first made his own acquaintance; he had accepted himself with all his failings, and had thought it sound philosophy to make the best of the bargain; and he hoped we would do the same.</p><p >Charley's last report was, that the boy was quiet. I could see, from my window, the lantern they had left him burning quietly; and I went to bed very happy to think that he was sheltered.</p><p >There was more movement and more talking than usual a little before day-break, and it awoke me. As I was dressing, I looked out of my window, and asked one of our men who had been among the active sympathisers last night, whether there was anything wrong about the house. The lantern was still burning in the loft-window.</p><p >“It's the boy, miss,” said he.</p><p >“Is he worse?” I inquired.</p><p >“Gone, miss.”</p><p >“Dead!”</p><p >“Dead, miss? No. Gone clean off.”</p><p >At what time of the night he had gone, or how, or why, it seemed hopeless ever to divine. The door remaining as it had been left, and the lantern standing in the window, it could only be supposed that he had got out by a trap in the floor which communicated with an empty cart-house below. But he had shut it down again, if that were so; and it looked as if it had not been raised. Nothing of any kind was missing. On this fact being clearly ascertained, we all yielded to the painful belief that delirium had come upon him in the night, and that, allured by some imaginary object, or pursued by some imaginary horror, he had strayed away in that worse than helpless state;—all of us, that is to say,
<pb xml:id="p308"/>
but Mr. Skimpole, who repeatedly suggested, in his usual easy light style, that it had occurred to our young friend that he was not a safe inmate, having a bad kind of fever upon him; and that he had, with great natural politeness, taken himself off.</p><p >Every possible inquiry was made, and every place was searched. The brick-kilns were examined, the cottages were visited, the two women were particularly questioned, but they knew nothing of him, and nobody could doubt that their wonder was genuine. The weather had for some time been too wet, and the night itself had been too wet, to admit of any tracing by footsteps. Hedge and ditch, and wall, and rick and stack, were examined by our men for a long distance round, lest the boy should be lying in such a place insensible or dead; but nothing was seen to indicate that he had ever been near. From the time when he was left in the loft-room, he vanished.</p><p >The search continued for five days. I do not mean that it ceased, even then; but that my attention was then diverted into a current very memorable to me.</p><p >As Charley was at her writing again in my room in the evening, and as I sat opposite to her at work, I felt the table tremble. Looking up, I saw my little maid shivering from head to foot.</p><p >“Charley,” said I, “are you so cold?”</p><p >“I think I am, miss,” she replied. “I don't know what it is. I can't hold myself still. I felt so, yesterday; at about this same time, miss. Don't be uneasy, I think I'm ill.”</p><p >I heard Ada's voice outside, and I hurried to the door of communication between my room and our pretty sitting-room, and locked it. Just in time, for she tapped at it while my hand was yet upon the key.</p><p >Ada called to me to let her in; but I said, “Not now, my dearest. Go away. There's nothing the matter; I will come to you presently.” Ah! it was a long, long time, before my darling girl and I were companions again.</p><p >Charley fell ill. In twelve hours she was very ill. I moved her to my room, and laid her in my bed, and sat down quietly to nurse her. I told my guardian all about it, and why I felt it was necessary that I should seclude myself, and my reason for not seeing my darling above all. At first she came very often to the door, and called to me, and even reproached me with sobs and tears; but I wrote her a long letter, saying that she made me anxious and unhappy, and imploring her, as she loved me, and wished my mind to be at peace, to come no nearer than the garden. After that, she came beneath the window, even oftener than she had come to the door; and, if I had learnt to love her dear sweet voice before when we were hardly ever apart, how did I learn to love it then, when I stood behind the window-curtain listening and replying, but not so much as looking out! How did I learn to love it afterwards, when the harder time came!</p><p >They put a bed for me in our sitting-room; and by keeping the door wide open, I turned the two rooms into one, now that Ada had vacated that part of the house, and kept them always fresh and airy. There was not a servant, in or about the house, but was so good that they would all most gladly have come to me at any hour of the day or night, without the least fear or unwillingness; but I thought it best to choose one
<pb xml:id="p309"/>
worthy woman who was never to see Ada, and whom I could trust to come and go with all precaution. Through her means, I got out to take the air with my guardian, when there was no fear of meeting Ada; and wanted for nothing in the way of attendance, any more than in any other respect.</p><p >And thus poor Charley sickened, and grew worse, and fell into heavy danger of death, and lay severely ill for many a long round of day and night. So patient she was, so uncomplaining, and inspired by such a gentle fortitude, that very often as I sat by Charley, holding her head in my arms—repose would come to her, so, when it would come to her in no other attitude—I silently prayed to our Father in heaven that I might not forget the lesson which this little sister taught me.</p><p >I was very sorrowful to think that Charley's pretty looks would change and be disfigured, even if she recovered—she was such a child, with her dimpled face—but that thought was, for the greater part, lost in her greater peril. When she was at the worst, and her mind rambled again to the cares of her father's sick bed, and the little children, she still knew me so far as that she would be quiet in my arms when she could lie quiet nowhere else, and murmur out the wanderings of her mind less restlessly. At those times I used to think, how should I ever tell the two remaining babies that the baby who had learned of her faithful heart to be a mother to them in their need, was dead!</p><p >There were other times when Charley knew me well, and talked to me; telling me that she sent her love to Tom and Emma, and that she was sure Tom would grow up to be a good man. At those times, Charley would speak to me of what she had read to her father as well as she could, to comfort him; of that young man carried out to be buried, who was the only son of his mother and she was a widow; of the ruler's daughter raised up by the gracious hand upon her bed of death. And Charley told me that when her father died, she had kneeled down and prayed in her first sorrow that he likewise might be raised up, and given back to his poor children; and that if she should never get better, and should die too, she thought it likely that it might come into Tom's mind to offer the same prayer for her. Then would I show Tom how those people of old days had been brought back to life on earth, only that we might know our hope to be restored in Heaven!</p><p >But of all the various times there were in Charley's illness, there was not one when she lost the gentle qualities I have spoken of. And there were many, many, when I thought in the night of the last high belief in the watching Angel, and the last higher trust in God, on the part of her poor despised father.</p><p >And Charley did not die. She flutteringly and slowly turned the dangerous point, after long lingering there, and then began to mend. The hope that never had been given, from the first, of Charley being in outward appearance Charley any more, soon began to be encouraged; and even that prospered, and I saw her growing into her old childish likeness again.</p><p >It was a great morning, when I could tell Ada all this as she stood out in the garden; and it was a great evening, when Charley and I at last took tea together in the next room. But, on that same evening, I felt that I was stricken cold.</p><pb  xml:id="p310"/><p >Happily for both of us, it was not until Charley was safe in bed again and placidly asleep, that I began to think the contagion of her illness was upon me. I had been able easily to hide what I had felt at tea-time, but I was past that already now, and I knew that I was rapidly following in Charley's steps.</p><p >I was well enough, however, to be up early in the morning, and to return my darling's cheerful blessing from the garden, and to talk with her as long as usual. But I was not free from an impression that I had been walking about the two rooms in the night, a little beside myself, though knowing where I was; and I felt confused at times—with a curious sense of fulness, as if I were becoming too large altogether.</p><p >In the evening I was so much worse, that I resolved to prepare Charley; with which view, I said “You're getting quite strong, Charley, are you not?”</p><p >“O quite!” said Charley.</p><p >“Strong enough to be told a secret, I think, Charley?”</p><p >“Quite strong enough for that, miss!” cried Charley. But Charley's face fell in the height of her delight, for she saw the secret in <hi rend="italics">my</hi> face; and she came out of the great chair, and fell upon my bosom, and said “O miss, it's my doing! It's my doing!” and a great deal more, out of the fulness of her grateful heart.</p><p >“Now, Charley,” said I, after letting her go on for a little while, “if I am to be ill, my great trust, humanly speaking, is in you. And unless you are as quiet and composed for me, as you always were for yourself, you can never fulfil it, Charley.”</p><p >“If you'll let me cry a little longer, miss,” said Charley. “O my dear, my dear! if you'll only let me cry a little longer, O my dear!”—how affectionately and devotedly she poured this out, as she clung to my neck, I never can remember without tears—“I'll be good.”</p><p >So I let Charley cry a little longer, and it did us both good.</p><p >“Trust in me, now, if you please, miss,” said Charley, quietly. “I am listening to everything you say.”</p><p >“It is very little at present, Charley. I shall tell your doctor to-night that I don't think I am well, and that you are going to nurse me.”</p><p >For that, the poor child thanked me with her whole heart.</p><p >“And in the morning, when you hear Miss Ada in the garden, if I should not be quite able to go to the window-curtain as usual, do you go, Charley, and say I am asleep—that I have rather tired myself, and am asleep. At all times keep the room as I have kept it, Charley, and let no one come.”</p><p >Charley promised, and I lay down, for I was very heavy. I saw the doctor that night, and asked the favor of him that I wished to ask, relative to his saying nothing of my illness in the house as yet. I have a very indistinct remembrance of that night melting into day, and of day melting into night again; but I was just able, on the first morning, to get to the window, and speak to my darling.</p><p >On the second morning I heard her dear voice—O how dear now!—outside; and I asked Charley, with some difficulty (speech being painful to me), to go and say I was asleep. I heard her answer softly, “Don't disturb her, Charley, for the world!”</p><p >“How does my own Pride look, Charley?” I enquired.</p><pb  xml:id="p311"/><p >“Disappointed, miss,” said Charley, peeping through the curtain.</p><p >“But I know she is very beautiful this morning.”</p><p >“She is indeed, miss,” answered Charley, peeping. “Still looking up at the window.”</p><p >With her blue clear eyes, God bless them, always loveliest when raised like that!</p><p >I called Charley to me, and gave her her last charge.</p><p >“Now, Charley, when she knows I am ill, she will try to make her way into the room. Keep her out, Charley, if you love me truly, to the last! Charley, if you let her in but once, only to look upon me for one moment as I lie here, I shall die.”</p><p >“I never will! I never will!” she promised me.</p><p >“I believe it, my dear Charley. And now come and sit beside me for a little while, and touch me with your hand. For I cannot see you, Charley; I am blind.”</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXXII. <lb/> THE APPOINTED TIME.</head><p >IT is night in Lincoln's Inn—perplexed and troublous valley of the shadow of the law, where suitors generally find but little day—and fat candles are snuffed out in offices, and clerks have rattled down the crazy wooden stairs, and dispersed. The bell that rings at nine o'clock, has ceased its doleful clangor about nothing; the gates are shut; and the night-porter, a solemn warder with a mighty power of sleep, keeps guard in his lodge. From tiers of staircase windows, clogged lamps like the eyes of Equity, bleared Argus with a fathomless pocket for every eye and an eye upon it, dimly blink at the stars. In dirty upper casements, here and there, hazy little patches of candle-light reveal where some wise draughtsman and conveyancer yet toils for the entanglement of real estate in meshes of sheepskin, in the average ratio of about a dozen of sheep to an acre of land. Over which bee-like industry, these benefactors of their species linger yet, though office-hours be past: that they may give, for every day, some good account at last.</p><p >In the neighboring court, where the Lord Chancellor of the Rag and Bottle shop dwells, there is a general tendency towards beer and supper. Mrs. Piper and Mrs. Perkins, whose respective sons, engaged with a circle of acquaintance in the game of hide and seek, have been lying in ambush about the bye-ways of Chancery Lane for some hours, and scouring the plain of the same thoroughfare to the confusion of passengers—Mrs. Piper and Mrs. Perkins have but now exchanged congratulations on the children being abed; and they still linger on a door-step over a few parting words. Mr. Krook and his lodger, and the fact of Mr. Krook's being “continual in liquor,” and the testamentary prospects of the young man are, as usual, the staple of their conversation. But they have something to say, likewise, of the Harmonic Meeting at the Sol's Arms; where the sound of the piano through the partly-opened windows jingles
<pb xml:id="p312"/>
out into the court, and where little Swills, after keeping the lovers of harmony in a roar like a very Yorick, may now be heard taking the gruff line in a concerted piece, and sentimentally adjuring his friends and patrons to Listen, listen, listen, Tew the wa-ter-Fall! Mrs. Perkins and Mrs. Piper compare opinions on the subject of the young lady of professional celebrity who assists at the Harmonic Meetings, and who has a space to herself in the manuscript announcement in the window; Mrs. Perkins possessing information that she has been married a year and a half, though announced as Miss M. Melvilleson, the noted syren, and that her baby is clandestinely conveyed to the Sol's Arms every night to receive its natural nourishment during the entertainments. “Sooner than which, myself,” says Mrs. Perkins, “I would get my living by selling lucifers.” Mrs. Piper, as in duty bound, is of the same opinion; holding that a private station is better than public applause, and thanking Heaven for her own (and, by implication, Mrs. Perkins's) respectability. By this time, the pot-boy of the Sol's Arms appearing with her supper-pint well frothed, Mrs. Piper accepts that tankard and retires in-doors, first giving a fair good night to Mrs. Perkins, who has had her own pint in her hand ever since it was fetched from the same hostelry by young Perkins before he was sent to bed. Now, there is a sound of putting up shop-shutters in the court, and a smell as of the smoking of pipes; and shooting stars are seen in upper windows, further indicating retirement to rest. Now, too, the policeman begins to push at doors; to try fastenings; to be suspicious of bundles; and to administer his beat, on the hypothesis that everyone is either robbing or being robbed.</p><p >It is a close night, though the damp cold is searching too; and there is a laggard mist a little way up in the air. It is a fine steaming night to turn the slaughter-houses, the unwholesome trades, the sewerage, bad water, and burial grounds to account, and give the Registrar of Deaths some extra business. It may be something in the air—there is plenty in it—or it may be something in himself, that is in fault; but Mr. Weevle, otherwise Jobling, is very ill at ease. He comes and goes, between his own room and the open street door, twenty times an hour. He has been doing so, ever since it fell dark. Since the Chancellor shut up his shop, which he did very early to-night, Mr. Weevle has been down and up, and down and up (with a cheap tight velvet skull-cap on his head, making his whiskers look out of all proportion), oftener than before.</p><p >It is no phenomenon that Mr. Snagsby should be ill at ease too; for he always is so, more or less, under the oppressive influence of the secret that is upon him. Impelled by the mystery, of which he is a partaker, and yet in which he is not a sharer, Mr. Snagsby haunts what seems to be its fountain-head—the rag and bottle shop in the court. It has an irresistible attraction for him. Even now, coming round by the Sol's Arms with the intension of passing down the court, and out at the Chancery Lane end, and so terminating his unpremediated after-supper stroll of ten minutes long from his own door and back again, Mr. Snagsby approaches.</p><p >“What, Mr. Weevle?” says the stationer, stopping to speak. “Are <hi rend="italics">you</hi> there?”</p><p >“Ay!” says Weevle. “Here I am, Mr. Snagsby.”</p><pb  xml:id="p313"/><p >“Airing yourself, as I am doing, before you go to bed?” the stationer enquires.</p><p >“Why, there's not much air to be got here; and what there is, is not very freshening,” Weevle answers, glancing up and down the court.</p><p >“Very true, sir. Don't you observe,” says Mr. Snagsby, pausing to sniff and taste the air a little; “don't you observe, Mr. Weevle, that you're—not to put too fine a point upon it—that you're rather greasy here, sir?”</p><p >“Why, I have noticed myself that there is a queer kind of flavor in the place to-night,” Mr. Weevle rejoins. “I suppose it's chops at the Sol's Arms.”</p><p >“Chops, do you think?” Oh!—Chops, eh?” Mr. Snagsby sniffs and tastes again. “Well, sir, I suppose it is. But I should say their cook at the Sol wanted a little looking after. She has been burning 'em, sir! And I don't think;” Mr. Snagsby sniffs and tastes again, and then spits and wipes his mouth; “I don't think—not to put too fine a point upon it—that they were quite fresh, when they were shown the gridiron.”</p><p >“That's very likely. It's a tainting sort of weather.”</p><p >“It <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a tainting sort of weather,” says Mr. Snagsby; “and I find it sinking to the spirits.”</p><p >“By George! <hi rend="italics">I</hi> find it gives me the horrors,” returns Mr. Weevle.</p><p >“Then, you see, you live in a lonesome way, and in a lonesome room, with a black circumstance hanging over it,” says Mr. Snagsby, looking in past the other's shoulder along the dark passage, and then falling back a step to look up at the house. “<hi rend="italics">I</hi> couldn't live in that room alone, as you do, sir. I should get so fidgetty and worried of an evening, sometimes, that I should be driven to come to the door, and stand here, sooner than sit there. But then it's very true that you didn't see, in your room, what <hi rend="italics">I</hi> saw there. That makes a difference.”</p><p >“I know quite enough about it,” returns Tony.</p><p >“It's not agreeable, is it?” pursues Mr. Snagsby, coughing his cough of mild persuasion behind his hand. “Mr. Krook ought to consider it in the rent. I hope he does, I am sure.”</p><p >“I hope he does,” says Tony. “But I doubt it!”</p><p >“You find the rent high, do you, sir?” returns the stationer. “Rents <hi rend="italics">are</hi> high about here. I don't know how it is exactly, but the law seems to put things up in price. Not,” adds Mr. Snagsby, with his apologetic cough, “that I mean to say a word against the profession I get my living by.”</p><p >Mr. Weevle again glances up and down the court, and then looks at the stationer. Mr. Snagsby, blankly catching his eye, looks upward for a star or so, and coughs a cough expressive of not exactly seeing his way out of this conversation.</p><p >“It's a curious fact, sir,” he observes, slowly rubbing his hands, “that he should have been—”</p><p >“Who's he?” interrupts Mr. Weevle.</p><p >“The deceased, you know,” says Mr. Snagsby, twitching his head and right eyebrow towards the staircase, and tapping his acquaintance on the button.</p><p >“Ah to be sure!” returns the other, as if he were not over-fond of the subject. “I thought we had done with him.”</p><pb  xml:id="p314"/><p >“I was only going to say, it's a curious fact, sir, that he should have come and lived here, and been one of my writers, and then that you should come and live here, and be one of my writers, too. Which there is nothing derogatory, but far from it in the appellation,” says Mr. Snagsby, breaking off with a mistrust that he may have unpolitely asserted a kind of proprietorshop in Mr. Weevle, “because I have known writers that have gone into Brewers' houses and done really very respectable indeed. Eminently respectable, sir,” adds Mr. Snagsby, with a misgiving that he has not improved the matter.</p><p >“It's a curious coincidence, as you say,” answers Weevle, once more glancing up and down the court.</p><p >“Seems a Fate in it, don't there?” suggests the stationer.</p><p >“There does.”</p><p >“Just so,” observes the stationer, with his confirmatory cough.</p><p >“Quite a Fate in it. Quite a Fate. Well, Mr. Weevle, I am afraid I must bid you good night;” Mr. Snagsby speaks as if it made him desolate to go, though he has been casting about for any means of escape ever since he stopped to speak; “my little woman will be looking for me, else. Good night, sir!”</p><p >If Mr. Snagsby hastens home to save his little woman the trouble of looking for him, he might set his mind at rest on that score. His little woman has had her eye upon him round the Sol's Arms all this time, and now glides after him with a pocket handkerchief wrapped over her head; honoring Mr. Weevle and his doorway with a very searching glance as she goes past.</p><p >“You'll know me again, ma'am, at all events,” says Mr. Weevle to himself; “and I can't compliment you on your appearance, whoever you are, with your head tied up in a bundle. Is this fellow <hi rend="italics">never</hi> coming!”</p><p >This fellow approaches as he speaks. Mr. Weevle softly holds up his finger, and draws him into the passage, and closes the street door. Then, they go up stairs; Mr. Weevle heavily, and Mr. Guppy (for it is he) very lightly indeed. When they are shut into the back room, they speak low.</p><p >“I thought you had gone to Jericho at least, instead of coming here,” says Tony.</p><p >“Why, I said about ten.”</p><p >“You said about ten,” Tony repeats. “Yes, so you did say about ten. But, according to my count, it's ten times ten—it's a hundred o'clock. I never had such a night in my life!”</p><p >“What has been the matter?”</p><p >“That's it!” says Tony. “Nothing has been the matter. But, here have I been stewing and fuming in this jolly old crib, till I have had the horrors falling on me as thick as hail. <hi rend="italics">There's</hi> a blessed-looking candle!” says Tony, pointing to the heavily-burning taper on his table with a great cabbage head and a long winding-sheet.</p><p >“That's easily improved” Mr. Guppy observes, as he takes the snuffers in hand.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Is</hi> it?” returns his friend. “Not so easily as you think. It has been smouldering like that, ever since it was lighted.”</p><p >“Why, what's the matter with you, Tony?” enquires Mr. Guppy, looking at him, snuffers in hand, as he sits down with his elbow on the table.</p><p >“William Guppy,” replies the other, “I am in the Downs. It's this
<pb xml:id="p315"/>
unbearably dull, suicidal room—and old Boguey down-stairs, I suppose.” Mr. Weevle moodily pushes the snuffer-tray from him with his elbow, leans his head on his hand, puts his feet on the fender, and looks at the fire. Mr. Guppy, observing him, slightly tosses his head, and sits down on the other side of the table in an easy attitude.</p><p >“Wasn't that Snagsby talking to you, Tony?”</p><p >“Yes, and be—yes, it was Snagsby,” says Mr. Weevle, altering the construction of his sentence.</p><p >“On business?”</p><p >“No. No business. He was only sauntering by, and stopped to prose.”</p><p >“I thought it was Snagsby,” says Mr. Guppy, “and thought it as well that he shouldn't see me; so I waited till he was gone.”</p><p >“There we go again, William G.!” cries Tony, looking up for an instant. “So mysterious and secret! By George, if we were going to commit a murder, we couldn't have more mystery about it!”</p><p >Mr. Guppy affects to smile; and with the view of changing the conversation, looks with an admiration, real or pretended, round the room at the Galaxy gallery of British beauty; terminating his survey with the portrait of Lady Dedlock over the mantel-shelf, in which she is represented on a terrace, with a pedestal upon the terrace, and a vase upon the pedestal, and her shawl upon the vase, and a prodigious piece of fur upon the shawl, and her arm on the prodigious piece of fur, and a bracelet on her arm.</p><p >“That's very like Lady Dedlock,” says Mr. Guppy. “It's a speaking likeness.”</p><p >“I wish it was,” growls Tony, without changing his position. “I should have some fashionable conversation here, then.”</p><p >Finding, by this time, that his friend is not to be wheedled into a more sociable humor, Mr. Guppy puts about upon the ill-used tack, and remonstrates with him.</p><p >“Tony,” says he, “I can make allowances for lowness of spirits, for no man knows what it is when it does come upon a man, better than I do; and no man perhaps has a better right to know it, than a man who has an unrequited image imprinted on his art. But there are bounds to these things when an unoffending party is in question, and I will acknowledge to you, Tony, that I don't think your manner on the present occasion is hospitable or quite gentlemanly.”</p><p >“This is strong language, William Guppy,” returns Mr. Weevle.</p><p >“Sir, it may be,” retorts Mr. William Guppy, “but I feel strongly when I use it.”</p><p >Mr. Weevle admits that he has been wrong, and begs Mr. William Guppy to think no more about it. Mr. William Guppy, however, having got the advantage, cannot quite release it without a little more injured remonstrance.</p><p >“No! Dash it, Tony,” says that gentleman, “you really ought to be careful how you wound the feelings of a man, who has an unrequited image imprinted on his art, and who is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> altogether happy in those chords which vibrate to the tenderest emotions. You, Tony, possess in yourself all that is calculated to charm the eye, and allure the taste. It is not—happily for you, perhaps, and I may wish that I could say the same—it is not your character to hover around one flower. The ole garden is open to you, and your airy pinions carry you through it.
<pb xml:id="p316"/>
Still, Tony, far be it from me, I am sure, to wound even your feelings without a cause!”</p><p >Tony again entreats that the subject may be no longer pursued, saying emphatically, “William Guppy, drop it!” Mr. Guppy acquiesces, with the reply, “I never should have taken it up, Tony, of my own accord.”</p><p >“And now,” says Tony, stirring the fire, “touching this same bundle of letters. Isn't it an extraordinary thing of Krook to have appointed twelve o'clock to-night to hand 'em over to me?”</p><p >“Very. What did he do it for?”</p><p >“What does he do anything for? <hi rend="italics">He</hi> don't know. Said, to-day was his birthday, and he'd hand 'em over to-night at twelve o'clock. He'll have drunk himself blind by that time. He has been at it all day.”</p><p >“He hasn't forgotten the appointment, I hope?”</p><p >“Forgotten? Trust him for that. He never forgets anything. I saw him to-night, about eight—helped him to shut up his shop—and he had got the letters then in his hairy cap. He pulled it off, and shewed 'em me. When the shop was closed, he took them out of his cap, hung his cap on the chair-back, and stood turning them over before the fire. I heard him a little while afterwards through the floor here, humming, like the wind, the only song he knows—about Bibo, and old Charon, and Bibo being drunk when he died, or something or other. He has been as quiet, since, as an old rat asleep in his hole.”</p><p >“And you are to go down at twelve?”</p><p >“At twelve. And, as I tell you, when you came it seemed to me a hundred.”</p><p >“Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, after considering a little with his legs crossed, “he can't read yet, can he?”</p><p >“Read! He'll never read. He can make all the letters separately, and he knows most of them separately when he sees them; he has got on that much, under me; but he can't put them together. He's too old to acquire the knack of it now—and too drunk.”</p><p >“Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, uncrossing and recrossing his legs; “how do you suppose he spelt out that name of Hawdon?”</p><p >“He never spelt it out. You know what a curious power of eye he has, and how he has been used to employ himself in copying things by eye alone. He imitated it—evidently from the direction of a letter; and asked me what it meant.”</p><p >“Tony,” says Mr. Guppy, uncrossing and recrossing his legs again; “should you say that the original was a man's writing or a woman's?”</p><p >“A woman's. Fifty to one a lady's—slopes a good deal, and the end of the letter ‘n,’ long and hasty.”</p><p >Mr. Guppy has been biting his thumb-nail during this dialogue, generally changing the thumb when he has changed the crossed leg. As he is going to do so again, he happens to look at his coat-sleeve. It takes his attention. He stares at it, aghast.</p><p >“Why, Tony, what on earth is going on in this house to-night? Is there a chimney on fire?”</p><p >“Chimney on fire!”</p><p >“Ah!” returns Mr. Guppy. “See how the soot's falling. See here, on my arm! See again, on the table here! Confound the stuff, it won't blow off—smears, like black fat!”</p><pb  xml:id="p317"/><p >They look at one another, and Tony goes listening to the door, and a little way up stairs, and a little way down stairs. Comes back, and says it's all right, and all quiet: and quotes the remark he lately made to Mr. Snagsby, about their cooking chops at the Sol's Arms.</p><p >“And it was then,” resumes Mr. Guppy, still glancing with remarkable aversion at his coat-sleeve, as they pursue their conversation before the fire, leaning on opposite sides of the table with their heads very near together, “that he told you of his having taken the bundle of letters from his lodger's portmanteau?”</p><p >“That was the time, sir,” answers Tony, faintly adjusting his whiskers. “Whereupon I wrote a line to my dear boy, the Honourable William Guppy, informing him of the appointment for to-night, and advising him not to call before: Boguey being a Slyboots.”</p><p >The light vivacious tone of fashionable life which is usually assumed by Mr. Weevle, sits so ill upon him to-night, that he abandons that and his whiskers together; and, after looking over his shoulder, appears to yield himself up, a prey to the horrors again.</p><p >“You are to bring the letters to your room to read and compare, and to get yourself into a position to tell him all about them. That's the arrangement, isn't it, Tony?” asks Mr. Guppy, anxiously biting his thumb-nail.</p><p >“You can't speak too low. Yes. That's what he and I agreed.”</p><p >“I tell you what, Tony—”</p><p >“You can't speak too low,” says Tony once more. Mr. Guppy nods his sagacious head, advances it yet closer, and drops into a whisper.</p><p >“I tell you what. The first thing to be done is, to make another packet, like the real one; so that, if he should ask to see the real one while it's in my possession, you can show him the dummy.”</p><p >“And suppose he detects the dummy as soon as he sees it—which with his biting screw of an eye is about five hundred times more likely than not,” suggests Tony.</p><p >“Then we'll face it out. They don't belong to him, and they never did. You found that; and you placed them in my hands—a legal friend of yours—for security. If he forces us to it, they'll be producible, won't they?”</p><p >“Ye-es,” is Mr. Weevle's reluctant admission.</p><p >“Why, Tony,” remonstrates his friend, “how you look! You don't doubt William Guppy? You don't suspect any harm?”</p><p >“I don't suspect anything more than I know, William,” returns the other, gravely.</p><p >“And what do you know?” urges Mr. Guppy, raising his voice a little; but on his friend's once more warning him, “I tell you, you can't speak too low,” he repeats his question without any sound at all; forming with his lips only the words, “What do you know?”</p><p >“I know three things. First, I know that here we are whispering in secrecy; a pair of conspirators.”</p><p >“Well!” says Mr. Guppy, “and we had better be that, than a pair of noodles, which we should be, if we were doing any thing else; for it's the only way of doing what we want to do. Secondly?”</p><p >“Secondly, it's not made out to me how it's likely to be profitable, after all.”</p><pb  xml:id="p318"/><p >Mr. Guppy casts up his eyes at the portrait of Lady Dedlock over the mantel-shelf, and replies, “Tony, you are asked to leave that to the honor of your friend. Besides its being calculated to serve that friend, in those chords of the human mind which—which need not be called into agonising vibration on the present occasion—your friend is no fool. What's that?”</p><p >“It's eleven o'clock striking by the bell of Saint Paul's. Listen, and you'll hear all the bells in the city jangling.”</p><p >Both sit silent, listening to the metal voices, near and distant, resounding from towers of various heights, in tones more various than their situations. When these at length cease, all seems more mysterious and quiet than before. One disagreeable result of whispering is, that it seems to evoke an atmosphere of silence, haunted by the ghosts of sound—strange cracks and tickings, the rustling of garments that have no substance in them, and the tread of dreadful feet, that would leave no mark on the sea-sand or the winter snow. So sensitive the two friends happen to be, that the air is full of these phantoms; and the two look over their shoulders by one consent, to see that the door is shut.</p><p >“Yes, Tony?” says Mr. Guppy, drawing nearer to the fire, and biting his unsteady thumb-nail. “You were going to say, thirdly?”</p><p >“It's far from a pleasant thing to be plotting about a dead man in the room where he died, especially when you happen to live in it.”</p><p >“But we are plotting nothing against him, Tony.”</p><p >“May be not, still I don't like it. Live here by yourself, and see how <hi rend="italics">you</hi> like it.”</p><p >“As to dead men, Tony,” proceeds Mr. Guppy, evading this proposal, “there have been dead men in most rooms.”</p><p >“I know there have; but in most rooms you let them alone, and—and they let you alone,” Tony answers.</p><p >The two look at each other again. Mr. Guppy makes a hurried remark to the effect that they may be doing the deceased a service; that he hopes so. There is an oppressive blank, until Mr. Weevle, by stirring the fire suddenly, makes Mr. Guppy start as if his heart had been stirred instead.</p><p >“Fah! Here's more of this hateful soot hanging about,” says he. “Let us open the window a bit, and get a mouthful of air. It's too close.”</p><p >He raises the sash, and they both rest on the window-sill, half in and half out of the room. The neighboring houses are too near, to admit of their seeing any sky without craning their necks and looking up; but lights in frowsy windows here and there, and the rolling of distant carriages, and the new expression that there is of the stir of men, they find to be comfortable. Mr. Guppy, noiselessly tapping on the window-sill, resumes his whispering in quite a light-comedy tone.</p><p >“By the bye, Tony, don't forget old Smallweed;” meaning the Younger of that name. “I have not let him into this, you know. That grandfather of his is too keen by half. It runs in the family.”</p><p >“I remember,” says Tony. “I am up to all that.”</p><p >“And as to Krook,” resumes Mr. Guppy. “Now, do you suppose he really has got hold of any other papers of importance, as he has boasted to you, since you have been such allies?”</p><pb  xml:id="p319"/><p >Tony shakes his head. “I don't know. Can't imagine. If we get through this business without rousing his suspicions, I shall be better informed no doubt. How can I know, without seeing them, when he don't know himself? He is always spelling out words from them, and chalking them over the table and the shop-wall, and asking what this is, and what that is; but his whole stock, from beginning to end, may easily be the waste paper he bought it as, for anything I can say. It's a monomania with him, to think he is possessed of documents. He has been going to learn to read them this last quarter of a century, I should judge, from what he tells me.”</p><p >“How did he first come by that idea, though? that's the question,” Mr. Guppy suggests with one eye shut, after a little forensic meditation. “He may have found papers in something he bought, where papers were not supposed to be; and may have got it into his shrewd head, from the manner and place of their concealment, that they are worth something.”</p><p >“Or he may have been taken in, in some pretended bargain. Or he may have been muddled altogether, by long staring at whatever he <hi rend="italics">has</hi> got, and by drink, and by hanging about the Lord Chancellor's court and hearing of documents for ever,” returns Mr. Weevle.</p><p >Mr. Guppy sitting on the window-sill, nodding his head and balancing all these possibilities in his mind, continues thoughtfully to tap it, and clasp it, and measure it with his hand, until he hastily draws his hand away.</p><p >“What, in the Devil's name,” he says, “is this! Look at my fingers!”</p><p >A thick, yellow liquor defiles them, which is offensive to the touch and sight, and more offensive to the smell. A stagnant, sickening oil, with some natural repulsion in it that makes them both shudder.</p><p >“What have you been doing here? What have you been pouring out of window?”</p><p >“I pouring out of window! Nothing, I swear! Never, since I have been here!” cries the lodger.</p><p >And yet look here—and look here! When he brings the candle, here, from the corner of the window-sill, it slowly drips and creeps away down the bricks; here, lies in a little thick nauseous pool.</p><p >“This is a horrible house,” says Mr. Guppy, shutting down the window. “Give me some water, or I shall cut my hand off.”</p><p >He so washes, and rubs, and scrubs, and smells, and washes, that he has not long restored himself with a glass of brandy, and stood silently before the fire, when Saint Paul's bell strikes twelve, and all those other bells strike twelve from their towers of various heights in the dark air, and in their many tones. When all is quiet again, the lodger says:</p><p >“It's the appointed time at last. Shall I go?”</p><p >Mr. Guppy nods, and gives him a “lucky touch” on the back; but not with the washed hand, though it is his right hand.</p><p >He goes down-stairs; and Mr. Guppy tries to compose himself, before the fire, for waiting a long time. But in no more than a minute or two the stairs creak, and Tony comes swiftly back.</p><p >“Have you got them?”</p><p >“Got them! No. The old man's not there.”</p><p >He has been so horribly frightened in the short interval, that his terror
<pb xml:id="p320"/>
seizes the other, who makes a rush at him, and asks loudly, “What's the matter?”</p><p >“I couldn't make him hear, and I softly opened the door and looked in. And the burning smell is there—and the soot is there, and the oil is there—and he is not there!”—Tony ends this with a groan.</p><p >Mr. Guppy takes the light. They go down, more dead than alive, and holding one another, push open the door of the back shop. The cat has retreated close to it, and stands snarling—not at them; at something on the ground, before the fire. There is very little fire left in the grate, but there is a smouldering suffocating vapor in the room, and a dark greasy coating on the walls and ceiling. The chairs and table, and the bottle so rarely absent from the table, all stand as usual. On one chair-back, hang the old man's hairy cap and coat.</p><p >“Look!” whispers the lodger, pointing his friend's attention to these objects with a trembling finger. “I told you so. When I saw him last, he took his cap off, took out the little bundle of old letters, hung his cap on the back of the chair—his coat was there already, for he had pulled that off, before he went to put the shutters up—and I left him turning the letters over in his hand, standing just where that crumbled black thing is upon the floor.”</p><p >Is he hanging somewhere? They look up. No.</p><p >“See!” whispers Tony. “At the foot of the same chair, there lies a dirty bit of thin red cord that they tie up pens with. That went round the letters. He undid it slowly, leering and laughing at me, before he began to turn them over, and threw it there. I saw it fall.”</p><p >“What's the matter with the cat?” says Mr. Guppy. “Look at her!”</p><p >“Mad, I think. And no wonder, in this evil place.”</p><p >They advance slowly, looking at all these things. The cat remains where they found her, still snarling at the something on the ground, before the fire and between the two chairs. What is it? Hold up the light?</p><p >Here is a small burnt patch of flooring; here is the tinder from a little bundle of burnt paper, but not so light as usual, seeming to be steeped in something; and here is—is it the cinder of a small charred and broken log of wood sprinkled with white ashes, or is it coal? O Horror, he IS here! and this, from which we run away, striking out the light and overturning one another into the street, is all that represents him.</p><p >Help, help, help! come into this house for Heaven's sake!</p><p >Plenty will come in, but none can help. The Lord Chancellor of that Court, true to his title in his last act, has died the death of all Lord Chancellors in all Courts, and of all authorities in all places under all names soever, where false pretences are made, and where injustice is done. Call the death by any name Your Highness will, attribute it to whom you will, or say it might have been prevented how you will, it is the same death eternally—inborn, inbred, engendered in the corrupted humours of the vicious body itself, and that only—Spontaneous Combustion, and none other of all the deaths that can be died.</p></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><head >NEW AND IMPORTANT WORKS</head><p >PUBLISHED BY GEORGE COX, 18, KING STREET, COVENT GARDEN.</p><p >[REMOVED FROM 12, KING WILLIAM STREET, STRAND.]</p><div><head >MAPS</head><p >PUBLISHED UNDER THE SUPERINTENDENCE OF <lb/> The Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge, <lb/> Price 9d., coloured; 6d. plain, each.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The whole of the Maps and Plans have been most carefully revised, and all the recent</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">discoveries added.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Plain. </cell><cell> Coloured. </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> THE ATLAS COMPLETE, 163 Maps, and 52 Plans of Towns, with Index to more than 25,000 Places, in 1 Vol., half morocco or russia </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> — in 2 Vols. </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> THE LIBRARY ATLAS, containing all the Maps of EUROPE, ASIA, AFRICA, AMERICA, and AUSTRALIA, 163 in number, with the Index, in 1 Vol., half morocco or russia </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> THE FAMILY ATLAS, containing 65 Coloured Maps, with the Index, half morocco </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> .. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Family Atlas has been selected with the greatest discrimination for general use and reference, but purchasers can form their own Atlas with, or without the Index to Places, and have it bound in their own style on application to the Publisher. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> THE CYCLOPAEDIAN ATLAS, containing 30 Maps, with the Index, half bound </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> ATLAS OF INDIA, 26 Coloured Maps, half-bound </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> .. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> THE SCHOOL ATLAS, MODERN, 25 Maps, with the Index </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 19 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> — ANCIENT, half-bound </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 11 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> — ANCIENT and MODERN, half-bound </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> OUTLINE MAPS FOR LEARNERS. Part I., containing 12 Maps </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> — Part II., containing 8 Maps </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> THE WORLD ON THE GNOMONIC PROJECTION. </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> MAP OF ENGLAND AND WALES, on roller, fully coloured </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> GEOLOGICAL MAP OF ENGLAND AND WALES, fully coloured, by hand </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> .. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> — On Roller or in Case </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> .. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> THE STARS, ON THE GNOMONIC PROJECTION </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> — Six Maps, larger size </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> THE INDEX TO THE MAPS, Atlas size, or 8vo. cloth </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> THE MAP OF LONDON, Corrected to the Present Time </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> — 3s. bound in cloth, or 6s. on roller, varnished. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p2a"/><head >LIST OF THE MAPS FORMING THE COMPLETE ATLAS.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">Single Maps, Sixpence, Plain; Ninepence, Coloured.</hi></p><list  type="simple"><item>1. World in Hemispheres, West.</item><item>2. World in Hemispheres, East.</item><item>3. World on Mercator's Projection, West.</item><item>4. World on Mercator's Projection, East.</item><item>5. World, Ancient, West.</item><item>6. World, Ancient, East.</item><item>7. World on Gnomonic Projection, I., Africa and South Europe.</item><item>8. World on Gnomonic Projection, II., America.</item><item>9. World on Gnomonic Projection, III., Polynesia.</item><item>10. World on Gnomonic Projection, IV., Asia.</item><item>11. World on Gnomonic Projection, V., from North Pole to 45° N. Lat.</item><item>12. World on Gnomonic Projection, VI., from South Pole to 45° S. Lat. Sold in Wrapper only; price 3s. plain, and 4s. 6d. col.</item><item>13. Europe, General Map.</item><item>14. British Isles.</item><item>15. England and Wales, Geological. 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item><item>16. England and Wales, Canals and Railways.</item><item>16a. England and Wales, General.</item><item>17. England and Wales, I., North-east.</item><item>18. England and Wales, II., North-west.</item><item>19. England and Wales, III., East Central.</item><item>20. England and Wales, IV., West Central.</item><item>21. England and Wales, V., South-east.</item><item>21a. England and Wales, VI., South-west.</item><item>22. Scotland, General.</item><item>23. Scotland, I., South to Perthshire.</item><item>24. Scotland, II., North.</item><item>25. Scotland, III., Islands—Hebrides, Orkneys, Shetlands.</item><item>26. Ancient Britain, I., England.</item><item>27. Ancient Britain, II., Caledonia.</item><item>28. Ireland, General.</item><item>29. Ireland, North to Dublin.</item><item>30. Ireland, South.</item><item>31. Netherlands and Belgium.</item><item>32. France, Ancient. Gallia Transalpina.</item><item>33. France in Provinces.</item><item>34. France, I., North-west to Paris.</item><item>35. France, II., North-east from Paris to the Rhine.</item><item>36. France, III., South, from Poitiers to the Mediterranean.</item><item>37. Switzerland.</item><item>38. Italy, General, with Sicily, Malta, Sardinia, and Corsica.</item><item>39. Italy, Ancient, I., North to Arretium.</item><item>40. Italy, Modern, I., Northern.</item><item>41. Italy, Ancient, II., to Gulf of Tarentum.</item><item>42. Italy, Modern, II., Central.</item><item>43. Italy, Ancient, III., South, with Sicilia.</item><item>44. Italy, Modern, III., South, with Sicily.</item><item>45. Corsica, Sardinia, and Balearic Islands.</item><item>46. Spain and Portugal, Ancient, Hispania or Iberia.</item><item>47. Spain and Portugal, Modern.</item><item>48. Spain, I., North-west, to Madrid.</item><item>49. Spain, II., North-east, Madrid to Mediterranean.</item><item>50. Spain, III., South, Madrid to Gibraltar.</item><item>51. Portugal.</item><item>52. Germany, General.</item><item>53. Germany, I., Holstein, and Pomerania to Bavaria.</item><item>54. Germany, II., Eastern Prussia.</item><item>55. Germany, III., Bavaria, Switzerland, and the Tyrol.</item><item>56. Germany, IV., (Austrian Dominions, I.) Bohemia to Sclavonia.</item><item>57. Austrian Dominions, II., Eastern Hungary and Transylvania.</item><item>58. Austrian Dominions, III., Croatia, Sclavonia, and Dalmatia, with Index Map.</item><item>59. Poland.</item><item>60. Sweden, Norway, and Denmark, General.</item><item>61. Sweden, South.</item><item>62. Denmark, and part of Norway.</item><item>63. Sweden and Norway, North, with Russia, I., Finland.</item><item>64. Russia, in Europe, General.</item><item>65. Russia, II., North-east, Archangel, Volgada, &amp;c.</item><item>66. Russia, III., North-west, St. Petersburg to Vilna.</item><item>67. Russia, IV., St. Petersburg to Moscow.</item><item>68. Russia, V., Vilna to Kiev.</item><item>69. Russia, VI., Smolensk, the Ukraine, to the Don Cossacks.</item><item>70. Russia, VII., South-cast, Moscow to Astrakhar.</item><item>71. Russia, VIII., South, the Pruth to the Sea of Azov, and Index Map.</item><item>72. Russia, IX., Caucasus, Georgia.</item><item>73. Turkish Empire &amp; Kingdom of Greece.</item><item>74. Grecian Archipelago, Ancient.</item><item>75. Macedonia and Thracia.</item><item>76. Turkey, I., North to Constantinople.</item><item>77. Greece, Ancient, N.—Illyria to Attica.</item><item>78. Turkey, II., South, and Kingdom of Greece, North.</item><item>79. Greece, Ancient, South.</item><item>80. Greece, Modern.</item><item>81. Asia, General Map.</item><item>82. Asia Minor, Ancient.</item><item>83. Asia Minor, Modern.</item><item>84. Syria, Ancient.</item><item>85. Syria, Modern.</item><item>86. Palestine in the Time of our Saviour.</item><item>87. Palestine, Modern.</item><item>88. Arabia, Egypt, Nubia, and Abyssinia.</item><item>89. Persian Empire, East part of Ancient.</item><item>90. Persia, Modern.</item><item>91. Siberia, Western, Independent Tartary, Khiva, Bokhara, &amp;c.</item><item>92. Siberia, Eastern, Kamtchatka.</item><item>93. Siberia and Chinese Tartary.</item><item>94. Bokhara, Afghanistan, Beloochistan, &amp;c.</item><item>95. India, XII., General.</item><item>96. India, I., South; and Ceylon.</item><item>97. India, II., Madras, Goa, Mysore, &amp;c.</item><item>98. India, III., Bombay, the Nizam's Dominions, &amp;c.</item><item>99. India, IV., Circars, Parts of the Nizam's Dominions, &amp;c.</item><item>100. India, V., Sinde, Gujerat, Cutch, &amp;c.</item><item>101. India, VI., Kandeish, States in Malwa, &amp;c.</item><item>102. India, VII., Allahabad, Behar, Bengal, Rewah, &amp;c.</item><item>103. India, VIII., Calcutta, Bengal (Eastern), Assam, Sikhim, Bhotan, &amp;c.</item><item>104. India, IX., Delhi, Ajmeer, &amp;c.</item><item>105. India, X., Bengal, Northern, Oude, Nepaul, &amp;c.,</item><item>106. India, XI., the Panjab, Gholab Singh's Dominions, &amp;c.</item><item>107. The Panjab, Gholab Singh's Dominions and Buhawalpoor.</item><item>108. China.</item><item>109. China and Birmah. Parts of Cochin China and Siam.</item><item>110. Malay Archipelago. Sumatra, Java, Borneo, Singapore, Labuan, &amp;c.</item><item>111. Islands in the Indian Occan. Madagascar, Mauritius, &amp;c.</item><item>112. Japan.</item><item>113. Africa, General Map.</item><item>114. Africa, North, I., Morocco.</item><item>115. Africa, North, II., Algiers.</item><item>116. Africa, North, III., Tunis, and part of Tripoli.</item><item>117. Africa, North, IV., Tripoli.</item><item>118. Africa, North, V., Tripoli, and Egypt to Alexandria.</item><item>119. Africa, Ancient, or Libya, I., Mauritania to Byzacium.</item><pb xml:id="p3a"/><item>120. Africa, Ancient, or Libya, II., Syrtis Minor to Alexandria.</item><item>121. Egypt, Ancient.</item><item>122. Egypt, Modern.</item><item>123. Africa, West, I., Senegal River to Cape St. Paul.</item><item>124. Africa, West, II., Central; Bight of Benin to Lake Tchad.</item><item>125. Africa, South, Cape Colony and Kafraria, &amp;c.</item><item>126. Islands in the Atlantic, Azores, Canaries, Cape de Verd, &amp;c.</item><item>127. America, North, General.</item><item>128. America, North, British.</item><item>129. America, North, United States and Canada.</item><item>130. America, North, I., Nova Scotia and part of New Brunswick, &amp;c.</item><item>131. America, North, II., Lower Canada, parts of Maine, New Brunswick, &amp;c.</item><item>132. America, North, III., Upper Canada, parts of New York and Michigan.</item><item>133. America, North, IV., Lake Superior, part of Upper Canada, North Michigan.</item><item>134. America, North, V., Michigan, Wisconsin, Iowa, &amp;c.</item><item>135. America, North, VI., New Hampshire, Vernont, New York, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Rhode Island, New Jersey.</item><item>136. America, North, VII., Pennsylvania, Virginia, Maryland, Delaware, New Jersey, and district of Columbia.</item><item>137. America, North, VIII., Ohio, part of Kentucky, Indiana, and Virginia.</item><item>138. America, North, IX., Part of Missouri, Illinois, Iowa, and Indiana.</item><item>139. America, North, X., Arkansas, Tennessee, Eastern parts of Mississippi, Missouri, &amp;c.</item><item>140. America, North, XI., North and South Carolina.</item><item>141. America, North, XII., Georgia, Tennessee, West, North Carolina, West, South Carolina, West, Alabama, West.</item><item>142. America, North, XIII., Louisiana, West, Mississippi, West, Alabama, East.</item><item>143. America, North, XIV., Florida.</item><item>144. America, North, XV., Texas, California, New Mexico, Utah, &amp;c., and Northern States of Mexico.</item><item>145. America, North, Mexico, Guatemala, &amp;c.</item><item>146. West India Islands, and Caribbean Sea.</item><item>147. British West Indies, Jamaica, Trinidad, Antigua, &amp;c.</item><item>148. America, South, General.</item><item>149. America, South, I., Ecuador, New Granada, Venezuela, and part of Brazil.</item><item>150. America, South, II., Guyana and North Brazil.</item><item>151. America, South, III., Bolivia and Peru.</item><item>152. America, South, IV., South Brazil, Paraguay, and Uruguay.</item><item>153. America, South, V., Argentine Republic, and Chile.</item><item>154. America, South, VI., Patagonia, with South Shetlands.</item><item>155. Pacific Ocean.</item><item>156. Polynesia, or Islands in the Pacific.</item><item>157. Australia.</item><item>158. New South Wales, with Plan of Sydney.</item><item>159. Western Australia—Van Diemen's Land.</item><item>160. Islands of New Zealand.</item><item>161. Principal Rivers in the World.</item></list></div><div type="section"><head >PLANS.</head><list  type="simple"><item>162. Amsterdam.</item><item>163. Antwerp.</item><item>164. Athens.</item><item>165. Berlin.</item><item>166. Birmingham.</item><item>167. Bordeaux.</item><item>168. Boston.</item><item>169. Brussels.</item><item>170. Calcutta.</item><item>171.<hi rend="italics">a</hi>Canton and its approaches, Macao, &amp;c.</item><item>171. Constantinople.</item><item>172. Copenhagen.</item><item>173. Dresden.</item><item>174. Dublin.</item><item>175. Dublin, Environs of.</item><item>176. Edinburgh.</item><item>177. Edinburgh, Environs of.</item><item>178. Florence.</item><item>179. Frankfort.</item><item>180. Geneva.</item><item>181. Genoa.</item><item>182. Hamburg.</item><item>183. Lisbon.</item><item>184. Liverpool.</item><item>185. London, West, in one double sheet.</item><item>186. London, East,</item><item>187. London, Environs of.</item><item>188. Madrid.</item><item>189. Marseilles.</item><item>190. Milan.</item><item>191. Moscow.</item><item>192. Munich.</item><item>193. Naples.</item><item>194. New York.</item><item>195. Oporto.</item><item>196. Paris, West.</item><item>197. Paris, East.</item><item>198. Paris, Environs of.</item><item>199. Parma.</item><item>200. St. Petersburgh.</item><item>201. Philadelphia.</item><item>202. Pompeii.</item><item>203. Rome, Ancient.</item><item>204. Rome, Modern.</item><item>205. Stockholm.</item><item>206. Syracuse.</item><item>207. Toulon.</item><item>208. Turin.</item><item>209. Venice, West.</item><item>210. Venice, East, with Environs.</item><item>211. Vienna.</item><item>212. Warsaw.</item></list><p ><hi rend="italics">Purchasers can have any of the above in case, on roller, or bound according to their order,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">on applying to the Publisher.</hi></p><p >“One of the most serviceable contributions to our means of acquiring geographical knowledge, is the volume published under the auspices of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge, bearing the title of the ‘Atlas of India.’ The change which has taken place in the study of geography of late years is extraordinary. Although one of the simplest, and, at the same time, one of the most interesting of sciences, it has been shamefully neglected in schools, and military tutors who are entrusted with the task of preparing young men for the army too often find that, the stock of geographical acquirement with which their pupils have to start amounts to little more than an acquaintance with the names of the capitals of the chief countries in Europe—a familiarity with their situation is often quite out of the question! Let it, however, be observed that the map makers and sellers are in part to blame for this. Until now, maps have borne a very high price, and are too often carelessly and inaccurately prepared. You may get the latitude and longitude of a place, but, when you come to search for it, the chances are that it is a degree or two, if not more, away from its proper situation. And, even in the best maps, insufficient distinction is made in the trace of the various parts of the earth. One may tell the broad divisions without being able to determine the boundaries of the possessions of different nations. It is in respect to all these matters that the Atlas published by the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge rises above all competitors. It is the <hi rend="italics">completest</hi> work of the kind extant. For instance, it not only gives a map of the whole empire of India from Ceylon to Peshawar at one view, on which is exhibited very clearly, by the mode of colouring, the British territory, those states that are either subsidiary, or tributary, and those that are independent; it is also an index to the map of India in twelve parts, so that any one requiring more detail as regards the rivers, roads, towns, &amp;c., &amp;c., may readily find the part he may wish to consult. We particularly notice, likewise, that a vast number of political states are shown which are not noticed on any map that we have seen, except on the published sheets of the large Indian Atlas in course of publication by the East India Company. We attribute the accuracy of this work to the fact that it has been revised by Mr. J. Walker, the Geographer to the Hon. East India Company—a gentleman who has devoted his life to the preparation of works of this kind, and is famed for his great accuracy. The indices to all the signs and peculiar names in the maps are serviceable appendages, and no less useful are the statistics given at the corner of the larger maps.”—<hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette, July</hi> 10, 1852.</p></div></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p4a"/><head >IMPORTANT WORKS <lb/> JUST PUBLISHED.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £. </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> NATIONAL CYCLOPÆDIA, Volumes I. to XII., cloth lettered, each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >COMPLETION OF THE “NATIONAL CYCLOPÆDIA OF USEFUL KNOWLEDGE.”—On the 1st of February, 1847, the publication of “The National Cyclopædia” <hi rend="italics">was commenced.</hi> The Work is now <hi rend="italics">completed,</hi> in 48 Parts, and 12 Volumes. The Publisher has a real gratification in <hi rend="italics">repeating the original announcement:</hi>—“The National Cyclopædia” is founded upon the “Penny Cyclopædia.” The Proprietor of that Work, by a careful <hi rend="italics">abridgment</hi> of its vast materials, with the addition of all <hi rend="italics">progressive information that the lapse of time demands, is producing a</hi> CYCLOPÆDIA FOR THE NATION, of the most extensive interest and utility, at a price which precludes all competition. No similar copyright materials exist for the production of a <hi rend="italics">cheap Cyclopædia,</hi> whose popularity shall be founded upon the acknowledged excellence of the sources from which it is derived.</p><p >“THE NATIONAL CYCLOPÆDIA” is <hi rend="italics">a Cyclopædia of Alphabetical Reference</hi> for every subject of human inquiry, embracing—ANCIENT AND MODERN LITERATURE; HISTORY, CIVIL AND ECCLESIASTICAL; CHRONOLOGY; BIOGRAPHY; GEOGRAPHY AND TOPOGRAPHY; LAW AND GOVERNMENT; SOCIAL ECONOMY. PHILOSOPHY; MATHEMATICS; PHYSICAL SCIENCE; CHEMISTRY; GEOLOGY AND MINERALOGY; ZOOLOGY, BOTANY; MEDICINE, SURGERY, AND ANATOMY; AGRICULTURE; ARTS, MANUFACTURES, AND TRADE. ARCHITECTURE; PAINTING AND ENGRAVING; SCULPTURE; MUSIC.</p><p >In Twelve Volumes, <hi rend="italics">demy-octavo,</hi> of more than five hundred pages each, may be had complete in sets, in the following styles of binding:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell> In cloth, lettered, handsomely and strongly bound </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Neatly and strongly half-bound in calf, lettered, coloured linings, and sprinkled edges </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Very handsomely half-bound in russia, lettered, marbled linings and edges, in 6 Volumes </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >“It is, beyond doubt, the most useful and valuable work of the kind at the cost which has ever appeared.”—<hi rend="italics">Nottingham Mercury.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell> KNIGHT'S CYCLOPÆDIA of the INDUSTRY OF ALL NATIONS, Embellished with numerous new Woodcuts of Implements, Machines, Processes, and Seats of Industry, in One Volume, handsomely bound in cloth, lettered </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >The Industry of all Nations is a vast subject. The Exhibition of 1851 presented objects and suggested principles of industrial economy that imparted a new interest to what had been before published. The People were anxiously looking for information upon this great theme. The curiosity and the emulation of the vast army of workers were stirred into more than common activity by the preparations for the “Industrial Gathering from all Lands.” The “Cyclopædia of Industry” was published as <hi rend="italics">a Companion to the Exhibition of</hi> 1851, and a Permanent Dictionary of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce.</p><p >“The Work before us collects in one view, under a variety of heads, whatever is novel and rare, and what has hitherto been obscure or imperfectly understood. It forms a work of amusement and instruction, embracing the applications of Science and Art to Productive Industry as developed in the Great Exhibition.”</p><pb  xml:id="p5a"/><p >PICTORIAL SHAKSPERE. NATIONAL EDITION. Edited by CHARLES KNIGHT. Just Completed.</p><p >The Text of this Edition is printed in a clear and beautiful type extending across the page. Many hundred woodcuts illustrate the work, and to each play a short critical notice is added. The original Pictorial Shakspere has been long out of print, and the numerous inquiries for copies of that work induced the <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Fditor</sic><corr>Editor</corr></choice> to publish the National Edition.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Complete set of Six Volumes, cloth, lettered </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume I. Comedies </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume II. Comedies </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume I. Histories </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume II. Histories </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume I. Tragedies </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Volume II. Tragedies </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >“We have before said that this was one of the best editions of the works of the immortal dramatist ever published. The size is convenient, the type and paper are of the best, the illustrations, though not profuse, are excellent, and the illustrative notes, it is sufficient to say, are by Mr. Charles Knight. Withal it is surprisingly cheap.”—<hi rend="italics">Leeds Times.</hi></p><p >“Amongst the numerous works which have emanated from Mr. Knight's press, few, if any, stand higher than this publication. The spirit with which it was commenced has been fully maintained; and the volumes, when completed, will form, although a <hi rend="italics">cheap,</hi> yet a truly beautiful and popular copy of Shakspere.”—<hi rend="italics">Plymouth Herald.</hi></p><p >“In this beautiful edition of the Works of the great dramatist, we have not merely a combination of typographical excellence and critical accuracy, but we have also another quality very strikingly obvious, and that is singular cheapness. There is no one in the present day who is better fitted to appreciate the beauties and explain the difficulties of Shakspere than is Mr. Knight; and the work when completed will be valuable for its text, illustration, and criticism.”—<hi rend="italics">Wiltshire County Mirror.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell> WILLIAM SHAKSPERE; a Biography, edited by CHARLES KNIGHT, forming a companion Volume to the National Edition, with numerous woodcuts, One Volume, cloth lettered </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><row><cell> STUDIES OF SHAKSPERE, edited by CHARLES KNIGHT, forming a Companion Volume to the National Edition </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >“There are few readers who have not access to some edition of the works of ‘The greatest in our literature—the greatest in all literature,’ but there are a vast number who have no aids in the proper appreciation of Shakspere's excellence.”—<hi rend="italics">The Author.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p6a"/><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> KNIGHT'S EXCURSION TRAIN COMPANION.—EXCURSIONS FROM LONDON, in One Volume, handsomely bound in cloth, lettered </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Or in handsome cloth binding, in Five Sections, each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >“The Excursion Train Companion” is issued in 20 <hi rend="italics">separate Numbers,</hi> each being complete in itself as regards a particular locality; but the Work is made up in FIVE SECTIONS, each taking some particular main or branch line of Railway, and is entitled “THE TRAVELLER'S JOY.”</p><p >“The Descriptions appear to contain all that is necessary to point out, in a satisfactory manner, the peculiar interest, historical or otherwise, of each locality, without being overburdened with the superfluous details usually dragged in to swell the volume of local guide-books; and the style in which they are written is, in spirit and adaptation to the large and mixed class to which they are addressed, inferior to none of Mr. Charles Knight's popular publications.”—<hi rend="italics">The Times, June</hi> 25, 1851.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> KNIGHTS CYCLOPÆDIA OF LONDON, Embellished with Woodcuts, in One Volume, handsomely bound in cloth, lettered </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE PUBLISHER, JAN., 1851.—“In the year 1844 was completed a Work on ‘LONDON,’ edited by CHARLES KNIGHT, which extended to Six large Volumes. It is proposed to publish a digested abridgment of that Work, with every necessary addition and correction, that may be completed in One handsome Octavo Volume, WITH ELABORATE WOODCUTS.”</p><p >“The descriptions before us are peculiarly adapted for those readers who wish to be made acquainted with</p><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">‘The things of fame</l><l part="N">That do adorn this city,’</l></lg><p >and the woodcuts give an accurate idea to the stranger of the buildings contained in it.”</p><p >
<table><row><cell> PICTORIAL HALF-HOURS, or MISCELLANIES OF ART, containing many hundred beautiful Woodcuts, from Pictures of the Old Masters, Sculpture, Delineations of Natural History, Sketches of Rural Scenery, and other works, in Four Volumes, handsomely bound in cloth each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> In Two Volumes, handsomely half-bound calf, marbled linings and edges </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >“Nobody understands better than Mr. Knight the great charm of a Picture Book. ‘The Miscellanies of Art,’ or ‘Pictorial Half-Hours,’ will be an amusing companion for any leisure ‘half-hour;’ and from its instructive tales and entertaining descriptions should be found in the library of all young people.”</p><p >“The cheapness of this publication cannot fail of ensuring a large demand.”—<hi rend="italics">Devonport Independent.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell> PICTORIAL HALF-HOURS OF LONDON TOPOGRAPHY, forming a Supplement to “PICTORIAL HALF HOURS.” Parts I. and II. each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ Part III., completing the Work </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ handsome cloth binding, uniform with “THE PICTORIAL HALF-HOURS” </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ Uniform with “TRAVELLER'S JOY.” </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p7a"/><head >KNIGHT'S <lb/> 160 COPYRIGHT <lb/> Shilling Volumes for all Readers.</head><list  type="simple"><head>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS TO THE SERIES.</head><item>LORD BROUGHAM.</item><item>LORD NUGENT.</item><item>CHAS. KNIGHT, <hi rend="italics">Editor.</hi></item><item>PROFESSOR LONG.</item><item>E. W. LANE.</item><item>CHARLES LAMB.</item><item>A. T. MALKIN, A.M.</item><item>MRS. JAMESON.</item><item>MISS MARTINEAU.</item><item>G. L. CRAIK, A.M.</item><item>C. MAC FARLANE.</item><item>A. DE MORGAN.</item><item>REV. C. G. NICOLAY.</item><item>W. YOUATT.</item><item>JAMES RENNIE, A.M.</item><item>W. MARTIN.</item><item>DR. KITTO.</item><item>SIR CHARLES BELL.</item><item>SIR JOHN FRANCIS DAVIS.</item><item>MRS. POOLE.</item><item>DR. LANKESTER.</item><item>DR. SOUTHWOOD SMITH.</item><item>T. R. PLANCHÉ.</item><item>RALPH N. WORNUM.</item><item>W. WITTICH.</item><item>A. VIEUSSEUX.</item><item>G. H. LEWES.</item><item>MADAME BLAZ DE BURY.</item><item>A. RAMSAY.</item><item>T. C. BANFIELD.</item><item>GEORGE DENNIS.</item><item>JAMES THORNE.</item><item>GEORGE DODD.</item><item>JOHN SAUNDERS.</item></list><p >“In every house in the Kingdom, from the palace of the peer to the humble cottage of the peasant, ought to be found ‘Knight's Shilling Volumes for all Readers.’” — <hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette.</hi></p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Each Volume, sewed </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> In cloth </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> In Double Volumes, with gilt edges </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> In Double Volumes, sprinkled </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> In Treble Volumes, with gilt edges </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> __________ sprinkled </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 8 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Lord Brougham's Statesmen of the Time of George III. A <hi rend="italics">New Edition,</hi> corrected by the Author. 6 vols. 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Lord Brougham's Dialogues on Instinet. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Lord Brougham's Two Discourses on the Objects, Pleasures, and Advantages of Science, and of Political Science. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Lord Brougham and Sir C. Bell's Edition of Paley's Natural Theology. 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“These are among the best of Lord Brongham's writings, and we are satisfied will be cherished as valuable contributions to the literature of his country ages after the names and works of many of his enemies are forgotten.”—<hi rend="italics">Economist.</hi></p><p >Sir John Davis's Manners and Customs of the Chinese and Sketches of China. <hi rend="italics">New Editions.</hi> 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“In Mr. Davis's account of China we find every subject brought forward that can throw light on the laws and institutions of a people to whom, we think, that justice has not been rendered by foreigners, which is their due.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p><p >Lane's Modern Egyptians. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Lane's ‘Account of the Manners and Customs of the Modern Egyptians’ forms an admirable <hi rend="italics">pendant</hi> to the ‘Manners and Customs of the Chinese’ by Mr. Davis. These two authors are perfect masters of their subjects. Both are well acquainted with the languages, and both have been domesticated with the people, of the two countries respectively, whose manners and customs they have undertaken to describe; the former after a residence of seven, the latter of nearly twenty years. These circumstances give their books a strong claim to be considered as books of standard value.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p><p >Lane's Arabian Tales and Anecdotes. Selected from the Arabian Nights. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“One of the peculiar and most interesting features of Mr. Lane's new translation of ‘The Thousand and One Nights’ is the introduction, by the way of notes, of many short tales or anecdotes, which form an integral portion of the vast collection of stories, the principal of which are known in England as ‘The Arabian Nights’ Entertainments,’ but which have been for the most part omitted by all previous European translators. It appeared to the Editor of the Weekly Volume that these Anecdotes would form of themselves a valuable little work, illustrating as they do many Oriental customs and modes of thought.”—<hi rend="italics">Editor's Preface.</hi></p><p >The Englishwoman in Egypt. By MRS. POOLE. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“This work, by the sister of Mr. Lane, is one of the most interesting books of travels we ever met with. The descriptions of the manners and customs of the Egyptian ladies are minute and graphic.”—<hi rend="italics">Derbyshire Courier.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p8a"/><p >Lord Nugent's Lands Classical and Sacred. <hi rend="italics">Second Edition.</hi> 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“No work of recent date on the same topics better merits and will better repay the attention of the reader.”</p><p >Miss Martineau's Tales:—FEATS ON THE FIORD, and THE BILLOW AND THE ROCK. 2 vols. 2.</p><p >“These volumes will be read with delight through every generation in a house.”—<hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.</hi></p><p >Mrs. Jameson's Lives of the Early Italian Painters, and of the Progress of the Art in Italy. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Knight's Life of Caxton, the First English Printer. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The Father of Printing could not have found a more suitable or a more enthusiastic biographer.”—<hi rend="italics">Patriot.</hi></p><p >Knight's Results of Machinery, and Capital and Labour. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The two tracts, originally published separately, are here incorporated and remodelled, the general subject of the Production of Wealth being thus fully, though popularly, expounded. The statistical details are brought up to the present time.</p><p >A Volume of Varieties. By C. KNIGHT. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >A collection of scattered papers written by Mr. Knight at various periods of a long literary life, chiefly with the view of “doing something to advance the Education of the people.”</p><p >Lamb's Tales from Shakspere, with Scenes Selected by C. KNIGHT, and Wood Engravings by W. HARVEY. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >In this edition Mr. Knight has added to each Tale a few <hi rend="italics">Scenes</hi> from Shakspere, which may be advantageously read after the perusal of the Tale, to furnish some notion of the original excellence of the wonderful dramas upon which the Tales are founded.</p><p >Insect and Bird Architecture, and Miscellanies. On the Ravages, the Preservation for the Purposes of Study, and the Classification of Insects: and on the Habits and Faculties of Birds. By JAMES RENNIE, A.M. <hi rend="italics">New Editions.</hi> 5 vols. 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“So clear and untechnical are the descriptions, that the most uninitiated, after perusing them, will see <hi rend="italics">wonders</hi> where formerly he saw <hi rend="italics">nothing.</hi>”—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Examiner.</hi></p><p >The Elephant, the Horse, and the Dog—the Three Friends of Man. By C. KNIGHT and W. MARTIN. And a Chapter on the Diseases of the Horse. By W. YOUATT. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The object of these works is to furnish very complete details of the three quadrupeds who have been the great instruments furnished by Divine Providence to man, to enable him to “replenish the earth and subdue it;” and who by their remarkable sagacity have, in various states of society, deserved to be regarded as his especial friends.</p><p >Sketch of the History of Monkeys. 100 Woodcuts. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Sketches in Natural History—MAMMALIA. 600 Woodcuts. 6 vols. 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >These volumes, with the Elephant, Horse, and Dog, complete the Class Mammalia.</p><p >Tasso's Recovery of Jerusalem. Translated by FAIRFAX. With Lives of Tasso and Fairfax, by C. KNIGHT. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“It is at least doubtful whether any of the modern renderings of the Tuscan epic are, on the whole, superior in strength and richness of expression to this of our ‘British Fairfax,’ which secured the praise of Milton, Waller, Hume, and Collins.”—<hi rend="italics">Sheffield Mercury.</hi></p><p >Mind amongst the Spindles: a Selection from the Lowell Offering. With Introduction, by C. KNIGHT. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“We believe that great good may be effected by a knowledge diffused in every building throughout the land where there is a mule or a loom, of what the factory girls of Lowell have done to exhibit the cheering influences of ‘Mind amongst the Spindles.’”—<hi rend="italics">C. Knight.</hi></p><p >Memoirs of a Working Man. With Preface, by C. KNIGHT. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >This work shows how a man, through self-education and self-government, may become intelligent, respectable, and happy, even in the humblest walks of life.</p><p >The Food of Man. By DR. LANKESTER. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“We should recommend every housekeeper and every farmer to have a copy of this most useful publication in his house for the benefit of his family.”—<hi rend="italics">Cork Examiner.</hi></p><p >History of Literature and Learning in England, from the Earliest Time to the Present Day; with <hi rend="italics">Specimens</hi> of the Principal Writers. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. 6 vols. 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“An invaluable text-book to all students of English literature.”—<hi rend="italics">Critic.</hi></p><p >Spenser and his Poetry. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The object of this publication is to present not merely an account of Spenser and his works, but such an edition of his poetry as shall contain all of it that is of universal and indestructible interest.</p><p >Bacon, his Writings and his Philosophy. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Combining in one book the uses and attractions of a life of Bacon; a complete bibliography of his different works; a history of each from its first conception to its finished form; a distinct exposition of its scope and tendency; a selection of their most beautiful and instructive passages; and a general estimate of the philosopher and his writings, at once characterised by logical acumen, and a deep, fresh sense of imaginative grandeur.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><p >The Pursuit of Knowledge under Difficulties. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >A body of examples to show how the most unpropitious circumstances have been unable to conquer an ardent desire for the acquisition of knowledge.</p><p >Female Examples of the Pursuit of Knowledge under Difficulties. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. <hi rend="italics">A New Work.</hi> 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >As a record, it is full of anecdote and interest. The book, as it stands, is a pleasant one—worthy of being accepted by all thoughtful women and honourable men.” — <hi rend="italics">Athenœum.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p9a"/><p >History of British Commerce, from</p><p >the Earliest Time to the Present Day. By G. L. CRAIK, A.M. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“To the merchant, the capitalist, the manufacturer, the tradesman, to all who are desirous of knowing by what means England has arrived at her present state of commercial greatness and prosperity, we recommend this work as the cheapest and by far the best mode of obtaining the desired information.”—<hi rend="italics">Lincoln Standard.</hi></p><p >Wittich's Curiosities of Physical Geography. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >CONTENTS:—SNOW-MOUNTAINS—GLACIERS—AVALANCHES—MOUNTAINS-SLIPS—ICEBERGS AND ICEFIELDS—THE GULF-STREAM—THE SAMOON—TRADE-WINDS—MONSOONS—PLAINS AND DESERTS—THE SAHARA—THE SELVA, OR FOREST DESERT OF THE AMAZONAS—THE PAMPAS—THE LLANOS—EARTHQUAKES—VALCANOES.</p><p >Wittich's Visit to the Western Coast of Norway. With a Memoir of the Author, by PROFESSOR LONG. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Mr. Wittich was one of the most distinguished geographers of modern times; in knowledge of the subject, and in the method of handling it, inferior to none; and only less known because his labours have not appeared, like those of Ritter and others, in voluminous works that bear the author's name. He has contributed more largely to the diffusion of geographical knowledge, and more largely to the giving to it some scientific method and precision, than any person who has yet lived in the British Islands.”—<hi rend="italics">Memoir, by Professor Long.</hi></p><p >The Lost Senses—DEAFNESS AND BLINDNESS. By DR. KITTO. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Dr. Kitto, when twelve years old, was deprived of his hearing by falling from a ladder; and the work is a record of his experience, observations, and reflections with regard to his calamity during a deafness of twenty-eight years.</p><p >Molière, Racine, and the French Classical Drama. By MADAME BLAZ DE BURY. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“To those who are ignorant of the French language this little work will be comprehensible and most charming.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p><p >The Spanish Drama—LOPE DE VEGA AND CALDERON. By G. H. LEWES. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A lively and brief account of the two most eminent dramatists of Spain.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenaeum.</hi></p><p >The Cid. A Short Chronicle founded on the Early Poetry of Spain. By G. DENNIS, Author of ‘The Cities and Cemeteries of Etruria.‘ 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“One of the most absorbing and romantic narratives we ever read.”</p><p >Life of Gresham, the Founder of the Royal Exchange. By C. MAC FARLANE. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A well written and very interesting biography of this remarkable English merchant.”—<hi rend="italics">John o' Great Journal.</hi></p><p >Popular Customs and Recollections of Italy. By C. MAC FARLANE. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“An exceedingly interesting and agreeable little book.” <hi rend="italics">Sheffield Times.</hi></p><p >Old England Novelets:—THE CAMP OF REFUGE—THE DUTCH IN THE MEDWAY—A LEGEND OF READING ABBEY. By C. MAC FARLANE. 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The object of this seríes is “to illustrate some leading causes of the social condition of our country in times essentially different from our own.”</p><p >Romance Of Travel—THE EAST. By C. MAC FARLANE. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“We should feel disposed to utter a somewhat lengthened commendation upon the Oriental sketches of Mr. Mac Farlane, but that we deem such eulogiums altogether superfluous from the popularity already acquired by his writings.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p><p >Plutarch's Lives—THE CIVIL WARS OF ROME: Select Lives from Plutarch, newly translated, by PROFESSOR LONG, late Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge. With Notes. 5 vols. 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The manner in which the translation is executed demands the highest praise.....The style will be found much more precise and vigorous than that of the version by the Langhornes. But what give the book its chief value are Mr. Long's notes. which are equally learned and judicious.”—<hi rend="italics">Classical Museum, No. X.</hi></p><p >Chaucer's Canterbury Tales and Pic-tures of English Life. By JOHN SAUNDERS. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Readers who are only beginning to initiate themselves into the mysteries of antique spelling, Gallic construction, and other peculiarities inseparable from the age in which the father of English poets lived, will find this book of great assistance to their future studies.”—<hi rend="italics">The Apprentice.</hi></p><p >Rambles by Rivers. By JAMES THORNE. The Thames, the Avon, the Duddon, the Lea, and the Dove. 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Delightful volumes.....The reader finds himself rambling along some of the most interesting and celebrated streams of England, in the company of an intelligent, well-informed, and pleasant guide.’—<hi rend="italics">John o' Groat Journal.</hi></p><p >Historical Parallels. By A. MALKIN, A.M. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >A collection of narratives of great interest to those who are not largely read in history.</p><p >Napoleon Buonaparte; His Sayings and his Deeds. By A. VIEUSSEUX. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >A concise and popular sketch, and an endeavour to trace the inner workings of Napoleon's mind, elicited from his familiar conversations.</p><p >The Industry of the Rhine—AGRICULTURE AND MANUFACTURES. By T. C. BANFIELD. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“These very interesting volumes contain a great deal of valuable information.”—<hi rend="italics">Gardeners Chronicle.</hi></p><p >Hudibras and other Works of Samuel BUTLER. Edited by A. RAMSAY. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A careful analysis, with ample extracts; such as may be read with pleasure by the most fastidious.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenaeum.</hi></p><pb  xml:id="p10a"/><p >Flowers and their Associations, and the Field, Garden, and Woodland. By MISS PRATT. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“An agreeable, gossiping book—instructive and entertaining.”—<hi rend="italics">Gardeners' Chronicle.</hi></p><p >The Backwoods of Canada. By a LADY. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“An endeavour to afford every possible information to the wives and daughters of emigrants who contemplate seeking a home amid our Canadian wilds.”—<hi rend="italics">Preface.</hi></p><p >The Oregon Territory. By the Rev. G. C. NICOLAY. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Biographical History of Ancient and Modern Philosophy. By G. H. LEWES. 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A more readable book we scarcely know.”—<hi rend="italics">Cheltenham Journal.</hi></p><p >Philosophy of Health, written with a view to the Promotion of Human Longevity and Happiness. By Dr. SOUTHWOOD SMITH, Commissioner of the General Board of Health, <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 4 vols. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The distinguished medical reputation of the Author, and his extreme simplicity of style, arising from a thorough mastery of his subject, must recommend his complete exposition of the structure and functions of the body to all classes of persons who desire any knowledge of the fearful and wonderful organization of the human frame. Dr. Southwood Smith's work has a practical aim, as all his observations have reference to health and disease, and are intended to promote the eagerly desired blessings of ‘human longevity and happiness.’ ”—<hi rend="italics">Britannia.</hi></p><p >The Cabinet Portrait Gallery of Bri-tish Worthies. With 72 Steel Engravings, 12 vols. 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“We cordially recommend the work to those who would read elegantly written biographies of their country's greatest men.”—<hi rend="italics">Douglas Jerrold's Newspaper.</hi></p><p >Settlers and Convicts; or, Recollections of Sixteen Years' Labour in the Backwoods of Australia. By an EMIGRANT MECHANIC. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A valuable manual for all those whose circumstances or inclination lead to contemplate emigration as a means of relief from distress or difficulty at home.”—<hi rend="italics">Hertford Mercury.</hi></p><p >The Manufactures of Great Britain. By G. DODD. 6 vols. 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A book eminently suited to the times—should be read by all who would know how it is that England has acquired the character of being the great workshop of the world.”—<hi rend="italics">British Friend of India Magazine.</hi></p><p >The Epochs of Painting charac-terized: a Sketch of the History of Painting, Ancient and Modern, showing its gradual and various Development from the Earliest Ages to the Present Time. By RALPH N. WORNUM. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A clear and well-written sketch, comprehending a review of the progress of painting in every country where the art has obtained a cognizable degree of development, extending over a period of nearly three thousand years, and including biographical notices of many of the most eminent painters. It displays an intimate knowledge of the subject and considerable learning.”—<hi rend="italics">Builder.</hi></p><p >Pompeii; its Destruction and Re-discovery. <hi rend="italics">New Edition.</hi> 300 Woodcuts. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“In this work is given a detailed account of the ruins as they now exist, together with a description of their former state, as far as it can be made out; with occasional digressions upon points connected with the history or antiquities of the place, and notices of the most important and curious articles which have been discovered. The first portion of the work contains the public edifices, so far as they have as yet been disinterred; the second portion is devoted to the houses and private habits of their tenants.”—<hi rend="italics">Introduction.</hi></p><p >Popular Tumults; Illustrative of the Evils of Social Ignorance. 1 vol. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >This volume contains Accounts of Tumults of Religious Fanaticism—Tumults of Political Excitement—and Tumults for raising the Rate of Wages.</p><p >History of British Costume, from the Earliest Period to the Close of the Eighteenth Century. By J. R. PLANCHE, Esq., F.S.A. With numerous Illustrations. <hi rend="italics">New Edition,</hi> corrected and enlarged, and an Index added. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“On presenting this new edition of ‘The History of British Costume’ to the public, the author has merely to state that it has undergone thorough revision and correction; that he has supplied many deficiencies, incorporated the most important discoveries and opinions which have resulted from the latest researches, or been promulgated in recent archaeological publications; and added an Index to facilitate the reader's reference to any particular article mentioned or described in its pages.”—<hi rend="italics">Preface to New Edition.</hi></p><p >Secret Societies of the Middle Ages.</p><p >An Account of the Rise and Progress of the celebrated Eastern Association, known as THE ASSASSINS; of the Foundation, History, and violent Suppression of the KNIGHTS TEMPLARS; and of the Origin, Proceedings, and Decline of the FEHMGERICHTE, or SECRET SOCIETIES OF WESTPHALIA. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The Book of Table-Talk. By several CONTRIBUTORS. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“An excellent book for railway reading.”—<hi rend="italics">Critic.</hi></p><p >Physical Geography of the Holy Land. By JOHN KITTO, D.D., F.S.A., Editor of the Pictorial Bible. 2 vols. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The country which God especially set apart for his great designs, and which, in consequence, contains no spot of ground on which some commissioned angel has not trod, or which does not suggest some incident in the histories of patriarchs, prophets, apostles, priests, and kings, whose names supply the familiar links by which our minds measure old times—this country must needs excite a peculiar interest in us, scarcely inferior to that with which our own native land is regarded.”—<hi rend="italics">Author's Introduction.</hi></p><p >Paris: its Historical Buildings and its Revolutions. <hi rend="italics">New Edition,</hi> continued to the Present Time. 3 vols. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“The account of the Revolution of Paris in 1848 is the best we have read of the many narratives that have been published on that popular subject. It is closer, more complete, and impresses the causes of the catastrophe more clearly; while the Introduction conveys an idea of the power and numbers of the Republicans, by briefly bringing together the insurrections or disturbances that have taken place since 1830. It is a well-timed book; for the previous part enables the reader to get beyond the ignorant present, and see what Paris has always been.”—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p></div><div type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p11a"/><head >Knight's Pictorial Works.</head><div type="section"><opener >With about 4000 Engravings, in Twenty-Seven Shilling Parts, or 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in <lb/> 2 handsome volumes, cloth,</opener><head >THE PICTORIAL GALLERY OF ARTS.</head><p >Vol. I., USEFUL ARTS; Vol. II., FINE ARTS.</p><p >‘The great purpose which is to be kept in mind, in this and similar works which teach by pictures as well as words, is the expansion of the intellect of all who see and read. What our “PICTORIAL MUSEUM” is to the world of “ANIMATED NATURE” our “PICTORIAL GALLERY” is to the world of “ART.” The “Museum” exhibits the great Author of Good displaying His power and wisdom in the creation of the wonderful varieties of life with which the earth is filled, all His creatures accomplishing the purposes of their being in harmony with the great scheme of His providence. The “Gallery” exhibits the same benevolent teacher of Man leading him forward from the humblest exercise of his faculties to the most complete development of his intellectual powers; and, through the agency of these powers, enabling him “to subdue the earth,” and elevate himself in the scale of being, by the aid of the accumulated knowledge of society, heaped up for him by the experience of many generations. The one work is a sequel to the other. Each has especial reference to the instruction of the people, particularly the young.‘—<hi rend="italics">Original Prospectus.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><opener >A PICTORIAL COMPANION AND KEY TO EVERY <lb/> HISTORY OF ENGLAND.<lb/>With 3000 Woodcuts and 24 Coloured Engravings, price 36<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in Twenty-Four parts, or <lb/> 2 handsome volumes, cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi></opener><head >OLD ENGLAND; <lb/> A PICTORIAL MUSEUM OF NATIONAL ANTIQUITIES.</head><p >This work opens to all ranks, at the cheapest rate, a view of the REGAL, ECCLESIASTICAL, BARONIAL, MUNICIPAL, and POPULAR ANTIQUITIES of England, given in a chronological order; and thus the work is a Companion and a Key to every English History. The Engravings embrace the most remarkable of our buildings from the earliest times—DRUIDICAL REMAINS, CATHEDRALS, ABBEYS, CHURCHES, COLLEGES, CASTLES, CIVIC HALLS, MANSIONS, SEPULCHRAL MONUMENTS of our Princes and Nobles, portraits of British Worthies and representations of localities associated with their names, ancient Pictures and Illuminations of Historical Events, the Great Seals and Arms of the Monarchy, Coins and Medals, Autographs; with the fullest pictorial indications of the INDUSTRY, the ARTS, the SPORTS, the DRESSES, and the DAILY LIFE of the People.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >Price 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in Parts, or 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in handsome cloth,</opener><head >OLD ENGLAND'S WORTHIES.</head><p >A Gallery of 72 Portraits on Steel, and 12 splendid illuminated Engravings of some remarkable place or monument associated with the life of some one of ‘OLD ENGLAND'S WORTHIES,’ arranged in a chronological order, thus enabling the reader to become familiar with the greatest names of his countrymen in illustrative succession.</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p12a"/><opener >With 1500 Woodcuts and 13 Coloured Maps, forming a SCRIPTURE ATLAS; price 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in <lb/> Parts, or in handsome cloth, 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >THE PICTORIAL SUNDAY-BOOK.</head><p >By J. KITTO, Editor of the Pictorial Bible.</p><p >The publication now submitted to Christian families is intended to present, at the very cheapest rate, a series of engravings illustrative of the Bible History, the Prophecies, the Psalms, the Life of Our Saviour, and the Acts of his Apostles; exhibiting the Scenes of the great Events recorded in Scripture, the Customs of the Jews, the Natural History of the Holy Land, and the Antiquities which throw a light upon the Sacred Writings, with a body of Scriptural Narrative and Explanation, continuing from number to number; each number forming, as it is judged, a fitting portion for a Sunday's leisure.</p><p >THE SCRIPTURE ATLAS, with the Geography of the Holy Land, is sold separately. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> sewed, or 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >With 4000 Woodcuts, in Twenty-Seven Shilling parts, or 34<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in 2 handsome <lb/> volumes, cloth,</opener><head >THE PICTORIAL MUSEUM OF ANIMATED NATURE.</head><p >The reader, at the very smallest price, is put in possession of, by far, the most extensive collection that has ever been produced of pictorial representations of all the important quadrupeds, birds, fishes, reptiles, and insects which fill the earth; with a corresponding description of the animal, its structure, its habits, its localities, its use; not given in a dry and repulsive form, but with that simplicity which may furnish just conceptions to all, but especially to the young, of the wonders and beauties of God's creation.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >THE BEST EDITION OF SHAKSPERE IN ONE VOLUME, <lb/> ILLUSTRATED BY W. HARVEY. Price 13<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth, <hi rend="italics">Sixth Edition,</hi></opener><head > THE WORKS OF WILLIAM SHAKSPERE; <lb/> CONTAINING HIS PLAYS AND POEMS, FROM THE TEXT OF <lb/> THE EDITIONS BY CHARLES KNIGHT.</head><p >With Explanatory Notes and Facts connected with his Life and Writings, abridged from <lb/> ‘William Shakspere, a Biography.’</p></div><div type="section"><opener >Fourth Edition of 3000 copies each, with an additional Chapter on Poisons by DR. GLADSTONE, <lb/> price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</opener><head >HOUSEHOLD SURGERY; <lb/> OR, HINTS ON EMERGENCIES.</head><p >By JOHN F. SOUTH, SURGEON TO ST. THOMAS'S HOSPITAL.</p><p >The object of this Work is to afford some useful hints as to the means which people have in their own power to employ when accidents happen which require immediate attention and no medical man is at hand, and often cannot be obtained for hours. Such cases are neither few nor unimportant, and many serious consequences—nay, even death—may be prevented if a judicious person, having been put on the track, make use of the simple remedies almost every house affords.</p><p >“We have seldom seen a book of wider or more sound practical utility than this unpretending little volume. We can conscientiously recommend Mr. South's Manual to the notice of the public. It is not a class-book; IT IS EVERYBODY'S BOOK; and above all, travellers, emigrants, and residents in remote country places should not fail to provide themselves with it.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p><p >G. COX, 18, KING STREET, COVENT GARDEN.</p></div></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p13a"/><opener >12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</opener><head >MOTT'S <lb/> NEW SILVER ELECTRO PLATE,</head><p >Possessing in a pre-eminent degree the qualities of Sterling Silver.</p><p >A table may be elegantly furnished with this beautiful manufacture at a <lb/> fifth of the cost of Silver, from which it cannot be distinguished.</p><p >W. MOTT invites particular attention to his very extensive stock of all articles of Plate required for the Sideboard, Dinner and Breakfast Tables, now manufactured in this elegant material, comprising superb Epergnes, Candelabra, Salad Stands, Wine Coolers, Waiters, Corner Dishes, Meat and Venison Dishes, Dish Covers, Cruet Frames, Liqueur Stands, Spoons, and Forks, Tea and Coffee Services, Tea Kettles, Toast Racks, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> TEA POTS from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 each. </cell></row><row><cell> CRUET FRAMES, great variety from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 each. </cell></row><row><cell> LIQUEUR FRAMES, elegant designs from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 each. </cell></row><row><cell> WAITERS, of every size, from 8 to 24 inches, commencing at </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 each. </cell></row><row><cell> FLOWER VASES, with glass linings from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 each. </cell></row><row><cell> DISH COVERS, 12 to 20 Guineas the set. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SPOONS AND FORKS.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Fiddle. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Threaded. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> King's. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Table Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Table Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Dessert Forks </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Tea Spoons </cell><cell> per dozen </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gravy Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Sauce Ladles </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Soup Ladles </cell><cell> each </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Salt Spoons </cell><cell> per pair </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLETS OF PRICES GRATIS. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row></table>
</p><closer >W. MOTT, 12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p14a"/><opener >Manufactory, 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON.</opener><head >English Watches that may be relied upon for <lb/> Accuracy and Durability.</head><p >MOTT'S <lb/> English Patent Levers in Gold Cases and <lb/> Gold Dial.—Ten Guineas.</p><p >In order to assimilate as nearly as possible the cost of his best English Watches to the price of Foreign, over which they possess an immeasurable superiority in the grand requirements of correct performance and durability, W. MOTT has made a considerable reduction in the scale of prices, at the same time maintaining the high character by which, for so many years, they have been distinguished.</p><p >
<table><head>GOLD CASES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, double back and gold dial </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, with engraved back </cell><cell> 11 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, full size, highly finished </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, engraved back </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, enamel dial </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, engraved back </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, very flat construction </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 18 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>SILVER CASES.</head><row><cell> Patent Lever, double back, jewelled </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, to go while winding </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, very flat construction </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Patent Lever, Hunting cases </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >WATCHES REPAIRED, AND ONE LENT GRATIS DURING THE TIME, <lb/> AT THE <lb/> MANUFACTORY, <lb/> No. 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, <lb/> CORNER OF FRIDAY STREET.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p15a"/><head >WATERLOW'S <lb/> PATENT IMPROVED AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, <lb/> OR PORTABLE <lb/> PRINTING MACHINE,</head><p >FOR THE COUNTING-HOUSE, OFFICE, OR LIBRARY, <lb/> BY MEANS OF WHICH <lb/> EVERY PERSON MAY BECOME HIS OWN PRINTER.</p><p >The process is simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing, piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.</p><p >Many hundreds of these Presses have now been sold, and are being successfully used by Railway and Public Companies, Bankers, Merchants, Amateurs, &amp;c., &amp;c.; also in Public and Private Schools, for the production of Lessons in Music, Drawing, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p><p >The Press may be seen at work at the Patentees,’ and specimens of its production will be forwarded free, upon application.</p><p >
<table><head>PRICES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> On Mahogany Stand. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 11 × 9 </cell><cell> £7 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 16½ × 10½ </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> To print a Subject </cell><cell> 18 × 13½ </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><div><head >PATENT AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS FOR TRAVELLERS,</head><p >WHICH FROM ITS COMPACT FORM IS RECOMMENDED FOR USE ON <lb/> VOYAGES AND FOREIGN MISSIONS.</p><p >To Print a Subject 11 × 9 Price complete £9 9 0.</p><p >PATENTEES—WATERLOW AND SONS, 65 TO 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</p><p >From the City Article of “The Times.”</p><p >A very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, which will be productive of great convenience to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared paper, with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly valuable.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p16a"/><head >PATENT LETTER COPYING PRESSES.</head><p >These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Lever Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Screw Press, wrt. iron beam. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Damping Boxes. </cell></row><row><cell> Large 4to </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> £3 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 11s. </cell></row><row><cell> Foolscap Folio </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12s. </cell></row><row><cell> Post Folio </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 14s. </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>MAHOGANY STANDS FOR COPYING PRESSES.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> Quarto. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Foolscap. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> Folio. </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 1 drawer </cell><cell> £1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell><cell>   </cell><cell> — </cell><cell>   </cell></row><row><cell> 2 drawer </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> £2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 drawer </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 2 drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> 3 drawer and flaps </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 14 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><div><head >COPYING BOOKS,</head><p >OF BLUE OR CREAM-WOVE COPYING PAPER, OF FIRST QUALITY, <lb/> TYPE-PAGED BY STEAM POWER.</p><p >
<table><row><cell> QUARTER BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell><cell> HALF BOUND. </cell><cell> Each. </cell><cell> per doz. </cell></row><row><cell> 500 LEAVES </cell><cell> 8s. </cell><cell> 84s. </cell><cell> 500 LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 102s. </cell></row><row><cell> 750 LEAVES </cell><cell> 10s. </cell><cell> 105s. </cell><cell> 750 LEAVES </cell><cell> 13s. </cell><cell> 138s. </cell></row><row><cell> 1000 LEAVES </cell><cell> 12s. </cell><cell> 126s. </cell><cell> 1000 LEAVES </cell><cell> 15s. </cell><cell> 156s. </cell></row></table>
</p></div><div><head >Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink, <lb/> FOR COPYING LETTERS.</head><p >The only <hi rend="italics">really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="italics">used</hi> in many of the <hi rend="italics">Principal Establishments in London,</hi>
<lb/> and is universally admitted the best yet produced.</p><p >Per PINT, 2s. Per QUART, 3s. Per DOZEN QUARTS, 30s. Per GALLON, 10s. Per HALF-GALLON, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per GALLON, do., do., 12s.</p></div><div><head >STATIONERY CASES, OF POLISHED MAHOGANY <lb/> OR OAK.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>   </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> No. 1, with secret drawer, lock, and key, &amp;c., to hold foolscap and letter papers, envelopes, wax, &amp;c., and fitted with pen-tray and inkstand </cell><cell> 35 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> No. 2, for large letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c. </cell><cell> 24 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> No. 3, for small letter paper, envelopes, &amp;c., &amp;c. </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >Sufficient paper, envelopes, &amp;c., to fill the above cases, of the best quality, would be respectively about 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >These Stationery Cases are admirably adapted for <lb/> presents.</p><p >WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65 to 68, London Wall, London.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p17a"/><head >NEW SPORTING NEWSPAPER.</head><p >On the 1st of January will be published, price Sixpence, <lb/> to be continued Weekly, <lb/> THE FIRST NUMBER OF <lb/> THE FIELD; <lb/> OR, <lb/> COUNTRY GENTLEMAN'S NEWSPAPER.</p><p >With occasional Illustrations; <lb/> DEVOTED ESPECIALLY TO</p><list  type="simple"><item>HUNTING,</item><item>SHOOTING,</item><item>YACHTING,</item><item>RACING,</item><item>COURSING,</item><item>CRICKETING,</item><item>FISHING,</item><item>ARCHERY.</item></list><p >Agricultural and Health-giving pursuits generally. With a COMPREHENSIVE SUMMARY OF THE WEEK'S NEWS; Law and Police Reports, Lists of Markets, Theatricals, Fashionable Intelligence, Reviews of Books, Veterinary Information, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Temporary Office for Advertisements and Communications to the Editor,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">No. 5, Red Lion Passage, Red Lion Court, Fleet Street.</hi></p><p >Bradbury &amp; Evans, Printers, Whitefriars.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p19a"/><head >USE <lb/> MARSLAND, SON, &amp; CO'S <lb/> UNRIVALLED AND REGISTERED <lb/> GRIFFIN CROCHET COTTON.</head><p >MARSLAND, SON, and Co. beg to call particular attention to their unrivalled “GRIFFIN CROCHET COTTON,” which has deservedly attained such an EXTRAORDINARY celebrity throughout the whole country, arising from its decided superiority over every other cotton yet presented to the public.</p><p >From the many advantages which MARSLAND, SON, and Co. enjoy in the most improved machinery and great manufacturing skill, together with a rapidly increasing trade, they are enabled to produce both Crochet and Sewing Cotton, which will defy all competition.</p><p >Their CROCHET COTTON is made of a peculiar material, which renders it exceedingly pleasant to work with; it has a soft, yet cabled surface, is extremely free from fibre, is warranted not to twist or curl in the working, or to shrink in the washing, and has an extraordinary silkiness of finish, which causes the pattern, when crocheted and washed, to possess a beautiful pearly appearance never before attained by any other manufacture.</p><p >M. S. and Co's. manufacture of CROCHET COTTON contains every variety of Colours, warranted fast.</p><p >The Editresses of the “Ladies' Newspaper,” the “Ladies' Own Book,” the Editor of the “Shortway Edging and Round D'Oyley,” the “Exhibition and Teignmouth,” the Editor of the “Bijou,” and all the leading Publishers of the present day, are bringing out their works and patterns to suit the numbers of MARSLAND, SON, and Co's. Crochet Cotton.</p><p >M. S. and Co., also manufacture NINE CORD, SIX CORD, and THREE CORD SEWING COTTON, of a quality equal to their Crochet Cotton, which is sold at the same establishments.</p><div type="section"><head >The full lengths are guaranteed.</head><p >Sold retail by the principal Berlin Wool venders, drapers, haberdashers, smallware dealers, &amp;c.</p><p >N.B.—The trade supplied by Messrs. Faudel and Philips, Messrs. Hutton and Co. and Messrs. Block and Son, Newgate Street, London: Messrs. Todd, Burns, and Co. and Messrs. Cannock, White, and Co. Dublin; Messrs. Lindsay Brothers, and Messrs. John Arnott and Co. Belfast; Messrs. Revington and Co. Limerick; Messrs. Fitzgibbon and Co. and Messrs. Arnott and Co. Cork; by all the leading warehouses in Manchester; or at the Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester, where all orders by post or personal application will be immediately attended to </p><closer > LONDON AGENT: EDWARD WRIGHT, 33, LAWRENCE LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</closer></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p20a"/><head >MARSLAND, SON, &amp; CO'S <lb/> NEWLY REGISTERED, VARIEGATED, AND COLORED <lb/> CROCHET COTTON.</head><p >CRESTS AND CENTRES FOR D'OYLEYS, &amp;c. MARSLAND, SON, and Co.s. Crochet Thread, No. 24: Penelope <lb/> Crochet Hook, No. 3.</p><p >Work the ground in open, and the design in close squares. <hi rend="italics">Vide “Ladies Newspaper,”</hi> Edited by Maddlle. DUFOUR, for recommendation of Marsland Son, and Co's Cottou.</p><p >FOR MATTS, D'OYLEYS, MACASSARS, &amp;c., &amp;c <lb/> WARRANTED FAST COLORS.</p><p >Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</p><p >A new and original design will be issued every month.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p21a"/><head >CHRISTMAS.</head><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">THE Winter's blasts sweep o'er the moor,</l><l part="N">The snow blocks up the cottage door;</l><l part="N">Without there's nothing much akin</l><l part="N">To scenes re-acting now within.</l><l part="N">The Boys think feasting is secure,</l><l part="N">The Girls are looking—not demure.</l><l part="N">The holly bough show berries red.</l><l part="N">The bright fire shoots its glare ahead.</l><l part="N">Tables and chairs are moved away,</l><l part="N">The season's sports they would delay.</l><l part="N">But mind! a Misletoe's suspended;</l><l part="N">Its purpose (of course) not comprehended.</l><l part="N">But young ones virtuously will sip</l><l part="N">Melliferous dew from Iosy lip.</l><l part="N">Yet eyes which settle lover's fate,</l><l part="N">On STYLES of DRESS so much dilate.</l><l part="N">That if o'er hearts you'd have dominion,</l><l part="N">Be sure to take <hi rend="italics">“a Dear's”</hi> opinion,</l><l part="N">I've seen on many a Christmas Day,</l><l part="N">These gentlemen sure to push their way;</l><l part="N">Whose Dress by MOSES' art is made</l><l part="N">The GEM and ORNAMENT of Trade.</l><l part="N">I've seen such things as these transpire.</l><l part="N">When youths dress'd in their new attire,</l><l part="N">If that at MOSES' Mart was bought,</l><l part="N">'T'as quite a shoal of praises brought.</l><l part="N">The MAKE, the STYLE, and the low charge,</l><l part="N">The fame of MOSES' must enlarge.</l></lg><p >JUVENILE DRESS, and every description of OVERCOATS cheaper and <lb/> better than at any other House in the World.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >E. MOSES &amp; SON'S <lb/> AUTUMN AND WINTER LIST OF PRICES.</head><p >
<table><head>MEN'S WINTER COATS.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> The New BEQUEME Over-Coat, designed by E. MOSES &amp; SON from 25<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Pea Coats </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Chesterfields and Codringtons, various materials </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Witney Wrapper </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 16 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Derby Coat, made to wear as an Over or Surtout Coat from 21<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The MELTON MOWBRAY, a new and elegant Overcoat from 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Wellington Sac, made to form Coat, Cloak, and Traveller's Companion, designed by and only to be had of E. Moses &amp; Son, from 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>BOYS' WINTER COATS.</head><row><cell> Byron Coat from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Chesterfield from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> The Bulwer, in cloth of all colours, and the new Melton Mowbray material, a neat gentlemanly style of Coat 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>WALKING, FISHING &amp; SHOOTING COATS.</head><row><cell> Plaid Shooting Coats from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> The Melton Mowbray Cambridge Coat, quite a new material 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Fishing Coats in endless variety, suited either for Sporting, Gardening, or House Coat, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 5 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>AUTUMN AND WINTER WAISTCOATS.</head><row><cell> White Quilting (for Dress) 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Kerseymere 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Doeskins, Tweeds, &amp;c. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 9 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Embroidered Cloth from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> A large assortment of Fancy Thibets, and a variety of Fancy Materials from 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 13 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>AUTUMN AND WINTER TROUSERS.</head><row><cell>   </cell><cell> £ </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell></row><row><cell> Tweeds from 4s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 7 </cell><cell> 6 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Kerseymere, for Dress from 9s. 6d. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Black Doeskin, for Dress from 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 6 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> A large assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskins 18s., 22s. to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>DRESS COATS.</head><row><cell> Dress Coat from </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 17 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best quality from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>FROCK COATS.</head><row><cell> Frock Coat from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Best Coat from </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>JUVENILE CLOTHING.</head><row><cell> Tunic and Hussar Suit from 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 12 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Polka Jacket, handsomely trimmed 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Spanish Dress from 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><head>LIVERIES.</head><row><cell> Page's suit from </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 8 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Footman's </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 15 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Groom's </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Coachman's </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p ><hi rend="italics">All the above materials are made into Suits to match, and form a very comfortable dress, either for Travelling, Walking, or Office.</hi></p><p >LADIES' AND GENTLEMEN'S HOSIERY.</p><p >The Largest Stock in the Kingdom,</p><p >
<table><head> LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</head><row><cell> Summer Cloth Habits, with ⅞ train from </cell><cell> 2 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superior Cloth Habits </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 3 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row><row><cell> Superfine quality </cell><cell> 4 </cell><cell> 10 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row></table>
</p><p >HATS AND CAPS, THE NEWEST STYLES AT <lb/> THE LOWEST PRICES.</p><p >A large Assortment of HUNTING and SHOOTING BOOTS, including the celebrated GROUSE BOOT.</p><p >CAUTION.—E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the Public against imposition, having learned that the <hi rend="italics">untradesmanlike falsehood</hi> of “being connected with their Establishment,” or “It's the same concern,” has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons. They beg to state they have NO CONNECTION WITH ANY OTHER HOUSE IN OR OUT OF LONDON, EXCEPT THEIR OWN ESTABLISHMENTS, as follows:—</p><p >London City Establishments:—154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, (opposite the Church) all communicating.</p><p >London West End Branch:—506, 507, and 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, and 3, Hart-street, all communicating.</p><p >Bradford, “Yorkshire” Branch, 19 and 20, Bridge-street.</p><p >Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p><p >The FUR and SHAWL DEPARTMENT is now replete with every Novelty of the Season.</p><p >IMPORTANT.—Should any article not give satisfaction, it will be exchanged, if desired, or, if preferred, the money will be returned without hesitation. All Goods are marked, in plain figures, the lowest prices, from which no abatement can be made.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed from sunset on Fridays till sunset on Saturdays, when business is resumed till</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p><p >A New Book, entitled “The World's Pharos,” containing the “Emigrant's Assistant,” full Lists of Prices, and directions for self-measurement, may be had on application, or post free to any part of the kingdom.</p><p >E. MOSES &amp; SON, <lb/> MERCHANT TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, <lb/> AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p22a"/><head >HEAL &amp; SON'S EIDER DOWN QUILT,</head><p >The most luxurious Covering for the Bed, the Couch, or the Carriage.</p><p >PRICED LIST SENT POST-FREE.</p><p >The Catalogue contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, Mahogany, Rosewood, &amp; Walnut Tree Woods.</p><p >HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS <lb/> AND <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING, <lb/> SENT FREE BY POST FROM THEIR <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTORY, <lb/> 196, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</p><closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS</closer></div></back></text></TEI>