<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. X:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name><name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name><name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name><name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Harris Henderson, and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.  120K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_pageThe Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. X</title><author>Boz</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>Phiz</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>     40 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LondonChapman &amp; Hall, 186, Strand</publisher><date>1836</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number Dickens 13 pt. 10 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-12-03"> Jill Kuhn Sexton finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-27">Harris Henderson finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><titlePage><titlePart type="main"> No. X.]</titlePart><docEdition>[PRICE  1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PICKWICK CLUB <lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE <lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES <lb/> AND <lb/> Sporting Transactions <lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS. </titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor>
EDITED BY “BOZ.”
</docAuthor><docEdition>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVI</docDate>
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><head >Popular Works just published.</head><div type="section"><opener >Cloth, gilt edges, price 6<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> silk, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> or morocco, elegant, 8<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener><head >THE SENTIMENT OF FLOWERS,</head><p >  With Twelve Groups of Flowers, tastefully designed and coloured.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Second Edition.</hi></p><p >“A charming little book. With a dozen of sweet floral coloured plates, it is precisely the thing for fair lady's boudoir.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“One of the prettiest little books we have seen. It contains a neatly-told biography, if we may use the term, of each flower—all the graceful anecdotes connected with them, and some very beautiful and appropriate poetical quotations,”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p></div><div><p ><gap extent="several paragraphs" reason="book plate pasted over"/></p></div><div type="section"><opener >CURIOUS AND USEFUL LITTLE WORK.</opener><head >SHARPE'S DIAMOND DICTIONARY OF THE ENGLISH LANGUAGE, <lb/> WITH FORTY-FIVE DECORATIONS FROM THE WORKS OF SHAKESPEARE.</head><p >Containing every important word in the Language; in a volume of the smallest size, executed in a style of clearness and beauty perfectly unrivalled. Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> bound in cloth, gilt edges; 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> silk or embossed roan; 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >TILT'S SPLENDIDLY ILLUSTRATED EDITION.</opener><head >THE LAY OF THE LAST MINSTREL.</head><p >BY SIR WALTER SCOTT, BART.</p><p >Beautifully printed, and illustrated with Thirteen Line Engravings by eminent Artists. In a handsome foolscap 8vo volume, price 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> neatly bound in cloth, or 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> handsomely bound in morocco.</p><closer >CHARLES TILT, FLEET STREET.</closer></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill1"><p><hi rend="italics">page 296</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill2"><p><hi rend="italics">page 301</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pv"/><head >ADDRESS.</head><p >TEN months have now elapsed since the appearance of the first number of the PICKWICK PAPERS. At the close of the year, and the conclusion of half his task, their Author may perhaps, without any unwarrantable intrusion on the notice of the Public, venture to say a few words for himself.</p><p >He has long been desirous to embrace the first opportunity of announcing that it is his intention to adhere to his original pledge of confining this work to twenty numbers. He has every temptation to exceed the limits he first assigned to himself, that brilliant success, an enormous and increasing sale, the kindest notice, and the most extensive popularity, can hold out. They are, one and all, sad temptations to an author, but he has determined to resist them; firstly, because he wishes to keep the strictest faith with his readers; and, secondly, because he is most anxious that when the POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB form a complete work, the book may not have to contend against the heavy disadvantage of being prolonged beyond his original plan.</p><p >For ten months longer, then, if the Author be permitted to retain his health and spirits, the PICKWICK PAPERS will be issued in their present form, and will then be completed. By what fresh adventures they may be succeeded is no matter for present consideration. The Author merely hints that he has strong reason to believe that a great variety of other documents still lie hidden in the repository from which these were taken, and that they may one day see the light.</p><p >With this short speech, Mr. Pickwick's Stage-Manager makes his most grateful bow, adding, on behalf of himself and publishers, what the late eminent Mr. John Richardson, of Horsemonger Lane Southwark, and the Yellow Caravan with the Brass Knocker, always said on behalf of himself and company, at the close of every performance—</p><p >“Ladies and gentlemen, for these marks of your favour, we beg to return you our sincere thanks; and allow us to inform you, that we shall keep perpetually going on beginning again, regularly, until the end of the fair.”</p><closer >
<dateline>December 1836.</dateline>
</closer></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="text"><pb  xml:id="p275"/><head >[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXVII.</head><head >
SAMUEL WELLER MAKES A PILGRIMAGE TO DORKING, AND BEHOLDS HIS MOTHER-IN-LAW.
</head><p >THERE still remaining an interval of two days, before the time agreed upon, for the departure of the Pickwickians to Dingley Dell, Mr. Weller sat himself down in a back room at the George and Vulture, after eating an early dinner, to muse on the best way of disposing of his time. It was a remarkably fine day; and he had not turned the matter over in his mind ten minutes, when he was suddenly struck filial and affectionate; and it occurred to him so strongly that he ought to go down to see his father, and pay his duty to his mother-in-law, that he was lost in astonishment at his own remissness in never thinking of this moral obligation before. Anxious to atone for his past neglect without another hour's delay, he straightway walked up stairs to Mr. Pickwick, and requested leave of absence for this laudable purpose.</p><p >“Certainly, Sam, certainly,” said Mr. Pickwick, his eyes glistening with delight at this manifestation of good feeling, on the part of his attendant; “certainly, Sam.”</p><p >Mr. Weller made a grateful bow.</p><p >“I am very glad to see that you have so high a sense of your duties as a son, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“I always had, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller.</p><p >“That's a very gratifying reflection, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, approvingly.</p><p >“Wery, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller; “if ever I vanted anythin' o' my father, I always asked for it in a wery 'spectful and obligin' manner. If he didn't give it me, I took it, for fear I should be led to do anythin' wrong, through not havin' it. I saved him a world o' trouble this vay, Sir.”</p><p >“That's not precisely what I meant, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, shaking his head, with a slight smile.</p><p >“All good feelin', Sir—the wery best intentions, as the gen'lm 'n said ven he run away from his wife, 'cos she seemed unhappy with him,” replied Mr. Weller.</p><p >“You may go, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Thank'ee, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller; and having made his best bow, and put on his best clothes, Sam planted himself on the top of the Arundel coach, and journeyed on to Dorking.</p><p >The Marquis of Granby, in Mrs. Weller's time, was quite a model of a road-side public-house of the better class—just large enough to be convenient, and small enough to be snug. On the opposite side of the road was a large sign-board on a high post, representing the head and shoulders of a gentleman with an apoplectic countenance, in a red coat, with deep blue facings, and a touch of the same over his three-cornered
<pb xml:id="p276"/>
hat, for a sky. Over that again, were a pair of flags, and beneath the last button of his coat were a couple of cannon; and the whole formed an expressive and undoubted likeness of the Marquis of Granby of glorious memory. The bar window displayed a choice collection of geranium plants, and a well-dusted row of spirit phials. The open shutters bore a variety of golden inscriptions, eulogistic of good beds and neat wines; and the choice group of countrymen and hostlers lounging about the stable-door and horse-trough, afforded presumptive proof of the excellent quality of the ale and spirits which were sold within. Sam Weller paused, when he dismounted from the coach, to note all these little indications of a thriving business, with the eye of an experienced traveller; and having done so, stepped in at once, highly satisfied with everything he had observed.</p><p >“Now, then,” said a shrill female voice, the instant Sam thrust in his head at the door, “what do you want, young man?”</p><p >Sam looked round in the direction whence the voice proceeded. It came from a rather stout lady of comfortable appearance, who was seated beside the fire-place in the bar, blowing the fire to make the kettle boil for tea. She was not alone, for on the other side of the fire-place, sitting bolt upright in a high-backed chair, was a man in thread-bare black clothes, with a back almost as long and stiff as that of the chair itself, who caught Sam's most particular and especial attention at once.</p><p >He was a prim-faced, red-nosed man, with a long thin countenance and a semi-rattlesnake sort of eye—rather sharp, but decidedly bad. He wore very short trousers, and black-cotton stockings, which, like the rest of his apparel, were particularly rusty. His looks were starched, but his white neckerchief was not; and its long limp ends straggled over his closely-buttoned waistcoat in a very uncouth and unpicturesque fashion. A pair of old, worn, beaver gloves, a broad-brimmed hat, and a faded green umbrella, with plenty of whalebone sticking through the bottom, as if to counterbalance the want of a handle at the top, lay on a chair beside him; and being disposed in a very tidy and careful manner, seemed to imply that the red-nosed man, whoever he was, had no intention of going away in a hurry.</p><p >To do the red-nosed man justice, he would have been very far from wise if he had entertained any such intention, for, to judge from all appearances, he must have been possessed of a most desirable circle of acquaintance, if he could have reasonably expected to be more comfortable anywhere else. The fire was blazing brightly, under the influence of the bellows, and the kettle was singing gaily, under the influence of both. A small tray of tea-things was arranged on the table; a plate of hot buttered toast was gently simmering before the fire; and the red-nosed man himself was busily engaged in converting a large slice of bread, into the same agreeable edible, through the instrumentality of a long brass toasting-fork.   Beside him, stood a glass of reeking hot pine-apple rum and water, with a slice of lemon in it: and every time the red-nosed man stopped to bring the round of bread to his eye, with the view of ascertaining how it got on, he imbibed a drop or two of the hot pine-apple rum and water, and smiled upon the rather stout lady, as she blew the fire.</p><pb  xml:id="p277"/><p >Sam was so lost in the contemplation of this comfortable scene, that he suffered the first inquiry of the rather stout lady to pass wholly unheeded. It was not until it had been twice repeated, each time in a shriller tone, that he became conscious of the impropriety of his behaviour.</p><p >“Governor in?” inquired Sam, in reply to the question.</p><p >“No, he isn't,” replied Mrs. Weller, for the rather stout lady was no other than the quondam relict and sole executrix of the dead-and-gone Mr. Clarke;—“No, he isn't, and I don't expect him, either.”</p><p >“I suppose he's a drivin' up to-day?” said Sam.</p><p >“He may be, or he may not,” replied Mrs. Weller, buttering the round of toast which the red-nosed man had just finished, “I don't know, and, what's more, I don't care. Ask a blessin', Mr. Stiggins.”</p><p >The red-nosed man did as he was desired, and instantly commenced on the toast with fierce voracity.</p><p >The appearance of the red-nosed man had induced Sam, at first sight, to more than half suspect that he was the deputy shepherd, of whom his estimable parent had spoken. The moment he saw him eat, all doubt on the subject was removed, and he perceived at once that if he proposed to take up his temporary quarters where he was, he must make his footing good without delay. He therefore commenced proceedings by putting his arm over the half-door of the bar, coolly unbolting it, and leisurely walking in.</p><p >“Mother-in-law,” said Sam, “how are you?”</p><p >“Why, I do believe he is a Weller,” said Mrs. W., raising her eyes to Sam's face, with no very gratified expression of countenance.</p><p >“I rayther think he is,” said the imperturbable Sam; “and I hope this here reverend gen'lm'n 'll excuse me saying that I wish I was <hi rend="italics">the</hi> Weller as owns you, mother-in-law.”</p><p >This was a double-barrelled compliment: it implied that Mrs. Weller was a most agreeable female, and also that Mr. Stiggins had a clerical appearance. It made a visible impression at once; and Sam followed up his advantage by kissing his mother-in-law.</p><p >“Get along with you,” said Mrs. Weller, pushing him away.</p><p >“For shame, young man,” said the gentleman with the red nose.</p><p >“No offence, Sir, no offence,” replied Sam; “you're wery right, though; it ain't the right sort o' thing, ven mothers-in-law is young and good looking, is it, Sir?”</p><p >“It's all vanity,” said Mr. Stiggins.</p><p >“Ah, so it is,” said Mrs. Weller, setting her cap to rights.</p><p >Sam thought it was, too, but he held his peace.</p><p >The deputy shepherd seemed by no means best pleased with Sam's arrival; and when the first effervescence of the compliment had subsided, even Mrs. Weller looked as if she could have spared him without the smallest inconvenience. However, there he was; and as he couldn't be decently turned out, they all three sat down to tea.</p><p >“And how's father?” said Sam.</p><p >At this inquiry, Mrs. Weller raised her hands, and turned up her eyes, as if the subject were too painful to be alluded to.</p><pb  xml:id="p278"/><p >Mr. Stiggins groaned.</p><p >“What's the matter with that 'ere gen'lm'n?” inquired Sam.</p><p >“He's shocked at the way your father goes on, in—” replied Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“Oh, he is, is he?” said Sam.</p><p >“And with too good reason,” added Mrs. Weller, gravely.</p><p >Mr. Stiggins took up a fresh piece of toast, and groaned heavily.</p><p >“He is a dreadful reprobate,” said Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“A man of wrath!” exclaimed Mr. Stiggins. And he took a large semi-circular bite out of the toast, and groaned again.</p><p >Sam felt very strongly disposed to give the reverend Mr. Stiggins something to groan for, but he repressed his inclination, and merely asked, “What's the old 'un up to, now?”</p><p >“Up to, indeed!” said Mrs. Weller, “oh, he has a hard heart. Night after night does this excellent man—don't frown, Mr. Stiggins, I will say you <hi rend="italics">are</hi> an excellent man—come and sit here, for hours together, and it has not the least effect upon him.”</p><p >“Well, that is odd,” said Sam; “it 'ud have a wery considerable effect upon me, if I wos in his place, I know  that.”</p><p >“The fact is, my young friend,” said Mr. Stiggins, solemnly, “he has an obderrate bosom. Oh, my young friend, who else could have resisted the pleading of sixteen of our fairest sisters, and withstood their exhortations to subscribe to our noble society for providing the infant negroes in the West Indies with flannel waistcoats and moral pocket handkerchiefs?”</p><p >“What's a moral pocket ankercher?” said Sam; “I never see one o' them articles o' furniter.”</p><p >“Those which combine amusement with instruction, my young friend,” replied Mr. Stiggins, “blending select tales with wood-cuts.”</p><p >“Oh, I know,” said Sam, “them as hangs up in the linen-drapers' shops, with beggars' petitions and all that 'ere upon 'em?”</p><p >Mr. Stiggins began a third round of toast, and nodded assent.</p><p >“And he wouldn't be persuaded by the ladies, wouldn't he?” said Sam.</p><p >“Sat and smoked his pipe, and said the infant negroes were—what did he say the infant negroes were?” said Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“Little humbugs,” replied Mr. Stiggins, deeply affected.</p><p >“Said the infant negroes were little humbugs,” repeated Mrs. Weller. And they both groaned at the atrocious conduct of the elder Mr. Samuel.</p><p >A great many more iniquities of a similar nature might have been disclosed, only the toast being all eat, the tea having got very weak, and Sam holding out no indications of meaning to go, Mr. Stiggins suddenly recollected that he had a most pressing appointment with the shepherd, and took himself off accordingly.</p><p >The tea-things had been scarcely put away, and the hearth swept up, when the London coach deposited Mr. Weller senior at the door, his legs deposited him in the bar, and his eyes shewed him his son.</p><p >“What, Sammy!” exclaimed the father.</p><pb  xml:id="p279"/><p >“What, old Nobs!” ejaculated the son. And they shook hands heartily.</p><p >“Wery glad to see you, Sammy,” said the elder Mr. Weller, “though how you've managed to get over your mother-in-law, is a mystery to me. I only vish you'd write me out the receipt, that's all.”</p><p >“Hush!” said Sam, “she's at home, old feller.”</p><p >“She ain't vithin hearin',” replied Mr. Weller; “she always goes and blows up, down stairs, for a couple of hours arter tea; so we'll just give ourselves a damp, Sammy.”</p><p >Saying this, Mr. Weller mixed two glasses of spirits and water, and produced a couple of pipes; and the father and son sitting down opposite each other, Sam on one side the fire, in the high-backed chair, and Mr. Weller senior on the other, in an easy ditto, they proceeded to enjoy themselves with all due gravity.</p><p >“Anybody been here, Sammy?” asked Mr. Weller senior, drily, after a long silence.</p><p >Sam nodded an expressive assent.</p><p >“Red-nosed chap?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >Sam nodded again.</p><p >“Amiable man that 'ere, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller, smoking violently.</p><p >“Seems so,” observed Sam.</p><p >“Good hand at accounts,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Is he?” said Sam.</p><p >“Borrows eighteenpence on Monday, and comes on Tuesday for a shillin' to make it up half a crown; calls again on Vensday for another half crown to make it five shillin's, and goes on, doubling, till he gets it up to a five pund note in no time, like them sums in the 'rithmetic book 'bout the nails in the horse's shoes, Sammy.”</p><p >Sam intimated by a nod that he recollected the problem alluded to by his parent.</p><p >“So you vouldn't subscribe to the flannel veskits?” said Sam, after another interval of smoking.</p><p >“Cert'nly not,” replied Mr. Weller; “what's the good o' flannel veskits to the young niggers abroad? But I'll tell you what it is, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller, lowering his voice, and bending across the fire-place, “I'd come down wery handsome towards straight veskits for some people at home.”</p><p >As Mr. Weller said this, he slowly recovered his former position, and winked at his first-born, in a profound manner.</p><p >“It cert'nly seems a queer start to send out pocket ankechers to people as don't know the use on 'em,” observed Sam.</p><p >“They're alvays a doin' some gammon of that sort, Sammy,” replied his father. “T'other Sunday I vas walkin' up the road, ven who should I see a standin at a chapel-door, with a blue soup-plate in her hand, but your mother-in-law. I werily believe there was change for a couple o' suv'rins in it, then, Sammy, all in ha'pence; and as the people come out, they rattled the pennies in, till you'd ha' thought that no
<pb xml:id="p280"/>
mortal plate as ever was baked, could ha' stood the wear and tear. What d'ye think it was all for?”</p><p >“For another tea-drinkin', perhaps,” said Sam.</p><p >“Not a bit on it,” replied the father; “for the shepherd's water-rate, Sammy.”</p><p >“The shepherd's water-rate!” said Sam.</p><p >“Ay,” replied Mr. Weller, “there was three quarters owin', and the shepherd hadn't paid a farden, not he—perhaps it might be on account that the water warn't o' much use to him, for it's wery little o' that tap he drinks, Sammy, wery; he knows a trick worth a good half dozen of that, he does. Hows'ever, it warn't paid, and so they cuts the water off. Down goes the shepherd to chapel, gives out as he's a persecuted saint, and says he hopes the heart of the turncock as cut the water off, 'll be softened, and turned in the right vay, but he rayther thinks he's booked for somethin' uncomfortable. Upon this, the women calls a meetin', sings a hymn, wotes your mother-in-law into the chair, wolunteers a col-lection next Sunday, and hands it all over to the shepherd. And if he ain't got enough out on 'em, Sammy, to make him free of the water company for life,” said Mr. Weller, in conclusion, “I'm one Dutchman, and you're another, and that's all about it.”</p><p >Mr. Weller smoked for some minutes in silence, and then resumed—</p><p >“The worst o' these here shepherds is, my boy, that they reg'larly turns the heads of all the young ladies, about here. Lord bless their little hearts, they thinks it's all right, and don't know no better; but they're the wictims o' gammon, Samivel, they're the wictims o' gammon.”</p><p >“I s'pose they are,” said Sam.</p><p >“Nothin' else,” said Mr. Weller, shaking his head gravely; “and wot aggrawates me, Samivel, is to see 'em a wastin' all their time and labour in making clothes for copper-coloured people as don't want 'em, and taking no notice of the flesh-coloured Christians as do. If I'd my vay, Samivel, I'd just stick some o' these here lazy shepherds behind a heavy wheelbarrow, and run 'em up and down a fourteen-inch-wide plank all day. That 'ud shake the nonsense out of 'em, if anythin' vould.”</p><p >Mr. Weller having delivered this gentle recipe with strong emphasis, eked out by a variety of nods and contortions of the eye, emptied his glass at a draught, and knocked the ashes out of his pipe, with native dignity.</p><p >He was engaged in this operation, when a shrill voice was heard in the passage.</p><p >“Here's your dear relation, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller; and Mrs. W. hurried into the room.</p><p >“Oh, you've come back, have you!” said Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“Yes, my dear,” replied Mr. Weller filling a fresh pipe.</p><p >“Has Mr. Stiggins been back?” said Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“No, my dear, he hasn't,” replied Mr. Weller, lighting the pipe by the ingenious process of holding to the bowl thereof, between the tongs, a red-hot coal from the adjacent fire; “and what's more, my dear, I shall manage to surwive it, if he don't come back at all.”</p><pb  xml:id="p281"/><p >“Ugh, you wretch,” said Mrs. Weller.</p><p >“Thank'ee, my love,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Come, come, father,” said Sam, “none o' these little lovin's afore strangers. Here's the reverend gen'lm'n a comin' in now.”</p><p >At this announcement, Mrs. Weller hastily wiped off the tears which she had just begun to force on; and Mr. W. drew his chair sullenly into the chimney corner.</p><p >Mr. Stiggins was easily prevailed on, to take another glass of the hot pine-apple rum and water, and a second, and a third, and then to refresh himself with a slight supper, previous to beginning again. He sat on the same side as Mr. Weller senior; and every time he could contrive to do so, unseen by his wife, that gentleman indicated to his son the hidden emotions of his bosom, by shaking his fist over the deputy shepherd's head, a process which afforded his son the most unmingled delight and satisfaction, the more especially as Mr. Stiggins went on, quietly drinking the hot pine-apple rum and water, wholly unconscious of what was going forward.</p><p >The major part of the conversation was confined to Mrs. Weller and the reverend Mr. Stiggins; and the topics principally descanted on, were the virtues of the shepherd, the worthiness of his flock, and the high crimes and misdemeanours of everybody beside—dissertations which the elder Mr. Weller occasionally interrupted by half suppressed references to a gentleman of the name of Walker, and other running commentaries of the same kind.</p><p >At length Mr. Stiggins, with several most indubitable symptoms of having quite as much pine-apple rum and water about him, as he could comfortably accommodate, took his hat and his leave: and Sam was, immediately afterwards, shewn to bed by his father. The respectable old gentleman wrung his hand fervently, and seemed disposed to address some observations to his son, but on Mrs. Weller advancing towards him, he appeared to relinquish his intention, and abruptly bade him good night.</p><p >Sam was up betimes next day, and having partaken of a hasty breakfast, prepared to return to London. He had scarcely set foot without the house, when his father stood before him.</p><p >“Goin', Sammy?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Off at once,” replied Sam.</p><p >“I vish you could muffle that 'ere Stiggins, and take him with you,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“I am ashamed o' you, old two-for-his-heels,” said Sam, reproachfully, “what do you let him shew his red nose in the Markis o' Granby at all, for?”</p><p >Mr. Weller the elder fixed on his son an earnest look, and replied—</p><p >Cause I'm a married man, Samivel, 'cause I'm a married man. Ven you're a married man, Samivel, you'll understand a good many things as you don't understand now; but vether it's worth while goin' through so much, to learn so little, as the charity-boy said ven he got to the end of the alphabet, is a matter o' taste. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> rayther think it isn't.”</p><pb  xml:id="p282"/><p >“Well,” said Sam, “good bye.”</p><p >“Tar, tar, Sammy,” replied his father.</p><p >“I've only got to say this here,” said Sam, stopping short, “that if <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was the properiator o' the Markis o' Granby, and that 'ere Stiggins came and made toast in <hi rend="italics">my</hi> bar, I'd—”</p><p >“What?” interposed Mr. Weller, with great anxiety. “What?”</p><p >“—Pison his rum and water,” said Sam.</p><p >“No!” said Mr. Weller, shaking his son eagerly by the hand, “would you raly, Sammy—would you, though?”</p><p >“I would,” said Sam. “I wouldn't be too hard upon him, at first: I'd just drop him in the water-butt, and put the lid on; and then if I found he was insensible to kindness, I'd try the other persvasion.”</p><p >The elder Mr. Weller bestowed a look of deep, unspeakable admiration on his son, and, having once more grasped his hand, walked slowly away, revolving in his mind the numerous reflections to which his advice had given rise.</p><p >Sam looked after him, till he turned a corner of the road, and then set forward on his walk to London. He meditated at first on the probable consequences of his own advice, and the likelihood and unlikelihood of his father's adopting it. He dismissed the subject from his mind, however, with the consolatory reflection that time alone would shew; and this is just the reflection we would impress upon the reader.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXVIII.</head><head >
A GOOD-HUMOURED CHRISTMAS CHAPTER, CONTAINING AN ACCOUNT OF A WEDDING, AND SOME OTHER SPORTS BESIDE, WHICH ALTHOUGH IN THEIR WAY, EVEN AS GOOD CUSTOMS AS MARRIAGE ITSELF, ARE NOT QUITE SO RELIGIOUSLY KEPT UP, IN THESE DEGENERATE TIMES.
</head><p >As brisk as bees, if not altogether as light as fairies, did the four Pickwickians assemble on the morning of the twenty-second day of December, in the year of grace in which these, their faithfully-recorded adventures, were undertaken and accomplished. Christmas was close at hand, in all his bluff and hearty honesty; it was the season of hospitality, merriment, and open-heartedness; the old year was preparing, like an ancient philosopher, to call his friends around him, and amidst the sound of feasting and revelry to pass gently and calmly away. Gay and merry was the time; and right gay and merry were at least four of the numerous hearts that were gladdened by its coming.</p><p >And numerous indeed are the hearts to which Christmas brings a brief season of happiness and enjoyment. How many families whose members have been dispersed and scattered far and wide, in the restless struggles of life, are then re-united, and meet once again in that happy state of companionship and mutual good-will, which is a source of such pure and unalloyed delight, and one so incompatible with the cares and
<pb xml:id="p283"/>
sorrows of the world, that the religious belief of the most civilised nations, and the rude traditions of the roughest savages, alike number it among the first joys of a future state of existence, provided for the blest and happy! How many old recollections, and how many dormant sympathies, does Christmas time awaken!</p><p >We write these words now, many miles distant from the spot at which, year after year, we met on that day, a merry and joyous circle. Many of the hearts that throbbed so gaily then, have ceased to beat; many of the looks that shone so brightly then, have ceased to glow; the hands we grasped, have grown cold; the eyes we sought, have hid their lustre in the grave; and yet the old house, the room, the merry voices and smiling faces, the jest, the laugh, the most minute and trivial circumstance connected with those happy meetings, crowd upon our mind at each recurrence of the season, as if the last assemblage had been but yesterday. Happy, happy Christmas, that can win us back to the delusions of our childish days, that can recal to the old man the pleasures of his youth, and transport the sailor and the traveller, thousands of miles away, back to his own fire-side and his quiet home!</p><p >But we are so taken up, and occupied, with the good qualities of Christmas, who, by the way, is quite a country gentleman of the old school, that we are keeping Mr. Pickwick and his friends waiting in the cold, on the outside of the Muggleton coach, which they have just attained, well wrapped up, in great coats, shawls, and comforters. The portmanteaus and carpet-bags have been stowed away, and Mr. Weller and the guard are endeavouring to insinuate into the fore-boot a huge cod-fish several sizes too large for it, which is snugly packed up, in a long brown basket, with a layer of straw over the top, and which has been left to the last, in order that he may repose in safety on the half-dozen barrels of real native oysters, all the property of Mr. Pickwick, which have been arranged in regular order, at the bottom of the receptacle. The interest displayed in Mr. Pickwick's countenance is most intense, as Mr. Weller and the guard try to squeeze the cod-fish into the boot, first head first, and then tail first, and then top upwards, and then bottom upwards, and then side-ways, and then long-ways, all of which artifices the implacable cod-fish sturdily resists, until the guard accidentally hits him in the very middle of the basket, whereupon he suddenly disappears into the boot, and with him, the head and shoulders of the guard himself, who, not calculating upon so sudden a cessation of the passive resistance of the cod-fish, experiences a very unexpected shock, to the unsmotherable delight of all the porters and by-standers. Upon this, Mr. Pickwick smiles with great good humour, and drawing a shilling from his waistcoat pocket, begs the guard, as he picks himself out of the boot, to drink his health in a glass of hot brandy and water, at which, the guard smiles too, and Messrs. Snodgrass, Winkle, and Tupman, all smile in company. The guard and Mr. Weller disappear for five minutes, most probably to get the hot brandy and water, for they smell very strongly of it, when they return, the coachman mounts to the box, Mr. Weller jumps up behind, the Pickwickians pull their coats round their legs, and their shawls over their noses; the helpers
<pb xml:id="p284"/>
pull the horse-cloths off, the coachman shouts out a cheery “All right,” and away they go.</p><p >They have rumbled through the streets, and jolted over the stones, and at length reach the wide and open country. The wheels skim over the hard and frosty ground; and the horses, bursting into a canter at a smart crack of the whip, step along the road as if the load behind them, coach, passengers, cod-fish, oyster barrels, and all, were but a feather at their heels. They have descended a gentle slope, and enter upon a level, as compact and dry as a solid block of marble, two miles long. Another crack of the whip, and on they speed, at a smart gallop, the horses tossing their heads and rattling the harness as if in exhilaration at the rapidity of the motion, while the coachman holding whip and reins in one hand, takes off his hat with the other, and resting it on his knees, pulls out his handkerchief, and wipes his forehead, partly because he has a habit of doing it, and partly because it's as well to shew the passengers how cool he is, and what an easy thing it is to drive four-in-hand, when you have had as much practice as he has. Having done this very leisurely (otherwise the effect would be materially impaired), he replaces his handkerchief, pulls on his hat, adjusts his gloves, squares his elbows, cracks the whip again, and on they speed, more merrily than before.</p><p >A few small houses scattered on either side of the road, betoken the entrance to some town or village. The lively notes of the guard's key bugle vibrate in the clear cold air, and wake up the old gentleman inside, who carefully letting down the window-sash half way, and standing sentry over the air, takes a short peep out, and then carefully pulling it up again, informs the other inside that they're going to change directly; on which the other inside wakes himself up, and determines to postpone his next nap until after the stoppage. Again the bugle sounds lustily forth, and rouses the cottager's wife and children, who peep out at the house-door, and watch the coach till it turns the corner, when they once more crouch round the blazing fire, and throw on another log of wood against father comes home, while father himself, a full mile off, has just exchanged a friendly nod with the coachman, and turned round, to take a good long stare at the vehicle as it whirls away.</p><p >And now the bugle plays a lively air as the coach rattles through the ill-paved streets of a country town; and the coachman, undoing the buckle which keeps his ribands together, prepares to throw them off the moment he stops. Mr. Pickwick emerges from his coat collar, and looks about him with great curiosity; perceiving which, the coachman informs Mr. Pickwick of the name of the town, and tells him it was market-day yesterday, both which pieces of information Mr. Pickwick retails to his fellow-passengers, whereupon they emerge from their coat collars too, and look about them also. Mr. Winkle, who sits at the extreme edge, with one leg dangling in the air, is nearly precipitated into the street, as the coach twists round the sharp corner by the cheesemonger's shop, and turns into the market-place; and before Mr. Snodgrass, who sits next to him, has recovered from his alarm, they pull up at the inn yard, where the fresh horses, with cloths on, are already
<pb xml:id="p285"/>
waiting. The coachman throws down the reins and gets down himself, and the other outside passengers drop down also, except those who have no great confidence in their ability to get up again, and they remain where they are, and stamp their feet against the coach to warm them; looking with longing eyes and red noses at the bright fire in the inn bar, and the sprigs of holly with red berries which ornament the window.</p><p >But the guard has delivered at the corn-dealer's shop, the brown paper packet he took out of the little pouch which hangs over his shoulder by a leathern strap, and has seen the horses carefully put to, and has thrown on the pavement the saddle which was brought from London on the coach-roof, and has assisted in the conference between the coachman and the hostler about the grey mare that hurt her off-fore-leg last Tuesday, and he and Mr. Weller are all right behind, and the coachman is all right in front, and the old gentleman inside, who has kept the window down full two inches all this time, has pulled it up again, and the cloths are off, and they are all ready for starting, except the “two stout gentlemen,” whom the coachman enquires after with some impatience. Hereupon the coachman, and the guard, and Sam Weller, and Mr. Winkle, and Mr. Snodgrass, and all the hostlers, and every one of the idlers, who are more in number than all the others put together, shout for the missing gentlemen as loud as they can bawl. A distant response is heard from the yard, and Mr. Pickwick and Mr. Tupman come running down it, quite out of breath, for they have been having a glass of ale a-piece, and Mr. Pickwick's fingers are so cold that he has been full five minutes before he could find the sixpence to pay for it. The coachman shouts an admonitory “Now, then, gen'lm'n,” the guard re-choes it—the old gentleman inside, thinks it a very extraordinary thing that people <hi rend="italics">will</hi> get down when they know there isn't time for it—Mr. Pickwick struggles up on one side, Mr. Tupman on the other, Mr. Winkle cries “All right,” and off they start. Shawls are pulled up, coat collars are re-adjusted, the pavement ceases, the houses disappear; and they are once again dashing along the open road, with the fresh clear air blowing in their faces, and gladdening their very hearts within them.</p><p >Such was the progress of Mr. Pickwick and his friends by the Muggleton Telegraph, on their way to Dingley Dell; and at three o'clock that afternoon, they all stood, high and dry, safe and sound, hale and hearty, upon the steps of the Blue Lion, having taken on the road quite enough of ale and brandy, to enable them to bid defiance to the frost that was binding up the earth in its iron fetters, and weaving its beautiful net-work upon the trees and hedges. Mr. Pickwick was busily engaged in counting the barrels of oysters, and superintending the disinterment of the cod-fish, when he felt himself gently pulled by the skirts of the coat; and looking round, he discovered that the individual who resorted to this mode of catching his attention, was no other than Mr. Wardle's favourite page, better known to the readers of this unvarnished history by the distinguishing appellation of the fat boy.</p><p >“Aha!” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Aha!” said the fat boy.</p><pb  xml:id="p286"/><p >And as he said it, he glanced from the cod-fish to the oyster-barrels, and chuckled joyously. He was fatter than ever.</p><p >“Well, you look rosy enough, my young friend,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“I've been asleep, right in front of the tap-room fire,” replied the fat boy, who had heated himself to the colour of a new chimney-pot, in the course of an hour's nap. “Master sent me over with the chay-cart, to carry your luggage up to the house. He'd ha' sent some saddle horses, but he thought you'd rather walk, being a cold day.”</p><p >“Yes, yes,” said Mr. Pickwick, hastily, for he remembered how they had travelled over nearly the same ground on a previous occasion. “Yes, we would rather walk. Here, Sam.”</p><p >“Sir,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Help Mr. Wardle's servant to put the packages into the cart, and then ride on with him. We will walk forward at once.”</p><p >Having given this direction, and settled with the coachman, Mr. Pickwick and his three friends struck into the footpath across the fields, and walked briskly away, leaving Mr. Weller and the fat boy confronted together for the first time. Sam looked at the fat boy with great astonishment, but without saying a word; and began to stow the things rapidly away in the cart, while the fat boy stood quietly by, and seemed to think it a very interesting sort of thing to see Mr. Weller working by himself.</p><p >“There,” said Sam, throwing in the last carpet bag. “There they are.”</p><p >“Yes,” said the fat boy, in a very satisfied tone, “there they are.”</p><p >“Vell, young twenty stun,” said Sam, “you're a nice specimen of a prize boy, you are.”</p><p >“Thankee,” said the fat boy.</p><p >“You ain't got nothin' on your mind, as makes you fret yourself, have you?” inquired Sam.</p><p >“Not as I knows on,” replied the boy.</p><p >“I should rayther ha' thought, to look at you, that you was a labourin' under an unrequited attachment to some young 'ooman,” said Sam.</p><p >The fat boy shook his head.</p><p >“Vell,” said Sam, “I'm glad to hear it. Do you ever drink anythin'?”</p><p >“I likes eating, better,” replied the boy.</p><p >“Ah,” said Sam, “I should ha' s'posed that; but what I mean is, should you like a drop of anythin' as'd warm you? but I s'pose you never was cold, with all them elastic fixtures, was you?”</p><p >“Sometimes,” replied the boy; “and I likes a drop of something, when it's good.”</p><p >“Oh, you do, do you?” said Sam, “come this vay, then.”</p><p >The Blue Lion tap was soon gained, and the fat boy swallowed a glass of liquor without so much as winking,—a feat which considerably advanced him in Mr. Weller's good opinion. Mr. Weller having transacted a similar piece of business on his own account, they got into the cart.</p><p >“Can you drive?” said the fat boy.</p><pb  xml:id="p287"/><p >“I should rayther think so,” replied Sam.</p><p >“There, then,” said the fat boy, putting the reins in his hand, and pointing up a lane, “It's as straight as you can go; you can't miss it.”</p><p >With these words, the fat boy laid himself affectionately down by the side of the cod-fish, and placing an oyster-barrel under his head for a pillow, fell asleep instantaneously.</p><p >“Vell,” said Sam, “of all the cool boys ever I set my eyes on, this here young gen'lm'n is about the coolest. Come, vake up, young dropsy.”</p><p >But as young dropsy evinced no symptoms of returning animation, Sam Weller sat himself down in front of the cart, and starting the old horse with a jerk of the rein, jogged steadily on, towards Manor Farm.</p><p >Meanwhile, Mr. Pickwick and his friends having walked their blood into active circulation, proceeded cheerfully on; the paths were hard, the grass was crisp and frosty, the air had a fine, dry, bracing coldness, and the rapid approach of the grey twilight (slate-coloured is a better term in frosty weather) made them look forward with pleasant anticipation to the comforts which awaited them at their hospitable entertainer's. It was the sort of afternoon that might induce a couple of elderly gentlemen, in a lonely field, to take off their great coats and play at leap-frog in pure lightness of heart and gaiety; and we firmly believe that had Mr. Tupman at that moment proffered “a back,” Mr. Pickwick would have accepted his offer with the utmost avidity.</p><p >However, Mr. Tupman did not volunteer any such personal accommodation, and the friends walked on, conversing merrily. As they turned into a lane which they had to cross, the sound of many voices burst upon their ears; and before they had even had time to form a guess as to whom they belonged, they walked into the very centre of the party who were expecting their arrival—a fact which was first notified to the Pickwickians, by the loud “Hurrah,” which burst from old Wardle's lips, when they appeared in sight.</p><p >First, there was Wardle himself, looking, if that were possible, more jolly than ever; then there were Bella and her faithful Trundle; and, lastly, there were Emily and some eight or ten young ladies, who had all come down to the wedding which was to take place next day, and were in as happy and important a state as young ladies usually are, on such momentous occasions; and they were, one and all, startling the fields and lanes far and wide with their frolic and laughter.</p><p >The ceremony of introduction, under such circumstances, was very soon performed, or we should rather say that the introduction was soon over, without any ceremony at all; and in two minutes thereafter, Mr. Pickwick was joking with the young ladies who wouldn't come over the stile while he looked, or who, having pretty feet and unexceptionable ankles, preferred standing on the top-rail for five minutes or so, and declaring that they were too frightened to move, with as much ease and absence of reserve or constraint, as if he had known them for life. It is worthy of remark too, that Mr. Snodgrass offered Emily far more assistance than the absolute terrors of the stile (although it was full three feet high, and had only a couple of stepping-stones) would seem to
<pb xml:id="p288"/>
require; while one black-eyed young lady in a very nice little pair of boots with fur round the top, was observed to scream very loudly, when Mr Winkle offered to help her over.</p><p >All this was very snug and pleasant: and when the difficulties of the stile were at last surmounted, and they once more entered on the open field, old Wardle informed Mr. Pickwick how they had all been down in a body to inspect the furniture and fittings-up of the house, which the young couple were to tenant, after the Christmas holidays; at which communication Bella and Trundle both coloured up, as red as the fat boy after the tap-room fire; and the young lady with the black eyes and the fur round the boots, whispered something in Emily's ear, and then glanced archly at Mr. Snodgrass, to which Emily responded that she was a foolish girl, but turned very red, notwithstanding; and Mr. Snodgrass, who was as modest as all great geniuses usually are, felt the crimson rising to the crown of his head, and devoutly wished, in the inmost recesses of his own heart, that the young lady aforesaid, with her black eyes, and her archness, and her boots with the fur round the top, were all comfortably deposited in the adjacent county.</p><p >But if they were social and happy, outside the house, what was the warmth and cordiality of their reception when they reached the farm! The very servants grinned with pleasure at sight of Mr. Pickwick: and Emma bestowed a half-demure, half-impudent, and all pretty look of recognition on Mr. Tupman, which was enough to make the statue of Bonaparte in the passage, unfold his arms, and clasp her within them.</p><p >The old lady was seated in customary state in the front parlour, but she was rather cross, and by consequence, most particularly deaf. She never went out herself, and like a great many other old ladies of the same stamp, she was apt to consider it an act of domestic treason, if any body else took the liberty of doing what she couldn't. So, bless her old soul, she sat as upright as she could, in her great chair, and looked as fierce as might be—and that was benevolent after all.</p><p >“Mother,” said Wardle, “Mr. Pickwick. You recollect him.”</p><p >“Never mind,” replied the old lady with great dignity. “Don't trouble Mr. Pickwick about an old creetur like me. Nobody cares about me now, and it's very nat'ral they shouldn't.” Here the old lady tossed her head, and smoothed down her lavender-coloured silk dress, with trembling hands.</p><p >“Come, come, Ma'am,” said Mr. Pickwick, “I can't let you cut an old friend in this way. I have come down expressly to have a long talk, and another rubber with you; and we'll show these boys and girls how to dance a minuet, before they're eight-and-forty hours older.”</p><p >The old lady was rapidly giving way, but she did not like to do it all at once; so she only said, “Ah! I can't hear him.”</p><p >“Nonsense, mother,” said Wardle. “Come, come, don't be cross, there's a good soul. Recollect Bella; come, you must keep her spirits up, poor girl.”</p><p >The good old lady heard this, for her lip quivered as her son said it. But age has its little infirmities of temper, and she was not quite brought round yet. So, she smoothed down the lavender-coloured
<pb xml:id="p289"/>
dress again, and turning to Mr. Pickwick said, “Ah, Mr. Pickwick, young people was very different, when I was a girl.”</p><p >“No doubt of that, Ma'am,” said Mr. Pickwick, “and that's the reason why I would make much of the few that have any traces of the old stock,”—and saying this, Mr. Pickwick gently pulled Bella towards him, and bestowing a kiss upon her forehead, bade her sit down on the little stool at her grandmother's feet. Whether the expression of her countenance, as it was raised towards the old lady's face, called up a thought of old times, or whether the old lady was touched by Mr. Pickwick's affectionate good nature, or whatever was the cause, she was fairly melted; so, she threw herself on her grand-daughter's neck, and all the little ill-humour evaporated in a gush of silent tears.</p><p >A happy party they were, that night. Sedate and solemn were the score of rubbers in which Mr. Pickwick and the old lady played together; and uproarious was the mirth of the round table. Long after the ladies had retired, did the hot elder wine, well qualified with brandy and spice, go round, and round, and round again; and sound was the sleep, and pleasant were the dreams that followed. It is a remarkable fact, that those of Mr. Snodgrass bore constant reference to Emily Wardle; and that the principal figure in Mr. Winkle's visions, was a young lady with black eyes, an arch smile, and a pair of remarkably nice boots, with fur round the tops.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick was awakened early in the morning, by a hum of voices and pattering of feet, sufficient to rouse even the fat boy from his heavy slumbers. He sat up in bed, and listened. The female servants and female visitors were running constantly to and fro; and there were such multitudinous demands for warm water, such repeated outcries for needles and thread, and so many half-suppressed entreaties of “Oh, do come and tie me, there's a dear,” that Mr. Pickwick in his innocence began to imagine that something dreadful must have occurred, when he grew more awake, and remembered the wedding. The occasion being an important one, he dressed himself with peculiar care, and descended to the breakfast room.</p><p >There were all the female servants in a bran new uniform of pink muslin gowns with white bows in their caps, running about the house in a state of excitement and agitation, which it would be impossible to describe. The old lady was dressed out, in a brocaded grown, which had not seen the light for twenty years, saving and excepting such truant rays as had stolen through the chinks in the box in which it had been laid by, during the whole time. Mr. Trundle was in high feather and spirits, but a little nervous withal. The hearty old landlord was trying to look very cheerful and unconcerned, but failing signally in the attempt. All the girls were in tears and white muslin, except a select two or three, who were being honoured with a private view of the bride and bridesmaids, up stairs. All the Pickwickians were in most blooming array; and there was a terrific roaring on the grass in front of the house, occasioned by all the men, boys, and hobbledehoys attached to the farm, each of whom had got a white bow in his button hole, and all of whom were cheering with might and main: being incited thereto,
<pb xml:id="p290"/>
and stimulated therein, by the precept and example of Mr. Samuel Weller, who had managed to become mighty popular already, and was as much at home as if he had been born on the land.</p><p >A wedding is a licensed subject to joke upon, but there really is no great joke in the matter after all; we speak merely of the ceremony, and beg it to be distinctly understood that we indulge in no hidden sarcasm upon a married life. Mixed up with the pleasure and joy of the occasion, are the many regrets at quitting home, the tears of parting between parent and child, the consciousness of leaving the dearest and kindest friends of the happiest portion of human life, to encounter its cares and troubles with others still untried, and little known—natural feelings which we would not render this chapter mournful by describing, and which we should be still more unwilling to be supposed to ridicule.</p><p >Let us briefly say, then, that the ceremony was performed by the old clergyman, in the parish church of Dingley Dell, and that Mr. Pickwick's name is attached to the register, still preserved in the vestry thereof; that the young lady with the black eyes signed her name in a very unsteady and tremulous manner; and that Emily's signature, as the other bridesmaid, is nearly illegible; that it all went off in very admirable style; that the young ladies generally, thought it far less shocking than they expected; and that although the owner of the black eyes and the arch smile informed Mr. Winkle that she was sure she could never submit to anything so dreadful, we have the very best reasons for thinking she was mistaken. To all this, we may add, that Mr. Pickwick was the first who saluted the bride: and that in so doing, he threw over her neck, a rich gold watch and chain, which no mortal eyes but the jeweller's had ever beheld before. Then the old church bell rang as gaily as it could, and they all returned to breakfast.</p><p >“Vere does the mince-pies go, young opium eater?” said Mr. Weller to the fat boy, as he assisted in laying out such articles of consumption as had not been duly arranged on the previous night.</p><p >The fat boy pointed to the destination of the pies.</p><p >“Wery good,” said Sam, “stick a bit o' Christmas in 'em. T'other dish opposite. There; now ve look compact and comfortable, as the father said ven he cut his little boy's head off, to cure him o' squintin'.”</p><p >As Mr. Weller made the comparison, he fell back a step or two, to give full effect to it, and surveyed the preparations with the utmost satisfaction.</p><p >“Wardle,” said Mr. Pickwick, almost as soon as they were all seated, “a glass of wine, in honour of this happy occasion!”</p><p >“I shall be delighted, my boy,” said Wardle. “Joe—damn that boy, he's gone to sleep.”</p><p >“No, I ain't, Sir,” replied the fat boy, starting up from a remote corner, where, like the patron saint of fat boys—the immortal Horner—he had been devouring a Christmas pie, though not with the coolness and deliberation which characterised that young gentleman's proceedings.</p><p >“Fill Mr. Pickwick's glass.”</p><p >“Yes, Sir.”</p><p >The fat boy filled Mr. Pickwick's glass, and then retired behind his
<pb xml:id="p291"/>
master's chair, from whence he watched the play of the knives and forks, and the progress of the choice morsels, from the dishes, to the mouths of the company, with a kind of dark and gloomy joy that was most impressive.</p><p >“God bless you, old fellow,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Same to you, my boy,” replied Wardle; and they pledged each other, heartily.</p><p >“Mrs. Wardle,” said Mr. Pickwick, “we old folks must have a glass of wine together, in honour of this joyful event.”</p><p >The old lady was in a state of great grandeur just then, for she was sitting at the top of the table in the brocaded gown, with her newly-married daughter on one side, and Mr. Pickwick on the other, to do the carving. Mr. Pickwick had not spoken in a very loud tone, but she understood him at once, and drank off a full glass of wine to his long life and happiness; after which the worthy old soul launched forth into a minute and particular account of her own wedding, with a dissertation on the fashion of wearing high-heeled shoes, and some particulars concerning the life and adventures of the beautiful Lady Tollimglower, deceased, at all of which the old lady herself laughed very heartily indeed, and so did the young ladies too, for they were wondering among themselves what on earth grandma was talking about. When they laughed, the old lady laughed ten times more heartily: and said that they always had been considered capital stories, which caused them all to laugh again, and put the old lady into the very best of humours. Then the cake was cut, and passed through the ring; and the young ladies saved pieces to put under their pillows to dream of their future husbands on; and a great deal of blushing and merriment was thereby occasioned.</p><p >“Mr. Miller,” said Mr. Pickwick to his old acquaintance, the hard-headed gentleman, “a glass of wine?”</p><p >“With great satisfaction Mr. Pickwick,” replied the hard-headed gentleman, solemnly.</p><p >“You'll take me in?” said the benevolent old clergyman.</p><p >“And me,” interposed his wife.</p><p >“And me, and me,” said a couple of poor relations at the bottom of the table, who had eaten and drank very heartily, and laughed at every thing.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick expressed his heartfelt delight at every additional suggestion; and his eyes beamed with hilarity and cheerfulness.</p><p >“Ladies and gentlemen,” said Mr. Pickwick, suddenly rising —</p><p >“Hear, hear! Hear, hear! Hear, hear!” said Mr. Weller, in the excitement of his feelings.</p><p >“Call in all the servants,” cried old Wardle, interposing to prevent the public rebuke which Mr. Weller would otherwise most indubitably have received from his master.</p><p >“Give them a glass of wine each, to drink the toast in. Now, Pickwick.”</p><p >Amidst the silence of the company, the whispering of the women servants, and the awkward embarrassment of the men, Mr. Pickwick proceeded.</p><pb  xml:id="p292"/><p >“Ladies and gentlemen—no, I won't say ladies and gentlemen, I'll call you my friends, my dear friends, if the ladies will allow me to take so great a liberty”——</p><p >Here Mr. Pickwick was interrupted by immense applause from the ladies, echoed by the gentlemen, during which the owner of the eyes was distinctly heard to state that she could kiss that dear Mr. Pickwick, whereupon Mr. Winkle gallantly inquired if it couldn't be done by deputy, to which the young lady with the black eyes replied, “Go away”—and accompanied the request with a look which said as plainly as a look could do—— “if you can.”</p><p >“My dear friends,” resumed Mr. Pickwick, “I am going to propose the health of the bride and bridegroom—God bless 'em (cheers and tears). My young friend Trundle, I believe to be a very excellent and manly fellow; and his wife I know to be a very amiable and lovely girl, well qualified to transfer to another sphere of action the happiness which for twenty years she has diffused around her, in her father's house. (Here, the fat boy burst forth into stentorian blubberings, and was led forth by the coat collar, by Mr. Weller.) I wish,” added Mr. Pickwick, “I wish I was young enough to be her sister's husband, (cheers), but, failing that, I am happy to be old enough to be her father; for, being so, I shall not be suspected of any latent designs when I say, that I admire, esteem, and love them both (cheers and sobs). The bride's father, our good friend there, is a noble person, and I am proud to know him (great uproar). He is a kind, excellent, independent-spirited, fine-hearted, hospitable, liberal man (enthusiastic shouts from the poor relations, at all the adjectives; and especially at the two last). That his daughter may enjoy all the happiness, even he can desire; and that he may derive from the contemplation of her felicity all the gratification of heart and peace of mind which he so well deserves, is, I am persuaded, our united wish. So, let us drink their healths, and wish them prolonged life, and every blessing.”</p><p >Mr. Pickwick concluded amidst a whirlwind of applause; and once more were the lungs of the supernumeraries, under Mr. Weller's command, brought into active and efficient operation. Mr. Wardle proposed Mr. Pickwick; and Mr. Pickwick proposed the old lady. Mr. Snodgrass proposed Mr. Wardle, and Mr. Wardle proposed Mr. Snodgrass. One of the poor relations proposed Mr. Tupman, and the other poor relation proposed Mr. Winkle; and all was happiness and festivity, until the mysterious disappearance of both the poor relations beneath the table, warned the party that it was time to adjourn.</p><p >At dinner they met again, after a five and twenty mile walk, undertaken by the males at Wardle's recommendation, to get rid of the effects of the wine at breakfast; the poor relations had lain in bed all day, with the view of attaining the same happy consummation, but, as they had been unsuccessful, they stopped there. Mr. Weller kept the domestics in a state of perpetual hilarity; and the fat boy divided his time into small alternate allotments of eating and sleeping.</p><p >The dinner was as hearty an affair as the breakfast, and was quite as
<pb xml:id="p293"/>
noisy, without the tears. Then came the dessert and some more toasts. Then came the tea and coffee; and then, the ball.</p><p >The best sitting room at Manor Farm was a good, long, dark-pannelled room with a high chimney piece, and a capacious chimney, up which you could have driven one of the new patent cabs, wheels and all. At the upper end of the room, seated in a shady bower of holly and evergreens, were the two best fiddlers, and the only harp, in all Muggleton. In all sorts of recesses, and on all kinds of brackets, stood massive old silver candlesticks with four branches each. The carpet was up, the candles burnt bright, the fire blazed and crackled on the hearth; and merry voices and light-hearted laughter rang through the room. If any of the old English yeomen had turned into  fairies when they died, it was just the place in which they would have held their revels.</p><p >If any thing could have added to the interest of this agreeable scene, it would have been the remarkable fact of Mr. Pickwick's appearing without his gaiters, for the first time within the memory of his oldest friends.</p><p >“You mean to dance?” said Wardle.</p><p >“Of course I do,” replied Mr. Pickwick, “Don't you see I am dressed for the purpose?” and Mr. Pickwick called attention to his speckled silk stockings, and smartly tied pumps.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">You</hi> in silk stockings!” exclaimed Mr. Tupman jocosely.</p><p >“And why not Sir—why not?” said Mr. Pickwick, turning warmly upon him.</p><p >“Oh, of course there is no reason why you shouldn't wear them,” responded Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“I imagine not Sir—I imagine not,” said Mr.  Pickwick in a very peremptory tone.</p><p >Mr. Tupman had contemplated a laugh, but he found it was a serious matter; so he looked grave, and said they were a very pretty pattern.</p><p >“I hope they are,” said Mr. Pickwick fixing his eyes upon his friend. “You see nothing extraordinary in these stockings, <hi rend="italics">as</hi> stockings, I trust Sir?”</p><p >“Certainly not—oh certainly not,” replied Mr. Tupman. He walked away; and Mr. Pickwick's countenance resumed its customary benign expression.</p><p >“We are all ready, I believe,” said Mr. Pickwick, who was stationed with the old lady at the top of the dance, and had already made four false starts, in his excessive anxiety to commence.</p><p >“Then begin at once,” said Wardle. “Now.”</p><p >Up struck the two fiddles and the one harp, and off went Mr. Pickwick into hands across, when there was a general clapping of hands, and a cry of “Stop, stop.”</p><p >“What's the matter!” said Mr. Pickwick, who was only brought to, by the fiddles and harp desisting, and could have been stopped by no other earthly power, if the house had been on fire.</p><p >“Where's Arabella Allen?” said a dozen voices.</p><pb  xml:id="p294"/><p >“And Winkle?” added Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“Here we are!” exclaimed that gentleman, emerging with his pretty companion from the corner; and, as he did so, it would have been hard to tell which was the redder in the face, he or the young lady with the black eyes.</p><p >“What an extraordinary thing it is, Winkle,” said Mr. Pickwick, rather pettishly, “that you couldn't have taken your place before.”</p><p >“Not at all extraordinary,” said Mr. Winkle.</p><p >“Well,” said Mr. Pickwick, with a very expressive smile, as his eyes rested on Arabella, “well, I don't know that it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> extraordinary, either, after all.”</p><p >However, there was no time to think more about the matter, for the fiddles and harp began in real earnest. Away went Mr. Pickwick—hands across, down the middle to the very end of the room, and half way up the chimney, back again to the door—poussette everywhere—loud stamp on the ground—ready for the next couple—off again—all the figure over once more—another stamp to beat out the time—next couple, and the next, and the next again—never was such going; and at last, after they had reached the bottom of the dance, and full fourteen couple after the old lady had retired in an exhausted state, and the clergyman's wife had been substituted in her stead, did that gentleman, when there was no demand whatever on his exertions, keep perpetually dancing in his place, to keep time to the music, smiling on his partner all the while with a blandness of demeanour which baffles all description.</p><p >Long before Mr. Pickwick was weary of dancing, the newly-married couple had retired from the scene. There was a glorious supper down stairs, notwithstanding, and a good long sitting after it; and when Mr. Pickwick awoke, late the next morning, he had a confused recollection of having, severally and confidentially, invited somewhere about five-and-forty people to dine with him at the George and Vulture, the very first time they came to London; which Mr. Pickwick rightly considered a pretty certain indication of his having taken something besides exercise, on the previous night.</p><p >“And so your family has games in the kitchen to-night, my dear, has they?” inquired Sam of Emma.</p><p >“Yes, Mr. Weller,” replied Emma; “we always have on Christmas eve. Master wouldn't neglect to keep it up, on any account.”</p><p >“Your master's a wery pretty notion of keepin' anythin' up, my dear,” said Mr. Weller; “I never see such a sensible sort of man as he is, or such a reg'lar gen'l'm'n.”</p><p >“Oh, that he is!” said the fat boy, joining in the conversation; “don't he breed nice pork!” and the fat youth gave a semi-cannibalic leer at Mr. Weller, as he thought of the roast legs and gravy.</p><p >“Oh, you've woke up, at last, have you?” said Sam.</p><p >The fat boy nodded.</p><p >“I'll tell you what it is, young boa constructer,” said Mr. Weller, impressively, “if you don't sleep a little less, and exercise a little more, ven you comes to be a man you'll lay yourself open to the same sort
<pb xml:id="p295"/>
o' personal inconwenience as was inflicted on the old gen'lm'n as wore the pig-tail.”</p><p >“What did they do to him?” inquired the fat boy, in a faltering voice.</p><p >“I'm a goin' to tell you,” replied Mr. Weller; “he was one o' the largest patterns as was ever turned out—reg'lar fat man, as hadn't caught a glimpse of his own shoes for five-and-forty years.”</p><p >“Lor!” exclaimed Emma.</p><p >“No, that he hadn't, my dear,” said Mr. Weller, “and if you'd put an exact model of his own legs on the dinin' table afore him, he wouldn't ha' known 'em. Well, he always walks to his office with a wery handsome gold watch-chain hanging out, about a foot and a half, and a gold watch in his fob pocket as was worth—I'm afraid to say how much, but as much as a watch can be—a large, heavy, round manafacter, as stout for a watch, as he was for a man, and with a big face in proportion. ‘You'd better not carry that 'ere watch,’ says the old gen'l'm'n's friends, ‘you'll be robbed on it,’ says they. ‘Shall I?’ says he. ‘Yes, will you,’ says they. ‘Vell,’ says he, ‘I should like to see the thief as could get this here watch out, for I'm blessed if <hi rend="italics">I</hi> ever can; it's such a tight fit,’ says he, ‘and venerver I vants to know what's o'clock, I'm obliged to stare into the bakers' shops,’ he says. Well, then he laughs as hearty as if he was a goin' to pieces, and out he walks again' with his powdered head and pig-tail, and rolls down the Strand vith the chain hangin' out furder than ever, and the great round watch almost bustin' through his grey kersey smalls. There warn't a pickpocket in all London as didn't take a pull at that chain, but the chain 'ud never break, and the watch 'ud never come out, so they soon got tired o' dragging such a heavy old gen'l'm'n along the pavement, and he'd go home and laugh till the pig-tail wibrated like the penderlum of a Dutch clock. At last, one day the old gen'l'm'n was a rollin' along, and he sees a pickpocket as he know'd by sight, a-comin' up, arm in arm vith a little boy vith a wery large head. ‘Here's a game,’ says the old gen'l'm'n to himself, ‘they're a-goin' to have another try, but it won't do.’ So he begins a chucklin' wery hearty, ven, all of a sudden, the little boy leaves hold of the pickpocket's arm, and rushes headforemost straight into the old gen'l'm'n's stomach, and for a moment doubled him right up vith the pain. ‘Murder!’ says the old gen'lm'n. ‘All right, Sir,’ says the pickpocket, a whisperin' in his ear. And ven he come straight agin', the watch and chain was gone, and what's worse than that, the old gen'l'm'n's digestion was all wrong ever artervards, to the wery last day of his life; so just you look about you, young feller, and take care you don't get too fat.”</p><p >As Mr. Weller concluded this moral tale, with which the fat boy appeared much affected, they all three wended their way to the large kitchen, in which the family were by this time assembled, according to annual custom on Christmas eve, observed by old Wardle's forefathers from time immemorial.</p><p >From the centre of the ceiling of this kitchen, old Wardle had just suspended with his own hands a huge branch of misletoe, and this same
<pb xml:id="p296"/>
branch of misletoe instantaneously gave rise to a scene of general and most delightful struggling and confusion; in the midst of which Mr. Pickwick with a gallantry which would have done honour to a descendant of Lady Tollimglower herself, took the old lady by the hand, led her beneath the mystic branch, and saluted her in all courtesy and decorum. The old lady submitted to this piece of practical politeness with all the dignity which befitted so important and serious a solemnity, but the younger ladies not being so thoroughly imbued with a superstitious veneration of the custom, or imagining that the value of a salute is very much enhanced if it cost a little trouble to obtain it, screamed and struggled, and ran into corners, and threatened and remonstrated, and did every thing but leave the room, until some of the less adventurous gentlemen were on the point of desisting, when they all at once found it useless to resist any longer, and submitted to be kissed with a good grace. Mr. Winkle kissed the young lady with the black eyes, and Mr. Snodgrass kissed Emily; and Mr. Weller, not being particular about the form of being under the misletoe, kissed Emma and the other female servants, just as he caught them. As to the poor relations, they kissed everybody, not even excepting the plainer portion of the young-lady visiters, who, in their excessive confusion, ran right under the misletoe, directly it was hung up, without knowing it! Wardle stood with his back to the fire, surveying the whole scene, with the utmost satisfaction; and the fat boy took the opportunity of appropriating to his own use, and summarily devouring, a particularly fine mince-pie, that had been carefully put by, for somebody else.</p><p >Now the screaming had subsided, and faces were in a glow and curls in a tangle, and Mr. Pickwick, after kissing the old lady as before-mentioned, was standing under the misletoe, looking with a very pleased countenance on all that was passing around him, when the young lady with the black eyes, after a little whispering with the other young ladies, made a sudden dart forward, and, putting her arm round Mr. Pickwick's neck, saluted him affectionately on the left cheek; and before Mr. Pickwick distinctly knew what was the matter, he was surrounded by the whole body, and kissed by every one of them.</p><p >It was a pleasant thing to see Mr. Pickwick in the centre of the group, now pulled this way, and then that, and first kissed on the chin and then on the nose, and then on the spectacles, and to hear the peals of laughter which were raised on every side; but it was a still more pleasant thing to see Mr. Pickwick, blinded shortly afterwards with a silk-handkerchief, falling up against the wall, and scrambling into corners, and going through all the mysteries of blindman's buff, with the utmost relish for the game, until at last he caught one of the poor relations; and then had to evade the blind-man himself which he did with a nimbleness and agility that elicited the admiration and applause of all beholders. The poor relations caught just the people whom they thought would like it; and when the game flagged, got caught themselves. When they were all tired of blind-man's buff, there was a great game at snap-dragon, and when fingers enough were burned with that, and all the raisins gone, they sat down by the huge fire of blazing
<pb xml:id="p297"/>
logs to a substantial supper, and a mighty bowl of wassail, something smaller than an ordinary wash-house copper, in which the hot apples were hissing and bubbling with a rich look, and a jolly sound, that were perfectly irresistible.</p><p >“This,” said Mr. Pickwick, looking round him, “this is, indeed, comfort.”</p><p >“Our invariable custom,” replied Mr. Wardle. “Every body sits down with us on Christmas eve, as you see them now—servants and all; and here we wait till the clock strikes twelve, to usher Christmas in, and wile away the time with forfeits and old stories. Trundle, my boy, rake up the fire.”</p><p >Up flew the bright sparks in myriads as the logs were stirred, and the deep red blaze sent forth a rich glow, that penetrated into the furthest corner of the room, and cast its cheerful tint on every face.</p><p >“Come,” said Wardle, “a song—a Christmas song. I'll give you one, in default of a better.”</p><p >“Bravo,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Fill up,” cried Wardle. “It will be two hours good, before you see the bottom of the bowl through the deep rich colour of the wassail; fill up all round, and now for the song.”</p><p >Thus saying, the merry old gentleman, in a good, round, sturdy voice, commenced without more ado—</p><lg  type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><head>A Christmas Carol.</head><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">I CARE not for Spring; on his fickle wing</l><l part="N">Let the blossoms and buds be borne:</l><l part="N">He woos them amain with his treacherous rain,</l><l part="N">And he scatters them ere the morn.</l><l part="N">An inconstant elf, he knows not himself,</l><l part="N">Or his own changing mind an hour,</l><l part="N">He'll smile in your face, and, with wry grimace,</l><l part="N">He'll wither your youngest flower.</l></lg><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Let the Summer sun to his bright home run,</l><l part="N">He shall never be sought by me;</l><l part="N">When he's dimmed by a cloud I can laugh aloud,</l><l part="N">And care not how sulky he be;</l><l part="N">For his darling child is the madness wild</l><l part="N">That sports in fierce fever's train;</l><l part="N">And when love is too strong, it don't last long,</l><l part="N">As many have found to their pain.</l></lg><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">A mild harvest night, by the tranquil light</l><l part="N">Of the modes and gentle moon,</l><l part="N">Has a far sweeter sheen for me, I ween,</l><l part="N">Than the broad and unblushing noon.</l><l part="N">But every leaf awakens my grief,</l><l part="N">As it lieth beneath the tree;</l><l part="N">So let Autumn air be never so fair,</l><l part="N">It by no means agrees with me.</l></lg><pb xml:id="p298"/><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">But my song I troll out, for CHRISTMAS stout,</l><l part="N">The hearty, the true, and the bold;</l><l part="N">A bumper I drain, and with might and main</l><l part="N">Give three cheers for this Christmas old.</l><l part="N">We'll usher him in with a merry din</l><l part="N">That shall gladden his joyous heart,</l><l part="N">And we'll keep him up while there's bite or sup,</l><l part="N">And in fellowship good, we'll part.</l></lg><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">In his fine honest pride, he scorns to hide</l><l part="N">One jot of his hard-weather scars;</l><l part="N">They're no disgrace, for there's much the same trace</l><l part="N">On the cheeks of our bravest tars.</l><l part="N">Then again I sing 'till the roof doth ring,</l><l part="N">And it echoes from wall to wall—</l><l part="N">To the stout old wight, fair welcome to-night,</l><l part="N">As the King of the Seasons all!</l></lg></lg><p >This song was tumultuously applauded, for friends and dependents make a capital audience; and the poor relations especially were in perfect extasies of rapture. Again was the fire replenished, and again went the wassail round.</p><p >“How it snows!” said one of the men, in a low tone.</p><p >“Snows, does it?” said Wardle.</p><p >“Rough, cold night, Sir,” replied the man; “and there's a wind got up, that drifts it across the fields, in a thick white cloud.”</p><p >“What does Jem say?” inquired the old lady. “There ain't any thing the matter, is there?”</p><p >“No, no, mother,” replied Wardle; “he says there's a snow-drift, and a wind that's piercing cold. I should know that, by the way it rumbles in the chimney.”</p><p >“Ah!” said the old lady, “there was just such a wind, and just such a fall of snow, a good many years back, I recollect—just five years before your poor father died. It was a Christmas eve, too; and I remember that on that very night he told us the story about the goblins that carried away old Gabriel Grub.”</p><p >“The story about what?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Oh, nothing—nothing,” replied Wardle. “About an old sexton, that the good people down here suppose to have been carried away by goblins.”</p><p >“Suppose!” ejaculated the old lady. “Is there any body hardy enough to disbelieve it? Suppose! Haven't you heard ever since you were a child, that he <hi rend="italics">was</hi> carried away by the goblins, and don't you know he was?”</p><p >“Very well, mother, he was, if you like,” said Wardle, langhing. “He <hi rend="italics">was</hi> carried away by goblins, Pickwick; and there's an end of the matter.”</p><p >“No, no,” said Mr. Pickwick, “not an end of it, I assure you; for I must hear how, and why, and all about it.”</p><pb  xml:id="p299"/><p >Wardle smiled, as every head was bent forward to hear; and filling out the wassail with no stinted hand, nodded a health to Mr. Pickwick, and began as follows—</p><p >But bless our editorial heart, what a long chapter we have been betrayed into! We had quite forgotten all such petty restrictions as chapters, we solemnly declare. So here goes, to give the goblin a fair start in a new one. A clear stage and no favour for the goblins, ladies and gentlemen, if you please.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XXVIII.</head><head >
THE STORY OF THE GOBLINS WHO STOLE A SEXTON.
</head><p >“IN an old abbey town, down in this part of the country, a long, long while ago—so long, that the story must be a true one, because our great grandfathers implicitly believed it—there officiated as sexton and grave-digger in the church-yard, one Gabriel Grub. It by no means follows that because a man is a sexton, and constantly surrounded by emblems of mortality, therefore he should be a morose and melancholy man; your undertakers are the merriest fellows in the world, and I once had the honour of being on intimate terms with a mute, who in private life, and off duty, was as comical and jocose a little fellow as ever chirped out a devil-may-care song, without a hitch in his memory, or drained off a good stiff glass of grog without stopping for breath. But notwithstanding these precedents to the contrary, Gabriel Grub was an ill-conditioned, cross-grained, surly fellow—a morose and lonely man, who consorted with nobody but himself, and an old wicker bottle which fitted into his large deep waistcoat pocket; and who eyed each merry face as it passed him by, with such a deep scowl of malice and ill-humour, as it was difficult to meet without feeling something the worse for.</p><p >“A little before twilight one Christmas eve, Gabriel shouldered his spade, lighted his lantern, and betook himself towards the old church-yard, for he had got a grave to finish by next morning, and feeling very low he thought it might raise his spirits perhaps, if he went on with his work at once. As he wended his way, up the ancient street, he saw the cheerful light of the blazing fires gleam through the old casements, and heard the loud laugh and the cheerful shouts of those who were assembled around them; he marked the bustling preparations for next day's good cheer, and smelt the numerous savoury odours consequent thereupon, as they steamed up from the kitchen windows in clouds. All this was gall and wormwood to the heart of Gabriel Grub; and as groups of children, bounded out of the houses, tripped across the road, and were met, before they could knock at the opposite door, by half a dozen curly-headed little rascals who crowded round them as they flocked up stairs to spend the evening in their Christmas games, Gabriel smiled grimly, and clutched the handle of his spade with a firmer grasp, as he
<pb xml:id="p300"/>
thought of measles, scarlet-fever, thrush, hooping-cough, and a good many other sources of consolation beside.</p><p >“In this happy frame of mind, Gabriel strode along, returning a short, sullen growl to the good-humoured greetings of such of his neighbours as now and then passed him, until he turned into the dark lane which led to the churchyard. Now Gabriel had been looking forward to reaching the dark lane, because it was, generally speaking, a nice gloomy mournful place, into which the towns-people did not much care to go, except in broad day-light, and when the sun was shining; consequently he was not a little indignant to hear a young urchin roaring out some jolly song about a merry Christmas, in this very sanctuary, which had been called Coffin Lane ever since the days of the old abbey, and the time of the shaven-headed monks. As Gabriel walked on, and the voice drew nearer, he found it proceeded from a small boy, who was hurrying along, to join one of the little parties in the old street, and who, partly to keep himself company, and partly to prepare himself for the occasion, was shouting out the song at the highest pitch of his lungs. So Gabriel waited till the boy came up, and then dodged him into a corner, and rapped him over the head with his lantern five or six times, just to teach him to modulate his voice. And as the boy hurried away with his hand to his head, singing quite a different sort of tune, Gabriel Grub chuckled very heartily to himself, and entered the churchyard, locking the gate behind him.</p><p >“He took off his coat, set down his lantern, and getting into the unfinished grave, worked at it for an hour or so, with right good will. But the earth was hardened with the frost, and it was no very easy matter to break it up, and shovel it out; and although there was a moon, it was a very young one, and shed little light upon the grave, which was in the shadow of the church. At any other time, these obstacles would have made Gabriel Grub very moody and miserable, but he was so well pleased with having stopped the small boy's singing, that he took little heed of the scanty progress he had made, and looked down into the grave when he had finished work for the night, with grim satisfaction, murmuring as he gathered up his things—</p><lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Brave lodgings for one, brave lodgings for one,</l><l part="N">A few feet of cold earth, when life is done;</l><l part="N">A stone at the head, a stone at the feet,</l><l part="N">A rich, juicy meal for the worms to eat;</l><l part="N">Rank grass over head, and damp clay around,</l><l part="N">Brave lodgings for one, these, in holy ground!</l></lg><p >“ ‘Ho! ho!’ laughed Gabriel Grub, as he sat himself down on a flat tombstone which was a favourite resting place of his; and drew forth his wicker bottle. ‘A coffin at Christmas—a Christmas Box. Ho! ho! ho!’ ”</p><p >“‘Ho! ho! ho!’ repeated a voice which sounded close behind him.</p><p >“Gabriel paused in some alarm, in the act of raising the wicker bottle to his lips, and looked round. The bottom of the oldest grave about him, was not more still and quiet, than the churchyard in the pale
<pb xml:id="p301"/>
moonlight. The cold hoar frost glistened on the tomb stones, and sparkled like rows of gems among the stone carvings of the old church. The snow lay hard and crisp upon the ground, and spread over the thickly-strewn mounds of earth, so white and smooth a cover, that it seemed as if corpses lay there, hidden only by their winding sheets. Not the faintest rustle broke the profound tranquillity of the solemn scene. Sound itself appeared to be frozen up, all was so cold and still.</p><p >“ ‘It was the echoes,’ said Gabriel Grub, raising the bottle to his lips again.</p><p >“ ‘It was <hi rend="italics">not,</hi>’” said a deep voice.</p><p >“Gabriel started up, and stood rooted to the spot with astonishment and terror; for his eyes rested on a form which made his blood run cold.</p><p >“Seated on an upright tombstone, close to him, was a strange unearthly figure, whom Gabriel felt at once, was no being of this world. His long fantastic legs which might have reached the ground, were cocked up, and crossed after a quaint, fantastic fashion; his sinewy arms were bare, and his hands rested on his knees. On his short round body he wore a close covering, ornamented with small slashes; and a short cloak dangled at his back; the collar was cut into curious peaks, which served the goblin in lieu of ruff or neckerchief; and his shoes curled up at the toes into long points. On his head he wore a broad-brimmed sugar loaf hat, garnished with a single feather. The hat was covered with the white frost, and the goblin looked as if he had sat on the same tombstone very comfortably, for two or three hundred years. He was sitting perfectly still; his tongue was put out, as if in derision; and he was grinning at Gabriel Grub with such a grin as only a goblin could call up.</p><p >“ ‘It was <hi rend="italics">not</hi> the echoes,’” said the goblin.</p><p >“Gabriel Grub was paralysed, and could make no reply.</p><p >“ ‘What do you do here on Christmas eve?’” said the goblin sternly.</p><p >“ ‘I came to dig a grave Sir,’ stammered Gabriel Grub.</p><p >“ ‘What man wanders among graves and churchyards on such a night as this?’” said the goblin.</p><p >“ ‘Gabriel Grub! Gabriel Grub!’ screamed a wild chorus of voices that seemed to fill the church-yard. Gabriel looked fearfully round—nothing was to be seen.</p><p >“ ‘What have you got in that bottle?’ said the goblin.</p><p >“ ‘Hollands, Sir,’ replied the sexton, trembling more than ever; for he had bought it of the smugglers, and he thought that perhaps his questioner might be in the excise department of the goblins.</p><p >“ ‘Who drinks Hollands alone, and in a church-yard, on such a night as this?’ said the goblin.</p><p >“ ‘Gabriel Grub! Gabriel Grub!’ exclaimed the wild voice again.</p><p >“The goblin leered maliciously at the terrified sexton, and then raising his voice, exclaimed—</p><p >“ ‘And who, then, is our fair and lawful prize?’</p><p >“To this inquiry the invisible chorus replied, in a strain that sounded
<pb xml:id="p302"/>
like the voices of many choristers singing to the mighty swell of the old church organ—a strain that seemed borne to the sexton's ears upon a gentle wind, and to die away as its soft breath passed onward—but the burden of the reply was still the same, ‘Gabriel Grub! Gabriel Grub!’</p><p >“The goblin grinned a broader grin than before, as he said, ‘Well, Gabriel, what do you say to this?’</p><p >“The sexton gasped for breath.</p><p >“ ‘What do you think of this, Gabriel?’ said the goblin, kicking up his feet in the air on either side the tombstone, and looking at the turned-up points with as much complacency as if he had been contemplating the most fashionable pair of Wellingtons in all Bond Street.</p><p >“ ‘It's—it's—very curious, Sir,’ replied the sexton, half dead with fright, ‘very curious, and very pretty, but I think I'll go back and finish my work, Sir, if you please.</p><p >“ ‘Work!’ said the goblin, ‘what work?’</p><p >“ ‘The grave, Sir, making the grave,’ stammered the sexton.</p><p >“ ‘Oh, the grave, eh?’ said the goblin, ‘who makes graves at a time when all other men are merry, and takes a pleasure in it?’</p><p >“Again the mysterious voices replied, ‘Gabriel Grub! Gabriel Grub!’</p><p >“ ‘I'm afraid my friends want you, Gabriel,’ said the goblin, thrusting his tongue further into his cheek than ever—and a most astonishing tongue it was—‘I'm afraid my friends want you, Gabriel,’ said the goblin.</p><p >“ ‘Under favour, Sir,’ replied the horror-struck sexton, ‘I don't think they can, Sir; they don't know me, Sir; I don't think the gentlemen have ever seen me, Sir.’</p><p >“ ‘Oh yes they have,’ replied the goblin; ‘we know the man with the sulky face and the grim scowl, that came down the street to-night, throwing his evil looks at the children, and grasping his burying spade the tighter. We know the man that struck the boy in the envious malice of his heart, because the boy could be merry, and he could not. We know him, we know him.’</p><p >“Here the goblin gave a loud shrill laugh, that the echoes returned twenty fold, and throwing his legs up in the air, stood upon his head, or rather upon the very point of his sugar-loaf hat, on the narrow edge of the tombstone, from whence he threw a summerset with extraordinary agility, right to the sexton's feet, at which he planted himself in the attitude in which tailors generally sit upon the shop-board.</p><p >“ ‘I—I—am afraid I must leave you, Sir,’ said the sexton, making an effort to move.</p><p >“ ‘Leave us!’ said the goblin, ‘Gabriel Grub going to leave us. Ho! ho! ho!’</p><p >“As the goblin laughed, the sexton observed for one instant a brilliant illumination within the windows of the church, as if the whole building were lighted up; it disappeared, the organ pealed forth a lively air, and whole troops of goblins, the very counterpart of the first one, poured into the churchyard, and began playing at leap-frog with the tombstones, never stopping for an instant to take breath, but overing
<pb xml:id="p303"/>
the highest among them, one after the other, with the most marvellous dexterity. The first goblin was a most astonishing leaper, and none of the others could come near him; even in the extremity of his terror the sexton could not help observing, that while his friends were content to leap over the common-sized gravestones, the first one took the family vaults, iron railings and all, with as much ease as if they had been so many street posts.</p><p >“At last the game reached to a most exciting pitch; the organ played quicker and quicker, and the goblins leaped faster and faster, coiling themselves up, rolling head over heels upon the ground, and bounding over the tombstones like foot-balls. The sexton's brain whirled round with the rapidity of the motion he beheld, and his legs reeled beneath him, as the spirits flew before his eyes, when the goblin king suddenly darting towards him, laid his hand upon his collar, and sank with him through the earth.</p><p >“When Gabriel Grub had had time to fetch his breath, which the rapidity of his descent had for the moment taken away, he found himself in what appeared to be a large cavern, surrounded on all sides by crowds of goblins, ugly and grim; in the centre of the room, on an elevated seat, was stationed his friend of the churchyard; and close beside him stood Gabriel Grub himself, without the power of motion.</p><p >“ ‘Cold to-night,’ said the king of the goblins, ‘very cold. A glass of something warm, here.’</p><p >“At this command, half a dozen officious goblins, with a perpetual smile upon their faces, whom Gabriel Grub imagined to be courtiers, on that account, hastily disappeared, and presently returned with a goblet of liquid fire, which they presented to the king.</p><p >“ ‘Ah!’ said the goblin, whose cheeks and throat were quite transparent, as he tossed down the flame, ‘This warms one, indeed: bring a bumper of the same, for Mr. Grub.’</p><p >“It was in vain for the unfortunate sexton to protest that he was not in the habit of taking anything warm at night; for one of the goblins held him while another poured the blazing liquid down his throat, and the whole assembly screeched with laughter as he coughed and choked, and wiped away the tears which gushed plentifully from his eyes, after swallowing the burning draught.</p><p >“ ‘And now,’ said the king, fantastically poking the taper corner of his sugar-loaf hat into the sexton's eye, and thereby occasioning him the most exquisite pain—‘And now, show the man of misery and gloom a few of the pictures from our own great storehouse.’</p><p >“As the goblin said this, a thick cloud which obscured the further end of the cavern, rolled gradually away, and disclosed, apparently at a great distance, a small and scantily furnished, but neat and clean apartment. A crowd of little children were gathered round a bright fire, clinging to their mother's gown, and gambolling round her chair. The mother occasionally rose, and drew aside the window-curtain as if to look for some expected object; a frugal meal was ready spread upon the table, and an elbow chair was placed near the fire. A knock was heard at the door: the mother opened it, and the children crowded round her,
<pb xml:id="p304"/>
and clapped their hands for joy, as their father entered. He was wet and weary, and shook the snow from his garments, as the children crowded round him, and seizing his cloak, hat, stick, and gloves, with busy zeal, ran with them from the room. Then as he sat down to his meal before the fire, the children climbed about his knee, and the mother sat by his side, and all seemed happiness and comfort.</p><p >“But a change came upon the view, almost imperceptibly. The scene was altered to a small bed-room, where the fairest and youngest child lay dying; the roses had fled from his cheek, and the light from his eye; and even as the sexton looked upon him with an interest he had never felt or known before, he died. His young brothers and sisters crowded round his little bed, and seized his tiny hand, so cold and heavy; but they shrunk back from its touch, and looked with awe on his infant face; for calm and tranquil as it was, and sleeping in rest and peace as the beautiful child seemed to be, they saw that he was dead, and they knew that he was an angel looking down upon, and blessing them, from a bright and happy Heaven.</p><p >“Again the light cloud passed across the picture, and again the subject changed. The father and mother were old and helpless now, and the number of those about them was diminished more than half; but content and cheerfulness sat on every face, and beamed in every eye, as they crowded round the fireside, and told and listened to old stories of earlier and bygone days. Slowly and peacefully the father sank into the grave, and, soon after, the sharer of all his cares and troubles followed him to a place of rest and peace. The few, who yet survived them, knelt by their tomb, and watered the green turf which covered it with their tears; then rose and turned away, sadly and mournfully, but not with bitter cries, or despairing lamentations, for they knew that they should one day meet again; and once more they mixed with the busy world, and their content and cheerfulness were restored. The cloud settled upon the picture, and concealed it from the sexton's view.</p><p >“ ‘What do you think of <hi rend="italics">that?</hi>’ said the goblin, turning his large face towards Gabriel Grub.</p><p >“Gabriel murmured out something about its being very pretty, and looked somewhat ashamed, as the goblin bent his fiery eyes upon him.</p><p >“ ‘<hi rend="italics">You</hi> a miserable man!’ said the goblin, in a tone of excessive contempt. ‘You!’ He appeared disposed to add more, but indignation choked his utterance, so he lifted up one of his very pliable legs, and flourishing it above his head a little, to insure his aim, administered a good sound kick to Gabriel Grub; immediately after which, all the goblins in waiting crowded round the wretched sexton, and kicked him without mercy, according to the established and invariable custom of courtiers upon earth, who kick whom royalty kicks, and hug whom royalty hugs.</p><p >“ ‘Show him some more,’ said the king of the goblins.</p><p >“At these words the cloud was again dispelled, and a rich and beautiful landscape was disclosed to view—there is just such another to this day, within half a mile of the old abbey town. The sun shone from out
<pb xml:id="p305"/>
the clear blue sky, the water sparkled beneath his rays, and the trees looked greener, and the flowers more gay, beneath his cheering influence. The water rippled on, with a pleasant sound, the trees rustled in the light wind that murmured among their leaves, the birds sang upon the boughs, and the lark carolled on high, her welcome to the morning. Yes, it was morning, the bright, balmy morning of summer; the minutest leaf, the smallest blade of grass, was instinct with life. The ant crept forth to her daily toil, the butterfly fluttered and basked in the warm rays of the sun; myriads of insects spread their transparent wings, and revelled in their brief but happy existence. Man walked forth, elated with the scene; and all was brightness and splendour.</p><p >“ ‘<hi rend="italics">You</hi> a miserable man!’ said the king of the goblins, in a more contemptuous tone than before. And again the king of the goblins gave his leg a flourish; again it descended on the shoulders of the sexton; and again the attendant goblins imitated the example of their chief.</p><p >“Many a time the cloud went and came, and many a lesson it taught to Gabriel Grub, who although his shoulders smarted with pain from the frequent applications of the goblin's feet thereunto, looked on with an interest which nothing could diminish. He saw that men who worked hard, and earned their scanty bread with lives of labour, were cheerful and happy; and that to the most ignorant, the sweet face of nature was a never-failing source of cheerfulness and joy. He saw those who had been delicately nurtured, and tenderly brought up, cheerful under privations, and superior to suffering, that would have crushed many of a rougher grain, because they bore within their own bosoms the materials of happiness, contentment, and peace. He saw that women, the tenderest and most fragile of all God's creatures, were the oftenest superior to sorrow, adversity, and distress; and he saw that it was because they bore in their own hearts an inexhaustible well-spring of affection and devotedness. Above all, he saw that men like himself, who snarled at the mirth and cheerfulness of others, were the foulest weeds on the fair surface of the earth; and setting all the good of the world against the evil, he came to the conclusion that it was a very decent and respectable sort of world after all. No sooner had he formed it, than the cloud which had closed over the last picture, seemed to settle on his senses, and lull him to repose. One by one, the goblins faded from his sight, and as the last one disappeared, he sunk to sleep.</p><p >“The day had broken when Gabriel Grub awoke, and found himself lying at full length on the flat grave stone in the church yard, with the wicker bottle lying empty by his side, and his coat, spade, and lantern, all well whitened by the last night's frost, scattered on the ground. The stone on which he had first seen the goblin seated, stood bolt up-right before him, and the grave at which he had worked, the night before, was not far off. At first he began to doubt the reality of his adventures, but the acute pain in his shoulders when he attempted to rise, assured him that the kicking of the goblins was certainly not ideal. He was staggered again, by observing no traces of footsteps in the snow
<pb xml:id="p306"/>
on which the goblins had played at leap frog with the grave-stones, but he speedily accounted for this circumstance when he remembered that being spirits, they would leave no visible impression behind them. So Gabriel Grub got on his feet as well as he could, for the pain in his back; and brushing the frost off his coat, put it on, and turned his face towards the town.</p><p >“But he was an altered man, and he could not hear the thought of returning to a place where his repentance would be scoffed it, and his reformation disbelieved. He hesitated for a few moments; and then turned away to wander where he might, and seek his bread elsewhere.</p><p >“The lantern, the spade, and the wicker bottle, were found that day in the churchyard. There were a great many speculations about the sexton's fate at first, but it was speedily determined that he had been carried away by the goblins; and there were not wanting some very credible witnesses who had distinctly seen him whisked through the air on the back of a chestnut horse blind of one eye, with the hind quarters of a lion, and the tail of a bear. At length all this was devoutly believed; and the new sexton used to exhibit to the curious for a trifling emolument, a good-sized piece of the church weathercock which had been accidentally kicked off by the aforesaid horse in his aërial flight, and picked up by himself in the churchyard, a year or two afterwards.</p><p >“Unfortunately these stories were somewhat disturbed by the unlooked-for re-appearance of Gabriel Grub himself, some ten years afterwards, a ragged, contented, rheumatic old man. He told his story to the clergyman, and also to the mayor; and in course of time it began to be received as a matter of history, in which form it has continued down to this very day. The believers in the weathercock tale, having misplaced their confidence once, were not easily prevailed upon to part with it again, so they looked as wise as they could, shrugged their shoulders, touched their foreheads, and murmured something about Gabriel Grub's having drunk all the Hollands, and then fallen asleep on the flat tombstone; and they affected to explain what he supposed he had witnessed in the goblin's cavern, by saying that he had seen the world, and grown wiser. But this opinion, which was by no means a popular one at any time, gradually died off; and be the matter how it may, as Gabriel Grub was afflicted with rheumatism to the end of his days, this story has at least one moral, if it teach no better one—and that is, that if a man turns sulky and drinks by himself at Christmas time, he may make up his mind to be not a bit the better for it, let the spirits be ever so good, or let them be even as many degrees beyond proof, as those which Gabriel Grub saw, in the goblin's cavern.”</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pvi"/><head >SPLENDID NEW YEAR'S GIFT.</head><p >In quarto, bound in a peculiarly elegant and novel manner, price 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >THE PICTORIAL ALBUM; <lb/> OR, <lb/> CABINET OF PAINTINGS FOR THE YEAR 1837.</p><p >Containing ELEVEN DESIGNS, executed in Oil Colours by G. BAXTER, and forming perfect Fac-similes <lb/> of the original Pictures. With Letter-Press Illustrations.</p><p >THE POETRY BY MISS LANDON—THE PROSE BY JAMES OLLIER, ESQ.</p><p >“Of all the novelties of the season, this is <hi rend="italics">the</hi> novelty—a decided original, and, what is better, as beautiful as it is new.”—<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p><p >“Unique, among the annual tribe, as regards its embellishments, which are the grand attraction. They have the appearance of highly-elaborated miniatures, executed with body colours, and mounted on tinted paper. The subjects are various, including landscapes, interiors, and figures; and the different style of each artist is imitated completely. The binding of the book is correspondingly novel and striking.”—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p><p >“The literature of the Pictorial Album is of high pretension, and of an elevated order; the tales are written with spirit, and the poetry is considerably superior to the average verse which we find in the Annuals.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><head >THE CHEAPEST ORIGINAL MISCELLANY EVER PUBLISHED;</head><p > COMPRISING BOTH <lb/> HUMOROUS AND SERIOUS TALES, <lb/> BY THE MOST EMINENT WRITERS OF THE DAY.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Price One Shilling, with Two Illustrations,</hi>
<lb/> No. 10 OF <lb/> THE LIBRARY OF FICTION; <lb/> OR, <lb/> FAMILY STORY-TELLER.</p><p >CONTAINING</p><p >THE MIDSHIPMAN'S EXPEDIENTS, OR THE DEPUTY CLEAN SHIRT, by the Author of “RATTLIN THE REEFER.”</p><p >THE RIVAL COLOURS, by ALEXANDER CAMPBELL.</p><p >THE ONE WITNESS; A TALE OF THE LAW.</p><p >THE PREACHER PARROT, OR THE TRIALS OF TRUTH, by DOUGLAS JERROLD.</p><p >The following are amongst the numerous distinguished Writers who either have contributed, or have <lb/> engaged to contribute, to this Periodical: </p><list  type="simple"><item>“Boz.”</item><item>THE COUNTESS OF BLESSINGTON.</item><item>SHERIDAN KNOWLES.</item><item>MISS L. E. LANDON.</item><item>CAPTAIN GLASCOCK</item><item>MRS. S. C. HALL.</item><item>Author of “Rattlin the Reefer.”</item><item>E. MAYHEW, Author of “Make your Wills.”</item><item>CHARLES OLLIER, Author of “Incsilla.”</item><item>G. P. R. JAMES.</item><item>MISS MITFORD.</item><item>DOUGLAS JERROLD.</item><item>ALLAN CUNNINGHAM.</item><item>DR. MAGINN.</item><item>C. WHITEHEAD, Author of the “Cavalier.”</item><item>T. K. HERVEY.</item><item>“THE GENTLEMAN IN BLACK.”</item></list><p >THE FIRST VOLUME IS JUST COMPLETED, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Price Eight Shillings,</hi>
<lb/> Handsomely bound in cloth, with FOURTEEN ILLUSTRATIONS.</p><p >CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, Strand.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pvii"/><head >Splendidly illustrated Works,</head><p >JUST PUBLISHED BY CHARLES TILT, FLEET STREET.</p><div type="section"><head >J. D. HARDINGS NEW WORK.</head><p >This day is published, price 34<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> half-bound in morocco, <lb/> HARDING'S PORTFOLIO OF DRAWINGS; <lb/> A SERIES OF TWENTY-FOUR HIGHLY-FINISHED SKETCHES.</p><p >An edition has also been prepared, beautifully coloured, under MR. HARDING'S superintendence, so as exactly to imitate the original Drawings, price 55<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >ELEGANT VOLUME FOR THE DRAWING-ROOM TABLE.</head><p >Price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> superbly bound in morocco, <lb/> FINDEN'S GALLERY OF THE GRACES; <lb/> A Series of Thirty-Six beautiful Female Heads, illustrating celebrated Passages in Modern <lb/> British Poets, with accompanying Extracts.</p><p >The Paintings were designed expressly for this work by the most eminent Artists, and the whole engraved with the greatest care, under the superintendence of the Messrs. FINDEN. The binding, in richness and luxury, far surpasses anything of the kind ever attempted.</p></div><div type="section"><head >BEAUTIFUL WORK, WITH COLOURED PLATES.</head><p >Just published, in one large 8vo. volume, price 31<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> <lb/> THE ROMANCE OF NATURE; <lb/> OR, THE FLOWER SEASONS ILLUSTRATED.</p><p >BY LOUISA ANNE TWAMLEY.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Second Edition.</hi></p><p >“This is a book of singular beauty and taste. Twenty-seven exquisite coloured drawings of favourite flowers are accompanied by graceful quotations from the various authors who have felt their ‘sweetest inspiration,’ and some charming original poems. Whether for tasteful decoration, originality, or grace, we have seen no superior to this most beautiful volume.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >SPLENDID VOLUME FOR A PRESENT.</head><p >This day is published, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> LE BYRON DES DAMES; <lb/> OR, <lb/> PORTRAITS OF THE PRINCIPAL FEMALE CHARACTERS IN LORD BYRON'S POEMS.</p><p >This Volume is in large 4 to, bound in rose-coloured Morocco, very richly gilt, and contains Thirty-nine Plates from original Paintings, engraved under the superintendence of W. and E. FINDEN. Each subject is illustrated by Critical Remarks and Poetical Extracts.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >In imperial folio, half morocco, price 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >HARDING'S SKETCHES AT HOME AND ABROAD, </head><p > In Fifty-one large Plates, containing more than Sixty Views, tinted in imitation of the <lb/> original Drawings.</p></div><div type="section"><head >LADY BLESSINGTON'S NEW WORK.</head><p >Price 21<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> neatly bound and gilt, <lb/> HEATH'S DRAWING-ROOM PORTFOLIO; <lb/> Containing Seven large and beautiful Engravings, with fanciful Illustrations by the <lb/> COUNTESS OF BLESSINGTON.</p></div><div type="section"><head >FINDEN'S LANDSCAPE AND PORTRAIT ILLUSTRATIONS <lb/> OF <lb/> THE LIFE AND WORKS OF LORD BYRON.</head><p >In three vols., royal 8vo, containing One Hundred and Twenty-six Plates. Price, handsomely half-bound in Morocco, gilt edges, 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> whole bound in Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> or Morocco elegant, superbly gilt, 6<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >The Plates are engraved by the FINDENS, in their best style, from original Drawings by all our most eminent Artists, not of imaginary subjects, but of actual Landscape Views, illustrative of the scenery of Lord Byron's Life, and the local ties from which he drew his descriptions; together with a highly valuable Series of Original Portraits of the distinguished Individuals whose names occupy a prominent place in his Writings, and a full and interesting Letter-press Description of each Engraving: and thus, in addition to all the qualities of the passing productions of the year, possessing an interest lasting as the fame of the great Poet, whose immortal Works they are intended to illustrate.</p></div></div></back></text></TEI>