<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. V:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name><name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name><name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name><name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>M. Brooke Phillips</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Harris Henderson, and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca.  115K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_pageThe Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. V</title><author>Boz</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>R. Seymour and Phiz</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> 37 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LondonChapman &amp; Hall, 186, Strand</publisher><date>1836</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number Dickens 13 pt. 5 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-11-18"> Jill Kuhn Sexton finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-09-24">Harris Henderson finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><titlePage><titlePart type="main"> No. V.]</titlePart><docEdition>[PRICE  1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PICKWICK CLUB <lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE <lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES <lb/> AND <lb/> Sporting Transartions <lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS.  
</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor>
EDITED BY “BOZ.”</docAuthor><docEdition>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.
</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVI.</docDate>
</docImprint></titlePage></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill1"><p><hi rend="italics">page 117</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill2"><p><hi rend="italics">page 132</hi></p></figure>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="text"><pb  xml:id="p115"/><head >[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XII.</head><head >DESCRIPTIVE OF A VERY IMPORTANT PROCEEDING ON THE PART OF MR. PICKWICK; NO LESS AN EPOCH IN HIS LIFE, THAN IN THIS HISTORY.</head><p >MR. PICKWICK's apartments in Goswell Street, although on a limited scale, were not only of a very neat and comfortable description, but peculiarly adapted for the residence of a man of his genius and observation. His sitting-room was the first floor front, his bed-room the second floor front; and thus, whether he were sitting at his desk in the parlour, or standing before the dressing-glass in his dormitory, he had an equal opportunity of contemplating human nature in all the numerous phases it exhibits, in that not more populous than popular thoroughfare. His landlady, Mrs. Bardell—the relict and sole executrix of a deceased custom-house officer—was a comely woman of bustling manners and agreeable appearance, with a natural genius for cooking, improved by study and long practice into an exquisite talent. There were no children, no servants, no fowls. The only other inmates of the house were a large man, and a small boy; the first a lodger, the second a production of Mrs. Bardell's. The large man was always home precisely at ten o'clock at night, at which hour he regularly condensed himself into the limits of a dwarfish French bedstead in the back parlour; and the infantine sports and gymnastic exercises of Master Bardell were exclusively confined to the neighbouring pavements and gutters. Cleanliness and quiet reigned throughout the house; and in it Mr. Pickwick's will was law.</p><p >To any one acquainted with these points of the domestic economy of the establishment, and conversant with the admirable regulation of Mr. Pickwick's mind, his appearance and behaviour on the morning previous to that which had been fixed upon for the journey to Eatanswill, would have been most mysterious and unaccountable. He paced the room to and fro with hurried steps, popped his head out of the window at intervals of about three minutes each, constantly referred to his watch, and exhibited many other manifestations of impatience, very unusual with him. It was evident that something of great importance was in contemplation, but what that something was not even Mrs. Bardeli herself had been enabled to discover.</p><p >“Mrs. Bardell,” said Mr. Pickwick at last, as that amiable female approached the termination of a prolonged dusting of the apartment—</p><p >“Sir,” said Mrs. Bardell.</p><p >“Your little boy is a very long time gone.”</p><p >“Why it's a good long way to the Borough, Sir,” remonstrated Mrs. Bardell.</p><pb  xml:id="p116"/><p >“Ah,” said Mr. Pickwick, “very true; so it is.”</p><p >Mr. Pickwick relapsed into silence, and Mrs. Bardell resumed her dusting.</p><p >“Mrs. Bardell,” said Mr. Pickwick, at the expiration of a few minutes.</p><p >“Sir,” said Mrs. Bardell again.</p><p >“Do you think it's a much greater expense to keep two people, than to keep one?”</p><p >“La, Mr. Pickwick,” said Mrs. Bardell, colouring up to the very border of her cap, as she fancied she observed a species of matrimonial twinkle in the eyes of her lodger; “La, Mr. Pickwick, what a question!”</p><p >“Well, but <hi rend="italics">do</hi> you?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“That depends—” said Mrs. Bardell, approaching the duster very near to Mr. Pickwick's elbow, which was planted on the table; “that depends a good deal upon the person, you know, Mr. Pickwick; and whether it's a saving and careful person, Sir.”</p><p >“That's very true,” said Mr. Pickwick, “but the person I have in my eye (here he looked very hard at Mrs. Bardell) I think possesses these qualities; and has, moreover, a considerable knowledge of the world, and a great deal of sharpness, Mrs. Bardell; which may be of material use to me.”</p><p >“La, Mr. Pickwick,” said Mrs. Bardell; the crimson rising to her cap-border again.</p><p >“I do,” said Mr. Pickwick, growing energetic, as was his wont in speaking of a subject which interested him, “I do, indeed; and to tell you the truth, Mrs. Bardell, I have made up my mind.”</p><p >“Dear me, Sir,” exclaimed Mrs. Bardell.</p><p >“You'll think it very strange now,” said the amiable Mr. Pickwick, with a good-humoured glance at his companion, “that I never consulted you about this matter, and never even mentioned it, till I sent your little boy out this morning—eh?”</p><p >Mrs. Bardell could only reply by a look. She had long worshipped Mr. Pickwick at a distance, but here she was, all at once, raised to a pinnacle to which her wildest and most extravagant hopes had never dared to aspire. Mr. Pickwick was going to propose—a deliberate plan, too—sent her little boy to the Borough, to get him out of the way—how thoughtful—how considerate!</p><p >“Well,” said Mr. Pickwick, “what do you think?”</p><p >“Oh, Mr. Pickwick,” said Mrs. Bardell, trembling with agitation, you're very kind, Sir”</p><p >“It'll save you a good deal of trouble, won't it?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Oh, I never thought anything of the trouble, Sir,” replied Mrs. Bardell; “and, of course, I should take more trouble to please you then, than ever; but it is so kind of you, Mr. Pickwick to have so much consideration for my loneliness.”</p><p >“Ah, to be sure,” said Mr. Pickwick;  “I never thought of that. When I am in town, you'll always have somebody to sit with you. To be sure, so you will.”</p><pb  xml:id="p117"/><p >“I'm sure I ought to be a very happy woman,” said Mrs. Bardell.</p><p >“And your little boy—” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Bless his heart,” interposed Mrs. Bardell, with a maternal sob.</p><p >“He, too, will have a companion,” resumed Mr. Pickwick, “a lively one, who'll teach him, I'll be bound, more tricks in a week, than he would ever learn in a year.” And Mr. Pickwick smiled placidly.</p><p >“Oh you dear—” said Mrs. Bardell.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick started.</p><p >“Oh you kind, good, playful dear,” said Mrs. Bardell; and without more ado, she rose from her chair, and flung her arms round Mr. Pickwick's neck, with a cataract of tears, and a chorus of sobs.</p><p >“Bless my soul,” cried the astonished Mr. Pickwick;—“Mrs. Bardell my good woman—dear me, what a situation—pray consider.—Mrs. Bardell, don't—if anybody should come—”</p><p >“Oh, let them come,” exclaimed Mrs. Bardell, frantically; “I'll never leave you—dear, kind, good, soul;”  and, with these words, Mrs. Bardell clung the tighter.</p><p >“Mercy upon me,” said Mr. Pickwick, struggling violently, “I hear somebody coming up the stairs. Don't, don't, there's a good creature, don't.” But entreaty and remonstrance were alike unavailing: for Mrs. Bardell had fainted in Mr. Pickwick's arms; and before he could gain time to deposit her on a chair, Master Bardell entered the room, ushering in Mr. Tupman, Mr. Winkle, and Mr. Snodgrass.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick was struck motionless  and speechless. He stood with his lovely burden in his arms, gazing vacantly on the countenances of his friends, without the slighest attempt at recognition or explanation. They, in their turn, stared at him; and Master Bardell, in his turn, stared at everybody.</p><p >The astonishment of the Pickwickians was so absorbing, and the perplexity of Mr. Pickwick was so  extreme, that they might have remained in exactly the same relative situations until  the suspended animation of the lady was restored, had it not been for a most beautiful and touching expression of filial affection on the part of her youthful son. Clad in a tight suit of corderoy, spangled with brass buttons of a very considerable size, he at first stood at the door astounded and uncertain; but by degrees, the impression that his mother must have suffered some personal damage, pervaded his partially developed mind, and considering Mr. Pickwick as the aggressor, he set up an appalling and semi-earthly kind of howling, and butting forward with his head, commenced assailing that immortal gentleman about the  back and legs, with such blows and pinches as the strength of his arm, and the violence of his excitement, allowed.</p><p >“Take this little villain away,” said the agonised Mr. Pickwick, “he's mad.”</p><p >“What <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the matter?” said the three tongue-tied Pickwickians.</p><p >“I don't know,” replied Mr. Pickwick, pettishly. “Take away the boy—(here Mr. Winkle carried the interesting boy, screaming and struggling, to the further end of the apartment).—Now help me, lead this woman down stairs.”</p><pb  xml:id="p118"/><p >“Oh, I am better now,” said Mrs. Bardell, faintly.</p><p >“Let me lead you down stairs,” said the ever gallant Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“Thank you, Sir—thank you;” exclaimed Mrs. Bardell, hysterically And down stairs she was led accordingly, accompanied by her affectionate son.</p><p >“I cannot conceive—” said Mr. Pickwick, when his friend returned.—“I cannot conceive what has been the matter with that woman. I had merely announced to her my intention of keeping a man servant, when she fell into the extraordinary paroxysm in which you found her. Very extraordinary thing.”</p><p >“Very,” said his three friends.</p><p >“Placed me in such an extremely awkward situation,” continued Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Very;” was the reply of his followers, as they coughed slightly, and looked dubiously at each other.</p><p >This behaviour was not lost upon Mr. Pickwick. He remarked their incredulity. They evidently suspected him.</p><p >“There is a man in the passage now,” said Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“It's the man I spoke to you about,” said Mr. Pickwick, “I sent for him to the Borough this morning. Have the goodness to call him up, Snodgrass.”</p><p >Mr. Snodgrass did as he was desired; and Mr. Samuel Weller forthwith presented himself.</p><p >“Oh—you remember me, I suppose?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“I should think so,” replied Sam, with a patronising wink. “Queer start that 'ere, but he was one too many for you, warn't he? Up to snuff and a pinch or two over—eh?”</p><p >“Never mind that matter now,” said Mr. Pickwick hastily, “I want to speak to you about something else. Sit down.”</p><p >“Thank'ee, Sir,” said Sam. And down he sat without farther bidding, having previously deposited his old white hat on the landing outside the door. “Ta'nt a werry good 'un to look at,” said Sam, “but it's an astonishin' 'un to wear; and afore the brim went, it was a wery handsome tile. Hows'ever it's lighter without it, that's one thing, and every hole lets in some air, that's another—wentilation gossamer I calls it.” On the delivery of this sentiment, Mr. Weller smiled agreeably upon the assembled Pickwickians.</p><p >“Now with regard to the matter on which I, with the concurrence of these gentlemen, sent for you,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“That's the pint, Sir,” interposed Sam; “out vith it, as the father said to the child, ven he swallowed a farden.”</p><p >“We want to know, in the first place,” said Mr. Pickwick, “whether you have any reason to be discontented with your present situation.”</p><p >“Afore I answers that 'ere question, gen'l'm'n,” replied Mr. Weller, “<hi rend="italics">I</hi> should like  to know, in the first place, whether you're a goin' to purwide me vith a better.”</p><p >A sunbeam of placid benevolence played on Mr. Pickwick's features as he said, “I have half made up my mind to engage you myself.”</p><p >“Have you, though?” said Sam.</p><pb  xml:id="p119"/><p >Mr. Pickwick nodded in the affirmative.</p><p >“Wages?” inquired Sam.</p><p >“Twelve pounds a year,” replied Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Clothes?”</p><p >“Two suits.”</p><p >“Work?”</p><p >“To attend upon me; and travel about with me and these gentlemen here.”</p><p >“Take the bill down,” said Sam, emphatically. “I'm let to a single gentleman, and the terms is agreed upon.”</p><p >“You accept the situation?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Cert'nly,” replied Sam. “If the clothes fits me half as well as the place, they'll do.”</p><p >“You can get a character of course?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Ask the landlady o' the White Hart about that, Sir,” replied Sam.</p><p >“Can you come this evening?”</p><p >“I'll get into the clothes this minute, if they're here,” said Sam with great alacrity.</p><p >“Call at eight this evening,” said Mr. Pickwick; and if the inquiries are satisfactory, they shall be provided.”</p><p >With the single exception of one amiable indiscretion, in which an assistant housemaid had equally participated, the history of Mr. Weller's conduct was so very blameless, that Mr. Pickwick felt fully justified in closing the engagement that very evening. With the promptness and energy which characterised not only the public proceedings, but all the private actions of this extraordinary man, he at once led his new attendant to one of those convenient emporiums where gentlemen's new and second-hand clothes are provided, and the troublesome and inconvenient formality of measurement dispensed with; and before night had closed in, Mr. Weller was furnished with a grey coat with the ‘P. C.’ button, a black hat with a cockade to it, a pink striped waistcoat, light breeches and gaiters, and a variety of other necessaries, too numerous to recapitulate.</p><p >“Well,” said that suddenly-transformed individual, as he took his seat on the outside of the Eatanswill coach next morning; “I wonder vether I'm meant to be a footman, or a groom, or a game-keeper, or a seedsman. I looks like a sort of compo of every one on 'em. Never mind; there's change of air, plenty to see, and little to do; and all this suits my complaint uncommon, so long life to the Pickvicks, says I.”</p></div><div type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p120"/><head >CHAPTER XIII.</head><head >SOME ACCOUNT OF EATANSWILL; OF THE STATE OF PARTIES THEREIN; AND OF THE ELECTION OF A MEMBER TO SERVE IN PARLIAMENT FOR THAT ANCIENT, LOYAL, AND PATRIOTIC BOROUGH.</head><p >WE will frankly acknowledge, that up to the period of our being first immersed in the voluminous papers of the Pickwick club, we had never heard of Eatanswill; we will with equal candour admit, that we have in vain searched for proof of the actual existence of such a place at the present day. Knowing the deep reliance to be placed on every note and statement of Mr. Pickwick's, and not presuming to set up our recollection against the recorded declarations of that great man, we have consulted every authority, bearing upon the subject, to which we could possibly refer. We have traced every name in schedules A and B, without meeting with that of Eatanswill; we have minutely examined every corner of the Pocket County Maps issued for the benefit of society by our distinguished publishers, and the same result has attended our investigation. We are therefore led to believe, that Mr. Pickwick, with that anxious desire to abstain from giving offence to any, and with those delicate feelings for which all who knew him well know he was so eminently remarkable, purposely substituted a fictitious designation, for the real name of the place in which his observations were made. We are confirmed in this belief by a little circumstance, apparently slight and trivial in itself, but when considered in this point of view, not undeserving of notice. In Mr. Pickwick's note-book, we can just trace an entry of the fact, that the places of himself and followers were booked by the Norwich coach; but this entry was afterwards lined through, as if for the purpose of concealing even the direction in which the borough is situated. We will not, therefore, hazard a guess upon the subject, but will at once proceed with this history; content with the materials which its characters have provided for us.</p><p >It appears, then, that the Eatanswill people, like the people of many other small towns, considered themselves of the utmost and most mighty importance, and that every man in Eatanswill, conscious of the weight that attached to his example, felt himself bound to unite, heart and soul, with one of the two great parties that divided the town—the Blues and the Buffs. Now the Blues lost no opportunity of opposing the Buffs, and the Buffs lost no opportunity of opposing the Blues; and the consequence was, that whenever the Buffs and Blues met together at public meeting, Town-Hall, fair, or market, disputes and high words arose between them. With these dissensions it is almost superfluous to say that every thing in Eatanswill was made a party-question. If the Buffs proposed to new skylight the market-place, the Blues got up public
<pb xml:id="p121"/>
meetings, and denounced the proceeding; if the Blues proposed the erection of an additional pump in the High Street, the Buffs rose as one man and stood aghast at the enormity. There were Blue shops and Buff shops, Blue inns and Buff inns;—there was a Blue aisle and a Buff aisle, in the very church itself.</p><p >Of course it was essentially and indispensably necessary that each of these powerful parties should have its chosen organ and representative: and, accordingly, there were two newspapers in the town—the Eatanswill Gazette and the Eatanswill Independent; the former advocating Blue principles, and the latter conducted on grounds decidedly Buff. Fine newspapers they were. Such leading articles, and such spirited attacks!—“Our worthless contemporary the Gazette”—“That disgraceful and dastardly journal, the Independent”—“That false and scurrilous print, the Independent”—“That vile and slanderous calumniator, the Gazette;”—these, and other spirit-stirring denunciations were strewn plentifully over the columns of each, in every number, and excited feelings of the most intense delight and indignation in the bosoms of the townspeople.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick, with his usual foresight and sagacity, had chosen a peculiarly desirable moment for his visit to the borough. Never was such a contest known. The Honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall, was the Blue candidate; and Horatio Fizkin, Esq., of Fizkin Lodge, near Eatanswill, had been prevailed upon by his friends to stand forward on the Buff interest. The Gazette warned the electors of Eatanswill that the eyes not only of England, but of the whole civilised world, were upon them; and the Independent imperatively demanded to know, whether the constituency of Eatanswill were the grand fellows they had always taken them for, or base and servile tools, undeserving alike of the name of Englishmen and the blessings of freedom. Never had such a commotion agitated the town before.</p><p >It was late in the evening, when Mr. Pickwick and his companions, assisted by Sam, dismounted from the roof of the Eatanswill coach. Large blue silk flags were flying from the windows of the Town Arms Inn, and bills were posted in every sash, intimating, in gigantic letters, that the honourable Samuel Slumkey's Committee sat there daily. A crowd of idlers were assembled in the road, looking at a hoarse man in the balcony, who was apparently talking himself very red in the face in Mr. Slumkey's behalf; but the force and point of whose arguments were somewhat impaired by the perpetual beating of four large drums which Mr. Fizkin's committee had stationed at the street corner. There was a busy little man beside him, though, who took off his hat at intervals and motioned to the people to cheer, which they regularly did, most enthusiastically; and as the red-faced gentleman went on talking till he was redder in the face than ever, it seemed to answer his purpose quite as well as if anybody had heard him.</p><p >The Pickwickians had no sooner dismounted, than they were surrounded by a branch mob of the honest and independent, who forthwith set up three deafening cheers, which being responded to by the main body (for it's not at all necessary for a crowd to know what they are
<pb xml:id="p122"/>
cheering about) swelled into a tremendous roar of triumph, which stopped even the red-faced man in the balcony.</p><p >“Hurrah!” shouted the mob in conclusion.</p><p >“One cheer more,” screamed the little fugleman in the balcony; and out shouted the mob again, as if lungs were cast iron, with steel works.</p><p >“Slumkey for ever!” roared the honest and independent.</p><p >“Slumkey for ever!” echoed Mr. Pickwick, taking off his hat.</p><p >“No Fizkin,” roared the crowd.</p><p >“Certainly not,” shouted Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Hurrah!” And then there was another roaring, like that of a whole menagerie when the elephant has rung the bell for the cold meat.</p><p >“Who is Slumkey?” whispered Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“I don't know,” replied Mr. Pickwick in the same tone. “Hush. Don't ask any questions. It's always best on these occasions to do what the mob do.”</p><p >“But suppose there are two mobs?” suggested Mr. Snodgrass.</p><p >“Shout with the largest,” replied Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >Volumes could not have said more.</p><p >They entered the house, the crowd opening right and left to let them pass, and cheering vociferously. The first object of consideration was to secure quarters for the night.</p><p >“Can we have beds here?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, summoning the waiter.</p><p >“Don't know, Sir,” replied the man; “afraid we're full, Sir—I'll inquire, sir.” Away he went for that purpose, and presently returned, to ask whether the gentlemen were “Blue.”</p><p >As neither Mr. Pickwick nor his companions took any vital interest in the cause of either candidate, the question was rather a difficult one to answer. In this dilemma Mr. Pickwick bethought himself of his new friend, Mr. Perker.</p><p >“Do you know a gentleman of the name of Perker?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Certainly, Sir; honourable Mr. Samuel Slumkey's agent.”</p><p >“He is Blue, I think?”</p><p >“Oh yes, Sir.”</p><p >“Then <hi rend="italics">we</hi> are Blue,” said Mr. Pickwick; but observing that the man looked rather doubtful at this accommodating announcement, he gave him his card, and desired him to present it to Mr. Perker forthwith, if he should happen to be in the house. The waiter retired; and reappearing almost immediately with a request that Mr. Pickwick would follow him, led the way to a large room on the first floor, where, seated at a long table covered with books and papers, was Mr. Perker.</p><p >“Ah—ah my dear Sir,” said the little man, advancing to meet him; “very happy to see you, my dear Sir, very. Pray sit down. So you have carried your intention into effect. You have come down here to see an election—eh?”</p><p >Mr. Pickwick replied in the affirmative.</p><p >“Spirited contest, my dear Sir,” said the little man.</p><pb  xml:id="p123"/><p >“I am delighted to hear it,” said Mr. Pickwick, rubbing his hands “I like to see sturdy patriotism, on whatever side it is called forth;—and so it's a spirited contest?”</p><p >“Oh yes,” said the little man, “very much so indeed. We have opened all the public houses in the place, and left our adversary nothing but the beer-shops—masterly stroke of policy that, my dear Sir, eh?”—and the little man smiled complacently, and took a large pinch of snuff.</p><p >“And what are the probabilities as to the result of the contest?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Why doubtful, my dear Sir; rather doubtful as yet,” replied the little man. “Fizkin's people have got three-and-thirty voters in the lock-up coach-house at the White Hart.”</p><p >“In the coach-house!” said Mr. Pickwick, considerably astonished by this second stroke of policy.</p><p >“They keep 'em locked up there, till they want 'em,” resumed the little man. “The effect of that is, you see, to prevent our getting at them; and even if we could, it would be of no use, for they keep them very drunk on purpose. Smart fellow Fizkin's agent—very smart fellow indeed.”</p><p >Mr. Pickwick stared, but said nothing.</p><p >“We are pretty confident, though,” said Mr. Perker, sinking his voice almost to a whisper. “We had a little tea-party here, last night—five-and-forty women, my dear Sir—and gave every one of 'em a green parasol when she went away.”</p><p >“A parasol!” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Fact, my dear Sir, fact. Five-and-forty green parasols, at seven and six-pence a-piece. All women like finery,—extraordinary the effect of those parasols. Secured all their husbands, and half their brothers—beats stockings, and flannel, and all that sort of thing hollow. My idea, my dear Sir, entirely. Hail, rain, or sunshine, you can't walk half a dozen yards up the street, without encountering half a dozen green parasols.”</p><p >Here the little man indulged in a convulsion of mirth, which was only checked by the entrance of a third party.</p><p >This was a tall, thin man, with a sandy-coloured head inclined to baldness, and a face in which solemn importance was blended with a look of unfathomable profundity. He was dressed in a long brown surtout, with a black cloth waistcoat, and drab trousers. A double eye-glass dangled at his waistcoat: and on his head he wore a very low-crowned hat with a broad brim. The new comer was introduced to Mr. Pickwick as Mr. Pott, the editor of the Eatanswill Gazette. After a few preliminary remarks, Mr. Pott turned round to Mr. Pickwick, and said with solemnity—</p><p >“This contest excites great interest in the metropolis, Sir?”</p><p >“I believe it does,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“To which I have reason to know,” said Pott, looking towards Mr. Perker for corroboration,—“to which I have reason to know my article of last Saturday in some degree contributed.”</p><pb  xml:id="p124"/><p >“Not the least doubt of that,” said the little man.</p><p >“The press is a mighty engine, Sir,” said Pott.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick yielded his fullest assent to the proposition.</p><p >“But I trust, Sir,” said Pott, “that I have never abused the enormous power I wield. I trust, Sir, that I have never pointed the noble instrument which is placed in my hands, against the sacred bosom of private life, or the tender breast of individual reputation;—I trust, Sir, that I have devoted my energies to—to endeavours—humble they may be, humble I know they are—to instil those principles of—which—are—”</p><p >Here the editor of the Eatanswill Gazette, appearing to ramble, Mr. Pickwick came to his relief, and said—</p><p >“Certainly.”</p><p >“And what, Sir”—said Pott—“what, Sir, let me ask you as an impartial man, is the state of the public mind in London, with reference to my contest with the Independent?”</p><p >“Greatly excited, no doubt,” interposed Mr. Perker, with a look of slyness which was very likely accidental.</p><p >“That contest,” said Pott, “shall be prolonged so long as I have health and strength, and that portion of talent with which I am gifted. From that contest, Sir, although it may unsettle men's minds and excite their feelings, and render them incapable for the discharge of the everyday duties of ordinary life; from that contest, Sir, I will never shrink, till I have set my heel upon the Eatanswill Independent. I wish the people of London, and the people of this country to know, Sir, that they may rely upon me;—that I will not desert them, that I am resolved to stand by them, Sir, to the last.”</p><p >“Your conduct is most noble, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick; and he grasped the hand of the magnanimous Pott.</p><p >“You are, Sir, I perceive, a man of sense and talent,” said Mr. Pott, almost breathless with the vehemence of his patriotic declaration. “I am most happy, Sir, to make the acquaintance of such a man.”</p><p >“And I,” said Mr. Pickwick, “feel deeply honoured by this expression of your opinion. Allow me, Sir, to introduce you to my fellow-travellers, the other corresponding members of the club I am proud to have founded.”</p><p >“I shall be delighted,” said Mr. Pott.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick withdrew, and returning with his three friends, presented them in due form to the editor of the Eatanswill Gazette.</p><p >“Now my dear Pott,” said little Mr. Perker, “the question is, what are we to do with our friends here?”</p><p >“We can stop in this house, I suppose,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Not a spare bed in the house, my dear Sir—not a single bed.”</p><p >“Extremely awkward,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Very;” said his fellow-voyagers.</p><p >“I have an idea upon this subject,” said Mr. Pott, “which I think may be very successfully adopted. They have two beds at the Peacock, and I can boldly say, on behalf of Mrs. Pott, that she will be delighted to accommodate Mr. Pickwick and any one of his friends, if the other
<pb xml:id="p125"/>
two gentlemen and their servant do not object to shifting, as they best can, at the Peacock.”</p><p >After repeated pressings on the part of Mr. Pott, and repeated protestations on that of Mr. Pickwick that he could not think of incommoding or troubling his amiable wife, it was decided that this was the only feasible arrangement that could be made. So it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> made; and after dining together at the Town Arms, the friends separated, Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass repairing to the Peacock, and Mr. Pickwick and Mr. Winkle proceeding to the mansion of Mr. Pott; it having been previously arranged that they should all re-assemble at the Town Arms in the morning, and accompany the honourable Samuel Slumkey's procession to the place of nomination.</p><p >Mr. Pott's domestic circle was limited to himself and his wife. All men whom mighty genius has raised to a proud eminence in the world, have usually some little weakness which appears the more conspicuous from the contrast it presents to their general character. If Mr. Pott had a weakness, it was, perhaps, that he was <hi rend="italics">rather</hi> too submissive to the somewhat contemptuous controul and sway of his wife. We do not feel justified in laying any particular stress upon the fact, because on the present occasion all Mrs. Pott's most winning ways were brought into requisition to receive the two gentlemen.</p><p >“My dear,” said Mr. Pott, “Mr. Pickwick—Mr. Pickwick of London.”</p><p >Mrs. Pott received Mr. Pickwick's paternal grasp of the hand with enchanting sweetness: and Mr. Winkle, who had not been announced at all, slided and bowed, unnoticed, in an obscure corner.</p><p >“P. my dear—” said Mrs. Pott.</p><p >“My life,” said Mr. Pott.</p><p >“Pray introduce the other gentleman.”</p><p >“I beg a thousand pardons,” said Mr. Pott. “Permit me—Mrs. Pott, Mr. —”</p><p >“Winkle,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Winkle,” echoed Mr. Pott; and the ceremony of introduction was complete.</p><p >“We owe you many apologies, Ma'am,” said Mr. Pickwick, “for disturbing your domestic arrangements at so short a notice.”</p><p >“I beg you won't mention it, Sir,” replied the feminine Pott, with vivacity. “It is a high treat to me, I assure you, to see any new faces; living as I do, from day to day, and week to week, in this dull place, and seeing nobody.”</p><p >“Nobody, my dear!” exclaimed Mr. Pott, archly.</p><p >“Nobody but <hi rend="italics">you,</hi>” retorted Mrs. Pott, with asperity.</p><p >“You see, Mr. Pickwick,” said the host in explanation of his wife's lament, “that we are in some measure cut off from many enjoyments and pleasures of which we might otherwise partake. My public station, as editor of the Eatanswill Gazette, the position which that paper holds in the country, my constant immersion in the vortex of politics—”</p><p >“P. my dear—” interposed Mrs. Pott.</p><p >“My life—” said the editor.</p><pb  xml:id="p126"/><p >“I wish, my dear, you would endeavour to find some topic of conversation in which these gentlemen might take some rational interest.”</p><p >“But my love,” said Mr. Pott, with great humility, “Mr. Pickwick does take an interest in it.”</p><p >“It's well for him if he can,” said Mrs. Pott, emphatically; “I am wearied out of my life with your politics, and quarrels with the Independent, and nonsense. I am quite astonished P. at your making such an exhibition of your absurdity.”</p><p >“But my dear—” said Mr. Pott.</p><p >“Oh, nonsense, don't talk to me;” said Mrs. Pott. “Do you play <hi rend="italics">écarte,</hi> Sir?”</p><p >“I shall be very happy to learn, under your tuition,” replied Mr. Winkle.</p><p >“Well, then, draw that little table into this window, and let me get out of hearing of those prosy politics.”</p><p >“Jane,” said Mr. Pott, to the servant who brought in candles, “go down into the office, and bring me up the file of the Gazette for Eighteen Hundred and Twenty Eight. I'll just read you—” added the editor, turning to Mr. Pickwick, “I'll just read you a few of the leaders I wrote at that time, upon the Buff job of appointing a new tollman to the turnpike here; I rather think they'll amuse you.”</p><p >“I should like to hear them very much, indeed,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >Up came the file, and down sat the editor, with Mr. Pickwick at his side.</p><p >We have in vain pored over the leaves of Mr. Pickwick's note-book, in the hope of meeting with a general summary of these beautiful compositions. We have every reason to believe that he was perfectly enraptured with the vigour and freshness of the style; indeed Mr. Winkle has recorded the fact that his eyes were closed, as if with excess of pleasure, during the whole time of their perusal.</p><p >The announcement of supper put a stop both to the game at écarte, and the recapitulation of the beauties of the Eatanswill Gazette. Mrs. Pott was in the highest spirits and the most agreeable humour. Mr. Winkle had already made considerable progress in her good opinion, and she did not hesitate to inform him, confidentially, that Mr. Pickwick was “a delightful old dear.” These terms convey a familiarity of expression, in which few of those who were intimately acquainted with that colossal-minded man, would have presumed to indulge. We have preserved them, nevertheless, as affording at once a touching and a convincing proof of the estimation in which he was held by every class of society, and the ease with which he made his way to their hearts and feelings.</p><p >It was a late hour of the night—long after Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass had fallen asleep in the inmost recesses of the Peacock—when the two friends retired to rest. Slumber soon fell upon the senses of Mr. Winkle, but his feelings had been excited, and his admiration roused; and for many hours after sleep had rendered him insensible to earthly objects, the face and figure of the agreeable Mrs. Pott presented themselves again and again to his wandering imagination.</p><pb  xml:id="p127"/><p >The noise and bustle which ushered in the morning, were sufficient to dispel from the mind of the most romantic visionary in existence, any associations but those which were immediately connected with the rapidly-approaching election. The beating of drums, the blowing of horns and trumpets, the shouting of men, and tramping of horses, echoed and re-echoed through the streets from the earliest dawn of day; and an occasional fight between the light skirmishers of either party, at once enlivened the preparations, and agreeably diversified their character.</p><p >“Well, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, as his valet appeared at his bedroom door, just as he was concluding his toilet; “all alive to-day, I suppose?”</p><p >“Reg'lar game, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller; “our people's a col-lecting down at the Town Arms, and they're a hollering themselves hoarse already.”</p><p >“Ah,” said Mr. Pickwick, “do they seem devoted to their party, Sam?”</p><p >“Never see such dewotion in my life, Sir.”</p><p >“Energetic, eh?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Uncommon,” replied Sam; “I never see men eat and drink so much afore. I wonder they a'nt afeer'd o' bustin.”</p><p >“That's the mistaken kindness of the gentry here,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Werry likely,” replied Sam, briefly.</p><p >“Fine, fresh, hearty fellows they seem,” said Mr. Pickwick, glancing from the window.</p><p >“Werry fresh,” replied Sam; “me, and the two waiters at the Peacock, has been a pumpin' over the independent woters as supped there last night.”</p><p >“Pumping over independent voters!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Yes,” said his attendant, “every man slept vere he fell down; we dragged 'em out, one by one, this mornin' and put 'em under the pump, and they're in reg'lar fine order, now. Shillin' a head the committee paid for that 'ere job.”</p><p >“Can such things be!” exclaimed the astonished Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Lord bless your heart, Sir,” said Sam, “why where was you half baptized?—that's nothin', that a'nt.”</p><p >“Nothing?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Nothin' at all, Sir,” replied his attendant. “The night afore th last day o' the last election here, the opposite party bribed the bar-maid at the Town Arms, to hocus the brandy and water of fourteen unpolled electors as was a stoppin' in the house.”</p><p >“What do you mean by ‘hocussing’ brandy and water?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Puttin' laud'num in it,” replied Sam. “Blessed if she didn't send 'em all to sleep till twelve hours arter the election was over. They took one man up to the booth, in a truck, fast asleep, by way of experiment, but it was no go—they wouldn't poll him; so they brought him back, and put him to bed again.”</p><pb  xml:id="p128"/><p >“Strange practices, these,” said Mr. Pickwick; half speaking to himself, and half addressing Sam.</p><p >“Not half so strange as a miraculous circumstance as happened to my own father, at an election-time, in this wery place, Sir,” replied Sam.</p><p >“What was that?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Why he drove a coach down here once,” said Sam; “ 'Lection time came on, and he was engaged by vun party to bring down woters from London. Night afore he was a going to drive up, committee on t'other side sends for him quietly, and away he goes vith the messenger, who shows him in;—large room—lots of gen'l'm'n—heaps of papers, pens and ink, and all that 'ere. ‘Ah, Mr. Weller,’ says the gen'l'm'n in the chair, ‘glad to see you, Sir; how are you?’—‘Werry well, thank'ee, Sir,’ says my father; ‘I hope <hi rend="italics">you're</hi> pretty middlin,’ says he—‘Pretty well, thank'ee, Sir,’ says the gen'l'm'n; ‘sit down, Mr. Weller—pray sit down, sir.’ So my father sits down, and he and the gen'l'm'n looks wery hard at each other. ‘You don't remember me?’ says the gen'l'm'n?—‘Can't say I do,’ says my father—‘Oh, I know you,’ says the gen'l'm'n; ‘know'd you ven you was a boy,’ says he.—‘Well, I don't remember you,’ says my father—‘That's wery odd,’ says the gen'l'm'n—‘Wery,’ says my father—‘You must have a bad mem'ry Mr. Weller,’ says the gen'l'm'n—‘Well, it is a wery bad 'un,’ says my father—‘I thought so,’ says the gen'l'm'n. So then they pours him out a glass o' wine, and gammons him about his driving, and gets him into a reg'lar good humour, and at last shoves a twenty pound note in his hand. ‘It's a wery bad road between this and London,’ says the gen'l'm'n—‘Here and there it <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a wery heavy road,’ says my father—‘'Specially near the canal, I think,’ says the gen'l'm'n—‘Nasty bit, that 'ere,’ says my father—‘Well, Mr. Weller,’ says the gen'l'm'n, ‘you're a wery good whip, and can do what you like with your horses, we know. We're all wery fond o' you, Mr. Weller, so in case you <hi rend="italics">should</hi> have an accident when you're a bringing these here woters down, and <hi rend="italics">should</hi> tip 'em over into the canal vithout hurtin' 'em, this is for yourself,’ says he—‘Gen'l'm'n, you're wery kind,’ says my father, ‘and I'll drink your health in another glass of wine,’ says he; vich he did, and then buttons up the money, and bows himself out. You vouldn't believe, Sir,” continued Sam, with a look of inexpressible impudence at his master, “that on the wery day as he came down with them woters, his coach <hi rend="italics">was</hi> upset on that 'ere wery spot, and ev'ry man on 'em was turned into the canal.”</p><p >“And got out again?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, hastily.</p><p >“Why,” replied Sam, very slowly, “I rather think one old gentleman was missin'; I know his hat was found, but I a'n't quite certain whether his head was in it or not. But what I look at, is the hex-traordinary, and wonderful coincidence, that arter what that gen'l'm'n said my father's coach should be upset in that wery place, and on that wery day!”</p><p >“It is, no doubt, a very extraordinary circumstance indeed,” said Mr. Pickwick. “But brush my hat, Sam, for I hear Mr. Winkle calling me to breakfast.”</p><pb  xml:id="p129"/><p >With these words Mr. Pickwick descended to the parlour, where he found breakfast laid, and the family already assembled. The meal was hastily despatched; each of the gentlemen's hats was decorated with an enormous blue favour, made up by the fair hands of Mrs. Pott herself, and as Mr. Winkle had undertaken to escort that lady to a house top, in the immediate vicinity of the hustings, Mr. Pickwick and Mr. Pott repaired alone to the Town Arms, from the back window of which, one of Mr. Slumkey's committee was addressing six small boys, and one girl, whom he dignified, at every second sentence, with the imposing title of “men of Eatanswill,” whereat the six small boys aforesaid cheered prodigiously.</p><p >The stable-yard exhibited unequivocal symptoms of the glory and strength of the Eatanswill Blues. There was a regular army of blue flags, some with one handle, and some with two, exhibiting appropriate devices, in golden characters four feet high, and stout in proportion. There was a grand band of trumpets, bassoons and drums, marshalled four abreast, and earning their money, if ever men did, especially the drum beaters, who were very muscular. There were bodies of constables with blue staves, twenty committee-men with blue scarfs, and a mob of voters with blue cockades. There were electors on horseback, and electors a-foot. There was an open carriage and four, for the honourable Samuel Slumkey; and there were four carriages and pair, for his friends and supporters: and the flags were rustling, and the band was playing, and the constables were swearing, and the twenty committeemen were squabbling, and the mob were shouting, and the horses were backing, and the post-boys perspiring; and everybody, and everything, then and there assembled, was for the special use, behoof, honour, and renown, of the honourable Samuel Slumkey of Slumkey Hall, one of the candidates for the representation of the Borough of Eatanswill, in the Commons House of Parliament of the United Kingdom.</p><p >Loud and long were the cheers, and mighty was the rustling of one of the blue flags, with “Liberty of the Press” inscribed thereon, when the sandy head of Mr. Pott was discerned in one of the windows, by the mob beneath; and tremendous was the enthusiasm when the honourable Samuel Slumkey himself, in top boots, and a blue necker-chief, advanced and seized the hand of the said Pott, and melo-dramatically testified by gestures to the crowd, his ineffaceable obligations to the Eatanswill Gazette.</p><p >“Is everything ready?” said the honourable Samuel Slumkey to Mr. Perker.</p><p >“Everything, my dear Sir,” was the little man's reply.</p><p >“Nothing has been omitted, I hope?” said the honourable Samuel Slumkey.</p><p >“Nothing has been left undone, my dear Sir—nothing whatever. There are twenty washed men at the street door for you to shake hands with; and six children in arms that you're to pat on the  head, and inquire the age of; be particular about the children, my dear Sir,—it has always a great effect, that sort of thing.”</p><p >“I'll take care,” said the honourable Samuel Slumkey.</p><pb  xml:id="p130"/><p >“And, perhaps, my dear Sir—” said the cautious little man, “perhaps if you <hi rend="italics">could</hi>—I don't mean to say it's indispensable—but if you <hi rend="italics">could</hi> manage to kiss one of 'em, it would produce a very great impression on the crowd.”</p><p >“Wouldn't it have as good an effect if the proposer or seconder did that?” said the honourable Samuel Slumkey.</p><p >“Why, I am afraid it wouldn't,” replied the agent; “if it were done by yourself, my dear Sir, I think it would make you very popular.”</p><p >“Very well,” said the honourable Samuel Slumkey, with a resigned air, “then it must be done. That's all.”</p><p >“Arrange the procession,” cried the twenty committee-men.</p><p >Amidst the cheers of the assembled throng, the band, and the constables, and the committee-men, and the voters, and the horsemen, and the carriages, took their places—each of the two-horse vehicles being closely packed with as many gentlemen as could manage to stand upright in it; and that assigned to Mr. Perker, containing Mr. Pickwick, Mr. Tupman, Mr. Snodgrass, and about half a dozen of the committee beside.</p><p >There was a moment of awful suspense as the procession waited for the honourable Samuel Slumkey to step into his carriage. Suddenly the crowd set up a great cheering.</p><p >“He has come out,” said little Mr. Perker, greatly excited; the more so as their position did not enable them to see what was going forward.</p><p >Another cheer, much louder.</p><p >“He has shaken hands with the men,” cried the little agent.</p><p >Another cheer, far more vehement.</p><p >“He has patted the babes on the head,” said Mr. Perker, trembling with anxiety.</p><p >A roar of applause that rent the air.</p><p >“He has kissed one of 'em!” exclaimed the delighted little man.</p><p >A second roar.</p><p >“He has kissed another,” gasped the excited manager.</p><p >A third roar.</p><p >“He's kissing 'em all!” screamed the enthusiastic little gentleman. And hailed by the deafening shouts of the multitude, the procession moved on.</p><p >How or by what means it became mixed up with the other procession, and how it was ever extricated from the confusion consequent thereupon, is more than we can undertake to describe, inasmuch as Mr. Pickwick's hat was knocked over his eyes, nose, and mouth, by one poke of a Buff flag staff, very early in the proceedings. He describes himself as being surrounded on every side, when he could catch a glimpse of the scene, by angry and ferocious countenances, by a vast cloud of dust, and by a dense crowd of combatants. He represents himself as being forced from the carriage by some unseen power, and being personally engaged in a pugilistic encounter; but with whom, or how, or why, he is wholly unable to state. He then felt himself forced up some wooden steps by the persons from behind: and on removing his hat, found himself surrounded by his friends, in the very front of the left hand side of
<pb xml:id="p131"/>
the hustings. The right was reserved for the Buff party, and the centre for the mayor and his officers; one of whom—the fat crier of Eatanswill—was ringing an enormous bell, by way of commanding silence, while Mr. Horatio Fizkin, and the Honourable Samuel Slumkey, with their hands upon their hearts, were bowing with the utmost affability to the troubled sea of heads that inundated the open space in front; and from whence arose a storm of groans, and shouts, and yells, and hootings, that would have done honour to an earthquake.</p><p >“There's Winkle,” said Mr. Tupman, pulling his friend by the sleeve.</p><p >“Where?” said Mr. Pickwick, putting on his spectacles, which he had fortunately kept in his pocket hitherto.</p><p >“There,” said Mr. Tupman, “on the top of that house.” And there sure enough, in the leaden gutter of a tiled roof, were Mr. Winkle and Mrs. Pott, comfortably seated in a couple of chairs, waving their handkerchiefs in token of recognition—a compliment which Mr. Pickwick returned by kissing his hand to the lady.</p><p >The proceedings had not yet commenced; and as an inactive crowd is generally disposed to be jocose, this very innocent action was sufficient to awaken their facetiousness.</p><p >“Oh you wicked old rascal,” cried one voice, “looking arter the girls, are you?”</p><p >“Oh you wenerable sinner,” cried another.</p><p >“Putting on his spectacles to look at a married 'ooman!” said a third.</p><p >“I see him a vinkin' at her, vith his vicked old eye,” shouted a fourth.</p><p >“Look arter your wife, Pott,” bellowed a fifth;—and then there was a roar of laughter.</p><p >As these taunts were accompanied with invidious comparisons between Mr. Pickwick and an aged ram, and several witticisms of the like nature; and as they moreover rather tended to convey reflections upon the honour of an innocent lady, Mr. Pickwick's indignation was excessive; but as silence was proclaimed at the moment, he contented himself by scorching the mob with a look of pity for their misguided minds, at which they laughed more boisterously than ever.</p><p >“Silence,” roared the mayor's attendants.</p><p >“Whiffin, proclaim silence,” said the mayor, with an air of pomp befitting his lofty station. In obedience to this command the crier performed another concerto on the bell, whereupon a gentleman in the crowd called out “muffins;” which occasioned another laugh.</p><p >“Gentlemen,” said the Mayor, at as loud a pitch as he could possibly force his voice to, “Gentlemen. Brother electors of the Borough of Eatanswill. We are met here to-day, for the purpose of choosing a representative in the room of our late—”</p><p >Here the Mayor was interrupted by a voice in the crowd.</p><p >“Suc-cess to the Mayor!” cried the voice, “and may he never desert the nail and sarspan business, as he got his money by.”</p><p >This allusion to the professional pursuits of the orator was received
<pb xml:id="p132"/>
with a storm of delight, which, with a bell-accompaniment, rendered the remainder of his speech inaudible, with the exception of the concluding sentence, in which he thanked the meeting for the patient attention with which they had heard him throughout,—an expression of gratitude which elicited another burst of mirth, of about a quarter of an hour's duration.</p><p >Next, a tall thin gentleman, in a very stiff white neckerchief, after being repeatedly desired by the crowd to “send a boy home, to ask whether he hadn't left his woice under the pillow,” begged to nominate a fit and proper person to represent them in Parliament. And when he said it was Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, near Eatanswill, the Fizkinites applauded, and the Slumkeyites groaned, so long, and so loudly, that both he and the seconder might have sung comic songs in lieu of speaking, without anybody's being a bit the wiser.</p><p >The friends of Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, having had their innings, a little choleric, pink-faced man stood forward to propose another fit and proper person to represent the electors of Eatanswill in Parliament; and very swimmingly the pink-faced gentleman would have got on, if he had not been rather too choleric to entertain a sufficient perception of the fun of the crowd. But after a very few sentences of figurative eloquence, the pink-faced gentleman got from denouncing those who interrupted him in the mob, to exchanging defiances with the gentlemen on the hustings; whereupon arose an uproar which reduced him to the necessity of expressing his feelings by serious pantomime, which he did, and then left the stage to his seconder, who delivered a written speech of half an hour's length, and wouldn't be stopped, because he had sent it all to the Eatanswill Gazette, and the Eatanswill Gazette had printed it, every word.</p><p >Then Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, near Eatanswill, presented himself for the purpose of addressing the electors; which he no sooner did, than the band employed by the honourable Samuel Slumkey, commenced performing with a power to which their strength in the morning was a trifle; in return for which, the Buff crowd belaboured the heads and shoulders of the Blue crowd; on which the Blue crowd endeavoured to dispossess themselves of their very unpleasant neighbours the Buff crowd; and a scene of struggling, and pushing, and fighting, succeeded, to which we can no more do justice than the Mayor could, although he issued imperative orders to twelve constables to seize the ring-leaders, who might amount in number to two hundred and fifty, or thereabouts. At all these encounters, Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, and his friends, waxed fierce and furious; until at last Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, begged to ask his opponent, the honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall, whether that band played by his consent; which question the honourable Samuel Slumkey declining to answer, Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, shook his fist in the countenance of the honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall; upon which the honourable Samuel Slumkey, his blood being up, defied Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, to mortal combat. At this violation of all known rules and precedents of order, the Mayor commanded another fantasia on the bell, and declared that he would
<pb xml:id="p133"/>
bring before himself, both Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, and the honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall, and bind them over to keep the peace. Upon this terrific denunciation, the supporters of the two candidates interfered, and after the friends of each party had quarrelled in pairs for three-quarters of an hour, Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, touched his hat to the honourable Samuel Slumkey: the honourable Samuel Slumkey touched his to Horatio Fizkin, Esquire: the band was stopped, the crowd were partially quieted, and Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, was permitted to proceed.</p><p >The speeches of the two candidates, though differing in every other respect, afforded a beautiful tribute to the merit and high worth of the electors of Eatanswill. Both expressed their opinion that a more independent, a more enlightened, a more public-spirited, a more noble-minded, a more disinterested set of men than those who had promised to vote for him, never existed on earth; each darkly hinted his suspicions that the electors in the opposite interest had certain swinish and besotted infirmities which rendered them unfit for the exercise of the important duties they were called upon to discharge. Fizkin expressed his readiness to do anything he was wanted; Slumkey, his determination to do nothing that was asked of him. Both said that the trade, the manufactures, the commerce, the prosperity, of Eatanswill, would ever be dearer to their hearts than any earthly object; and each had it in his power to state, with the utmost confidence, that he was the man who would eventually be returned.</p><p >There was a show of hands; the Mayor decided in favour of the honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall. Horatio Fizkin, Esquire, of Fizkin Lodge, demanded a poll, and a poll was fixed accordingly. Then a vote of thanks was moved to the Mayor for his able conduct in the chair; and the Mayor devoutly wishing that he had had a chair to display his able conduct in (for he had been standing during the whole proceedings) returned thanks. The processions re-formed, the carriages rolled slowly through the crowd, and its members screeched and shouted after them as their feelings or caprice dictated.</p><p >During the whole time of the polling, the town was in a perpetual fever of excitement. Everything was conducted on the most liberal and delightful scale. Exciseable articles were remarkably cheap at all the public houses; and spring vans paraded the streets for the accommodation of voters who were seized with any temporary dizziness in the head—an epidemic which prevailed among the electors, during the contest, to a most alarming extent, and under the influence of which they might frequently be seen lying on the pavements in a state of utter insensibility. A small body of electors remained unpolled on the very last day. They were calculating and reflecting persons, who had not yet been convinced by the arguments of either party, although they had had frequent conferences with each. One hour before the close of the poll, Mr. Perker solicited the honour of a private interview with these intelligent, these noble, these patriotic men. It was granted His arguments were brief, but satisfactory. They went in a body to the poll; and when they returned, the honourable Samuel Slumkey, of Slumkey Hall, was returned also.</p></div><div type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p134"/><head >CHAPTER XIV.</head><head >COMPRISING A BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE COMPANY AT THE PEACOCK ASSEMBLED; AND A TALE TOLD BY A BAGMAN.</head><p >IT is pleasant to turn from contemplating the strife and turmoil of political existence, to the peaceful repose of private life. Although in reality no great partisan of either side, Mr. Pickwick was sufficiently fired with Mr. Pott's enthusiasm, to apply his whole time and attention to the proceedings, of which the last chapter affords a description compiled from his own memoranda. Nor while he was thus occupied was Mr. Winkle idle, his whole time being devoted to pleasant walks and short country excursions with Mrs. Pott, who never failed, when such an opportunity presented itself, to seek some relief from the tedious monotony she so constantly complained of. The two gentlemen being thus completely domesticated in the Editor's house, Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass were in a great measure cast upon their own resources. Taking but little interest in public affairs, they beguiled their time chiefly with such amusements as the Peacock afforded, which were limited to a bagatelle-board in the first floor, and a sequestered skittle-ground in the back yard. In the science and nicety of both these recreations, which are far more abstruse than ordinary men suppose, they were gradually initiated by Mr. Weller, who possessed a perfect knowledge of such pastimes. Thus, notwithstanding that they were in a great measure deprived of the comfort and advantage of Mr. Pickwick's society, they were still enabled to beguile the time, and to prevent its hanging heavily on their hands.</p><p >It was in the evening, however, that the Peacock presented attractions which enabled the two friends to resist, even the invitations of the talented, though prosily inclined, Mr. Pott. It was in the evening that the “commercial room” was filled with a social circle, whose characters and manners it was the delight of Mr. Tupman to observe; whose sayings and doings it was the habit of Mr. Snodgrass to note down.</p><p >Most people know what sort of places commercial rooms usually are. That of the Peacock differed in no material respect from the generality of such apartments; that is to say, it was a large bare-looking room, the furniture of which had no doubt been better when it was newer, with a spacious table in the centre, and a variety of smaller dittos in the corners: an extensive assortment of variously shaped chairs, and an old Turkey carpet, bearing about the same relative proportion to the size of the room, as a lady's pocket-handkerchief might to the floor of a watch-box. The walls were garnished with one or two large maps; and several weather-beaten rough great coats, with complicated capes,
<pb xml:id="p135"/>
dangled from a long row of pegs in one corner. The mantel-shelf was ornamented with a wooden inkstand, containing one stump of a pen and half a wafer, a road-book and directory, a county history minus the cover, and the mortal remains of a trout in a glass coffin. The atmosphere was redolent of tobacco-smoke, the fumes of which had communicated a rather dingy hue to the whole room, and more especially to the dusty red curtains which shaded the windows. On the sideboard, a variety of miscellaneous articles were huddled together, the most conspicuous of which were some very cloudy fish-sauce cruets, a couple or driving-boxes, two or three whips, and as many travelling shawls, a tray of knives and forks, and the mustard.</p><p >Here it was that Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass were seated on the evening after the conclusion of the election, with several other temporary inmates of the house, smoking and drinking.</p><p >“Well, gents,” said a stout, hale personage of about forty, with only one eye—a very bright black eye, which twinkled with a roguish expression of fun and good humour, “Our noble selves, gents. I always propose that toast to the company, and drink Mary to myself. Eh, Mary?”</p><p >“Get along with you, you wretch,” said the hand-maiden, obviously not ill pleased with the compliment, however.</p><p >“Don't go away, Mary,” said the black-eyed man.</p><p >“Let me alone, imperence,” said the young lady.</p><p >“Never mind,” said the one-eyed man, calling after the girl as she left the room. “I'll step out by and by, Mary. Keep your spirits up, dear.” Here he went through the not very difficult process of winking upon the company with his solitary eye, to the enthusiastic delight of an elderly personage with a dirty face and a clay pipe.</p><p >“Rum creeters is women,” said the dirty-faced man, after a pause.</p><p >“Ah! no mistake about that,” said a very red-faced man, behind a cigar.</p><p >After this little bit of philosophy there was another pause.</p><p >“There's rummer things than women in this world though, mind you,” said the man with the black eye, slowly filling a large Dutch pipe, with a most capacious bowl.</p><p >“Are you married?” inquired the dirty-faced man.</p><p >“Can't say I am.”</p><p >“I thought not.” Here the dirty-faced man fell into extasies of mirth at his own retort, in which he was joined by a man of bland voice and placid countenance, who always made it a point to agree with everybody.</p><p >“Women after all, gentlemen,” said the enthusiastic Mr. Snodgrass, “are the great props and comforts of our existence.”</p><p >“So they are,” said the placid gentleman.</p><p >“When they're in a good humour,” interposed the dirty-faced man.</p><p >“And that's very true,” said the placid one.</p><p >“I repudiate that qualification,” said Mr. Snodgrass, whose thoughts were fast reverting to Emily Wardle, “I repudiate it with disdain—with indignation. Show me the man who says anything against women, as
<pb xml:id="p136"/>
women, and I boldly declare he is not a man.” And Mr. Snodgrass took his cigar from his mouth, and struck the table violently with his clenched fist.</p><p >“That's good sound argument,” said the placid man.</p><p >“Containing a position which I deny,” interrupted he of the dirty countenance.</p><p >“And there's certainly a very great deal of truth in what you observe too, Sir,” said the placid gentleman.</p><p >“Your health, Sir,” said the bagman with the lonely eye, bestowing an approving nod on Mr. Snodgrass.</p><p >Mr. Snodgrass acknowledged the compliment.</p><p >“I always like to hear a good argument,” continued the bagman, “a sharp one, like this; it's very improving; but this little argument about women brought to my mind a story I have heard an old uncle of mine tell, the recollection of which, just now, made me say there were rummer things than women to be met with, sometimes.”</p><p >“I should like to hear that same story,” said tho red-faced man with the cigar.</p><p >“Should you?” was the only reply of the bagman, who continued to smoke with great vehemence.</p><p >“So should I,” said Mr. Tupman, speaking for the first time. He was always anxious to increase his stock of experience.</p><p >“Should <hi rend="italics">you?</hi> Well then, I'll tell it. No I won't. I know you won't believe it,” said the man with the roguish eye, making that organ look more roguish than ever.</p><p >“If you say it's true, of course I shall,” said Mr. Tupman.</p><p >“Well, upon that understanding I'll tell it,” replied the traveller. “Did you ever hear of the great commercial house of Bilson and Slum? But it doesn't matter though, whether you did or not, because they retired from business long since. It's eighty years ago, since the circumstance happened to a traveller for that house, but he was a particular friend of my uncle's: and my uncle told the story to me. It's a queer name; but he used to call it </p><quote><floatingText><body ><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="quote"><head > THE BAGMAN'S STORY, </head><p > and he used to tell it, something in this way.</p><p >“One winter's evening, about five o'clock, just as it began to grow dusk, a man in a gig might have been seen urging his tired horse along the road which leads across Marlborough Downs, in the direction of Bristol. I say he might have been seen, and I have no doubt he would have been, if anybody but a blind man had happened to pass that way; but the weather was so bad, and the night so cold and wet, that nothing was out but the water, and so the traveller jogged along in the middle of the road, lonesome and dreary enough. If any bagman of that day could have caught sight of the little neck-or-nothing sort of gig, with a clay-coloured body and red wheels, and the vixenish illtempered, fast-going bay mare, that looked like a cross between a butcher's horse and a twopenny post-office pony, he would have known at once, that this traveller could have been no other than Tom
<pb xml:id="p137"/>
Smart, of the great house of Bilson and Slum, Cateaton Street, City. However, as there was no bagman to look on, nobody knew anything at all about the matter; and so Tom Smart and his clay-coloured gig with the red wheels, and the vixenish mare with the fast pace, went on together, keeping the secret among them, and nobody was a bit the wiser.</p><p >“There are many pleasanter places even in this dreary world, than Marlborough Downs when it blows hard; and if you throw in beside, a gloomy winter's evening, a miry and sloppy road, and a pelting fall of heavy rain, and try the effect, by way of experiment, in your own proper person, you will experience the full force of this observation.</p><p >“The wind blew—not up the road or down it, though that's bad enough, but sheer across it, sending the rain slanting down like the lines they used to rule in the copybooks at school, to make the boys slope well. For a moment it would die away, and the traveller would begin to delude himself into the belief that, exhausted with its previous fury, it had quietly lain itself down to rest, when, whoo! he would hear it growling and whistling in the distance, and on it would come rushing over the hill-tops, and sweeping along the plain, gathering sound and strength as it drew nearer, until it dashed with a heavy gust against horse and man, driving the sharp rain into their ears, and its cold damp breath into their very bones; and past them it would scour, far, far away, with a stunning roar, as if in ridicule of their weakness, and triumphant in the consciousness of its own strength and power.</p><p >“The bay mare splashed away, through the mud and water, with drooping ears, now and then tossing her head as if to express her disgust at this very ungentlemanly behaviour of the elements, but keeping a good pace notwithstanding, until a gust of wind, more furious than any that had yet assailed them, caused her to stop suddenly, and plant her four feet firmly against the ground, to prevent her being blown over. It's a special mercy that she did this, for if she <hi rend="italics">had</hi> been blown over, the vixenish mare was so light, and the gig was so light, and Tom Smart such a light weight into the bargain, that they must infallibly have all gone rolling over and over together, until they reached the confines of earth, or until the wind fell; and in either case the probability is, that neither the vixenish mare, nor the clay-coloured gig with the red wheels, nor Tom Smart, would ever have been fit for service again.</p><p >“ ‘Well, damn my straps and whiskers,’ says Tom Smart, (Tom sometimes had an unpleasant knack of swearing), ‘Damn my straps and whiskers,’ says Tom, ‘if this ain't pleasant, blow me.’</p><p >“You'll very likely ask me, why, as Tom Smart had been pretty well blown already, he expressed this wish to be submitted to the same process again. I can't say—all I know is, that Tom Smart said so—or at least he always told my uncle he said so, and it's just the same thing.</p><p >“ ‘Blow me,’ says Tom Smart; and the mare neighed as if she were precisely of the same opinion.</p><p >“ ‘Cheer up old girl,’ said Tom, patting the bay mare on the neck with the end of his whip. ‘It won't do pushing on, such a night as
<pb xml:id="p138"/>
this; the first house we come to we'll put up at, so the faster you go the sooner it's over. Soho, old girl—gently—gently.’</p><p >“Whether the vixenish mare was sufficiently well acquainted with the tones of Tom's voice to comprehend his meaning, or whether she found it colder standing still than moving on, of course I can't say. But I can say that Tom had no sooner finished speaking, than she pricked up her ears, and started forward at a speed which made the clay-coloured gig rattle till you would have supposed every one of the red spokes was going to fly out on the turf of Marlborough Downs; and even Tom, whip as he was, couldn't stop or check her pace, until she drew up, of her own accord, before a road-side inn on the right-hand side of the way, about half a quarter of a mile from the end of the Downs.</p><p >“Tom cast a hasty glance at the upper part of the house as he threw the reins to the hostler, and stuck the whip in the box. It was a strange old place, built of a kind of shingle, inlaid, as it were, with cross-beams, with gable-topped windows projecting completely over the pathway, and a low door with a dark porch, and a couple of steep steps leading down into the house, instead of the modern fashion of half a dozen shallow ones, leading up to it. It was a comfortable-looking place though, for there was a strong cheerful light in the bar-window, which shed a bright ray across the road, and even lighted up the hedge on the other side; and there was a red flickering light in the opposite window, one moment but faintly discernible, and the next gleaming strongly through the drawn curtains, which intimated that a rousing fire was blazing within. Marking these little evidences with the eye of an experienced traveller, Tom dismounted with as much agility as his half-frozen limbs would permit, and entered the house.</p><p >“In less than five minutes' time, Tom was ensconced in the room opposite the bar—the very room where he had imagined the fire blazing—before a substantial matter-of-fact roaring fire, composed of something short of a bushel of coals, and wood enough to make half a dozen decent gooseberry-bushes, piled half way up the chimney, and roaring and crackling with a sound that of itself would have warmed the heart of any reasonable man. This was comfortable, but this was not all, for a smartly dressed girl, with a bright eye and a neat ankle, was laying a very clean white cloth on the table; and as Tom sat with his slippered feet on the fender, and his back to the open door, he saw a charming prospect of the bar reflected in the glass over the chimney-piece, with delightful rows of green bottles and gold labels, together with jars of pickles and preserves, and cheeses and boiled hams, and rounds of beef, arranged on shelves in the most tempting and delicious array. Well, this was comfortable too; but even this was not all—for in the bar, seated at tea at the nicest possible little table, drawn close up before the brightest possible little fire, was a buxom widow of somewhere about eight and forty or thereabouts, with a face as comfortable as the bar, who was evidently the landlady of the house, and the supreme ruler over all these agreeable possessions. There was only one drawback to the beauty of the whole picture, and that
<pb xml:id="p139"/>
was a tall man—a very tall man—in a brown coat and bright basket buttons, and black whiskers, and wavy black hair, who was seated at tea with the widow, and who it required no great penetration to discover was in a fair way of persuading her to be a widow no longer, but to confer upon him the privilege of sitting down in that bar, for and during the whole remainder of the term of his natural life.</p><p >“Tom Smart was by no means of an irritable or envious disposition, but somehow or other the tall man with the brown coat and the bright basket buttons did rouse what little gall he had in his composition, and did make him feel extremely indignant, the more especially as he could now and then observe, from his seat before the glass, certain little affectionate familiarities passing between the tall man and the widow, which sufficiently denoted that the tall man was as high in favour as he was in size. Tom was fond of hot punch—I may venture to say he was <hi rend="italics">very</hi> fond of hot punch—and after he had seen the vixenish mare well fed and well littered down, and eaten every bit of the nice little hot dinner which the widow tossed up for him with her own hands, he just ordered a tumbler of it, by way of experiment. Now if there was one thing in the whole range of domestic art, which the widow could manufacture better than another, it was this identical article; and the first tumbler was adapted to Tom Smart's taste with such peculiar nicety, that he ordered a second with the least possible delay. Hot punch is a pleasant thing, gentlemen—an extremely pleasant thing under any circumstances—but in that snug old parlour, before the roaring fire, with the wind blowing outside till every timber in the old house creaked again, Tom Smart found it perfectly delightful. He ordered another tumbler, and then another—I am not quite certain whether he didn't order another after that—but the more he drank of the hot punch the more he thought of the tall man.</p><p >“‘Confound his impudence,’ said Tom Smart to himself, ‘what business has he in that snug bar? Such an ugly villain too!’ said Tom. ‘If the widow had any taste, she might surely pick up some better fellow than that.’ Here Tom's eye wandered from the glass on the chimney-piece, to the glass on the table, and as he felt himself becoming gradually sentimental, he emptied the fourth tumbler of punch and ordered a fifth.</p><p >“Tom Smart, gentlemen, had always been very much attached to the public line. It had long been his ambition to stand in a bar of his own, in a green coat, knee-cords, and tops. He had a great notion of taking the chair at convivial dinners, and he had often thought how well he could preside in a room of his own in the talking way, and what a capital example he could set to his customers in the drinking department. All these things passed rapidly through Tom's mind as he sat drinking the hot punch by the roaring fire, and he felt very justly and properly indignant that the tall man should be in a fair way of keeping such an excellent house, while he, Tom Smart, was as far off from it as ever. So, after deliberating over the two last tumblers, whether he hadn't a perfect right to pick a quarrel with the tall man for having contrived to get into the good graces of the buxom widow, Tom Smart
<pb xml:id="p140"/>
at last arrived at the satisfactory conclusion that he was a very ill-used and persecuted individual, and had better go to bed.</p><p >“Up a wide and ancient staircase the smart girl preceded Tom, shading the chamber candle with her hand, to protect it from the currents of air which in such a rambling old place might have found plenty of room to disport themselves in, without blowing the candle out, but which did blow it out nevertheless; thus affording Tom's enemies an opportunity of asserting that it was he, and not the wind, who extinguished the candle, and that while he pretended to be blowing it a-light again, he was in fact kissing the girl. Be this as it may, another light was obtained, and Tom was conducted through a maze of rooms, and a labyrinth of passages, to the apartment which had been prepared for his reception, where the girl bid him good night, and left him alone.</p><p >“It was a good large room with big closets, and a bed which might have served for a whole boarding-school, to say nothing of a couple of oaken presses that would have held the baggage of a small army; but what struck Tom's fancy most, was a strange, grim-looking, high-backed chair, carved in the most fantastic manner, with a flowered damask cushion, and the round knobs at the bottom of the legs carefully tied up in red cloth, as if it had got the gout in its toes. Of any other queer chair, Tom would only have thought it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> a queer chair, and there would have been an end of the matter; but there was something about this particular chair, and yet he couldn't tell what it was, so odd and so unlike any other piece of furniture he had ever seen, that it seemed to fascinate him. He sat down before the fire, and stared at the old chair for half an hour ;—Damn the chair, it was such a strange old thing, he couldn't take his eyes off it.</p><p >“‘Well,’ said Tom, slowly undressing himself, and staring at the old chair all the while, which stood with a mysterious aspect by the bed-side, ‘I never saw such a rum concern as that in my days. Very odd,’ said Tom, who had got rather sage with the hot punch, ‘Very odd.’ Tom shook his head with an air of profound wisdom, and looked at the chair again. He couldn't make anything of it though, so he got into bed, covered himself up warm, and fell asleep.</p><p >“In about half an hour, Tom woke up with a start, from a confused dream of tall men and tumblers of punch: and the first object that presented itself to his waking imagination was the queer chair.</p><p >“‘I won't look at it any more,’ said Tom to himself, and he squeezed his eyelids together, and tried to persuade himself he was going to sleep again. No use; nothing but queer chairs danced before his eyes, kicking up their legs, jumping over each other's backs, and playing all kinds of antics.</p><p >“‘I may as well see one real chair, as two or three complete sets of false ones,’ said Tom, bringing out his head from under the bed-clothes. There it was, plainly discernible by the light of the fire, looking as provoking as ever.</p><p >“Tom gazed at the chair; and, suddenly as he looked at it, a most extraordinary change seemed to come over it. The carving of the back gradually assumed the lineaments and expression of an old, shrivelled
<pb xml:id="p141"/>
human face; the damask cushion became an antique, flapped waistcoat; the round knobs grew into a couple of feet, encased in red cloth slippers, and the whole chair looked like a very ugly old man, of the previous century, with his arms a-kimbo. Tom sat up in bed, and rubbed his eyes to dispel the illusion. No. The chair was an ugly old gentleman; and what was more, he was winking at Tom Smart.</p><p >“Tom was naturally a headlong, careless sort of dog, and he had had five tumblers of hot punch into the bargain; so, although he was a little startled at first, he began to grow rather indignant when he saw the old gentleman winking and leering at him with such an impudent air. At length he resolved that he wouldn't stand it; and as the old face still kept winking away as fast as ever, Tom said, in a very angry tone—</p><p >“‘What the devil are you winking at me for?’</p><p >“‘Because I like it, Tom Smart,’ said the chair; or the old gentleman, whichever you like to call him. He stopped winking though, when Tom spoke, and began grinning like a superannuated monkey.</p><p >“‘How do you know my name, old nut-cracker face?’ inquired Tom Smart, rather staggered;—though he pretended to carry it off so well.</p><p >“‘Come, come Tom,’ said the old gentleman, ‘that's not the way to address solid Spanish Mahogany. Dam'me, you couldn't treat me with less respect if I was veneered.’ When the old gentleman said this, he looked so fierce that Tom began to grow frightened.</p><p >“‘I didn't mean to treat you with any disrespect, Sir,’ said Tom; in a much humbler tone than he had spoken in at first.</p><p >“‘Well, well,’  said the old fellow, ‘perhaps not—perhaps not. Tom—’</p><p >“‘Sir—’</p><p >“‘I know everything about you, Tom; everything. You're very poor Tom.’</p><p >“‘I certainly am,’ said Tom Smart. ‘But how came you to know that?’</p><p >“‘Never mind that,’ said the old gentleman; ‘you're much too fond of punch, Tom.’</p><p >“Tom Smart was just on the point of protesting that he hadn't tasted a drop since his last birth-day, but when his eye encountered that of the old gentleman, he looked so knowing that Tom blushed, and was silent.</p><p >“‘Tom,’ said the old gentleman, ‘the widow's a fine woman—remarkably fine woman—eh, Tom?’ Here the old fellow screwed up his eyes, cocked up one of his wasted little legs, and looked altogether so unpleasantly amorous, that Tom was quite disgusted with the levity of his behaviour;—at his time of life, too!</p><p >“‘I am her guardian, Tom,’  said the old gentleman.</p><p >“‘Are you?’  inquired Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘I knew her mother, Tom,’  said the old fellow; ‘and her grandmother. She was very fond of me—made me this waistcoat, Tom.”</p><p >“‘Did she?’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘And these shoes,’  said the old fellow, lifting up one of the red-cloth mufflers; ‘but don't mention it, Tom. I shouldn't like to have it known that she was so much attached to me. It might occasion some unpleasantness in the family.’ When the old rascal said this, he
<pb xml:id="p142"/>
looked so extremely impertinent, that, as Tom Smart afterwards declared, he could have sat upon him without remorse.</p><p >“‘I have been a great favourite among the women in my time, Tom, said the profligate old debauchee; ‘hundreds of fine women have sat in my lap for hours together. What do you think of that you dog, eh?’ The old gentleman was proceeding to recount some other exploits of his youth, when he was seized with such a violent fit of creaking that he was unable to proceed.</p><p >“‘Just serves you right, old boy,’ thought Tom Smart; but he didn't say anything.</p><p >“‘Ah!’ said the old fellow, ‘I am a good deal troubled with this now. I am getting old, Tom, and have lost nearly all my rails. I have had an operation performed, too—a small piece let into my back—and I found it a severe trial, Tom.’</p><p >“‘I dare say you did, Sir,’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘However,’ said the old gentleman, ‘that's not the point. Tom, I want you to marry the widow.’</p><p >“‘Me, Sir!’ said Tom.</p><p >“‘You;’ said the old gentleman.</p><p >“‘Bless your reverend locks,’ said Tom—(he had a few scattered horse-hairs left)—“‘bless your reverend locks, she wouldn't have me.’ And Tom sighed involuntarily, as he thought of the bar.</p><p >“‘Wouldn't she?’ said the old gentleman, firmly.</p><p >“‘No, no,’ said Tom; ‘there's somebody else in the wind. A tall man—a confoundedly tall man—with black whiskers.’</p><p >“‘Tom,’ said the old gentleman; ‘she will never have him.’</p><p >“‘Won't she?’ said Tom. ‘If you stood in the bar, old gentleman, you'd tell another story.’</p><p >“‘Pooh, pooh,’ said the old gentleman. ‘I know all about that.’</p><p >“‘About what?’ said Tom.</p><p >“‘The kissing behind the door, and all that sort of thing, Tom,’ said the old gentleman, and here he gave another impudent look, which made Tom very wroth, because as you all know, gentlemen, to hear an old fellow, who ought to know better, talking about these things, is very unpleasant—nothing more so.</p><p >“‘I know all about that, Tom,’ said the old gentleman. ‘I have seen it done very often in my time, Tom, between more people than I should like to mention to you; but it never came to anything after all.’</p><p >“‘You must have seen some queer things,’ said Tom, with an inquisitive look.</p><p >“‘You may say that, Tom,’ replied the old fellow, with a very complicated wink. ‘I am the last of my family, Tom,’ said the old gentleman, with a melancholy sigh.</p><p >“Was it a large one?’ inquired Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘There were twelve of us, Tom,’ said the old gentleman; fine straight-backed, handsome fellows as you'd wish to see. None of your modern abortions—all with arms, and with a degree of polish, though I say it that should not, which it would have done your heart good to behold.’</p><pb  xml:id="p143"/><p >“‘And what's become of the others, Sir?’ asked Tom Smart.</p><p >“The old gentleman applied his elbow to his eye as he replied, ‘Gone, Tom, gone. We had hard service, Tom, and they hadn't all my constitution. They got rheumatic about the legs and arms, and went into kitchens and other hospitals; and one of 'em, with long service and hard usage, positively lost his senses:—he got so crazy that he was obliged to be burnt. Shocking thing that, Tom.’</p><p >“‘Dreadful!’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“The old fellow paused for a few minutes, apparently struggling with his feelings of emotion, and then said,</p><p >“‘However, Tom, I am wandering from the point. This tall man, Tom, is a rascally adventurer. The moment he married the widow, he would sell off all the furniture, and run away. What would be the consequence? She would be deserted and reduced to ruin, and I should catch my death of cold in some broker's shop.’</p><p >“‘Yes, but—’</p><p >“‘Don't interrupt me,’ said the old gentleman. ‘Of you, Tom, I entertain a very different opinion; for I well know that if you once settled yourself in a public house, you would never leave it, as long as there was anything to drink within its walls.’</p><p >“‘I am very much obliged to you for your good opinion, Sir,’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘Therefore, resumed the old gentleman, in a dictatorial tone; ‘you shall have her, and he shall not.’</p><p >“‘What is to prevent it?’ said Tom Smart, eagerly.</p><p >“‘This disclosure,’ replied the old gentleman; ’he is already married.’</p><p >“‘How can I prove it?’ said Tom, starting half out of bed.</p><p >“The old gentleman untucked his arm from his side, and having pointed to one of the oaken presses, immediately replaced it, in its old position.</p><p >“‘He little thinks,’ said the old gentleman, ‘that in the right hand pocket of a pair of trousers in that press, he has left a letter, entreating him to return to his disconsolate wife, with six—mark me, Tom—six babes, and all of them small ones.’</p><p >“As the old gentleman solemnly uttered these words, his features grew less and less distinct, and his figure more shadowy. A film came over Tom Smart's eyes. The old man seemed gradually blending into the chair, the damask waistcoat to resolve into a cushion, the red slippers to shrink into little red cloth bags. The light faded gently away, and Tom Smart fell back on his pillow, and dropped asleep.</p><p >“Morning roused Tom from the lethargic slumber, into which he had fallen on the disappearance of the old man. He sat up in bed, and for some minutes vainly endeavoured to recal the events of the preceding night. Suddenly they rushed upon him. He looked at the chair, it was a fantastic and grim-looking piece of furniture, certainly, but it must have been a remarkably ingenious and lively imagination, that could have discovered any resemblance between it and an old man.</p><p >“‘How are you, old boy?’ said Tom. He was bolder in the day-light—most men are.</p><pb  xml:id="p144"/><p >“The chair remained motionless, and spoke not a word.</p><p >“‘Miserable morning,’ said Tom. No. The chair would not be drawn into conversation.</p><p >“‘Which press did you point to?—you can tell me that,’ said Tom. Devil a word, gentlemen, the chair would say.</p><p >“‘It's not much trouble to open it, any how,’ said Tom, getting out of bed very deliberately. He walked  up to one of the presses. The key was in the lock; he turned it, and opened the door. There <hi rend="italics">was</hi> a pair of trousers there. He put his hand into the pocket, and drew forth the identical letter the old gentleman had described!</p><p >“‘Queer sort of thing, this,’ said Tom Smart; looking first at the chair and then at the press, and then at the letter, and then at the chair again. ‘Very queer,’ said Tom. But as there was nothing in either to lessen the queerness, he thought he might as well dress himself, and settle the tall man's business at once—just to put him out of his misery.</p><p >“Tom surveyed the rooms he passed though, on his way down stairs, with the scrutinising eye of a landlord; thinking it not impossible, that before long, they and their contents would be his property. The tall man was standing in the snug little bar, with his hands behind him, quite at home. He grinned vacantly at Tom. A casual observer might have supposed he did it, only to show his white teeth; but Tom Smart thought that a consciousness of triumph was passing through the place where the tall man's mind would have been, if he had had any. Tom laughed in his face; and summoned the landlady.</p><p >“‘Good morning, Ma'am,’ said Tom Smart, closing the door of the little parlour as the widow entered.</p><p >“‘Good morning, Sir,’ said the widow. ‘What will you take for  breakfast, Sir?’</p><p >“Tom was thinking how he should open the case, so he made no answer.</p><p >“‘There's a very nice ham,’ said the widow, ‘and a beautiful cold larded fowl. Shall I send 'em in, Sir?’</p><p >“These words roused Tom from his reflections. His admiration of the widow increased as she spoke. Thoughtful creature! Comfortable provider!”</p><p >“‘Who is that gentleman in the bar, Ma'am?’ inquired Tom.</p><p >“‘His name is Jinkins, Sir,’ said the widow, slightly blushing.</p><p >“‘He's a tall man,’ said Tom.</p><p >“‘He is a very fine man, Sir,’ replied the widow, ‘and a very nice gentleman.’</p><p >“‘Ah!’ said Tom.</p><p >“‘Is there anything more you want, Sir?’ inquired the widow, rather puzzled by Tom's manner.</p><p >“‘Why, yes,’ said Tom. ‘My dear Ma'am, will you have the kindness to sit down for one moment?’</p><p >“The widow looked much amazed, but she sat down, and Tom sat down too, close beside her. I don't know how it happened, gentlemen—indeed my uncle used to tell me that Tom Smart said <hi rend="italics">he</hi> didn't know how it happened either—but somehow or other the  palm of Tom's
<pb xml:id="p145"/>
hand fell upon the back of the widow's hand, and remained there while he spoke.</p><p >“‘My dear Ma'am,’ said Tom Smart—he had always a great notion of committing the amiable—“My dear Ma'am, you deserve a very excellent husband;—you do indeed.’</p><p >“‘Lor, Sir!’ said the widow—as well she might; Tom's mode of commencing the conversation being rather unusual, not to say startling, the  fact of his never having set eyes upon her before the previous night, being taken into consideration. ‘Lor, Sir!’</p><p >“‘I scorn to flatter, my dear Ma'am,’ said Tom Smart. ‘You deserve a very admirable husband, and whoever he is, he'll be a very lucky man.’ As Tom said this, his eye involuntarily wandered from the widow's face to the comforts around him.</p><p >“The widow looked more puzzled than ever, and made an effort to rise. Tom gently pressed her hand, as if to detain her, and she kept her seat. Widows, gentlemen, are not usually timorous, as my uncle used to say.</p><p >“‘I am sure I am very much obliged to you, Sir, for your good opinion,’ said the buxom landlady, half laughing; ‘and if ever I marry again’—</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">‘If,’</hi> said Tom Smart, looking very shrewdly out at the right-hand corner of his left eye. <hi rend="italics">‘If’</hi>—</p><p >“‘Well,’ said the widow, laughing outright this time. “<hi rend="italics">When</hi> I do, I hope I shall have as good a husband as you describe.’</p><p >“‘Jinkins to wit,’ said Tom.</p><p >“‘Lor, Sir!’ exclaimed the widow.</p><p >“‘Oh, don't tell me,’ said Tom, ‘I know him.’</p><p >“‘I am sure nobody who knows him, knows anything bad of him,’ said the widow, bridling up at the mysterious air with which Tom had spoken.</p><p >“‘Hem,’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“The widow began to think it was high time to cry, so she took out her handkerchief, and inquired whether Tom wished to insult her, whether he thought it like a gentleman to take away the character of another gentleman behind his back, why, if he had got anything to say, he didn't say it to the man, like a man, instead of terrifying a poor weak woman in that way; and so forth.</p><p >“‘I'll say it to him fast enough,’ said Tom, ‘only I want you to hear it first.’</p><p >“‘What is it?’ inquired the widow, looking intently in Tom's countenance.</p><p >“‘I'll astonish you,’ said Tom, putting his hand in his pocket.</p><p >“‘If it is, that he wants money,’ said the widow, ‘I know that already, and you needn't trouble yourself.’</p><p >“‘Pooh, nonsense, that's nothing,’ said Tom Smart,; <hi rend="italics">‘I</hi> want money 'Tan't that.</p><p >“‘Oh dear, what can it be?’ exclaimed the poor widow.</p><p >“‘Don't be frightened,’ said Tom Smart. He slowly drew forth the letter, and unfolded it. ‘You won't scream?’ said Tom, doubtfully.</p><p >“‘No, no,’ replied the widow; ‘let me see it.’</p><p >“‘You won't go fainting away, or any of that nonsense?’ said Tom.</p><pb  xml:id="p146"/><p >“‘No, no,’ returned the widow, hastily.</p><p >“‘And don't run out, and blow him up,’ said Tom, ‘because I'll do all that for you; you had better not exert yourself.’</p><p >“‘Well, well,’ said the widow, ‘let me see it.’</p><p >“‘I will,’ replied Tom Smart; and, with these words, he placed the letter in the widow's hand.</p><p >“Gentlemen, I have heard my uncle say, that Tom Smart said, the widow's lamentations when she heard the disclosure would have pierced a heart of stone. Tom was certainly very tender-hearted, but they pierced his, to the very core. The widow rocked herself to and fro, and wrung her hands.</p><p >“‘Oh, the deception and villainy of the man!’ said the widow.</p><p >“‘Frightful, my dear Ma'am; but compose yourself,’ said Tom Smart.</p><p >“‘Oh, I can't compose myself,’ shrieked the widow. ‘I shall never find any one else I can love so much!’</p><p >“‘Oh yes you will, my dear soul,’ said Tom Smart, letting fall a shower of the largest-sized tears, in pity for the widow's misfortunes. Tom Smart, in the energy of his compassion, had put his arm round the widow's waist; and the widow, in a passion of grief, had clasped Tom's hand. She looked up in Tom's face, and smiled through her tears. Tom looked down in her's, and smiled through his.</p><p >“I never could find out, gentlemen, whether Tom did or did not kiss the widow at that particular moment. He used to tell my uncle he didn't, but I have my doubts about it. Between ourselves, gentlemen, I rather think he did.</p><p >“At all events, Tom kicked the very tall man out at the front door half an hour after, and married the widow a month after. And he used to drive about the country, with the clay-coloured gig with the red wheels, and the vixenish mare with the fast pace, till he gave up business many years afterwards, and went to France with his wife; and then the old house was pulled down.”</p></div></body></floatingText></quote><p >“Will you allow me to ask you,” said the inquisitive old gentleman, “what became of the chair?”</p><p >“Why,” replied the one-eyed bagman, “it was observed to creak very much on the day of the wedding; but Tom Smart couldn't say for certain, whether it was with pleasure or bodily infirmity. He rather thought it was the latter, though, for it never spoke afterwards.”</p><p >“Everybody believed the story, didn't they?” said the dirty-faced man, re-filling his pipe.</p><p >“Except Tom's enemies,” replied the bagman. “Some of 'em said Tom invented it altogether; and others said he was drunk, and fancied it, and got hold of the wrong  trousers by mistake before he went to bed. But nobody ever minded what <hi rend="italics">they</hi> said.”</p><p >“Tom Smart said it was all true?”</p><p >“Every word.”</p><p >“And your uncle?”</p><p >“Every letter.”</p><p >“They must have been nice men, both of 'em;” said the dirty-faced man.</p><p >“Yes, they were,” replied the bagman; “very nice men indeed!”</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><head >NEW AND SPLENDID VOLUME.</head><p >THIS DAY IS PUBLISHED, <lb/> BOUND IN A NOVEL AND VERY ELEGANT MANNER, <lb/> THE PICTORIAL ALBUM, <lb/> OR <lb/> CABINET OF PAINTINGS, <lb/> FOR THE YEAR 1837.</p><p >Containing ELEVEN DESIGNS, executed in Oil-colours by G. BAXTER, and forming perfect  Fac-similes of the original Pictures, by</p><list  type="simple"><item>J. BARNARD,</item><item>MISS F. CORBAUX,</item><item>J. HOLLAND,</item><item>G. JONES, R.A.</item><item>W. PICKERSGILL, R.A.</item><item>S. PROUT,</item><item>MRS. SEYFFARTH,</item><item>MISS E. SHARPE,</item><item>R. WESTALL, R.A.</item><item>W. WESTALL, A.R.A.</item><item>WITH LETTER-PRESS ILLUSTRATIONS.</item><item>THE POETRY BY MISS LANDON. THE PROSE BY JAMES OLLIER, ESQ.</item></list><p >IN offering to the public a NEW ANNUAL, the proprietors are aware that they are entering upon a field of great and honourable competition; nor should they perhaps have ventured to do so, but for a consciousness that the position they propose to take up is one never before occupied, and yet equally commanding as novel.</p><p >It has been reserved for the present publication to exhibit a display of art hitherto unattempted in works of a similar or indeed of any nature. The PICTORIAL ALBUM adds to the various graces of the artist's <hi rend="italics">design,</hi> the luxuriant charms of his <hi rend="italics">colouring;</hi> nor is this additional fascination wrought through the medium of mere water tints; the richer and more enduring effects of oil colours are insured, and thus a series of actual <hi rend="italics">paintings</hi> is placed at the disposal of the purchaser.</p><p >The proprietors in fact venture to express a confident anticipation, that the work altogether will form a splendid and interesting volume, admirably adapted for a New Year's Gift, and not less so for a standard adornment of the drawingroom table or the boudoir.</p><closer >CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.<lb/>
Bradbury and Evans, Printers.</closer></div></back></text></TEI>