<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc >
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the
Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members.
No. XVII:</emph> Electronic Edition. </title>
<author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp>
<name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name>
<name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name>
<name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name>
<name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name>
</respStmt>
<funder>Funding from the E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of
this title.</funder>
<respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Matthew Kern</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Harris Henderson, and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition>
</editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 285K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>

<date>2002.</date>
<availability status="unknown">
<p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. It may be
used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of
availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title>title_pageThe Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of
the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding
Members. No. XVII</title>
<title type="cover"/>
<author>Boz</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>Phiz</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent> 68 p., ill.</extent>
<publicationStmt>

<publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LONDON:CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<date>MDCCCXXXVII</date>
<authority/>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number Dickens 13 pt. 17 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel
Hill)</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc >
<editorialDecl>
<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. The text has
been encoded using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>
<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved. Encountered typographical errors
have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been
joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>All quotation marks, em dashes and ampersand have been transcribed as entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “ respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
<p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and
Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc >
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc >
<change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-12-10">
 Jill Kuhn Sexton 

finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change>
<change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-10-10">
Harris Henderson

 finished TEI/SGML encoding</change>
<change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">
Apex Data Services, Inc.

 finished transcribing the text.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text >
<front>
<titlePage>
<titlePart type="main"> No. XVII.]</titlePart>
<docEdition>[PRICE 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">THE
<lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS
<lb/> OF THE
<lb/> PICKWICK CLUB
<lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE
<lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES
<lb/> AND
<lb/> Sporting Transactions
<lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS. </titlePart>
</docTitle>
<docAuthor> EDITED BY “BOZ.” </docAuthor>
<docEdition>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.</docEdition>
<docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVII</docDate>
<seg part="N">BRADBURY AND EVANS.]</seg>
<seg part="N">[PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</seg>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pii"/>
<head >CHUBB'S NEW PATENT DETECTOR LOCK.</head>
<p >57, ST. PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</p>
<p >CHARLES CHUBB having succeeded in simplifying the form and arrangement of the parts of his
Improved Patent Detector Lock, for which new improvements his late Majesty granted his Royal Letters
Patent, is enabled to manufacture his NEW PATENT LOCKS at much less cost; at the same time retaining
all the security and advantages of his Improved Detector Lock, the merits of which have been so
fully ascertained and appreciated by the public. The New Patent Detector Locks are made of every
size, and for all purposes to which locks are applied.</p>
<p >The attention of Bankers, Merchants, &amp;c. is called to the following paragraph from the <hi rend="italics">Standard</hi> of the 6th of February last:—</p>
<p >“On Saturday morning, on the clerks entering the premises of Messrs. Charles Price and Co.,
William Street, Blackfriars, it was discovered that the offices had been burglariously entered
during the night. It appears that the outside door locks had been opened with skeleton keys, nine
desks in the counting-house had been forced open by a jemmy, and the lock of a large iron safe was
picked. The principal object of attack, however, was another iron safe (in which all the valuable
property was contained), which was fitted with one of Chubb's Patent Locks; this the thieves first
attempted to pick; failing in that, they next had recourse to the formidable and hitherto
destructive instrument, called the ‘Jack in the Box,’ but with this they were equally
unsuccessful, and, after the most determined attempts to open it, they were completely foiled in
their efforts to get at the property.”</p>
<p >TESTIMONIAL OF M. J. BRUNELL, ESQ. CIVIL ENGINEER.</p>
<p >“In point of security, Chubb's Patent Detector Lock is superior to any I am acquainted
with.</p>
<p >“M. J. BRUNELL.”</p>
<p >EXTRACT FROM DR. LARDNER'S CABINET CYCLOPÆDIA, No. 42, <hi rend="italics">p.</hi> 273.</p>
<p >“There can be no doubt but that the construction and arrangement of the parts, in Chubb's
Invention, do combine the four principal requisites of a good lock, viz. Security, Simplicity,
Strength, and Durability.”</p>
<p >The Patent Detector Locks may be fitted to Iron Safes, Chests and Doors, already in use.</p>
<div type="section">
<head >CHUBB'S PATENT COMBINATION LATCH,
<lb/> FOR FRONT DOORS, COUNTING-HOUSES, &amp;C.</head>
<p >These Latches are simple in their construction, low in price, and possess security far beyond any
yet offered to the public.</p>
<p >Prices of the Latches, with Two Keys—4 inches, 12s.; 5 inches, 13s.; 6 inches, 14s.
each.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >CHUBB'S PATENT MOVEABLE FIRE-PROOF STRONG ROOMS,
<lb/> CHESTS, SAFES, AND IRON DOORS,</head>
<p >which are perfectly secure against the force and ingenuity of the most skilful and determined
burglar, and are absolutely Fire-proof, even if exposed to the most destructive fire in any
situation.<ref xml:id="ref1" target="#n1">*</ref></p>
<note><p >* The efficacy of this invention has been proved by
enclosing some papers in a Patent Box made on the same principle, and exposing it in the furnace of
a steam-engine, where it soon became red-hot, and remained in that state for a considerable time;
when taken out, the papers were found to be uninjured.</p></note>
<p >MADE BY CHARLES CHUBB, INVENTOR AND PATENTEE,
<lb/> 57, ST. PAUL'S CHURCHYARD, LONDON.</p>
<p >A strong room, as generally constructed, cannot be removed, so that in case of a change of
residence, a considerable expense is incurred in again building one; but this loss and inconvenience
may be obviated, and perfect security obtained, by the adoption of the</p>
<p >PATENT MOVEABLE FIRE-PROOF STRONG ROOM,
<lb/> which is so constructed that it may be taken down, removed, and put together again with little
trouble. These advantages render them peculiarly applicable for Banks on the Continent and in the
Colonies.</p>
<p >Patent Fire-proof Boxes, forming a complete security for Deeds, Plate, Jewellery, &amp;c., all
sizes, on sale or made to order.</p>
<p >All the above are fitted with Chubb's Patent Detector Locks.</p>
<p >Wrought Iron Fire-proof Chests, Safes, and Iron Doors for Strong Rooms, Cash Boxes, Travelling
Desks, Despatch Boxes, Portfolios, and Private Boxes for depositing with Bankers, on sale and made
to order, all fitted with the Detector Locks.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="piii"/>
<head >THE PICKWICK ADVERTISER. No. XVII.</head>
<p >[<hi rend="italics">The impression of the Advertising Sheet is limited to</hi> 20,000—<hi rend="italics">but the circulation</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">of the Work being</hi> 26,000, <hi rend="italics">that number of Bills is
required.</hi>]</p>
<div type="section">
<head >POPULAR JUVENILE BOOKS,</head>
<p > ELEGANTLY EMBELLISHED.</p>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Neatly bound in Cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >REMEMBER;</head>
<p >OR,
<lb/> MAMMA'S BIRTHDAY.</p>
<p >BY MRS. BARWELL.</p>
<p >WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Neatly bound, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >THE JUVENILE PIANIST;</head>
<p > OR, A MIRROR OF
<lb/> MUSIC FOR INFANT MINDS
<lb/> BY ANN RODWELL,
<lb/> TEACHER OF THE PIANOFORTE.</p>
<p >Illustrated by upwards of One Hundred Musical Diagrams, and embellished with Engravings printed
in Colours.</p>
<p >“This instructive little work, which is illustrated with numerous engravings and diagrams
explanatory of its interesting art, is truly what it professes to be, a Mirror of Music for Infant
Minds, constructed with such simplicity and clearness, that it would be impossible, even for a very
young child, to read without deriving the wished for instruction. It is admirably calculated to
render the early practice of the piano easy and attractive.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning
Post.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo, neatly bound, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >POETRY FOR CHILDREN.</head>
<p >Selected by the late WM. BURDON.</p>
<p >A New Edition,
<lb/> WITH ILLUSTRATIONS PRINTED IN COLOURS.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Neatly bound in cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >THE TWO COUSINS,
<lb/> AND OTHER TALES.</head>
<p >By the Authoress of “POETIC SKETCHES.”</p>
<p >WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Neatly bound in cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >CAROLINE;</head>
<p >OR, THE
<lb/> PLEASURES OF A BIRTHDAY.</p>
<p >BY M. M. RODWELL,
<lb/> Author of “GEOGRAPHY OF THE BRITISH ISLES.”</p>
<p >WITH SIX ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Neatly bound in cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >THE SPOILED CHILD
<lb/> RECLAIMED.</head>
<p >BY M. M. RODWELL,
<lb/> WITH SIX ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
<p >“Two works brought out with great taste and neatness, for the amusement of children. The
stories are well told, the moral lessons they inculcate, precisely those which it is of most
importance to impress on the youthful mind.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenæum.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo, neatly bound, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head >ROSE AND ANNE.</head>
<p >A FIRST BOOK, IN MONOSYLLABLES,
<lb/> WITH SIX ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener >One volume, 12mo, neatly bound in cloth, gilt edges, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head >FLEURS DE POESIE MODERNE,</head>
<p > Containing the Beauties of A. De Lamartine, Victor Hugo, De Beranger, C. Delavigne.</p>
<p >“A selection made in the spirit of the day. Instead of a collection from other and old
collections, the compiler has chosen the best of modern French writers, and presented us with the
very best of their thoughts.”—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener >SECOND EDITION, <hi rend="italics">price One Shilling,</hi></opener>
<head >NURSERY GOVERNMENT;</head>
<p > OR,
<lb/> HINTS ADDRESSED TO MOTHERS AND NURSERYMAIDS,
<lb/> ON THE
<lb/> MANAGEMENT OF YOUNG CHILDREN.</p>
<p >BY MRS. BARWELL.</p>
<p >“This little pamphlet is one of the most sensibly-written productions on this interesting
subject that we ever remember to have perused. We have gone through it with a feeling of real
pleasure, and we earnestly recommend it to the notice of mothers, and all who have the care of young
children confided to them.”—<hi rend="italics">Salisbury Journal.</hi></p>
<closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND</closer>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="piv"/>
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Price One Shilling.</hi></opener>
<head >A FEW WORDS ON A FEW WINES.</head>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >CHAPTER I.—CHOICE OF WINE.</head>
<p >PORT IN THE WOOD.—GOOD WINE.—WHAT IT SHOULD NOT BE.—WHAT IT SHOULD
BE.—HOW TO OBTAIN WHAT YOU WANT.—MATURITY.—BOTTLED
WINE.—CONDITION.—BEES-WING.—CLARETY PORT.—THE WAY TO PURCHASE.—THE
BEST SORT.—KNOW YOUR OWN MIND.—WHITE
WINE.—ACIDITY.—SHERRY.—MADEIRA.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >CHAPTER II.—MANAGEMENT OF WINE</head>
<p >DIRECTIONS FOR.—FINING PORT.—CONDITION.—WHEN FIT TO BOTTLE.—WHITE WINE
FINING.—DIRECTIONS FOR
BOTTLING.—BOTTLES.—CORKS.—IMPLEMENTS.—PIERCING.—DRAWING.—CORKING.—PACKING.—THE
CELLAR.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >CHAPTER III.—TREATMENT OF WINE.</head>
<p >CORKSCREW.—DRAWING THE CORK.—DECANTING THE WINE.—WINE STRAINERS—DRINKING
WINE—TOO MUCH.—ENOUGH.—USE OF WINE.—ABUSE OF WINE.—DINING AT
HOME—DINING OUT.—LIGHT WINE.—ICING WINE.—WINE COOLERS.—WINE
GLASSES.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >TRAVELLING AND HUNTING MAPS.</head>
<p ><hi rend="italics">Mounted in cases adapted to the waistcoat pocket,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. each.</hi></p>
<p >MAPS OF THE ENGLISH COUNTIES,
<lb/> ENGRAVED BY SIDNEY HALL,
<lb/> WITH THE MAIL AND COACH ROADS CORRECTLY COLOURED.</p>
<list  type="simple">
<item>Bedfordshire</item>
<item>Berkshire</item>
<item>Buckinghamshire</item>
<item>Cambridgeshire</item>
<item>Cheshire</item>
<item>Cornwall</item>
<item>Cumberland</item>
<item>Derbyshire</item>
<item>Devonshire</item>
<item>Dorsetshire</item>
<item>Durham</item>
<item>England</item>
<item>Essex</item>
<item>Gloucestershire</item>
<item>Hampshire</item>
<item>Herefordshire</item>
<item>Hertfordshire</item>
<item>Huntingdonshire</item>
<item>Isle of Wight</item>
<item>Isles of Man, Jersey, &amp; Guernsey Kent</item>
<item>Lancashire</item>
<item>Leicestershire</item>
<item>Lincolnshire</item>
<item>Middlesex</item>
<item>Monmonthshire</item>
<item>Norfolk</item>
<item>Northamptonshire</item>
<item>Northumberland</item>
<item>Nottinghamshire</item>
<item>Oxfordshire</item>
<item>Rutlandshire</item>
<item>Shropshire</item>
<item>Somersetshire</item>
<item>Staffordshire</item>
<item>Suffolk</item>
<item>Surrey</item>
<item>Sussex</item>
<item>Warwickshire</item>
<item>Westmoreland</item>
<item>Wiltshire</item>
<item>Worcestershire</item>
</list>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s. double the size of the
above,</hi></opener>
<head > YORKSHIRE, IRELAND, SCOTLAND, AND WALES.</head>
<p >Complete Sets of the above, uniformly mounted and lettered, in a neat Case, may be had, price
Four Guineas.</p>
<closer >CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >DODSLEY'S AND RIVINGTON'S
<lb/> ANNUAL REGISTER FOR 1836.</head>
<p >Just published, in a large volume 8vo, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> boards, THE ANNUAL
REGISTER; or, a View of the History, Politics, and Literature of the Year 1836.</p>
<p >London: Printed for Baldwin and Cradock; J. G. and F. Rivington; Longman and Co.; Jeffery and
Son; Booker and Co.; J. M. Richardson; J. Booth; J. Rodwell; Sherwood and Co.; Hamilton and Co.;
Whittaker and Co.; J. Dowding; Simpkin, Marshall, and Co.; G. Lawford; T. Laycock; and H.
Renshaw.</p>
<p >By whom is also published, in a very large volume,
<lb/> price 24s.,
<lb/> A GENERAL INDEX to the ANNUAL REGISTER, from its commencement in 1758 to the year 1819,
inclusive; after which period each successive volume has a distinct index.</p>
<p >Separate volumes to complete sets may he had of the Publishers, but as several are becoming
scarce, an early application is recommended.</p>
<p >A few complete sets from the commencement in 1758 may still be had.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<opener >Second Edition, with numerous additions, bringing the History of the Colony to 1837, 2 vols.
post 8vo, with Map, price 21s. boards.</opener>
<head >HISTORICAL AND STATISTICAL ACCOUNT OF NEW SOUTH WALES, </head>
<p >both as a Penal Settlement and as a British Colony.</p>
<p >By JOHN DUNMORE LANG, D.D.</p>
<p >Senior Minister of the Scots Church, and Principal of the Australian College, Sydney, New South
Wales.</p>
<p >A. J. VALPY, Red Lion Court, Fleet Street, London; BELL and BRADFUTE, Edinburgh; and sold by all
Booksellers.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<opener >Just published, in 1 vol. 12mo, price 9s., </opener>
<head >THE ELEMENTS OF PHYSICS.</head>
<p >By THOMAS WEBSTER, M.A., of Trinity College, Cambridge; Fellow of the Cambridge Philosophical
Society, and Secretary to the Institution of Civil Engineers.</p>
<p >The object of the Author has been to exhibit, in a mathematical form, but without mathematical
technicalities and symbols, the various processes by which the establishment of any proposition in
Physics is arrived at, and the nature of the evidence which enables us to speak with confidence of
the truth of any theory: exhibiting, also, what may be considered as certain, what only probable,
and what absolutely unknown.</p>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener >II.
<lb/> Just <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>publisheded</sic><corr>published</corr></choice>, in 1 vol. 12mo, price 7s. 6d.,</opener>
<head >PARKES'S CHEMICAL CATECHISM.</head>
<p > A new Edition, Revised throughout, Corrected, and considerably enlarged, by WILLIAM BARKER,
M.B., of Trinity College, Dublin.</p>
<p >As many and important changes have lately taken place in the different branches of Chemistry,
especially in nomenclature and classification, the present Editor, as far as was consistent with
retaining the character and plan of the original work, has altered and revised it throughout, so as
to adapt it to the present state of Chemical Science.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<opener >III.
<lb/> Just published, in crown 8vo, with Frontispiece,
<lb/> Price 7s., </opener>
<head > ON THE BEAUTIFUL, THE PICTURESQUE, THE SUBLIME.</head>
<p > By the Rev. J. G. MACVICAR, M.A.</p>
<closer >London: Scott, Webster, and Geary, Charterhouse Square.</closer>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pv"/>
<head >BATHS.</head>
<p >OBSERVATIONS on the UTILITY of FUMIGATING, HOT AIR, and VAPOUR BATHS, so generally used on the
Continent for the cure of various diseases; with a summary of ninety-two important authenticated
cases treated at the Establishment, No. 40, Great Marlborough Street.</p>
<p >By JONATHAN GREEN, M.D., &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p >Published by Churchill, Medical Bookseller, Prince's Street, Soho, London. 2s. 6d. To be had of
all Booksellers.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >GROUSE, PARTRIDGE, AND PHEASANT
<lb/> SHOOTING.</head>
<p >Second Edition. Post 8vo. 6s. 6d.</p>
<p >THE OAKLEIGH SHOOTING CODE. By THOMAS OAKLEIGH, Esq. Comprising the 180 Canons on shooting
Grouse, Partridges, Pheasants, &amp;c. with numerous explanatory and other notes.</p>
<p >“We strongly recommend this work.” — <hi rend="italics">Sporting
Chronicle.</hi>—“Every gentleman, whether young or old, should provide himself with a
copy, previous to the ensuing shooting campaign.”—<hi rend="italics">New Sporting
Magazine.</hi>—“Since the well-known publication of Daniel's ‘Rural Sports’,
we have seen nothing worthy to be compared with the Canons of the Oakleigh Code.”—<hi rend="italics">Essex Mercury.</hi></p>
<p >James Ridgway and Sons, Piccadilly, and all Booksellers. Who have just published, a fourth
edition,</p>
<p >PERSONAL SAFETY FROM LIGHTNING DURING STORMS. AND THE RIGHT APPLICATION OF CONDUCTORS TO
BUILDINGS, &amp;c. 1s.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >MY BOOK;
<lb/> OR,
<lb/> THE ANATOMY OF CONDUCT.</head>
<p >BY
<lb/> JOHN HENRY SKELTON.</p>
<p >“Hail, ye small sweet courtesies of life, for smooth do ye make the road of it! Like grace
and beauty, which beget inclinations to love at first sight; 'tis ye, who open the door, and let the
stranger in.”—STERNE.</p>
<closer >London: Simpkin and Marshall.</closer>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >NEW PART OF
<lb/> ENCYCLOPÆDIA METROPOLITANA.</head>
<p >This day is published, price 1<hi rend="italics">l</hi>. 1s. boards,
<lb/> PART XLVI. of
<lb/> THE ENCYCLOPÆDIA METROPOLITANA; or, Universal Dictionary of Knowledge; on an original
plan, combining the twofold advantages of a Philosophical and an <choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Alphahetical</sic><corr>Alphabetical</corr></choice> Arrangement.</p>
<p >This Part contains—in PURE SCIENCES, Theory of Probabilities, by Mr. De Morgan; Definite
Integrals, by Mr. Mosly. In MIXED SCIENCES, Botany, continued. In HISTORY, to nearly the end of the
Seventeenth Century; and in the LEXICON, to Saxicola.</p>
<p >London: Printed for Baldwin and Cradock; J. G. and F. Rivington; J. Duncan; B. Fellowes; Suttaby
and Co.; E. Hodgson; J. Dowding; G. Lawford; T. Laycock; J. Fraser; J. M. Richardson; J. Bohn; T.
Allman; J. Bain; H. Dixon; J. Bryant; S. Hodgson: R. Hodgson; F. Westley; for J. H. Parker, Oxford;
and J. and J. J. Deighton, Cambridge.</p>
<p >The Proprietors regret extremely the length of time which has elapsed since the publication of
Part XLV., and which is attributable solely to the much-lamented death of the late respected Editor,
the Rev. Mr. Smedley. They trust that in the hands of the new Editor, it will be possible to publish
the few remaining Parts with considerable despatch; and as Mr. Smedley had nearly completed his
arrangements for the completion of the Work, there will be no difficulty in effecting it in a
consistent manner.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >THE SERAPHINE,</head>
<p >or Portable Organ, is now brought to the greatest perfection, the beauties of which are not to be
equalled for sweetness of tone, coupled with extraordinary power, although in size not larger than a
Cheffionier. The compass of the Seraphine is the same as the Organ, from F F F to F in
alt—five complete octaves. The lovers of the sublime works of Handel, Haydn, Mozart, &amp;c.,
will find this a most fascinating instrument, a decided rival to the Organ, and fully calculated for
public or private devotion, being capable of producing all the effects of that noble instrument. At
Bates's Organ &amp; Pianoforte Manufactory, 6, Ludgate-hill.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >IMPROVEMENT IN WRITING.</head>
<p >MR. CHITTENDEN, 94, High Holborn (British Plate Manufactory), will engage to render free,
legible, and expeditious, the hand-writing of any person, however bad, in an incredibly short period
of time. Short-hand taught in the most complete manner. The French, Italian, and Latin Languages by
a Professor of the University of Paris. Arithmetic, Drawing, and the Pianoforte taught. Bad Spelling
corrected. Correct Pronunciation taught. Private Lessons at a trifling extra charge.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >THE USEFUL and the USELESS —</head>
<p >The PUBLIC should discriminate between the GENUINE PATENT EVER-POINTED PENCIL and CUMBERLAND LEAD
POINTS, as manufactured for the last fifteen years, by G. RIDDLE, and the defective imitations
offered for sale at apparently low prices. For a patent pencil to be useful, the material must be
good, and the workmanship of the best description: the point, as well as the leads, must be finished
with mathematical precision, or the invention is useless. To ensure a Genuine Patent Ever-pointed
Pencil and Leads, observe the mark “Patent, G. Riddle, maker, London.” Sold by all the
usual venders throughout the kingdom.</p>
<p >Also, for Artists, G. Riddle's warranted pure Cumberland Lead Aencils in cedar.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >WATERPROOF COATS, &amp;c.</head>
<p >J. B. SMITH and CO. beg to call the attention of the Public to their process for rendering
Woollen Cloths, Camlets, and Gambroons WATERPROOF, without impeding the perspiration, NO CAOUTCHOUC
or any resinous matter being employed. The texture and appearance of the cloth remain <hi rend="italics">unaltered;</hi> it is <hi rend="italics">free</hi> from <hi rend="italics">smell,</hi> or any disagreeable property, and is rendered a <hi rend="italics">non-absorbent</hi>
of wet. The process, <hi rend="italics">not impeding the perspiration,</hi> is particularly adapted
for <hi rend="italics">Shooting and Hunting Coats.</hi></p>
<p >Cloths having undergone the process (which is effected in a few days), supplied by all
respectable Tailors.</p>
<closer >69, Wood Street, Cheapside, and
<lb/> 24, St. Martin's Court, Leicester Square.</closer>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >LAMING'S TASTELESS EFFERVESCING CHELTENHAM SALTS.—</head>
<p >By simply pouring cold water on these Salts, a highly agreeable draught is produced, like Soda
Water to the taste, and possessing all the beneficial effects to be derived from the use of the
Cheltenham Waters. They are personally used by many of the medical faculty, by whom they have been
declared to be the safest and mildest aperient in use.</p>
<p >“The traveller should not fail to take them with him.”—<hi rend="italics">Brockedon's Italy.</hi> “They answer well, without any kind of
inconvenience.”—<hi rend="italics">Sir B. C. Brodie, Serg. Surgeon to the Queen.</hi>
“We have seen nothing to equal them.”—<hi rend="italics">Lit. Gazette.</hi>
“They are the invention of a scientific surgeon, which affords a guarantee of their
excellence.”—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi> “One of the best conceivable family
medicines.”—<hi rend="italics">Stockton Paper.</hi></p>
<p >Sold in Bottles at 2s. 6d., 4s., and 10s. by all respectable Chemists.</p>
<closer >London Agent, R. E. Dear, 89, Bishopsgate Within.</closer>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pvi"/>
<head >ADAMS'S IMPROVED SPECTACLES.</head>
<p >H. ADAMS, OPTICIAN AND SPECTACLE MANUFACTURER, begs respectfully to solicit the attention of the
Nobility, Gentry, and the Public, to his stock of BRAZIL PEBBLES and GLASSES of every description,
ground on the most accurate principles to suit the various defects of sight, and elegantly mounted
in gold, silver, blued steel, tortoiseshell, and other frames.</p>
<p >To those who find their sight failing, he takes the liberty to recommend the use of his
PRESERVERS, by which the eyes may be saved for years from any further decay. He also assures those
Ladies and Gentlemen who may be disposed to honour him with their patronage, that they may rely upon
being suited in the most correct manner, not only with Pebbles or Glasses of the proper focus and
most perfect kind, but with frames peculiarly adapted to the face of the wearer, so that the centre
of each glass is brought exactly opposite to the pupil of the eye, which is of great importance,
although entirely neglected by many Opticians.</p>
<p >A pair of the best Brazil Pebbles fitted to a frame for 8s.</p>
<closer >2, Crawford Street, Portman Square, London, two doors from Baker Street.</closer>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >PREPARED METALLIC LABELS.</head>
<p >THESE LABELS are particularly recommended to Gentlemen, Florists, Nurserymen, &amp;c., as
possessing a decided superiority over all others now in use, being written upon easily with a common
pen, with the Prepared Ink. However long exposed to the weather, the writing cannot be obliterated.
Sold only by Messrs. Gordon, Thomsen, and Co., Seedsmen and Florists, 25, Fenchurch Street, London,
in packets of 50 and 100 each. Prepared Ink, 1s. 6d. per bottle. All Letters to be post paid.</p>
<p >
<table>
<row>
<cell>Dimensions
<lb/> in Inches.</cell>
<cell>No. 1.</cell>
<cell>No. 2.</cell>
<cell>No. 3.</cell>
<cell>No. 4.</cell>
<cell>No. 6.</cell>
<cell>Metallic Tallies</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1¼ by 2½.</cell>
<cell>2¼ by 5.</cell>
<cell>1½ by 5.</cell>
<cell>1 by 2 and 6.</cell>
<cell>2 by 2½.</cell>
<cell>2s. 6d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Prices per 100.</cell>
<cell>3s.</cell>
<cell>4s.</cell>
<cell>4s.</cell>
<cell>7s.</cell>
<cell>3s. 6d.</cell>
<cell>per 100.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >The public are cautioned against purchasing Metallic Labels elsewhere, as unless the metal is
prepared, and the prepared Ink used, the writing will be obliterated.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >LIST OF ARTICLES,</head>
<p >MANUFACTURED and Sold, Wholesale, Retail, and for Exportation, by MECHI, 4, Leadenhall Street,
(Fourth House from Cornhill, same side as the India House,) London.</p>
<list  type="simple">
<item>Table Cutlery and General Cutlery</item>
<item>Dish Covers</item>
<item>Tea Trays in Iron and Paper</item>
<item>Tea Caddies</item>
<item>Every Variety of <hi rend="italics">Real</hi> Sheffield Plated Goods</item>
<item>British Plate, or German Silver, Forks, Spoons, &amp;c., plated on Steel Goods, Dessert
Knives, &amp;c.</item>
<item>Albion Plate—Tea and Coffee Pots, Candlesticks, &amp;c.; being a description of superior
Britannia Metal Goods</item>
<item>Plate Leathers, Plate Powder, and Plate Brushes</item>
<item>Canteens for Large or Small Parties</item>
<item>Ladies' and Gentlemen's Wood and Leather Dressing Cases</item>
<item>Writing Cases, Pocket Books</item>
<item>Card Cases, Tablets</item>
<item>Workboxes, Writing Desks</item>
<item>Bagatelle Tables</item>
<item>Backgammon and Chess Boards</item>
<item>Chess and Draftsmen</item>
<item>Hair, Cloth, Tooth, Nail, Hat, and Shaving Brushes</item>
<item>Combs, Hones</item>
<item>Boot Jacks, Razors]</item>
<item>Strops, Paste</item>
<item>Shaving Powder, Naples Soap, &amp;c.</item>
</list>
<p >Any article made to Order at a Short Notice, without Additional Charge, as MECHI manufactures
nearly every Article he sells, in the LEADENHALL SKIN MARKET.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >RIDING, DRIVING, AND HUNTING
<lb/> WHIPS.</head>
<p >
<table>
<row>
<cell>Strong Riding Whips</cell>
<cell>1s.</cell>
<cell>each.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Town made ditto, with Plaited Whalebone Handles, and Solid Silver Mounts</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Driving Whips</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ditto, with Whalebone Handles, and Fashionable German Silver Octagon Mounts</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Capital Hunting Crops</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Malacca Cane Hunting Crops, from</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >At the Manufacturer's,
<lb/> J. CHEEK, Golden Perch, No. 52, Strand.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >AULMAC'S TARNISH LIQUID.</head>
<p >THIS Composition will clean and keep white dead or frosted Silver, also polished Silver and
Plated Goods, with great facility and brightness; and will clean and remove the tarnish from Ormolu,
dining-room, and table lamps, candelabras, and all other gilt metal ornamental articles, and is
invaluable for polished Brass, Copper, &amp;c. Manufactured and sold, wholesale and retail, at 242,
High Holborn, in Stone Bottles, at 6d. and 1s. each.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >DR. JOHN ARMSTRONG'S
<lb/> LIVER PILLS.</head>
<p >“I care not how I am physicked, so it be not by the adventure of a Quack, but advice of a
Physician, who, I am sure, will prescribe no more for me than may consist with my safety, and need
doth require.”—<hi rend="italics">Old Divine.</hi></p>
<p >THESE LIVER PILLS are now very generally recommended by the Faculty as the best Family Aperient,
as a fine Vermifage, as an Antibilious, and for an inactive Liver. Obstinate Sores heal under a
course of them; and Eruptions of the Skin disappear. They contain no Aloes, Gamboge, or Colocynth;
occasioning no Piles, nor any pain in their operation.</p>
<p >“John T. Eddy, Chemist, Bishop Stortford” is engraved on the Stamp, sealed with a
Tower on a Shield of ermine and gold. None else genuine.</p>
<p >Sold by all Patent Medicine Venders, in boxes at 1s. 1½d., 2s. 9d., and 4s. 6d.</p>
<p >N. B.—Ask for “DR. JOHN ARMSTRONG'S LIVER PILLS.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pvii"/>
<opener >Important to the NERVOUS, the AGED, the INFIRM, and all suffering from LOCAL and GENERAL
DEBILITY &amp;c.</opener>
<head >HARVEY'S RESTORATIVE CORDIAL.</head>
<p >This inestimable medicine stands unrivalled for its tonic virtues in all cases of nervous
debility, weakness of the stomach, loss of appetite, &amp;c. The generality of tonic medicines,
while they strengthen, excite the system, but this invaluable compound allays irritability, and
without stimulating, invigorates the constitution; giving tone to the stomach, promoting a healthy
digestion, bracing the nerves, elevating the spirits, and affording relief in the most distressing
cases of debility, whether owing to long illness, intemperance, sedentary habits, or residence in
warm climates. In the morning sickness of females it is exceedingly efficacious, and in the
complaints of young females its success has been most decided in giving health to the frame, and
bloom to the cheek; it assists the growth, and prevents (in those predisposed) the development of
consumption and scrofula. To the aged and infirm, it will impart energy and strength to the body,
cheerfulness and serenity to the mind. In loss of appetite, spasms, cramp of the stomach, nervous
headache, and lassitude from any cause, it will afford immediate relief. All those debilitated by
luxurious living, late hours, vexation, intense study, or confinement to business, will find this
cordial their best friend.—Price 4s. 6d. and 11s. per bottle. Sold by Boddington and Co., 90,
Charlotte-street, Rathbone-place; T. Butler, 4, Cheapside; and Sanger, 150, Oxford-street, London;
J. and R. Raimes, Edinburgh: New Apothecaries' Hall, Glasgow; and all Medicine Venders.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >FURS.</head>
<p >BOURNE' and SON, Successors to Mr. SCHNEIDER, 244, Regent Street, solicit respectfully the
Nobility and Gentry to inspect their extensive and valuable Stock of Furs, consisting of Russian and
Hudson's Bay Sables, Ermine, Chinchilla, German Martin Sable, Squirrel, and all other fashionable
Furs. Also Sable Tail, India, and Ostrich Feather Boas.—Bourne and Son having purchased a very
large quantity of Skins, which they have manufactured into fashionable Capes, Boas, &amp;c., which
they will warrant to be of the most perfect quality and manufacture. The great patronage B. and Son
have received has enabled them to mark their stock at prices very advantageous to purchasers.</p>
<p >N.B.—Furs Cleaned, Altered, and Repaired, or the full value allowed in exchange.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >COMFORT TO THE FEET.</head>
<p >PANNUSCORIUM OR LEATHER-CLOTH BOOTS AND SHOES, AND INDIA RUBBER WATERPROOF GOLOSHES.</p>
<p >EASE and Comfort in Walking, softness and elasticity to the most sensitive parts of the feet,
combined with the durability and appearance of leather, are the leading features and recommendations
of this invention.</p>
<p >Every lady and gentleman who suffers from tender feet arising from Corns, Bunions, Chilblains,
Distortion of the Toes, Gout, &amp;c. &amp;c., will, on trial, admit their great superiority over
every other kind of Shoes.</p>
<p >HALL AND CO. PATENTRES, Wellington Street, Strand, London.</p>
<p >The Patent India Rubber Waterproof Goloshes are the lightest and most useful and economical
article of the kind ever invented for keeping the feet dry.</p>
<p >H. &amp; Co. submit to the Public their newly invented Waterproof Dresses for Ladies and
Gentlemen, so portable that they may be carried with convenience in the pocket. Price—Ladies'
Cardinals, with Hood, &amp;c., 18s. Gentlemen's Dresses, comprising Cape, Over-alls, and Hood,
21s.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >MINERAL MAGNETS.—</head>
<p >Dr. SCHMIDT, of Berlin, having discovered a method of constructing Magnets of any power of
attraction, has succeeded in establishing their use as a certain and powerful remedy, when applied
according to his own practice, in the following Nervous and Functional Disorders:—Deafness,
either Rheumatic or Nervous, Tie Douloureux, Weakness of the Eye, from over exertion or age, in
Incipient Cataract, in general or partial Weakness of the Body, Pains arising from old wounds,
Headach, nervous or rheumatic, in Toothach or Faceach, in Hystery, Palsy, Gout, Tremors, Dizziness,
&amp;c.</p>
<p >Magnets, with directions for their medical use, may be obtained from Dr. Schmidt, who can be
consulted at his residence, 21, Half Moon-street, Piccadilly, from ten till four o'clock daily. Many
well authenticated cases have occurred since Dr. Schmidt's practice in London, which can be referred
to if required.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >EXTRACT OF ROSES FOR
<lb/> WASHING THE HAIR.</head>
<p >THIS much esteemed and elegant article is strongly recommended to the Nobility and Gentry, as not
only the most delicate and effectual preservative of the Hair, in its softest texture and pristine
colour, but as contributing to it a gloss and brightness which most cosmetic preparations, from
being composed of ardent spirits, destroy. By its use the Hair soon becomes soft and luxuriant, and
all harshness, from whatever cause arising, especially from sea bathing, is speedily removed; after
strong exercise, or in warm climates, its refreshing qualities must be proved to be appreciated.</p>
<p >Manufactured and sold by Rigge, Brockbank, and Rigge, 35, New Bond Street. Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per
Bottle.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >LADIES' BEST GOLD CHAINS.—</head>
<p >The weight is given by comparison with the weight of Sovereigns, being more easily referred to
than if stated in ounces and dwts. The quality of the gold is warranted equal to any that is worked
into articles of this description.</p>
<p >
<table>
<head>PRICES OF THE CABLE &amp; MATTED
<lb/> RING PATTERNS.</head>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 3 sovs.</cell>
<cell>£4</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 4 sovs.</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 5 sovs.</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 6 sovs.</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 7 sovs.</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 8 sovs.</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >
<table>
<head>The above Patterns, with bright star ornaments on every link.</head>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 3 sovs.</cell>
<cell>£5</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 4 sovs.</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 5 sovs.</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 6 sovs.</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 7 sovs.</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Same weight as 8 sovs.</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >NEW FLAT GOLD WATCHES.</head>
<p >
<table>
<head>VERTICAL CONSTRUCTION.</head>
<row>
<cell>The price, in gold cases, with well finished movements, warranted</cell>
<cell>£7</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table><table>
<head>HORIZONTAL CONSTRUCTION.</head>
<row>
<cell>The price, with accurately finished movements, in double-bottomed engine-turned cases,
jewelled, with silver dial, warranted</cell>
<cell>£9</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >THE PERFORMANCE OF THE HORIZONTAL CONSTRUCTION WILL BE FOUND EXCEEDINGLY ACCURATE.</p>
<p >T. COX SAVORY's,
<lb/> Working Silversmith &amp; Jeweller,
<lb/> 47, CORNHILL, LONDON.</p>
<p >A variety of Second-hand Silver Watches may be selected from all at two guineas each,
warranted.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pviii"/>
<head >THE MODERN TOILETTE.</head>
<p >The prevalence of refined TASTE, aided by JUDICIOUS SELECTION, is fast rendering this really
important department efficient and available for the promotion of the PERSONAL GRACES; the most
valued of these, a CLEAR and RADIANT COMPLEXION, is attained and preserved with pleasing facility by
the use of </p>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head > GOWLAND'S LOTION,</head>
<p >A preparation of which the SAFETY and UTILITY are demonstrated by the precedence it retains after
nearly a CENTURY of successful experience, as the most CONGENIAL appendage of the MODERN TOILET.
Cutaneous affections, irritability, and DISCOLORATIONS consequent upon variable temperature, and
other causes, subside upon its application, the Skin acquiring purity of surface, and the Complexion
a distinguishing and permanent freshness of tint.</p>
<p >GOWLAND'S LOTION has the Name and Address of the Proprietor, ROBERT SHAW, 33, QUEEN STREET,
CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, engraved on the Government Stamp, and each package is enclosed in the popular
Work entitled the “THEORY OF BEAUTY.” Prices 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> Quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> and in cases adapted for Travelling, and the
fashionable transits of the Season, from One to Five Guineas. Sold as above, and by respectable
Perfumers and Medicine Venders.</p>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >SHAW'S MINDORA OIL.</head>
<p >The admirers of ELEGANT and appropriate NOVELTY will be highly gratified by the COMPARATIVE
SUPERIORITY of this pre-eminent RESTORATIVE and BEAUTIFIER of the HAIR, in the several properties in
which it differs from all factitious articles of similar import; Mindora Oil possesses a native
PURITY and delicately subdued Fragrance perfectly unique, is unalloyed by COLOURING SUBSTANCES or
CHEMICAL ADMIXTURE, and presents, in point of CLEANLINESS, preservation of the original shade of the
Hair, and for the growth and embellishment of this esteemed ornament, the most acceptable medium for
the use of both sexes.</p>
<p >PREPARED for the TOILET by ROBERT SHAW, 33, QUEEN STREET, CHEAPSIDE. LONDON, (whose Signature
appears on the Label and Wrapper), in Bottles, enclosed in a practical TREATISE ON THE HAIR, at 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and in Stoppered
Bottles at 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Sold by the Proprietor as above,
and by Sanger, Hannay, Oxford-street; Prout, Strand; Rigge, Cheapside; and most respectable
Perfumers and Medicine Venders.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >CROSBY-HALL WINE ESTABLISHMENT, </head>
<p > 35, BISHOPSGATE-STREET-WITHIN.</p>
<p >CURRALL and SON, in tendering to their Friends and the Public their grateful acknowledgments for
the liberal patronage they have enjoyed for a period of nearly 30 years, beg to announce the
completion of their extensive Vaults under Crosby Hall, and to invite public notice to their stock
of Old Bottled and Draught Wines. Their Crusted Ports are of superior quality and flavour, being
shipped by houses of high reputation at Oporto, and bottled with sedulous attention. Their Sherries
also, with every other description of White Wines, are of equal character; and in Draught Wines the
same attention has been paid to quality. CURRALL and SON, being desirous to secure that patronage
which articles of the first quality, at fair and remunerating profits, will maintain, respectfully
submit the annexed list of cash prices:</p>
<p >
<table>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>PER DOZ.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Port from the wood</cell>
<cell>28s. to 33s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Port from the wood, three years in bottle</cell>
<cell>36s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Port from the wood, older, rich, and superior</cell>
<cell>42s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Port from the wood, very old, in wood and bottle</cell>
<cell>46s.</cell>
<cell>to 48s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Port from the wood, in pints</cell>
<cell>24s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, excellent dinner wine</cell>
<cell>28s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Superior Sherries</cell>
<cell>36s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, very fine, pale and brown</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>42s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, high-flavoured pale</cell>
<cell>46s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, choice old brown</cell>
<cell>46s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, very delicate, and extremely pale</cell>
<cell>52s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, old brown (rare quality)</cell>
<cell>52s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry, in pints, pale and brown</cell>
<cell>21s. to 24s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Brown Sherry of unusual quality in quarter casks. Madeira</cell>
<cell>38s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Madeira (by way of Calcutta), first quality</cell>
<cell>63s. to 66s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Madeira, in pints</cell>
<cell>33s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Bucellas (finest quality)</cell>
<cell>35s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Lisbon and Mountain</cell>
<cell>30s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Vidonia (old)</cell>
<cell>30s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Marsala</cell>
<cell>24s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Rota Tent</cell>
<cell>42s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cape Wines</cell>
<cell>16s. to 20s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Masdeu, the produce of the Masdeu Vineyards of Messrs. Durand and Co.</cell>
<cell>28s.</cell>
</row>
</table><table>
<head>FRENCH AND RHENISH WINES.</head>
<row>
<cell>White Sparkling Champagne</cell>
<cell>60s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Pink Sparkling Champagne</cell>
<cell>72s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Pink creaming Campagne</cell>
<cell>72s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>White creaming Campagne</cell>
<cell>72s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Claret</cell>
<cell>60s. to 63s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Claret, in pints</cell>
<cell>33s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Moselle</cell>
<cell>48s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sauterne</cell>
<cell>48s. to 60s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Hock</cell>
<cell>48s. to 60s.</cell>
</row>
</table><table>
<head>WINES PER GALLON.</head>
<row>
<cell>Port</cell>
<cell>12s. to 14s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sherry</cell>
<cell>13s. to 15s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cape</cell>
<cell>7s. to 8s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Marsala</cell>
<cell>11s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Marsala, finest imported, per quarter pipe</cell>
<cell>11<hi>l.</hi> 11s.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >Bottles, 3s. per dozen; hampers, 1s. per dozen, to be paid for, and the full amount allowed when
returned.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pix"/>
<head >TEETH.</head>
<p >A SAVING of TWENTY GUINEAS. The extraordinary improvements of late years being so little known to
those who visit the old practitioners, induces Mr. MOGGRIDGE to give publicity to his recent
invention in MODELLING, completing from one to a full set, and only requiring one visit; this
discovery not only saves trouble and anxiety to the patient, but allows them to be fixed without
spring clasps or wires, remaining more secure than any other method, supporting the other teeth,
fastening those that are loose without extracting or filing the roots, erasing the wrinkles from the
cheeks, and warranted for durability, mastication, and articulation. A complete set, fastened in
artificial gums or fine gold, natural or mineral, incorrodible teeth, Ten Guineas, the same as
charged thirty.—Mr. Moggridge, surgeon-dentist, 35, Conduit Street, Bond Street, formerly
pupil and sole assistant for ten years to Messrs. Parkinson.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >THE ORIGINAL PATENT PIN,</head>
<p >made by DURNFORD and CO., Manufacturers to their Royal Highnesses the Duchess of Kent and the
Princess Victoria.</p>
<p >This superior Patent Ornamental Pin still continues unrivalled in quality and price by any yet
produced. It is sold retail by all respectable Haberdashers, &amp;c., and supplied by DURNFORD and
Co., London and Gloucester; of whom also may be had, the best Black Mourning Pins, and superior
Drilled-eyed Needles.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >TO FLUTE PLAYERS.</head>
<p >W. &amp; N. BOAG solicit the attention of Flute Players to an extensive collection of their
FLUTES, which combine every desirable quality of the instrument, being finished in the first style
of workmanship, well seasoned, possessing great power and sweetness of tone, correctly in tune, and
at more than 30 per cent, under the prices usually charged for first-rate Flutes. An extensive
variety of excellent Second-hand Flutes by Rudall, Monzani, Prowse, and other Makers. An assortment
of Eight-Keyed (German Silver) Cocoa Flutes, Three Guineas each. Flutes exchanged or purchased.
Repairs in a superior style. No. 11, Great Turnstile, Holborn.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >LEVER WATCHES.</head>
<p >MASSEY'S PATENT DETACHED LEVER WATCHES, Capped, Jewelled, with maintaining Power and Seconds, may
be had from Six Guineas, and Ladies' Gold Verge Watches at Nine Guineas each,
warranted.—Watches of every description carefully repaired. Second-hand Watches taken in
exchange.</p>
<closer >MASSEY and WINDHAM, Patent Lever Watch Manufacturers, 4, Birchin Lane, and 78, Cornhill,
London.</closer>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >HER MAJESTY VICTORIA THE FIRST—</head>
<p >Her August Mother, the Duchess of Kent—His late Majesty William the Fourth—the
Dowager Queen Adelaide—the King of Hanover—the Duke of Sussex—the Duke of
Wellington—with all the leading Characters of the day,—the whole taken from life, are
now added to Madame TUSSAUD and SON'S Exhibition, Bazaar, Baker Street, Portman Square. Admittance,
1s. Second Room, 6d. Open from Eleven till Six, and from Seven till Ten. Brilliantly
illuminated.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >J. C. &amp; C. PENN, BOOT and SHOE MANUFACTURERS, 143, HOLBORN BARS, </head>
<p >beg to direct the attention of the Public to the immense assortment of Ladies', Gentlemen's,
Youths', and Children's Boots and Shoes, now on sale at their Establishment, “The Cordwainers'
Arms,” as above—consisting of every possible variety—suitable to all climes and
seasons, and combining the very best materials and workmanship, with the lowest possible price. The
following are a few of the articles particularly worthy of notice:—Ladies' double sole Boots
from 5s. 6d.; single sole ditto from 4s. 6d.; Leather and Prunello Shoes, double soles. from 4s.;
ditto ditto single soles from 2s. 6d.; real Morocco and kid Slippers 3s. 6d.; Gentlemen's Wellington
Boots from 14s.; Clarence Boots from 10s.; Blucher Boots from 6s. 6d.; Walking Shoes from 6s. 6d.;
single ditto ditto from 4s. 6d. A great variety of extra strong Boots and Shoes for Shooting.</p>
<p >An immense stock of Gentlemen's Boots and Shoes suitable for the export and wholesale trade
constantly on hand at the very lowest manufacturers' price.</p>
<p >Country Dealers supplied.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >HOW TO GET A GOOD DRESSING!!!</head>
<lg  type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">REFORM the State, with voice elate, let Politicians shout;</l>
<l part="N">Reform the Lords, Reform the Church, Reform the Land throughout;</l>
<l part="N"><choice xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><sic>Beform</sic><corr>Reform</corr></choice> your house, your plans, your purse, your ailments and your
ills;</l>
<l part="N">But oh! above all things, cry we, REFORM YOUR TAILORS' BILLS!!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Perhaps you say, in sore dismay, “How can the thing be done?”</l>
<l part="N">Whereat we cry, most easily, with DOUDNEY AND SON,</l>
<l part="N">Of <hi rend="italics">Lombard Street,</hi> at <hi rend="italics">Forty Nine,</hi> the number's on
the door;—</l>
<l part="N"><hi rend="italics">Established Anno Seventeen Hundred and Eighty Four.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Your person in a perfect Suit they'll prominently fix,</l>
<l part="N">In such as all who see admire, for <hi rend="italics">Three Pounds Twelve and Six,</hi></l>
<l part="N">GOOD WORK, GOOD CLOTH, GOOD QUALITY, and Patterns all the go!</l>
<l part="N">And MORNING COATS, the price <hi rend="italics">Fifteen</hi>—the charge,’ you'll own,
is low.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">And oh, ye SPORTSMEN, listen now, while we your pleasures cater,</l>
<l part="N">For <hi rend="italics">Two Pounds Ten,</hi> your Suit complete, including Leather Gaiter.</l>
<l part="N">Their TROUSERS, too, of many sorts, for Fishing or for Trav'ling,</l>
<l part="N">The price is small,—<hi rend="italics">Thirteen and Six,</hi>—and safe from all
unrav'ling.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Their PILOT JACKETS, <hi rend="italics">One Pound Ten,</hi> in which no man can founder,</l>
<l part="N">And PETERSHAM GREAT COATS the same,—a very warm wrap-rounder.</l>
<l part="N">The GUINEA CLOAK, a <hi rend="italics">Waterproof,</hi> which will withstand all
weather,—</l>
<l part="N">A proper “COMFORT IN A STORM,”—and wear as strong as leather.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Or if within your carriage green you're leisurely reclined,</l>
<l part="N">A fine fat Coachman on the box, and Footman tall behind;</l>
<l part="N">The moment their old suit shows rust, on collar, cuff, or knee,</l>
<l part="N">A LIVERY they'll furnish each for only <hi rend="italics">Three Pounds Three.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Then as for BOYS, the wearing dogs, who tear their clothes to pieces,</l>
<l part="N">They'll clothe them in good Coats and Frocks, your GIRLS in smart Pelisses;</l>
<l part="N">And should you want them Ready-made,—they say it without roguery,</l>
<l part="N">No House can show so cheap a Stock of Little Urchin's Toggery.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">Moreover, DOUDNEYS were the first who very kindly proffered</l>
<l part="N">Their Yearly Contracts for our Clothes,—the Cheapest over offered.</l>
<l part="N">Two SUITS <hi rend="italics">a-Year at Eight Pounds Six,</hi> and THREE for <hi rend="italics">Twelve Pounds Five,</hi></l>
<l part="N">Or FOUR for <hi rend="italics">Fifteen Pounds Eighteen,</hi>—'Tis you the benefit
derive.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">THREE WAISTCOATS for <hi rend="italics">One Pound</hi> they sell; and TROUSERS, Cantoons,
Drillings,—</l>
<l part="N">The Newest Patterns that are out,—THREE PAIRS for <hi rend="italics">Thirty
Shillings.</hi></l>
<l part="N">DOUDNEY AND SON, of <hi rend="italics">Lombard Street,</hi> their promises fulfil,</l>
<l part="N">The CITY MART'S at <hi rend="italics">Forty Nine</hi>—REFORM YOUR TAILOR'S BILL!</l>
</lg>
</lg>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="px"/>
<opener >TO FAMILIES
<lb/> TRAVELLING, PROMENADING, OR ENJOYING AQUATIC
<lb/> EXCURSIONS.</opener>
<head > ROWLAND'S
<lb/> KALYDOR.</head>
<p >THE ONLY EFFICIENT PROTECTOR OF THE SKIN.</p>
<p >THIS delightful preparation is extracted from Exotics of the mildest and most balsamic nature, is
warranted perfectly innocent, and free from mineral admixture—operating as a powerful cleanser
of the skin, it speedily eradicates Freckles, Tan, Pimples, Spots, Redness, and every other
Cutaneous defect, while its most remarkable property is, the removal of every trace of Sallowness
from the Complexion, which it restores to a freshness of tint, exciting both surprise and the most
pleasurable sensations.</p>
<p >Perseverance in the use of the Kalydor preserves unimpaired, those important functions of the
skin on which depend its purity, softness—not inaptly compared to velvet—and elasticity;
the Neck, Hands, and Arms assuming and retaining the radiant whiteness so much admired, and so
unequivocal a mark of attention to the niceties of the Toilet, and the Graces of Personal
Attraction.</p>
<p >It protects the Face and Skin from the injurious effects of the Sun and Dust during Travelling,
Promenading, or the enjoyment of Aquatic Excursions; and in cases of Sun-burns, Stings of Insects,
Parched Lips, Harsh Rough Skin, and an unpleasant heat of the Face, it immediately allays the
smarting irritability of the skin, as well as all inflammation, diffusing a DELIGHTFUL and PLEASING
COOLNESS.</p>
<p >To Gentlemen whose faces are tender after shaving, Rowland's Kalydor will be found excellent
beyond precedent, in ameliorating and allaying the irritation and smarting pain, and rendering the
skin soft and smooth.</p>
<p >This exotic preparation is perfectly innoxious, acting in all cases by promoting a healthy tone
of the minute vessels, and is the most elegant as well as effective preparation hitherto submitted
to universal patronage.</p>
<p >Sold in Half Pint Bottles, at 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, and
in Pints, at 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, duty included.</p>
<p >NOTICE.—The Name and Address of the Proprietors,
<lb/> A. ROWLAND AND SON, 20, HATTON GARDEN, LONDON,
<lb/> is engraved on the Government Stamp, which is pasted on each Bottle; also printed in RED, on
the Wrapper in which each is enclosed.</p>
<p >Many Shopkeepers sell Counterfeits of the above, composed of the most pernicious ingredients.
They call their <hi rend="italics">trash</hi> the “GENUINE,” and sign <hi rend="italics">A. RowlandSon,</hi> omitting the “&amp;”, recommending them as being <hi rend="italics">Cheap.</hi></p>
<p >Be sure to ask for Rowland's.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >ROWLAND'S
<lb/> ODONTO.</head>
<p >OR PEARL DENTIFRICE.</p>
<p >A Vegetable White Powder, prepared from Oriental Herbs of the most delicious odour and sweetness,
and free from any mineral, or pernicious ingredient. It eradicates tartar from the teeth, removes
decayed spots, preserves the enamel, and fixes the teeth firmly in their sockets, rendering them
beautifully white. It eradicates scurvy from the gums, strengthens, braces, and renders them of a
healthy red; it removes unpleasant tastes from the mouth, after fevers, taking medicine, &amp;c.,
and imparts a delightful fragrance to the breath. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per Box.</p>
<p >NOTICE.—The Name and Address of the Proprietor,
<lb/> A. Rowland &amp; Son, 20, Hatton Garden, London,
<lb/> Is engraved on the Government Stamp, which is pasted on each Box.</p>
<p >Be sure to ask for “ROWLAND'S.”</p>
<p >Sold by them, and by respectable Perfumers and Medicine Venders.</p>
</div>
</div>
</front>
<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pxi"/>
<p >
<figure xml:id="ill4"> </figure>
</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pxii"/>
<p >
<figure xml:id="ill5"> </figure>
</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pxiii"/>
<head >NEW WORK BY “BOZ.”</head>
<p >Messrs. CHAPMAN and HALL have the pleasure of announcing that they have completed arrangements
with Mr. CHARLES DICKENS, for the production of an ENTIRELY NEW WORK, to be published monthly, at
the same price, and in the same form, as the PICKWICK PAPERS. The first Number will appear on the
31st of March, 1838.</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<head >SKETCHES BY “BOZ.”</head>
<p >Messrs. CHAPMAN and HALL also beg to announce that they have purchased the entire Copyrights of
both Series of these popular Works, for the purpose of enabling the Subscribers to the PICKWICK
PAPERS to obtain the whole in one book of the same size, and at the same price. With this view, they
purpose publishing the complete collection in Twenty Monthly Numbers, price One Shilling each. The
first Number will appear on the 1st of November next, embellished (as will be all its successors)
with Two Illustrations, by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p>
<closer >186, STRAND,
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">August</hi> 26, 1837.</closer>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pxiv"/>
<head >New Works
<lb/> PREPARING FOR PUBLICATION.</head>
<div type="section">
<opener >I.
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In One Volume, square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo,</hi></opener>
<head >THE JUVENILE BUDGET;</head>
<p > OR,
<lb/> Stories for Little Readers:
<lb/> CHIEFLY COLLECTED FROM “THE JUVENILE FORGET-ME-NOT.”</p>
<p >BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p>
<p >WITH
<lb/> SIX ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<opener >II.
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In One Volume, square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo.</hi></opener>
<head >MORALS FROM THE CHURCH-YARD;</head>
<p >IN
<lb/> A SERIES OF CHEERFUL FABLES FOR THE YOUTH OF
<lb/> BOTH SEXES.</p>
<p >WITH
<lb/> EIGHT BEAUTIFULLY ENGRAVED ILLUSTRATIONS ON WOOD;
<lb/> FROM DESIGNS BY H. K. BROWNE.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<opener >III. </opener>
<head >A VISIT TO
<lb/> THE BRITISH MUSEUM:</head>
<p > CONTAINING
<lb/> A FAMILIAR DESCRIPTION OF EVERY OBJECT OF INTEREST
<lb/> IN THE
<lb/> VARIOUS DEPARTMENTS OF THAT ESTABLISHMENT
<lb/> WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS. </p>
<closer >CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND</closer>
</div>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="text">
<pb  xml:id="p499"/>
<head >[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head>
<div type="chapter">
<head >CHAPTER XLVI.</head>
<head > IS CHIEFLY DEVOTED TO MATTERS OF BUSINESS, AND THE TEMPORAL ADVANTAGE OF DODSON AND
FOGG.—MR. WINKLE REAPPEARS UNDER EXTRAORDINARY CIRCUMSTANCES; AND MR. PICKWICK'S BENEVOLENCE
PROVES STRONGER THAN HIS OBSTINACY. </head>
<p >JOB TROTTER, abating nothing of his speed, ran up Holborn, sometimes in the middle of the road,
sometimes on the pavement, and sometimes in the gutter, as the chances of getting along varied with
the press of men, women, children, and coaches, in each division of the thoroughfare, and,
regardless of all obstacles, stopped not for an instant until he reached the gate of Gray's Inn.
Notwithstanding all the expedition he had used, however, the gate had been closed a good half hour
when he reached it, and by the time he had discovered Mr. Perker's laundress, who lived with a
married daughter, who had bestowed her hand upon a non-resident waiter, and occupied the one-pair of
some number, in some street, closely adjoining to some brewery, somewhere behind Gray's Inn Lane, it
was within fifteen minutes of the time of closing the prison for the night. Mr. Lowten had still to
be ferreted out from the back parlour of the Magpie and Stump; and Job had scarcely accomplished
this object, and communicated Sam Weller's message, than the clock struck ten.</p>
<p >“There,” said Lowten, “it's too late now. You can't get in tonight; you've got
the key of the street, my friend.”</p>
<p >“Never mind me,” replied Job, “I can sleep anywhere. But won't it be better to
see Mr. Perker to-night, so that we may be there, the first thing in the morning?”</p>
<p >“Why,” responded Lowten, after a little consideration, “if it was in any body
else's case, Perker wouldn't be best pleased at my going up to his house, but as it's Mr.
Pickwick's, I think I may venture to take a cab and charge it to the office.” Deciding upon
this line of conduct, Mr. Lowten took up his hat, and begging the assembled company to appoint a
deputy chairman during his temporary absence, led the way to the nearest coach stand, and summoning
the cab of most promising appearance, directed the driver to repair to Montague Place, Russell
Square.</p>
<p >Mr. Perker had had a dinner party that day, as was testified by the appearance of lights in the
drawing-room windows, the sound of an improved grand piano, and an improveable cabinet voice issuing
therefrom; and a rather overpowering smell of meat which pervaded the steps and entry. In fact a
couple of very good country agencies happening to come up to town at the same time, an agreeable
little party had been got together to meet them, comprising Mr. Snicks the <pb xml:id="p500"/>
Life Office Secretary, Mr. Prosee the eminent counsel, three solicitors, one commissioner of
bankrupts, a special pleader from the Temple, a small-eyed peremptory young gentleman, his pupil,
who had written a lively book about the law of demises, with a vast quantity of marginal notes and
references; and several other eminent and distinguished personages. From this society little Mr.
Perker detached himself on his clerk being announced in a whisper; and repairing to the dining-room,
there found Mr. Lowten and Job Trotter looking very dim and shadowy by the light of a kitchen
candle, which the gentleman who condescended to appear in plush shorts and cottons for a quarterly
stipend, had, with a becoming contempt for the clerk and all things appertaining to “the
office,” placed upon the table.</p>
<p >“Now, Lowten,” said little Mr. Perker, shutting the door, “what's the matter?
No important letter come in a parcel, is there?”</p>
<p >“No, Sir,” replied Lowten. “This is a messenger from Mr. Pickwick,
Sir.”</p>
<p >“From Pickwick, eh?” said the little man, turning quickly to Job. “Well; what
is it?”</p>
<p >“Dodson and Fogg have taken Mrs. Bardell in execution for her costs, Sir,” said
Job.</p>
<p >“No!” exclaimed Perker, putting his hands in his pockets, and reclining against the
sideboard.</p>
<p >“Yes,” said Job. “It seems they got a cognovit out of her for the amount of'em,
directly after the trial.”</p>
<p >“By Jove!” said Perker, taking both hands out of his pockets and striking the
knuckles of his right against the palm of his left, emphatically, “those are the cleverest
scamps I ever had any thing to do with!”</p>
<p >“The sharpest practitioners <hi rend="italics">I</hi> ever knew, Sir,” observed
Lowten.</p>
<p >“Sharp!” echoed Perker. “There's no knowing where to have them.”</p>
<p >“Very true, Sir, there is not,” replied Lowten; and then both master and man pondered
for a few seconds with animated countenances, as if they were reflecting upon one of the most
beautiful and ingenious discoveries that the intellect of man had ever made. When they had in some
measure recovered from their trance of admiration, Job Trotter discharged himself of the rest of his
commission. Perker nodded his head thoughtfully, and pulled out his watch.</p>
<p >“At ten precisely I will be there,” said the little man. “Sam is quite right.
Tell him so. Will you take a glass of wine, Lowten?”</p>
<p >“No, thank you, Sir.”</p>
<p >“You mean yes, I think,” said the little man, turning to the sideboard for a decanter
and glasses.</p>
<p >As Lowten <hi rend="italics">did</hi> mean yes, he said no more upon the subject but enquired of
Job, in an audible whisper, whether the portrait of Perker, which hung opposite the fire-place,
wasn't a wonderful likeness, to which Job of course replied that it was. The wine being by this time
poured out, Lowten drank to Mrs. Perker and the children, and Job to Perker. The gentleman in the
plush shorts and cottons considering it no part of his duty to show the people from the office out,
consistently <pb xml:id="p501"/> declined to answer the bell, and they showed themselves out.
The attorney betook himself to his drawing-room, the clerk to the Magpie and Stump, and Job to
Covent Garden Market to spend the night in a vegetable basket.</p>
<p >Punctually at the appointed hour next morning the good-humoured little attorney tapped at Mr.
Pickwick's door, which was opened with great alacrity by Sam Weller.</p>
<p >“Mr. Perker, Sir,” said Sam, announcing the visitor to Mr. Pickwick, who was sitting
at the window in a thoughtful attitude. “Wery glad you've looked in accidentally, Sir. I
rayther think the gov'ner vants to have a vord and a half vith you, Sir.”</p>
<p >Perker bestowed a look of intelligence upon Sam, intimating that he understood he was not to say
he had been sent for: and beckoning him to approach, whispered briefly in his ear.</p>
<p >“Vy, you don't mean that'ere, Sir?” said Sam, starting back in excessive
surprise.</p>
<p >Perker nodded and smiled.</p>
<p >Mr. Samuel Weller looked at the little lawyer, then at Mr. Pickwick, then at the ceiling, then at
Perker again; grinned, laughed outright, and finally, catching up his hat from the carpet, without
further explanation disappeared.</p>
<p >“What does this mean?” enquired Mr. Pickwick, looking at Perker with astonishment.
“What has put Sam into this most extraordinary state?”</p>
<p >“Oh, nothing, nothing,” replied Perker. “Come my dear Sir, draw up your chair
to the table. I have a good deal to say to you.”</p>
<p >“What papers are those?” enquired Mr. Pickwick, as the little man deposited on the
table a small bundle of documents tied with red tape.</p>
<p >“The papers in Bardell and Pickwick,” replied Perker, undoing the knot with his
teeth.</p>
<p >Mr. Pickwick grated the legs of his chair against the ground; and throwing himself into it,
folded his hands and looked sternly—if Mr. Pickwick ever could look sternly—at his legal
friend.</p>
<p >“You don't like to hear the name of the case?” said the little man, still busying
himself with the knot.</p>
<p >“No, I do not indeed,” replied Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“Sorry for that,” resumed Perker, “because it will form the subject of our
conversation.”</p>
<p >“I would rather that the subject was never mentioned between us, Perker,” interposed
Mr. Pickwick hastily.</p>
<p >“Pooh pooh, my dear Sir,” said the little man, untying the bundle, and glancing
eagerly at Mr. Pickwick out of the corners of his eyes. “It must be mentioned. I have come
here on purpose. Now, are you ready to what I have to say, my dear Sir? No hurry; if you are not, I
can wait. I have got this morning's paper here. Your time shall be mine. There.” Hereupon the
little man threw one leg over the other, and made a show of beginning to read, with great composure
and application.</p>
<p >“Well, well,” said Mr. Pickwick with a sigh, but softening into a smile at the same
time. “Say what you have to say; it's the old story I suppose?”</p>
<pb  xml:id="p502"/>
<p >“With a difference, my dear Sir; with a difference,” rejoined Perker, deliberately
folding up the paper and putting it into his pocket again. “Mrs. Bardell, the plaintiff in the
action, is within these walls, Sir.”</p>
<p >“I know it,” was Mr. Pickwick's reply.</p>
<p >“Very good,” retorted Perker. “And you know how she comes here, I suppose; I
mean on what grounds, and at whose suit?”</p>
<p >“Yes; at least I have heard Sam's account of the matter,” said Mr. Pickwick, with
affected carelessness.</p>
<p >“Sam's account of the matter,” replied Perker, “is, I will venture to say, a
perfectly correct one. Well now, my dear Sir, the first question I have to ask, is, whether this
woman is to remain here?”</p>
<p >“To remain here!” echoed Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“To remain here, my dear Sir,” rejoined Perker, leaning back in his chair and looking
steadily at his client.</p>
<p >“How can you ask me?” said that gentleman. “It rests with Dodson and Fogg; you
know that very well.”</p>
<p >“I know nothing of the kind,” retorted Perker firmly. “It does <hi rend="italics">not</hi> rest with Dodson and Fogg; you know the men, my dear Sir, as well as I do.
It rests solely, wholly, and entirely with you.”</p>
<p >“With me!” ejaculated Mr. Pickwick, rising nervously from his chair, and reseating
himself directly afterwards.</p>
<p >The little man gave a double knock on the lid of his snuff-box, opened it, took a great pinch,
shut it up again, and repeated the words “—With you.”</p>
<p >“I say, my dear Sir,” pursued the little man, who seemed to gather confidence from
the snuff; “I say that her speedy liberation or perpetual imprisonment rests with you, and
with you alone. Hear me out, my dear Sir, if you please, and do not be so very energetic, for it
will only put you into a perspiration and do no good whatever. I say,” continued Perker,
checking off each position on a different finger, as he laid it down; “I say that nobody but
you can rescue her from this den of wretchedness; and that you can only do that, by paying the costs
of this suit—both of plaintiff and defendant—into the hands of these Freeman Court
sharks. Now pray be quiet, my dear Sir.”</p>
<p >Mr. Pickwick, whose face had been undergoing most surprising changes during this speech, and who
was evidently on the verge of a strong burst of indignation, calmed his wrath as well as he could;
and Perker, strengthening his argumentative powers with another pinch of snuff, proceeded.</p>
<p >“I have seen the woman this morning. By paying the costs, you can obtain a full release and
discharge from the damages; and further—this I know is a far greater object of consideration
with you, my dear Sir—a voluntary statement under her hand, in the form of a letter to me,
that this business was from the very first, fomented and encouraged and brought about, by these men,
Dodson and Fogg; that she deeply regrets ever having been the instrument of annoyance or injury to
you; and that she entreats me to intercede with you, and implore your pardon.”</p>
<p >“If I pay her costs for her,” said Mr. Pickwick, indignantly; “a valuable
document, indeed!”</p>
<pb  xml:id="p503"/>
<p >“No ‘<hi rend="italics">if</hi>’ in the case, my dear Sir,” said Perker,
triumphantly. “There is the very letter I speak of. Brought to my office by another woman at
nine o'clock this morning, before I had set foot in this place, or held any communication with Mrs.
Bardell, upon my honour.” And selecting the letter from the bundle, the little lawyer laid it
at Mr. Pickwick's elbow, and took snuff for two consecutive minutes without winking.</p>
<p >“Is this all you have to say to me?” enquired Mr. Pickwick, mildly.</p>
<p >“Not quite,” replied Perker. “I cannot undertake to say at this moment, whether
the wording of the cognovit, the nature of the ostensible consideration, and the proof we can get
together about the whole conduct of the suit, will be sufficient to justify an indictment for
conspiracy. I fear not, my dear Sir; they are too clever for that, I doubt. I do mean to say,
however, that the whole facts, taken together, will be sufficient to justify you in the minds of all
reasonable men. And now, my dear Sir, I put it to you. This one hundred and fifty pounds, or
whatever it may be—take it in round numbers—is nothing to you. A jury has decided
against you; well, their verdict is wrong, but still they decided as they thought right, and it <hi rend="italics">is</hi> against you. You have now an opportunity, on easy terms, of placing yourself
in a much higher position than you ever could by remaining here; which would only be imputed by
people who didn't know you to sheer, dogged, wrongheaded, brutal obstinacy: nothing else, my dear
Sir, believe me. Can you hesitate to avail yourself of it, when it restores you to your friends,
your old pursuits, your health and amusements; when it liberates your faithful and attached servant,
whom you otherwise doom to imprisonment for the whole of your life? and above all, when it enables
you to take the very magnanimous revenge—which I know, my dear Sir, is one after your own
heart—of releasing this woman from a scene of misery and debauchery, to which no man should
ever be consigned if I had my will, but the infliction of which, on any female, is frightful and
barbarous. Now I ask you, my dear Sir, not only as your legal adviser, but as your very true friend,
will you let slip the occasion of attaining all these objects and doing all this good, for the
paltry consideration of a few pounds finding their way into the pockets of a couple of rascals, to
whom it makes no manner of difference, except that the more they gain the more they'll seek, and so
the sooner be led into some piece of knavery that must end in a crash? I have put these
considerations to you, my dear Sir, very feebly and imperfectly, but I ask you to think of
them—turn them over in your mind as long as you please: I wait here most patiently for your
answer.”</p>
<p >Before Mr. Pickwick could reply, before Mr. Perker had taken one twentieth part of the snuff
which so unusually long an address imperatively required to be followed up with, there was a low
murmuring of voices outside, and then a hesitating knock at the door.</p>
<p >“Dear, dear,” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, who had been evidently roused by his friend's
appeal; “what an annoyance that door is! Who is that?”</p>
<p >“Me, Sir,” replied Sam Weller, putting in his head.</p>
<pb  xml:id="p504"/>
<p >“I can't speak to you just now, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick. “I am engaged at this
moment, Sam.”</p>
<p >“Beg your pardon, Sir,” rejoined Mr. Weller. “But here's a lady here, Sir, as
says she's somethin' wery partickler to disclose.”</p>
<p >“I can't see any lady,” replied Mr. Pickwick, whose mind was filled with visions of
Mrs. Bardell.</p>
<p >“I vouldn't make too sure o' that, Sir,” urged Mr. Weller, shaking his head.
“If you know'd who was near, Sir, I rayther think you'd change your note; as the hawk remarked
to himself vith a cheerful laugh, ven he heerd the robin redbreast a singin' round the
corner.”</p>
<p >“Who is it?” enquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“Vill you see her, Sir?” asked Mr. Weller, holding the door in his hand, as if he had
got some curious live animal on the other side.</p>
<p >“I suppose I must,” said Mr. Pickwick, looking at Perker.</p>
<p >“Vell then, all in to begin,” cried Sam. “Sound the gong, draw up the curtain,
and enter the two con-spirators.”</p>
<p >As Sam Weller spoke, he threw the door open, and there rushed tumultuously into the room, Mr.
Nathaniel Winkle, leading after him by the hand the identical young lady who, at Dingley Dell, had
worn the boots with the fur round the tops; and who, now a very pleasing compound of blushes and
confusion, and lilac silk, and a smart hat, and a rich lace veil, looked prettier than ever.</p>
<p >“Miss Arabella Allen!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, rising from his chair.</p>
<p >“No,” replied Mr. Winkle, dropping on his knees. “Mrs. Winkle. Pardon, my dear
friend, pardon.”</p>
<p >Mr. Pickwick could scarcely believe the evidence of his own senses, and perhaps would not have
done so, but for the corroborative testimony afforded by the smiling countenance of Perker, and the
bodily presence, in the background, of Sam and the pretty housemaid, who appeared to contemplate the
proceedings with the liveliest satisfaction.</p>
<p >“Oh, Mr. Pickwick,” said Arabella in a low voice, as if alarmed at the silence,
“can you forgive my imprudence?”</p>
<p >Mr. Pickwick returned no verbal response to this appeal, but he took off his spectacles in great
haste, and seizing both the young lady's hands in his, kissed her a great number of
times—perhaps a greater number than was absolutely necessary—and then, still retaining
one of her hands, told Mr. Winkle he was an audacious young dog, and bade him get up, which Mr.
Winkle, who had been for some seconds scratching his nose with the brim of his hat in a penitent
manner, did; whereupon Mr. Pickwick slapped him on the back several times, and then shook hands
heartily with Perker, who, not to be behindhand in the compliments of the occasion, saluted both the
bride and the pretty housemaid with right good will, and having wrung Mr. Winkle's hand most
cordially, wound up his demonstrations of joy, by taking snuff enough to set any half dozen men,
with ordinarily constructed noses, a sneezing for life.</p>
<p >“Why, my dear girl,” said Mr. Pickwick, “how has all this come about? Come, sit
down, and let me hear it all. How well she looks, doesn't she Perker?” added Mr. Pickwick,
surveying Arabella's face <pb xml:id="p505"/> with a look of as much pride and exultation, as if
she had been his own daughter.</p>
<p >“Delightful, my dear Sir,” replied the little man. “If I were not a married man
myself, I should be disposed to envy you, you dog, I should.” Thus expressing himself, the
little lawyer gave Mr. Winkle a poke in the chest, which that gentleman reciprocated; after which
they both laughed very loudly, but not so loudly as Mr. Samuel Weller, who had just relieved his
feelings by kissing the pretty house-maid under cover of the cupboard door.</p>
<p >“I can never be grateful enough to you, Sam, I am sure,” said Arabella, with the
sweetest smile imaginable. “I shall not forget your exertions in the garden at
Clifton.”</p>
<p >“Don't say nothin' wotever about it, Ma'm,” replied Sam. “I only assisted
natur, Ma'm; as the doctor said to the boy's mother, arter he'd bled him to death.”</p>
<p >“Mary, my dear, sit down,” said Mr. Pickwick, cutting short these compliments.
“Now then—how long have you been married, eh?”</p>
<p >Arabella looked bashfully at her lord and master, who replied, “Only three days.”</p>
<p >“Only three days, eh?” said Mr. Pickwick. “Why, what have you been doing these
three months?”</p>
<p >“Ah, to be sure,” interposed Perker; “come, account for this idleness. You see
Pickwick's only astonishment is, that it wasn't all over months ago.”</p>
<p >“Why the fact is,” replied Mr. Winkle, looking at his blushing young wife,
“that I could not persuade Bella to run away for a long time; and when I had persuaded her, it
was a long time more before we could find an opportunity. Mary had to give a month's warning, too,
before she could leave her place next door, and we couldn't possibly have done it without her
assistance.”</p>
<p >“Upon my word,” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, who by this time had resumed his spectacles,
and was looking from Arabella to Winkle, and from Winkle to Arabella, with as much delight depicted
in his countenance as warm-heartedness and kindly feeling can communicate to the human
face—“upon my word! you seem to have been very systematic in your proceedings. And is
your brother acquainted with all this, my dear?”</p>
<p >“Oh, no, no,” replied Arabella, changing colour. “Dear Mr. Pickwick, he must
only know it from you—from your lips alone. He is so violent, so prejudiced, and has been
so—so anxious in behalf of his friend, Mr. Sawyer,” added Arabella, looking down,
“that I fear the consequences dreadfully.”</p>
<p >“Ah, to be sure,” said Perker, gravely. “You must take this matter in hand for
them, my dear Sir. These young men will respect you when they would listen to nobody else. You must
prevent mischief, my dear Sir. Hot blood—hot blood.” And the little man took a warning
pinch, and shook his head doubtfully.</p>
<p >“You forget, my love,” said Mr. Pickwick, gently, “you forget that I am a
prisoner.”</p>
<p >“No, indeed I do not, my dear Sir,” replied Arabella. “I never <pb xml:id="p506"/> have forgotten it; never ceased to think how great your sufferings must have been in
this shocking place, but I hoped that what no consideration for yourself would induce you to do, a
regard to our happiness might. If my brother hears of this first from you, I feel certain we shall
be reconciled. He is my only relation in the world, Mr. Pickwick, and unless you plead for me, I
fear I have lost even him. I have done wrong—very, very wrong, I know.” Here poor
Arabella hid her face in her handkerchief, and wept bitterly.</p>
<p >Mr. Pickwick's nature was a good deal worked upon by these same tears, but when Mrs. Winkle,
drying her eyes, took to coaxing and entreating in the sweetest tones of a very sweet voice, he
became particularly restless, and evidently undecided how to act, as was evinced by sundry nervous
rubbings of his spectacle-glasses, nose, tights, head, and gaiters.</p>
<p >Taking advantage of these symptoms of indecision, Mr. Perker (to whom it appeared the young
couple had driven straight that morning) urged with legal point and shrewdness that Mr. Winkle,
senior, was still unacquainted with the important rise in life's flight of steps which his son had
taken; that the future expectations of the said son depended entirely upon the said Winkle senior
continuing to regard him with undiminished feelings of affection and attachment, which it was very
unlikely he would do if this great event were long kept a secret from him; that Mr. Pickwick
repairing to Bristol to seek Mr. Allen, might with equal reason repair to Birmingham to seek Mr.
Winkle, senior; lastly, that Mr. Winkle, senior, had good right and title to consider Mr. Pickwick
as in some degree the guardian and adviser of his son, and that it consequently behoved that
gentleman, and was indeed due to his personal character, to acquaint the aforesaid Winkle, senior,
personally, and by word of mouth, with the whole circumstances of the case, and with the share he
had taken in the transaction.</p>
<p >Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass arrived most opportunely in this stage of the pleadings, and as it
was necessary to explain to them all that had occurred, together with the various reasons pro and
con, the whole of the arguments were gone over again, after which everybody urged every argument in
his own way and at his own length. And at last Mr. Pickwick, fairly argued and remonstrated out of
all his resolutions, and being in imminent danger of being argued and remonstrated out of his wits,
caught Arabella in his arms, and declaring that she was a very amiable creature, and that he didn't
know how it was, but he had always been very fond of her from the first, said he could never find it
in his heart to stand in the way of young people's happiness, and they might do with him as they
pleased.</p>
<p >Mr. Weller's first act, on hearing this concession, was to dispatch Job Trotter to the
illustrious Mr. Pell, with an authority to deliver to the bearer the formal discharge which his
prudent parent had had the foresight to leave in the hands of that learned gentleman, in case it
should be at any time required on an emergency; his next proceeding was to invest his whole stock of
ready money in the purchase of five-and-twenty gallons of mild porter, which he himself dispensed on
the racket ground to everybody who would partake of it; this done, he <pb xml:id="p507"/>
hurra'd in divers parts of the building until he had lost his voice, and then quietly relapsed into
his usual collected and philosophical condition.</p>
<p >At three o'clock that afternoon, Mr. Pickwick took a last look at his little room, and made his
way as well as he could, through the throng of debtors who pressed eagerly forward to shake him by
the hand, until he reached the lodge steps. He turned here to look about him, and his eye lightened
as he did so. In all the crowd of wan emaciated faces, he saw not one which was not the happier for
his sympathy and charity.</p>
<p >“Perker,” said Mr. Pickwick, beckoning one young man towards him, “this is Mr.
Jingle, whom I spoke to you about.”</p>
<p >“Very good, my dear Sir,” replied Perker, looking hard at Jingle. “You will see
me again, young man, to-morrow. I hope you may live to remember deeply what I shall have to
communicate, Sir.”</p>
<p >Jingle bowed respectfully, trembled very much as he took Mr. Pickwick's proffered hand, and
withdrew.</p>
<p >“Job you know, I think?” said Mr. Pickwick, presenting that gentleman.</p>
<p >“I know the rascal,” replied Perker, good-humouredly. “See after your friend,
and be in the way to-morrow at one. Do you hear? Now, is there anything more?”</p>
<p >“Nothing,” rejoined Mr. Pickwick. “You have delivered the little parcel I gave
you for your old landlord, Sam?”</p>
<p >“I have, Sir,” replied Sam. “He bust out a cyrin', Sir, and said you wos wery
gen'rous and thoughtful, and he only wished you could have him innockilated for a gallopin'
consumption, for his old friend as had lived here so long wos dead, and he'd noveres to look for
another.”</p>
<p >“Poor fellow, poor fellow!” said Mr. Pickwick. “God bless you, my
friends!”</p>
<p >As Mr. Pickwick uttered this adieu, the crowd raised a loud shout, and many among them were
pressing forward to shake him by the hand again, when he drew his arm through Perker's, and hurried
from the prison, far more sad and melancholy, for the moment, than when he had first entered it.
Alas! how many sad and unhappy beings had he left behind! and how many of them lie caged there,
still!</p>
<p >A happy evening was that for at least one party in the George and Vulture, and light and cheerful
were two of the hearts that emerged from its hospitable door next morning; the owners thereof were
Mr. Pickwick and Sam Weller, the former of whom was speedily deposited inside a comfortable post
coach, with a little dickey behind, in which the latter mounted with great agility.</p>
<p >“Sir,” called out Mr. Weller, to his master.</p>
<p >“Well, Sam,” replied Mr. Pickwick, thrusting his head out of the window.</p>
<p >“I wish them horses had been three months and better in the Fleet, Sir.”</p>
<p >“Why, Sam?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“Vy, Sir,” exclaimed Mr. Weller, rubbing his hands, “how they vould go if they
had been!”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter">
<pb  xml:id="p508"/>
<head >CHAPTER XLVII.</head>
<head > RELATES HOW MR. PICKWICK, WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF SAMUEL WELLER, ESSAYED TO SOFTEN THE HEART
OF MR. BENJAMIN ALLEN, AND TO MOLLIFY THE WRATH OF MR. ROBERT SAWYER. </head>
<p >MR. BEN ALLEN and Mr. Bob Sawyer sat together in the little surgery behind the shop, discussing
minced veal and future prospects, when the discourse, not unnaturally, turned upon the practice
acquired by Bob the aforesaid, and his present chances of deriving a competent independence from the
honourable profession to which he had devoted himself.</p>
<p >“—Which, I think,” observed Mr. Bob Sawyer, pursuing the thread of the subject.
“which I think, Ben, are rather dubious.”</p>
<p >“What's rather dubious?” enquired Mr. Ben Allen, at the same time sharpening his
intellects with a draught of beer. “What's dubious?”</p>
<p >“Why, the chances,” responded Mr. Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“I forgot,” said Mr. Ben Allen. “The beer has reminded me that I forgot,
Bob—yes; they <hi rend="italics">are</hi> dubious.”</p>
<p >“It's wonderful how the poor people patronise me,” said Mr. Bob Sawyer, reflectively.
“They knock me up at all hours of the night, take medicine to an extent which I should have
conceived impossible, put on blisters and leeches with a perseverance worthy of a better cause, and
make additions to their families in a manner which is quite awful. Six of those last-named little
promissory notes, all due on the same day Ben, and all entrusted to me.”</p>
<p >“It's very gratifying, isn't it?” said Mr. Ben Allen, holding his plate for some more
minced veal.</p>
<p >“Oh, very,” replied Bob; “only not quite so much so as the confidence of
patients, with a shilling or two to spare, would be. This business was capitally described in the
advertisement, Ben. It is a practice, a very extensive practice—and that's all.”</p>
<p >“Bob,” said Mr. Ben Allen, laying down his knife and fork, and fixing his eyes on the
visage of his friend—“Bob, I'll tell you what it is.”</p>
<p >“What is it?” enquired Mr. Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“You must make yourself, with as little delay as possible, master of Arabella's one
thousand pounds.”</p>
<p >“Three per cent. consolidated Bank annuities, now standing in her name in the book or books
of the Governor and Company of the Bank of England,” added Bob Sawyer, in legal
phraseology.</p>
<p >“Exactly so,” said Ben. “She has it when she comes of age, or marries. She
wants a year of coming of age, and if you plucked up a spirit she needn't want a month of being
married.”</p>
<pb  xml:id="p509"/>
<p >“She's a very charming and delightful creature,” quoth Mr. Robert Sawyer, in reply;
“and has only one fault that I know of, Ben. It happens unfortunately, that that single
blemish is a want of taste. She don't like me.”</p>
<p >“It's my opinion that she don't know what she does like,” said Mr. Ben Allen,
contemptuously.</p>
<p >“Perhaps not,” remarked Mr. Bob Sawyer. “But it's my opinion that she does know
what she doesn't like, and that's of even more importance.”</p>
<p >“I wish,” said Mr. Ben Allen, setting his teeth together, and speaking more like a
savage warrior who fed upon raw wolf's flesh which he carved with his fingers, than a peaceable
young gentleman who eat minced veal with a knife and fork—“I wish I knew whether any
rascal really has been tampering with her, and attempting to engage her affections. I think I should
assassinate him, Bob.”</p>
<p >“I'd put a bullet in him if I found him out,” said Mr. Sawyer, stopping in the course
of a long draught of beer, and looking malignantly out of the porter pot. “If that didn't do
his business, I'd extract it afterwards, and kill him that way.”</p>
<p >Mr. Benjamin Allen gazed abstractedly on his friend for some minutes in silence, and then
said—</p>
<p >“You have never proposed to her point-blank, Bob?”</p>
<p >“No. Because I saw it would be of no use,” replied Mr. Robert Sawyer.</p>
<p >“You shall do it before you are twenty-four hours older,” retorted Ben, with
desperate calmness. “She <hi rend="italics">shall</hi> have you, or I'll know the reason
why—I'll exert my authority.”</p>
<p >“Well,” said Mr. Bob Sawyer, “We shall see.”</p>
<p >“We <hi rend="italics">shall</hi> see, my friend,” replied Mr. Ben Allen, fiercely.
He paused for a few seconds, and added in a voice broken by emotion, “You have loved her from
a child, my friend—you loved her when we were boys at school together, and even then she was
wayward, and slighted your young feelings. Do you recollect, with all the eagerness of a child's
love, one day pressing upon her acceptance two small carraway-seed biscuits and one sweet apple,
neatly folded into a circular parcel with the leaf of a copy-book?”</p>
<p >“I do,” replied Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“She slighted that, I think?” said Ben Allen.</p>
<p >“She did,” rejoined Bob. “She said I had kept the parcel so long in the pockets
of my corduroys, that the apple was unpleasantly warm.”</p>
<p >“I remember,” said Mr. Allen, gloomily. “Upon which we ate it ourselves, in
alternate bites.”</p>
<p >Bob Sawyer intimated his recollection of the circumstance last alluded to, by a melancholy frown;
and the two friends remained for some time absorbed, each in his own meditations.</p>
<p >While these observations were being exchanged between Mr. Bob Sawyer and Mr. Benjamin Allen, and
while the boy in the grey livery, marvelling at the unwonted prolongation of the dinner, cast an
anxious look from time to time towards the glass door, distracted by inward misgivings regarding the
amount of minced veal which would be ultimately <pb xml:id="p510"/> reserved for his individual
cravings, there rolled soberly on through the streets of Bristol, a private fly, painted of a sad
green colour, drawn by a chubby sort of brown horse, and driven by a surly looking man with his legs
dressed like the legs of a groom, and his body attired in the coat of a coachman. Such appearances
are common to many vehicles belonging to, and maintained by, old ladies of economical habits; and in
this vehicle there sat an old lady who was its mistress and proprietor.</p>
<p >“Martin!” said the old lady, calling to the surly man out of the front window.</p>
<p >“Well?” said the surly man, touching his hat to the old lady.</p>
<p >“Mr. Sawyer's,” said the old lady.</p>
<p >“I was going there,” said the surly man.</p>
<p >The old lady nodded the satisfaction which this proof of the surly man's foresight imparted to
her feelings; and the surly man giving a smart lash to the chubby horse, they all repaired to Mr.
Bob Sawyer's together.</p>
<p >“Martin!” said the old lady, when the fly stopped at the door of Mr. Robert Sawyer
late Nockemorf.</p>
<p >“Well?” said Martin.</p>
<p >“Ask the lad to step out and mind the horse.”</p>
<p >“I'm going to mind the horse myself,” said Martin, laying his whip on the roof of the
fly.</p>
<p >“I can't permit it on any account,” said the old lady; “your testimony will be
very important, and I must take you into the house with me. You must not stir from my side during
the whole interview. Do you hear?”</p>
<p >“I hear,” replied Martin.</p>
<p >“Well; what are you stopping for?”</p>
<p >“Nothing,” replied Martin. So saying, the surly man leisurely descended from the
wheel upon which he had been poising himself on the tops of the toes of his right foot, and having
summoned the boy in the grey livery, opened the coach-door, flung down the steps, and thrusting in a
hand enveloped in a dark wash-leather glove, pulled out the old lady with as much unconcern in his
manner as if she were a bandbox.</p>
<p >“Dear me,” exclaimed the old lady, “I am so flurried now I have got here
Martin, that I'm all in a tremble.”</p>
<p >Mr. Martin coughed behind the dark wash-leather glove, but expressed no further sympathy; so the
old lady, composing herself, trotted up Mr. Bob Sawyer's steps, and Mr. Martin followed. Immediately
upon the old lady's entering the shop, Mr. Benjamin Allen and Mr. Bob Sawyer, who had been putting
the spirits and water out of sight and upsetting nauseous drugs to take off the smell of the
tobacco-smoke, issued hastily forth in a transport of pleasure and affection.</p>
<p >“My dear aunt,” exclaimed Mr. Ben Allen, “how kind of you to look in upon us.
Mr. Sawyer, aunt; my friend Mr. Bob Sawyer that I have spoken to you about, regarding—you
know, aunt.” And here Mr. Ben Allen, who was not at the moment extraordinarily sober, added
<pb xml:id="p511"/> the word “Arabella,” in what was meant to be a whisper, but
which was in fact an especially audible and distinct tone of speech, which nobody could avoid
hearing, if anybody were so disposed.</p>
<p >“My dear Benjamin,” said the old lady, struggling with a great shortness of breath,
and trembling from head to foot — “don't be alarmed, my dear, but I think I had better
speak to Mr. Sawyer alone for a moment—only for one moment.”</p>
<p >“Bob,” said Mr. Ben Allen, “will you take my aunt into the surgery?”</p>
<p >“Certainly,” responded Bob, in a most professional voice. “Step this way, my
dear Ma'am. Don't be frightened, Ma'am. We shall be able to set you to rights in a very short time,
I have no doubt, Ma'am. Here, my dear Ma'am. Now then.” With this Mr. Bob Sawyer having handed
the old lady to a chair, shut the door, drew another chair close to her, and waited to hear detailed
the symptoms of some disorder from which he saw in perspective a long train of profits and
advantages.</p>
<p >The first thing the old lady did, was to shake her head a great many times, and begin to cry.</p>
<p >“Nervous,” said Bob Sawyer complacently. “Camphor-julep and water three times a
day, and composing draught at night.”</p>
<p >“I don't know how to begin, Mr. Sawyer,” said the old lady. “It is so very
painful and distressing.”</p>
<p >“You need not begin, Ma'am,” rejoined Mr. Bob Sawyer. “I can anticipate all you
would say. The head is in fault.”</p>
<p >“I should be very sorry to think it was the heart,” said the old lady, with a slight
groan.</p>
<p >“Not the slightest danger of that, Ma'am,” replied Bob Sawyer. “The stomach is
the primary cause.”</p>
<p >“Mr. Sawyer!” exclaimed the old lady, starting.</p>
<p >“Not the least doubt of it, Ma'am,” rejoined Bob, looking wondrous wise.
“Medicine, in time, my dear Ma'am, would have prevented it all.”</p>
<p >“Mr. Sawyer,” said the old lady, more flurried than before, “this conduct is
either great impertinence to one in my situation, Sir, or it arises from your not understanding the
object of my visit. If it had been in the power of medicine or any foresight I could have used to
prevent what has occurred, I should certainly have done so. I had better see my nephew at
once,” said the old lady, twirling her reticule indignantly, and rising as she spoke.</p>
<p >“Stop a moment, Ma'am,” said Bob Sawyer; “I am afraid I have not understood
you. What <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the matter, Ma'am?”</p>
<p >“My niece, Mr. Sawyer,” said the old lady—“your friend's
sister.”</p>
<p >“Yes, Ma'am,” said Bob, all impatience; for the old lady, although much agitated,
spoke with the most tantalising deliberation, as old ladies often do. “Yes, Ma'am.”</p>
<p >“Left my home, Mr. Sawyer, three days ago, on a pretended visit to my sister, another aunt
of hers, who keeps the large boarding school just beyond the third mile-stone, where there is a very
large laburnum <pb xml:id="p512"/> tree and an oak gate,” said the old lady, stopping in
this place to dry her eyes.</p>
<p >“Oh, devil take the laburnum tree! Ma'am,” said Bob, quite forgetting his
professional dignity in his anxiety. “Get on a little faster; put a little more steam on,
Ma'am, pray.”</p>
<p >“This morning,” said the old lady, slowly, “this morning, she—”</p>
<p >“She came back Ma'am, I suppose,” said Bob, with great animation. “Did she come
back?”</p>
<p >“No, she did not—she wrote,” replied the old lady.</p>
<p >“What did she say?” enquired Bob, eagerly.</p>
<p >“She said, Mr. Sawyer,” replied the old lady—“and it is this I want you
to prepare Benjamin's mind for, gently and by degrees; she said that she was—I have got the
letter in my pocket, Mr. Sawyer, but my glasses are in the carriage, and I should only waste the
time if I attempted to point out the passage to you, without them; she said, in short, Mr. Sawyer,
that she was married.”</p>
<p >“What!” said, or rather shouted, Mr. Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“Married,” repeated the old lady.</p>
<p >Mr. Bob Sawyer stopped to hear no more; but darting from the surgery into the outer shop, cried
in a stentorian voice, “Ben, my boy, she's bolted!”</p>
<p >Mr. Ben Allen, who had been slumbering behind the counter with his head half a foot or so below
his knees, no sooner heard this appalling communication, than he made a precipitate rush at Mr.
Martin, and twisting his hand in the neckcloth of that taciturn servitor, expressed an obliging
intention of choking him where he stood, which intention, with a promptitude often the effect of
desperation, he at once commenced carrying into execution with much vigour and surgical skill.</p>
<p >Mr. Martin, who was a man of few words and possessed but little power of eloquence or persuasion,
submitted to this operation with a very calm and agreeable expression of countenance, for some
seconds; finding, however, that it threatened speedily to lead to a result which would place it
beyond his power to claim any wages, board or otherwise, in all times to come, he muttered an
inarticulate remonstrance, and felled Mr. Benjamin Allen to the ground. As that gentleman had got
his hands entangled in his cravat, he had no alternative but to follow him to the floor. There they
both lay struggling, when the shop-door opened, and the party was increased by the arrival of two
most unexpected visitors, to wit, Mr. Pickwick and Mr. Samuel Weller.</p>
<p >The impression at once produced upon Mr. Weller's mind by what he saw, was, that Mr. Martin was
hired by the establishment of Sawyer late Nockemorf, to take strong medicine, or to go into fits and
be experimentalised upon, or to swallow poison now and then with the view of testing the efficacy of
some new antidotes, or to do something or other to promote the great science of medicine, and
gratify the ardent spirit of enquiry burning in the bosoms of its two young professors. So, without
presuming to interfere, Sam stood perfectly still, and looked on as if he were mightily interested
in the result of the then <pb xml:id="p513"/> pending experiment. Not so, Mr. Pickwick. He at
once threw himself upon the astonished combatants with his accustomed energy, and loudly called upon
the by-standers to interpose.</p>
<p >This roused Mr. Bob Sawyer, who had been hitherto quite paralysed by the frenzy of his companion;
and with that gentleman's assistance, Mr. Pickwick raised Ben Allen to his feet. Mr. Martin finding
himself alone on the floor, got up and looked about him.</p>
<p >“Mr. Allen,” said Mr. Pickwick, “what is the matter, Sir?”</p>
<p >“Never mind, Sir,” replied Mr. Allen, with haughty defiance.</p>
<p >“What is it?” enquired Mr. Pickwick, looking at Bob Sawyer. “Is he
unwell?”</p>
<p >Before Bob could reply, Mr. Ben Allen seized Mr. Pickwick by the hand, and murmured, in sorrowful
accents, “My sister, my dear Sir; my sister.”</p>
<p >“Oh, is that all!” said Mr. Pickwick. “We shall easily arrange that matter, I
hope. Your sister is safe and well, and I am here, my dear Sir, to—”</p>
<p >“Sorry to do anythin' as may cause an interruption to such wery pleasant proceedin's, as
the king said ven he dissolved the parliament,” interposed Mr. Weller, who had been peeping
through the glass door; “but there's another experiment here, Sir. Here's a wenerable old lady
a lyin' on the carpet vaitin' for dissection, or galwinism, or some other rewivin' and scientific
inwention.”</p>
<p >“I forgot,” exclaimed Mr. Ben Allen. “It is my aunt.”</p>
<p >“Dear me,” said Mr. Pickwick. “Poor lady! gently Sam, gently.”</p>
<p >“Strange sitivation for one o' the family,” observed Sam Weller, hoisting the aunt
into a chair. “Now, depitty Sawbones, bring out the wollatilly.”</p>
<p >The latter observation was addressed to the boy in grey, who, having handed over the fly to the
care of the street-keeper, had come back to see what all the noise was about. Between the boy in
grey, and Mr. Bob Sawyer, and Mr. Benjamin Allen (who having frightened his aunt into a fainting
fit, was affectionately solicitous for her recovery) the old lady was at length restored to
consciousness; and then Mr. Ben Allen, turning with a puzzled countenance to Mr. Pickwick, asked him
what he was about to say when he had been so alarmingly interrupted.</p>
<p >“We are all friends here, I presume?” said Mr. Pickwick, clearing his voice, and
looking towards the man of few words with the surly countenance, who drove the fly with the chubby
horse.</p>
<p >This reminded Mr. Bob Sawyer that the boy in grey was looking on, with eyes wide open and greedy
ears. The incipient chemist having been lifted up by his coat collar and dropped outside the door,
Bob Sawyer assured Mr. Pickwick that he might speak without reserve.</p>
<p >“Your sister, my dear Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick, turning to Benjamin Allen, “is
in London; well and happy.”</p>
<p >“Her happiness is no object to me, Sir,” said Mr. Benjamin Allen, with a flourish of
the hand.</p>
<p >“Her husband <hi rend="italics">is</hi> an object to <hi rend="italics">me,</hi>
Sir,” said Bob Sawyer. “He shall be an object to me, Sir, at twelve paces, and a very
pretty object <pb xml:id="p514"/> I'll make of him, Sir—a mean-spirited scoundrel!”
This, as it stood, was a very pretty denunciation, and magnanimous withal; but Mr. Bob Sawyer rather
weakened its effect, by winding up with some general observations concerning the punching of heads
and knocking out of eyes, which were commonplace by comparison.</p>
<p >“Stay, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick; “before you apply those epithets to the
gentleman in question, consider dispassionately the extent of his fault, and above all remember that
he is a friend of mine.”</p>
<p >“What!” said Mr. Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“His name,” cried Ben Allen. “His name.”</p>
<p >“Mr. Nathaniel Winkle,” said Mr. Pickwick, firmly.</p>
<p >Mr. Benjamin Allen deliberately crushed his spectacles beneath the heel of his boot, and having
picked up the pieces and put them into three separate pockets, folded his arms, bit his lips, and
looked in a threatening manner at the bland features of Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“Then it's you, is it, Sir, who have encouraged and brought about this match?”
inquired Mr. Benjamin Allen, at length.</p>
<p >“And it's this gentleman's servant, I suppose,” interrupted the old lady, “who
has been skulking about my house, and endeavouring to entrap my servants to conspire against their
mistress. Martin!”</p>
<p >“Well?” said the surly man, coming forward.</p>
<p >“Is that the young man you saw in the lane, whom you told me about this morning?”</p>
<p >Mr. Martin, who, as it has already appeared, was a man of few words, looked at Sam Weller, nodded
his head, and growled forth, “That's the man.” Mr. Weller, who was never proud, gave a
smile of friendly recognition as his eyes encountered those of the surly groom, and admitted, in
courteous terms, that he had “knowed him afore.”</p>
<p >“And this is the faithful creature,” exclaimed Mr. Ben Allen, “that I had
nearly suffocated! Mr. Pickwick, how dare you allow your fellow to be employed in the abduction of
my sister? I demand that you explain this matter, Sir.”</p>
<p >“Explain it, Sir!” cried Bob Sawyer, fiercely.</p>
<p >“It's a conspiracy,” said Ben Allen.</p>
<p >“A regular plant,” added Mr. Bob Sawyer.</p>
<p >“A disgraceful imposition,” observed the old lady.</p>
<p >“Nothing but a do,” remarked Martin.</p>
<p >“Pray hear me,” urged Mr. Pickwick, as Mr. Ben Allen fell into a chair that patients
were bled in, and gave way to his pocket-handkerchief. “I have rendered no assistance in this
matter, beyond that of being present at one interview between the young people, which I could not
prevent, and from which I conceived my presence would remove any slight colouring of impropriety
that it might otherwise have had: this is the whole share I have taken in the transaction, and I had
no suspicion that an immediate marriage was even contemplated. Though, mind,” added Mr.
Pickwick, hastily checking himself, “mind, I do not say I should have prevented it, if I <hi rend="italics">had</hi> known that it was intended.”</p>
<p >“You hear that, all of you; you hear that?” said Mr. Benjamin Allen.</p>
<pb  xml:id="p515"/>
<p >“I hope they do,” mildly observed Mr. Pickwick, looking round; “and,”
added that gentleman, his colour mounting as he spoke, “I hope they hear this, Sir,
also,—that from what has been stated to me, Sir, I assert that you were by no means justified
in attempting to force your sister's inclinations as you did, and that you should rather have
endeavoured by your kindness and forbearance to have supplied the place of other nearer relations
whom she has never known from a child. As regards my young friend, I must beg to add, that in every
point of worldly advantage, he is at least on an equal footing with yourself, if not on a much
better one, and that unless I hear this question discussed with becoming temper and moderation, I
decline hearing any more said upon the subject.”</p>
<p >“I vish to make a wery few remarks in addition to wot has been put forard by the honorable
gen'lm'n as has jist given over,” said Mr. Weller, stepping forth, “vich is this here: a
indiwidual in company has called me a feller.”</p>
<p >“That has nothing whatever to do with the matter, Sam,” interposed Mr. Pickwick.
“Pray hold your tongue.”</p>
<p >“I ain't a goin' to say nothin' on that ere pint, Sir,” replied Sam, “but
merely this here. P'raps that gen'lm'n may think as there vos a priory 'tachment, but there vorn't
nothin' o' the sort, for the young lady said in the wery beginnin' o' the keepin' company that she
couldn't abide him. Nobody's cut him out, and it 'ud ha' been just the wery same for him if the
young lady had never seen Mr. Vinkle. That's wot I vished to say, Sir, and I hope I've now made that
'ere gen'lm'n's mind easy.”</p>
<p >A short pause followed these consolatory remarks of Mr. Weller, and then Mr. Ben Allen rising
from his chair, protested that he would never see Arabella's face again, while Mr. Bob Sawyer,
despite Sam's flattering assurance, vowed dreadful vengeance on the happy bridegroom.</p>
<p >But, just when matters were at their height and threatening to remain so, Mr. Pickwick found a
powerful assistant in the old lady, who, evidently much struck by the mode in which he had advocated
her niece's cause, ventured to approach Mr. Benjamin Allen with a few comforting reflections, of
which the chief were, that after all, perhaps, it was well it was no worse; the least said the
soonest mended, and upon her word she did not know that it was so very bad after all; that what was
over couldn't be begun, and what couldn't be cured must be endured, with various other assurances of
the like novel and strengthening description. To all of which, Mr. Benjamin Allen replied that he
meant no disrespect to his aunt or anybody there, but if it were all the same to them, and they
would allow him to have his own way, he would rather have the pleasure of hating his sister till
death and after it.</p>
<p >At length when this determination had been announced half a hundred times, the old lady suddenly
bridling up and looking very majestic, wished to know what she had done that no respect was to be
paid to her years or station, and that she should be obliged to beg and pray in that way of her own
nephew, whom she remembered about five-and-twenty years before he was born, and whom she had known
<pb xml:id="p516"/> personally when he hadn't a tooth in his head; to say nothing of her
presence on the first occasion of his having his hair cut, and assistance at numerous other times
and ceremonies during his babyhood, of sufficient importance to found a claim upon his affection,
obedience, and sympathies, for ever.</p>
<p >While the good lady was bestowing this objurgation on Mr. Ben Allen, Bob Sawyer and Mr. Pickwick
had retired in close conversation to the inner room, where the former gentleman was observed to
apply himself several times to the mouth of a black bottle, under the influence of which, his
features gradually assumed a cheerful and even jovial expression. And at last he emerged from the
room, bottle in hand, and remarking that he was very sorry to say he had been making a fool of
himself, begged to propose the health and happiness of Mr. and Mrs. Winkle, whose felicity, so far
from envying, he would be the first to congratulate them upon. Hearing this, Mr. Ben Allen suddenly
arose from his chair, and seizing the black bottle drank the toast so heartily, that, the liquor
being strong, he became nearly as black in the face as the bottle itself. Finally the black bottle
went round till it was empty, and there was so much shaking of hands and interchanging of
complements, that even the metal-visaged Mr. Martin condescended to smile.</p>
<p >“And now,” said Bob Sawyer, rubbing his hands, “we'll have a jolly
night.”</p>
<p >“I am sorry,” said Mr. Pickwick, “that I must return to my inn. I have not been
accustomed to fatigue lately, and my journey has tired me exceedingly.”</p>
<p >“You'll take some tea, Mr. Pickwick?” said the old lady, with irresistible
sweetness.</p>
<p >“Thank you, I would rather not,” replied that gentleman. The truth is, that the old
lady's evidently increasing admiration was Mr. Pickwick's principal inducement for going. He thought
of Mrs. Bardell. and every glance of the old lady's eyes threw him into a cold perspiration.</p>
<p >As Mr. Pickwick could by no means be prevailed upon to stay, it was arranged at once, on his own
proposition, that Mr. Benjamin Allen should accompany him on his journey to the elder Mr. Winkle's,
and that the coach should be at the door at nine o'clock next morning. He then took his leave, and,
followed by Samuel Weller, repaired to the Bush. It is worthy of remark, that Mr. Martin's face was
horribly convulsed as he shook hands with Sam at parting, and that he gave vent to a smile and an
oath simultaneously, from which tokens it has been inferred by those who were best acquainted with
that gentleman's peculiarities that he expressed himself much pleased with Mr. Weller's society, and
requested the honor of his further acquaintance.</p>
<p >“Shall I order a private room, Sir?” inquired Sam, when they reached the Bush.</p>
<p >“Why, no, Sam,” replied Mr. Pickwick; “as I dined in the coffee room, and shall
go to bed soon, it is hardly worth while. See who there is in the traveller's room, Sam.”</p>
<p >Mr. Weller departed on his errand, and presently returned to say <pb xml:id="p517"/> that
there was only a gentleman with one eye, and the landlord, who were drinking a bowl of bishop
together.</p>
<p >“I will join them,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“He's a queer customer, the vun-eyed vun, Sir,” observed Mr. Weller, as he led the
way. “He's a gammonin' that 'ere landlord, he is, Sir, till he don't rightly know vether he's
a standing on the soles of his boots or the crown of his hat.”</p>
<p >The individual to whom this observation referred, was sitting at the upper end of the room when
Mr. Pickwick entered, and was smoking a large Dutch pipe, with his eye intently fixed upon the round
face of the landlord, a jolly looking old personage, to whom he had recently been relating some tale
of wonder, as was testified by sundry disjointed exclamations of, “Well, I wouldn't have
believed it! The strangest thing I ever heard! Couldn't have supposed it possible!” and other
expressions of astonishment which burst spontaneously from his lips as he returned the fixed gaze of
the one-eyed man.</p>
<p >“Servant, Sir,” said the one-eyed man to Mr. Pickwick. “Fine night,
Sir.”</p>
<p >“Very much so indeed,” replied Mr. Pickwick, as the waiter placed a small decanter of
brandy, and some hot water before him.</p>
<p >While Mr. Pickwick was mixing his brandy and water, the one-eyed man looked round at him
earnestly, from time to time, and at length said—</p>
<p >“I think I've seen you before.”</p>
<p >“I don't recollect you,” rejoined Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“I dare say not,” said the one-eyed man. “You didn't know me, but I knew two
friends of yours that were stopping at the Peacock at Eatanswill, at the time of the
Election.”</p>
<p >“Oh, indeed!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p >“Yes,” rejoined the one-eyed man. “I mentioned a little circumstance to them
about a friend of mine of the name of Tom Smart. Perhaps you've heard them speak of it.”</p>
<p >“Often,” rejoined Mr. Pickwick, smiling. “He was your uncle, I
think?”</p>
<p >“No, no—only a friend of my uncle's,” replied the one-eyed man.</p>
<p >“He was a wonderful man, that uncle of yours, though,” remarked the landlord, shaking
his head.</p>
<p >“Well, I think he was; I think I may say he was,” answered the one-eyed man. “I
could tell you a story about that same uncle, gentlemen, that would rather surprise you.”</p>
<p >“Could you?” said Mr. Pickwick. “Let us hear it by all means.”</p>
<p >The one-eyed Bagman ladled out a glass of negus from the bowl, and drank it, smoked a long whiff
out of the Dutch pipe, and then calling to Sam. Weller who was lingering near the door, that he
needn't go away unless he wanted to, because the story was no secret, fixed his eye upon the
landlord's, and proceeded in the words of the next chapter.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter">
<pb  xml:id="p518"/>
<head >CHAPTER XLVIII.</head>
<head > CONTAINING THE STORY OF THE BAGMAN'S UNCLE. </head>
<quote><floatingText><body >
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="quote">
<p >“My uncle, gentlemen,” said the bagman, “was one of the merriest, pleasantest,
cleverest fellows that ever lived. I wish you had known him, gentlemen. On second thoughts,
gentlemen, I <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> wish you had known him, for if you had, you would have
been all by this time in the ordinary course of nature, if not dead, at all events so near it, as to
have taken to stopping at home and giving up company, which would have deprived me of the
inestimable pleasure of addressing you at this moment. Gentlemen, I wish your fathers and mothers
had known my uncle. They would have been amazingly fond of him, especially your respectable mothers,
I know they would. If any two of his numerous virtues predominated over the many that adorned his
character, I should say they were his mixed punch and his after-supper song. Excuse my dwelling upon
these melancholy recollections of departed worth; you won't see a man like my uncle every day in the
week.</p>
<p >“I have always considered it a great point in my uncle's character, gentlemen, that he was
the intimate friend and companion of Tom Smart, of the great house of Bilson and Slum, Cateaton
Street, City. My uncle collected for Tiggin and Welps, but for a long time he went pretty near the
same journey as Tom; and the very first night they met, my uncle took a fancy for Tom, and Tom took
a fancy for my uncle. They made a bet of a new hat before they had known each other half an hour,
who should brew the best quart of punch and drink it the quickest. My uncle was judged to have won
the making, but Tom Smart beat him in the drinking by about half a salt-spoon-full. They took
another quart a-piece to drink each other's health in, and were staunch friends ever afterwards.
There's a destiny in these things gentlemen; we can't help it.</p>
<p >“In personal appearance, my uncle was a trifle shorter than the middle size; he was a
thought stouter too, than the ordinary run of people, and perhaps his face might be a shade redder.
He had the jolliest face you ever saw, gentlemen: something like Punch, with a handsomer nose and
chin; his eyes were always twinkling and sparkling with good humour, and a smile—not one of
your unmeaning wooden grins, but a real, merry, hearty, good-tempered smile, was perpetually on his
countenance. He was pitched out of his gig once, and knocked head first against a mile-stone. There
he lay, stunned, and so cut about the face with some gravel which had been heaped up alongside it,
that, to use my uncle's own strong expression, if his mother could have revisited the earth, she
wouldn't have known him. Indeed, when I come to think of the matter, gentlemen, I feel pretty sure
she wouldn't, for <pb xml:id="p519"/> she died when my uncle was two years and seven months old,
and I think it's very likely that even without the gravel, his top boots would have puzzled the good
lady not a little, to say nothing of his jolly red face. However, there he lay, and I have heard my
uncle say many a time that the man said who picked him up that he was smiling as merrily as if he
had tumbled out for a treat, and that after they had bled him, the first faint glimmerings of
returning animation were, his jumping up in bed, bursting out into a loud laugh, kissing the young
woman who held the basin, and demanding a mutton chop and a pickled walnut instantly. He was very
fond of pickled walnuts, gentlemen. He said he always found that, taken without vinegar, they
relished the beer.</p>
<p >“My uncle's great journey was in the fall of the leaf, at which time he collected debts and
took orders in the north: going from London to Edinburgh, from Edinburgh to Glasgow, from Glasgow
back to Edinburgh, and thence to London by the smack. You are to understand that this second visit
to Edinburgh was for his own pleasure. He used to go back for a week, just to look up his old
friends; and what with breakfasting with this one, and lunching with that, and dining with a third,
and supping with another, a pretty tight week he used to make of it. I don't know whether any of
you, gentlemen, ever partook of a real substantial hospitable Scotch breakfast, and then went out to
a slight lunch of a bushel of oysters, a dozen or so of bottled ale, and a noggin or two of whiskey
to close up with. If you ever did, you will agree with me that it requires a pretty strong head to
go out to dinner and supper afterwards.</p>
<p >“But, bless your hearts and eyebrows, all this sort of thing was nothing to my uncle. He
was so well seasoned that it was mere child's play. I have heard him say that he could see the
Dundee people out any day, and walk home afterwards without staggering; and yet the Dundee people
have as strong heads and as strong punch, gentlemen, as you are likely to meet with, between the
poles. I have heard of a Glasgow man and a Dundee man drinking against each other for fifteen hours
at a sitting. They were both suffocated as nearly as could be ascertained at the same moment, but
with this trifling exception, gentlemen, they were not a bit the worse for it.</p>
<p >“One night, within four-and-twenty hours of the time when he had settled to take shipping
for London, my uncle supped at the house of a very old friend of his, a Baillie Mac something, and
four syllables after it, who lived in the old town of Edinburgh. There were the baillie's wife, and
the baillie's three daughters, and the baillie's grown-up son, and three or four stout, bushy-eye
browed, canty old Scotch fellows that the baillie had got together to do honour to my uncle, and
help to make merry. It was a glorious supper. There was kippered salmon, and Finnan haddocks, and a
lamb's head, and a haggis; a celebrated Scotch dish, gentleman, which my uncle used to say always
looked to him, when it came to table, very much like a cupid's stomach; and a great many other
things besides, that I forget the names of, but very good things notwithstanding. The lassies were
pretty and agreeable; the baillie's wife one of the best creatures that <pb xml:id="p520"/> ever
lived; and my uncle in thoroughly good cue: the consequence of which was, that the young ladies
tittered and giggled, and the old lady laughed out loud, and the baillie and the other old fellows
roared till they were red in the face, the whole mortal time. I don't quite recollect how many
tumblers of whiskey toddy each man drank after supper, but this I know, that about one o'clock in
the morning, the baillie's grown-up son became insensible while attempting the first verse of
‘Willie brewed a peck o' maut;’ and he having been, for half an hour before, the only
other man visible above the mahogany, it occurred to my uncle that it was almost time to think about
going, especially as drinking had set in at seven o'clock in order that he might get home at a
decent hour. But thinking it might not be quite polite to go just then, my uncle voted himself into
the chair, mixed another glass, rose to propose his own health, addressed himself in a neat and
complimentary speech, and drank the toast with great enthusiasm. Still nobody woke; so my uncle took
a little drop more—neat this time, to prevent the toddy disagreeing with him, and laying
violent hands on his hat sallied forth into the street.</p>
<p >“It was a wild gusty night when my uncle closed the baillie's door; and settling his hat
firmly on his head to prevent the wind from taking it, thrust his hands into his pockets, and
looking upwards, took a short survey of the state of the weather. The clouds were drifting over the
moon at their giddiest speed, at one time wholly obscuring her, at another, suffering her to burst
forth in full splendour and shed her light on all the objects around; anon, driving over her again
with increased velocity, and shrouding everything in darkness. ‘Really, this won't do,’
said my uncle, addressing himself to the weather, as if he felt himself personally offended.
‘This is not at all the kind of thing for my voyage. It will not do at any price,’ said
my uncle, very impressively. And having repeated this, several times, he recovered his balance with
some difficulty—for he was rather giddy with looking up into the sky so long—and walked
merrily on.</p>
<p >“The baillie's house was in the Canongate, and my uncle was going to the other end of Leith
Walk, rather better than a mile's journey. On either side of him, there shot up against the dark
sky, tall, gaunt, straggling houses, with time-stained fronts, and windows that seemed to have
shared the lot of eyes in mortals, and to have grown dim and sunken with age. Six, seven, eight
stories high were the houses; story piled above story, as children build with cards—throwing
their dark shadows over the roughly paved road, and making the night darker. A few oil lamps were
scattered, at long distances, but they only served to mark the dirty entrance to some narrow close,
or to show where a common stair communicated, by steep and intricate windings with the various flats
above. Glancing at all these things with the air of a man who had seen them too often before, to
think them worthy of much notice now, my uncle walked up the middle of the street with a thumb in
each waistcoat pocket, indulging from time to time in various snatches of song, chaunted forth with
such good will and spirit, that the quiet honest folk started from their first sleep and lay
trembling in bed till the sound died away in the <pb xml:id="p521"/> distance; when, satisfying
themselves that it was only some drunken ne'er-do-weel finding his way home, they covered themselves
up warm and fell asleep again.</p>
<p >“I am particular in describing how my uncle walked up the middle of the street with his
thumbs in his waistcoat pockets, gentlemen, because, as he often used to say (and with great reason
too) there is nothing at all extraordinary in this story, unless you distinctly understand at the
beginning, that he was not by any means of a marvellous or romantic turn.</p>
<p >“Gentlemen, my uncle walked on with his thumbs in his waistcoat pockets, taking the middle
of the street to himself, and singing now a verse of a love song, and then a verse of a drinking
one; and when he was tired of both, whistling melodiously, until he reached the North Bridge, which
at this point connects the old and new towns of Edinburgh. Here he stopped for a minute to look at
the strange irregular clusters of lights piled one above the other, and twinkling afar off so high
in the air that they looked like stars gleaming from the castle walls on the one side and the Calton
Hill on the other, as if they illuminated veritable castles in the air, while the old picturesque
town slept heavily on in gloom and darkness below; its palace and chapel of Holyrood, guarded day
and night, as a friend of my uncle's used to say, by old Arthur's Seat, towering, surly and dark
like some gruff genius, over the ancient city he has watched so long. I say, gentlemen, my uncle
stopped here for a minute to look about him; and then, paying a compliment to the weather which had
a little cleared up, though the moon was sinking, walked on again as royally as before, keeping the
middle of the road with great dignity, and looking as if he should very much like to meet with
somebody who would dispute possession of it with him. There was nobody at all disposed to contest
the point, as it happened; and so on he went, with his thumbs in his waistcoat pockets, as peaceable
as a lamb.</p>
<p >“When my uncle reached the end of Leith Walk, he had to cross a pretty large piece of waste
ground which separated him from a short street which he had to turn down to go direct to his
lodging. Now in this piece of waste ground there was at that time an inclosure belonging to some
wheelwright, who contracted with the Post-office for the purchase of old worn-out mail coaches; and
my uncle being very fond of coaches, old, young, or middle-aged, all at once took it into his head
to step out of his road for no other purpose than to peep between the palings at these mails, about
a dozen of which he remembered to have seen, crowded together in a very forlorn and dismantled
state, inside. My uncle was a very enthusiastic, emphatic sort of person, gentlemen; so, finding
that he could not obtain a good peep between the palings, he got over them, and setting himself
quietly down on an old axletree, began to contemplate the mail coaches with a great deal of
gravity.</p>
<p >“There might be a dozen of them, or there might be more—my uncle was never quite
certain upon this point and being a man of very scrupulous veracity about numbers, didn't like to
say—but there they stood, all huddled together in the most desolate condition imaginable. The
doors had been torn from their hinges and removed, the linings had <pb xml:id="p522"/> been
stripped off, only a shred hanging here and there by a rusty nail; the lamps were gone, the poles
had long since vanished, the iron-work was rusty, the paint worn away; the wind whistled through the
chinks in the bare wood-work and the rain, which had collected on the roofs, fell drop by drop into
the insides with a hollow and melancholy sound. They were the decaying skeletons of departed mails,
and in that lonely place, at that time of night, they looked chill and dismal.</p>
<p >“My uncle rested his head upon his hands, and thought of the busy bustling people who had
rattled about, years before, in the old coaches, and were now as silent and changed; he thought of
the numbers of people to whom one of those crazy, mouldering vehicles had borne, night after night
for many years and through all weathers, the anxiously expected intelligence, the eagerly looked-for
remittance, the promised assurance of health and safety, the sudden announcement of sickness and
death. The merchant, the lover, the wife, the window, the mother, the schoolboy, the very child who
tottered to the door at the postman's knock—how had they all looked forward to the arrival of
the old coach. And where were they all now!</p>
<p >“Gentlemen, my uncle used to <hi rend="italics">say</hi> that he thought all this at the
time, but I rather suspect he learnt it out of some book afterwards, for he distinctly stated that
he fell into a kind of doze as he sat on the old axletree looking at the decayed mail coaches, and
that he was suddenly awakened by some deep church-bell striking two. Now, my uncle was never a fast
thinker, and if he had thought all these things, I am quite certain it would have taken him till
full half-past two o'clock at the very least. I am, therefore, decidedly of opinion, gentlemen, that
my uncle fell into the kind of doze without having thought about any thing at all.</p>
<p >“Be this as it may, a church bell struck two. My uncle woke, rubbed his eyes, and jumped up
in astonishment.</p>
<p >“In one instant, after the clock struck two, the whole of this deserted and quiet spot had
become a scene of the most extraordinary life and animation. The mail coach doors were on their
hinges, the lining was replaced, the iron-work was as good as new, the paint was restored, the lamps
were alight; cushions and great coats were on every coach box, porters were thrusting parcels into
every boot, guards were stowing away letter-bags, hostlers were dashing pails of water against the
renovated wheels; numbers of men were rushing about, fixing poles into every coach, passengers
arrived, portmanteaus were handed up, horses were put to, and in short it was perfectly clear that
every mail there was to be off directly. Gentlemen, my uncle opened his eyes so wide at all this,
that, to the very last moment of his life, he used to wonder how it fell out that he had ever been
able to shut 'em again.</p>
<p >“ ‘Now then,’ said a voice, as my uncle felt a hand on his shoulder,
‘You're booked for one inside. You'd better get in.’</p>
<p >‘<hi rend="italics">I</hi> booked!’ said my uncle, turning round.</p>
<p >“ ‘Yes, certainly.’</p>
<p >“My uncle, gentlemen, could say nothing, he was so very much astonished. The queerest thing
of all, was, that although there was such a crowd of persons, and although fresh faces were pouring
in, <pb xml:id="p523"/> every moment, there was no telling where they came from; they seemed to
start up in some strange manner from the ground or the air, and to disappear in the same way. When a
porter had put his luggage in the coach and received his fare, he turned round and was gone; and
before my uncle had well begun to wonder what had become of him, half-a-dozen fresh ones started up,
and staggered along under the weight of parcels which seemed big enough to crush them. The
passengers were all dressed so oddly too—large, broad-skirted laced coats with great cuffs and
no collars; and wigs, gentlemen,—great formal wigs with a tie behind. My uncle could make
nothing of it.</p>
<p >“ ‘Now, <hi rend="italics">are</hi> you going to get in?’ said the person who
had addressed my uncle before. He was dressed as a mail guard, with a wig on his head and most
enormous cuffs to his coat, and had got a lantern in one hand and a huge blunderbuss in the other,
which he was going to stow away in his little arm-chest. ‘<hi rend="italics">Are</hi> you
going to get in, Jack Martin?’ said the guard, holding the lantern to my uncle's face.</p>
<p >“ ‘Hallo,’ said my uncle, falling back a step or two. ‘That's
familiar?’</p>
<p >“ ‘It's so on the way-bill,’ replied the guard.</p>
<p >“ ‘Isn't there a ‘Mister’ before it?’ said my uncle—for he
felt, gentlemen, that for a guard he didn't know to call him Jack Martin, was a liberty which the
Post-office wouldn't have sanctioned if they had known it.</p>
<p >“ ‘No; there is not,’ rejoined the guard coolly.</p>
<p >“ ‘Is the fare paid?’ enquired my uncle.</p>
<p >“ ‘Of course it is,’ rejoined the guard.</p>
<p >“ ‘It is, is it?’ said my uncle. ‘Then here goes—which
coach?’</p>
<p >“ ‘This,’ said the guard, pointing to an old-fashioned Edinburgh and London
Mail, which had got the steps down, and the door open. ‘Stop—here are the other
passengers. Let them get in first.’</p>
<p >“As the guard spoke, there all at once appeared, right in front of my uncle, a young
gentleman in a powdered wig and a sky blue coat trimmed with silver, made very full and broad in the
skirts, which were lined with buckram. Tiggin and Welps were in the printed calico and waistcoat
piece line, gentlemen, so my uncle knew all the materials at once. He wore knee breeches and a kind
of leggings rolled up over his silk stockings, and shoes with buckles; he had ruffles at his wrists,
a three-cornered hat on his head, and a long taper sword by his side. The flaps of his waistcoat
came half way down his thighs, and the ends of his cravat reached to his waist. He stalked gravely
to the coach-door, pulled off his hat, and held it out above his head at arm's length, cocking his
little finger in the air at the same time, as some affected people do when they take a cup of tea:
then drew his feet together, and made a low grave bow, and then put out his left hand. My uncle was
just going to step forward, and shake it heartily, when he perceived that these attentions were
directed not towards him, but to a young lady, who just then appeared at the foot of the steps,
attired in an old-fashioned green velvet dress, with a long waist and stomacher. She had no bonnet
on her head, gentlemen, which was muffled in a black silk hood, but she looked round for an <pb xml:id="p524"/> instant as she prepared to get into the coach, and such a beautiful face as she
discovered my uncle had never seen—not even in a picture. She got into the coach, holding up
her dress with one hand, and as my uncle always said with a round oath, when he told the story, he
wouldn't have believed it possible that legs and feet could have been brought to such a state of
perfection unless he had seen them with his own eyes.</p>
<p >“But in this one glimpse of the beautiful face, my uncle saw that the young lady had cast
an imploring look upon him, and that she appeared terrified and distressed. He noticed too, that the
young fellow in the powdered wig, notwithstanding his show of gallantry, which was all very fine and
grand, clasped her tight by the wrist when she got in, and followed himself immediately afterwards.
An uncommonly ill-looking fellow in a close brown wig, and a plum-coloured suit, wearing a very
large sword and boots up to his hips, belonged to the party; and when he sat himself down next to
the young lady, who shrunk into a corner at his approach, my uncle was confirmed in his original
impression that something dark and mysterious was going forward, or, as he always said himself, that
‘there was a screw loose somewhere.’ It's quite surprising how quickly he made up his
mind to help the lady at any peril, if she needed help.</p>
<p >“ ‘Death and lightning!’ exclaimed the young gentleman, laying his hand upon
his sword, as my uncle entered the coach.</p>
<p >“ ‘Blood and thunder!’ roared the other gentleman. With this he whipped his
sword out, and made a lunge at my uncle without further ceremony. My uncle had no weapon about him,
but with great dexterity he snatched the ill-looking gentleman's three-cornered hat from his head,
and receiving the point of his sword right through the crown, squeezed the sides together, and held
it tight.</p>
<p >“ ‘Pink him behind,’ cried the ill-looking gentleman to his companion, as he
struggled to regain his sword.</p>
<p >“ ‘He had better not,’ cried my uncle, displaying the heel of one of his shoes
in a threatening manner. ‘I'll kick his brains out if he has any, or fracture his skull if he
hasn't.’ Exerting all his strength at this moment, my uncle wrenched the ill-looking man's
sword from his grasp, and flung it clean out of the coach-window, upon which the younger gentleman
vociferated ‘Death and lightning!’ again, and laid his hand upon the hilt of his sword
in a very fierce manner, but didn't draw it. Perhaps, gentlemen, as my uncle used to say, with a
smile, perhaps he was afraid of alarming the lady.</p>
<p >“ ‘Now gentlemen,’ said my uncle, taking his seat deliberately, ‘I don't
want to have any death with or without lightning in a lady's presence, and we have had quite blood
and thundering enough for one journey; so if you please, we'll sit in our places like quiet
insides—here, guard, pick up that gentleman's carving knife.’</p>
<p >“As quickly as my uncle said the words, the guard appeared at the coach-window with the
gentleman's sword in his hand. He held up his lantern, and looked earnestly in [my uncle's face as
he handed it in, when by its light my uncle saw, to his great surprise, that an immense crowd of
mail-coach guards swarmed round the <pb xml:id="p525"/> window, every one of whom had his eyes
earnestly fixed upon him too. He had never seen such a sea of white faces and red bodies, and
earnest eyes, in all his born days.</p>
<p >“ ‘This is the strangest sort of thing I ever had any thing to do with,’
thought my uncle—‘allow me to return you your hat, Sir.’</p>
<p >“The ill-looking gentleman received his three-cornered hat in silence—looked at the
hole in the middle with an enquiring air, and finally stuck it on the top of his wig, with a
solemnity the effect of which was a trifle impaired by his sneezing violently at the moment, and
jerking it off again.</p>
<p >“ ‘All right!’ cried the guard with the lantern, mounting into his little seat
behind. Away they went. My uncle peeped out of the coach-window as they emerged from the yard, and
observed that the other mails, with coachmen, guards, horses, and passengers complete, were driving
round and round in circles, at a slow trot of about five miles an hour. My uncle burnt with
indignation, gentlemen. As a commercial man, he felt that the mail bags were not to be trifled with,
and he resolved to memorialise the Post-office upon the subject, the very instant he reached
London.</p>
<p >“At present, however, his thoughts were occupied with the young lady who sat in the
furthest corner of the coach, with her face muffled closely in her hood: the gentleman with the sky
blue coat sitting opposite to her, and the other man in the plum-coloured suit, by her side, and
both watching her intently. If she so much as rustled the folds of her hood, he could hear the
ill-looking man clap his hand upon his sword, and tell by the other's breathing (it was so dark he
couldn't see his face) that he was looking as big as if he were going to devour her at a mouthful.
This roused my uncle more and more, and he resolved, come what come might, to see the end of it. He
had a great admiration for bright eyes, and sweet faces, and pretty legs and feet; in short he was
fond of the whole sex. It runs in our family, gentlemen—so am I.</p>
<p >“Many were the devices which my uncle practised to attract the lady's attention, or at all
events, to engage the mysterious gentlemen in conversation. They were all in vain; the gentlemen
wouldn't talk, and the lady didn't dare. He thrust his head out of the coach-window at intervals,
and bawled out to know why they didn't go faster. But he called till he was hoarse—nobody paid
the least attention to him. He leant back in the coach, and thought of the beautiful face, and the
feet and legs. This answered better; it wiled away the time, and kept him from wondering where he
was going to, and how it was he found himself in such an odd situation. Not that this would have
worried him much any way—he was a mighty, free and easy, roving, devilmay-care sort of person,
was my uncle, gentlemen.</p>
<p >“All of a sudden the coach stopped. ‘Hallo!’ said my uncle. ‘What's in
the wind now?’</p>
<p >“ ‘Alight here,’ said the guard, letting down the steps.</p>
<p >“ ‘Here!’ cried my uncle.</p>
<p >“ ‘Here,’ rejoined the guard.</p>
<p >“ ‘I'll do nothing of the sort,’ said my uncle.</p>
<pb  xml:id="p526"/>
<p >“ ‘Very well—then stop where you are,’ said the guard.</p>
<p >“ ‘I will,’ said my uncle.</p>
<p >“ ‘Do,’ said the guard.</p>
<p >“The other passengers had regarded this colloquy with great attention; and finding that my
uncle was determined not to alight, the younger man squeezed past him, to hand the lady out. At this
moment the ill-looking man was inspecting the hole in the crown of his three-cornered hat. As the
young lady brushed past, she dropped one of her gloves into my uncle's hand, and softly whispered
with her lips, so close to his face that he felt her warm breath on his nose, the single word,
‘Help!’ Gentlemen, my uncle leaped out of the coach at once with such violence that it
rocked on the springs again.</p>
<p >“ ‘Oh! you've thought better of it, have you?’ said the guard, when he saw my
uncle standing on the ground.</p>
<p >“My uncle looked at the guard for a few seconds, in some doubt whether it wouldn't be
better to wrench his blunderbuss from him, fire it in the face of the man with the big sword, knock
the rest of the company over the head with the stock, snatch up the young lady, and go off in the
smoke. On second thoughts, however, he abandoned this plan as being a shade too melo-dramatic in the
execution, and followed the two mysterious men, who, keeping the lady between them, were now
entering an old house in front of which the coach had stopped. They turned into the passage, and my
uncle followed.</p>
<p >“Of all the ruinous and desolate places my uncle had ever beheld, this was the most so. It
looked as if it had once been a large house of entertainment, but the roof had fallen in, in many
places, and the stairs were steep, rugged, and broken. There was a huge fire-place in the room into
which they walked, and the chimney was blackened with smoke, but no warm blaze lighted it up now.
The white feathery dust of burnt wood was still strewed over the hearth, but the stove was cold, and
all was dark and gloomy.</p>
<p >“ ‘Well,’ said my uncle as he looked about him, ‘A mail travelling at the
rate of six miles and a half an hour, and stopping for an indefinite time at such a hole as this, is
rather an irregular sort of proceeding I fancy. This shall be made known; I'll write to the
papers.’</p>
<p >“My uncle said this in a pretty loud voice, and in an open unreserved sort of manner, with
the view of engaging the two strangers in conversation if he could. But neither of them took any
more notice of him than whispering to each other, and scowling at him as they did so. The lady was
at the further end of the room, and once she ventured to wave her hand, as if beseeching my uncle's
assistance.</p>
<p >“At length the two strangers advanced a little, and the conversation began in earnest.</p>
<p >“ ‘You don't know this is a private room; I suppose, fellow,’ said the
gentleman in sky-blue.</p>
<p >“ ‘No I do not, fellow,’ rejoined my uncle ‘Only if this is a private
room specially ordered for the occasion, I should think the public room must be a <hi rend="italics">very</hi> comfortable one;’ with this, my uncle sat himself down in a high-backed chair and
took such an accurate measure of the gentleman with his eyes, that Tiggin and Welps could have
supplied <pb xml:id="p527"/> him with printed calico for a suit, and not an inch too much or too
little, from that estimate alone.</p>
<p >“ ‘Quit this room,’ said both the men together, grasping their swords.</p>
<p >“ ‘Eh?’ said my uncle, not at all appearing to comprehend their meaning.</p>
<p >“ ‘Quit the room, or you are a dead man,’ said the ill-looking fellow with the
large sword, drawing it at the same time and flourishing it in the air.</p>
<p >“ ‘Down with him!’ said the gentleman in sky-blue, drawing his sword also, and
falling back two or three yards. ‘Down with him!’ The lady gave a loud scream.</p>
<p >“Now, my uncle was always remarkable for great boldness and great presence of mind. All the
time that he had appeared so indifferent to what was going on, he had been looking slyly about for
some missile or weapon of defence, and at the very instant when the swords were drawn, he espied
standing in the chimney corner, an old basket-hilted rapier in a rusty scabbard. At one bound, my
uncle caught it in his hand, drew it, flourished it gallantly above his head, called aloud to the
lady to keep out of the way, hurled the chair at the man in sky-blue, and the scabbard at the man in
plum-colour, and taking advantage of the confusion, fell upon them both, pell-mell.</p>
<p >“Gentlemen, there is an old story—none the worse for being true—regarding a
fine young Irish gentleman, who being asked if he could play the fiddle, replied he had no doubt he
could, but he couldn't exactly say for certain, because he had never tried. This is not inapplicable
to my uncle and his fencing. He had never had a sword in his hand before, except once when he played
Richard the Third at a private theatre, upon which occasion it was arranged with Richmond that he
was to be run through from behind without shewing fight at all; but here he was, cutting and
slashing with two experienced swordsmen, thrusting, and guarding, and poking, and slicing, and
acquitting himself in the most manful and dexterous manner possible, although up to that time he had
never been aware that he had the least notion of the science. It only shows how true the old saying
is, that a man never knows what he can do, till he tries, gentlemen.</p>
<p >“The noise of the combat was terrific, each of the three combatants swearing like troopers,
and their swords clashing with as much noise as if all the knives and steels in Newport market were
rattling together at the same time. When it was at its very height, the lady, to encourage my uncle
most probably, withdrew her hood entirely from her face, and disclosed a countenance of such
dazzling beauty, that he would have fought against fifty men to win one smile from it and die. He
had done wonders before, but now he began to powder away like a raving mad giant.</p>
<p >“At this very moment, the gentleman in sky-blue turning round, and seeing the young lady
with her face uncovered, vented an exclamation of rage and jealousy; and turning his weapon against
her beautiful bosom, pointed a thrust at her heart which caused my uncle to utter a cry of
apprehension that made the building ring. The lady <pb xml:id="p528"/> stepped lightly aside,
and snatching the young man's sword from his hand before he had recovered his balance, drove him to
the wall, and running it through him and the pannelling up to the very hilt, pinned him there hard
and fast. It was a splendid example. My uncle, with a loud shout of triumph and a strength that was
irresistible, made his adversary retreat in the same direction, and plunging the old rapier into the
very centre of a large red flower in the pattern of his waist-coat, nailed him beside his friend;
there they both stood, gentlemen, jerking their arms and legs about in agony, like the toy-shop
figures that are moved by a piece of packthread. My uncle always said afterwards, that this was one
of the surest means he knew of, for disposing of an enemy; but it was liable to one objection on the
ground of expense, inasmuch as it involved the loss of a sword for every man disabled.</p>
<p >“ ‘The mail, the mail!’ cried the lady, running up to my uncle and throwing her
beautiful arms round his neck; ‘we may yet escape.’</p>
<p >“ ‘<hi rend="italics">May!</hi>’ said my uncle; ‘why, my dear, there's
nobody else to kill, is there?’ My uncle was rather disappointed, gentlemen, for he thought a
little quiet bit of love-making would be agreeable after the slaughtering, if it were only to change
the subject.</p>
<p >“ ‘We have not an instant to lose here,’ said the young lady. ‘He
(pointing to the young gentleman in sky blue) is the only son of the powerful Marquess of
Filletoville.’</p>
<p >“ ‘Well then, my dear, I'm afraid he'll never come to the title,’ said my
uncle, looking coolly at the young gentleman as he stood fixed up against the wall, in the
cockchaffer fashion I have described. ‘You have cut off the entail, my love.’</p>
<p >“ ‘I have been torn from my home and friends by these villains,’ said the young
lady, her features glowing with indignation. ‘That wretch would have married me by violence in
another hour.’</p>
<p >“ ‘Confound his impudence!’ said my uncle, bestowing a very contemptuous look
on the dying heir of Filletoville.</p>
<p >“ ‘As you may guess from what I have seen,’ said the young lady, ‘the
party are prepared to murder me if you appeal to any one for assistance. If their accomplices find
us here, we are lost. Two minutes hence may be too late. The mail!’—and with these
words, overpowered by her feelings and the exertion of sticking the young Marquess of Filletoville,
she sunk into my uncle's arms. My uncle caught her up, and bore her to the house-door. There stood
the mail with four long-tailed flowing-maned black horses, ready harnessed; but no coachman, no
guard, no ostler even, at the horses' heads.</p>
<p >“Gentlemen, I hope I do no injustice to my uncle's memory, when I express my opinion, that
although he was a bachelor, he <hi rend="italics">had</hi> held some ladies in his arms before this
time; I believe indeed, that he had rather a habit of kissing barmaids, and I know, that in one or
two instances had been seen by credible witnesses, to hug a landlady in a very perceptible manner. I
mention the circumstance, to show what a very uncommon sort of person this beautiful young lady must
have been to have affected my uncle in the way she did; he used to say, that as her long dark hair
trailed over his arm, and her beautiful dark eyes fixed themselves upon his face when she recovered,
he felt so strange <pb xml:id="p529"/> and nervous, that his legs trembled beneath him. But who
can look in a sweet soft pair of dark eyes, without feeling queer? I can't, gentlemen. I am afraid
to look at some eyes I know, and that's the truth of it.</p>
<p >“ ‘You will never leave me,’ murmured the young lady.</p>
<p >“ ‘Never,’ said my uncle. And he meant it too.</p>
<p >“ ‘My dear preserver!’ exclaimed the young lady. ‘My dear, kind brave
preserver!’</p>
<p >“ ‘Don't,’ said my uncle, interrupting her.</p>
<p >“ ‘Why?’ enquired the young lady.</p>
<p >“ ‘Because your mouth looks so beautiful when you speak,’ rejoined my uncle,
‘that I am afraid I shall be rude enough to kiss it.’</p>
<p >“The young lady put up her hand as if to caution my uncle not to do so, and said—no,
she didn't say anything—she smiled. When you are looking at a pair of the most delicious lips
in the world, and see them gently break into a roguish smile—if you are very near them, and
nobody else by—you cannot better testify your admiration of their beautiful form and colour
than by kissing them at once. My uncle did so, and I honour him for it.</p>
<p >“ ‘Hark!’ cried the young lady, starting. ‘The noise of wheels and
horses.’</p>
<p >“ ‘So it is,’ said my uncle, listening. He had a good ear for wheels and the
trampling of hoofs, but there appeared to be so many horses and carriages rattling towards them at a
distance, that it was impossible to form a guess at their number. The sound was like that of fifty
breaks, with six blood cattle in each.</p>
<p >“ ‘We are pursued!’ cried the young lady, clasping her hands. ‘We are
pursued. I have no hope but in you.’</p>
<p >“There was such an expression of terror in her beautiful face, that my uncle made up his
mind at once. He lifted her into the coach, told her not to be frightened, pressed his lips to hers
once more, and then advising her to draw up the window to keep the cold air out, mounted to the
box.</p>
<p >“ ‘Stay, love,’ cried the young lady.</p>
<p >“ ‘What's the matter?’ said my uncle, from the coach-box.</p>
<p >“ ‘I want to speak to you,’ said the young lady; ‘only a word—only
one word, dearest.’</p>
<p >“ ‘Must I get down?’ enquired my uncle. The lady made no answer, but she smiled
again. Such a smile, gentlemen!—it beat the other one all to nothing. My uncle descended from
his perch in a twinkling.</p>
<p >“ ‘What is it, my dear?’ said my uncle, looking in at the coach window. The
lady happened to bend forward at the same time, and my uncle thought she looked more beautiful than
she had done yet. He was very close to her just then, gentlemen, so he really ought to know.</p>
<p >“ ‘What is it, my dear?’ said my uncle.</p>
<p >“ ‘Will you never love any one but me—never marry any one beside?’ said
the young lady.</p>
<p >“My uncle swore a great oath that he never would marry any body <pb xml:id="p530"/>
else, and the young lady drew in her head, and pulled up the window. He jumped upon the box, squared
his elbows, adjusted the ribands, seized the whip which lay on the roof, gave one flick to the off
leader, and away went the four long-tailed, flowing-maned black horses, at fifteen good English
miles an hour, with the old mail coach behind them—whew! how they tore along!</p>
<p >“But the noise behind grew louder. The faster went the old mail, the faster came the
pursuers—men, horses, dogs, were leagued in the pursuit. The noise was frightful, but above
all rose the voice of the young lady, urging my uncle on, and shrieking ‘faster!
faster!’</p>
<p >“They whirled past the dark trees as feathers would be swept before a hurricane. Houses,
gates, churches, haystacks, objects of every kind they shot by, with a velocity and noise like
roaring waters suddenly let loose. But still the noise of pursuit grew louder, and still my uncle
could hear the young lady wildly screaming ‘faster! faster!’</p>
<p >“My uncle plied whip and rein, and the horses flew onward till they were white with foam;
and yet the noise behind increased, and yet the young lady cried ‘faster! faster!’ My
uncle gave a loud stamp upon the boot in the energy of the moment, and—found that it was grey
morning, and he was sitting in the wheelwright's yard on the box of an old Edinburgh mail, shivering
with the cold and wet, and stamping his feet to warm them! He got down, and looked eagerly inside
for the beautiful young lady—alas! there was neither door nor seat to the coach—it was a
mere shell.</p>
<p >“Of course my uncle knew very well that there was some mystery in the matter, and that
everything had passed exactly as he used to relate it. He remained staunch to the great oath he had
sworn to the beautiful young lady: refusing several eligible landladies on her account, and died a
bachelor at last. He always said what a curious thing it was that he should have found out, by such
a mere accident as his clambering over the palings, that the ghosts of mail—coaches and
horses, guards, coachmen, and passengers, were in the habit of making journeys regularly every
night; he used to add that he believed he was the only living person who had ever been taken as a
passenger on one of these excursions; and I think he was right, gentlemen—at least I never
heard of any other.”</p>
</div>
</body></floatingText></quote>
<milestone  unit="typography" n="---------"/>
<p >“I wonder what these ghosts of mail-coaches carry in their bags,” said the landlord,
who had listened to the whole story with profound attention.</p>
<p >“The dead letters of course,” said the Bagman.</p>
<p >“Oh, ah—to be sure,” rejoined the landlord. “I never thought of
that.”</p>
</div>
</div>
</body>
<back>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section">
<pb  xml:id="pxv"/>
<opener >TO THE NOBILITY, FAMILIES, KEEPERS OF HOTELS, SCHOOLS,
<lb/> AND ALL LARGE CONSUMERS OF TEA.</opener>
<head >THE TEA ESTABLISHMENT, </head>
<p >4 &amp; 5, KING WILLIAM STREET,
<lb/> CITY, LONDON
<lb/> (NEAR THE MANSION HOUSE).</p>
<p >IN accordance with the spirit with which we commenced this undertaking we have taken every means
in our power to bring it into notice, being convinced that the more publicity it obtained the better
it would be appreciated and supported; the main and leading principle on which it is conducted, and
which cannot be <hi rend="italics">too often repeated,</hi> being, to make the inhabitants of the
Metropolis, and the country generally, <hi rend="italics">participators in the advantage of the
opening of the Trade to China.</hi></p>
<p >There is this difference between ourselves and the common race of advertisers, with whom we
cannot for one moment be associated, that our object is <hi rend="italics">gained</hi> when we have
obtained a <hi rend="italics">fair trial and comparison.</hi> Our professions have been already
satisfactorily tested, and we can now, therefore, appeal to that portion of the Public who may not
already have given us a trial with more certainty of success. <hi rend="italics">Their interest</hi>
will be the most powerful advocate in our favour.</p>
<p >The <hi rend="italics">system</hi> pursued at this Establishment is, to deal out Teas to the
consumer of the finest and choicest quality, at a <hi rend="italics">very small advance</hi> on the
<hi rend="italics">original cost of importation;</hi> and, in some cases, owing to the depressed
state of the markets, <hi rend="italics">much below those limits.</hi> The increased extent of our
business enables us, in many instances, to sell Teas on more favourable terms than are usually
charged by the <hi rend="italics">wholesale houses</hi> to the <hi rend="italics">retail
dealer;</hi> thereby saving, to the consumer, from 20 to 25 per cent. on the <hi rend="italics">former price of the article,</hi> or about <hi rend="italics">one-fifth of its entire
value,</hi>—a most important consideration, forming, as it does, so considerable a portion of
the expenditure of every family.</p>
<div type="section">
<p >
<table>
<row>
<cell>GREEN TEA.</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Good small pale leaf Gunpowder. full burnt flavour per 1b.</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Finest Gunpowder, small bright close twisted leaf</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Good Imperial Gunpowder, pale round leaf</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Finest Imperial, bright leaf, full flavour</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Genuine Hyson</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fine Hyson, even leaf, full flavour</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Preferable Hyson, strong, brightish leaf</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><hi rend="italics">Superfine Hyson,</hi> full rich delicate flavour</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><hi rend="italics">Ouchain,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">finest</hi> Young Hyson, small curled
leaf, rich burnt flavour</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Twankay and Hyson Skin </cell>
<cell>3 4 to 3</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Finest Bloom Tea, Hyson flavour</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >
<table>
<head>BLACK TEA.</head>
<row>
<cell>Common Bohea</cell>
<cell>2 0 to 2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Good Bohea</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Good ordinary Congou </cell>
<cell>2 8 &amp; 2</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Good sound common Congou</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>4—recommended</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Strong Congou, rather blackish leaf</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fine stout Congou, blackish leaf, little Pekoe flavour</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Wiry blackish leaf Congou, Pekoe Souchong flavour</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The Finest Congou Tea, ripe Pekoe Souchong flavour</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0—recommended</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p >Cocoa, Chocolate, and Spices, of the best qualities, at exceedingly low prices.</p>
<p >Good Ceylon Coffee, 1s. 6d.—Jamaica, 1s. 8d.—Berbice, 1s. 10d.—Finest Mocha,
2s.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<p >We beg to call particular attention to the plan we have found it necessary to adopt, to prevent
families being imposed upon by persons whom they send for our Teas. In several instances, on the
paper being brought back, we have found the price <hi rend="italics">obliterated,</hi> and a <hi rend="italics">higher one</hi> substituted, to our injury in every respect; many, from this
circumstance, being induced to suppose our professions of no value. To prevent a recurrence of this
practice, we shall mark the price on the <hi rend="italics">inside</hi> of the wrapper which
contains the Tea, where it will always be found on inspection. We suggest, however, that in all
cases a <hi rend="italics">written order</hi> is the best. It is a security to <hi rend="italics">both seller and buyer</hi> that the proper article is delivered.</p>
<p >For the convenience of Families residing in the Country, and whose consumption is not adequate to
the purchase of an <hi rend="italics">original package,</hi> we have determined on weighing up
Chests and Half-Chests, in parcels from single pounds and upwards. This will enable several Families
to join together in the purchase, and afterwards divide it. On a Chest, containing eighty pounds, we
shall inclose two pounds as <hi rend="italics">over-weight,</hi> and on Half-Chests, that is forty
pounds, we shall inclose a single pound. The advantage is <hi rend="italics">obvious,</hi>
independent of the great saving in price.</p>
<p >The Teas we shall so pack will be the Black at 3s. 4d.—4s.—4s. 6d. and 5s.; and in
Green Teas those at 4s., Hyson at 5s. and 6s., and Gunpowder at 6s. and 6s. 6d. Teas for the Country
also secured in Tin Canisters, in packages of six pounds and upwards.</p>
<closer >RIDGWAY, SIDNEY, &amp; CO.
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Importers of and Dealers in Tea.</hi>
<lb/>KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY,
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Near the Mansion House.</hi></closer>
</div>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p1"/>
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Edinburgh, September</hi> 1837.</opener>
<head >LIFE OF SIR WALTER SCOTT, BART.</head>
<p >BY J. G. LOCKHART, ESQ.,
<lb/> HIS LITERARY EXECUTOR.</p>
<p >VOLUME FIRST APPEARED ON 18TH MARCH.</p>
<p >VOLUME SECOND ON 1ST MAY.</p>
<p >VOLUME THIRD ON 1ST JUNE.</p>
<p >VOLUME FOURTH ON 1ST JULY.</p>
<p >VOLUME FIFTH
<lb/><hi rend="italics">Will appear on</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st October.</hi></p>
<div type="section">
<head >CONTENTS OF VOLUME FIFTH.</head>
<p >CHAP. I.—Autumn at Abbotsford—Scott's Hospitality—Visit of Sir Humphrey
Davy—Henry Mackenzie—Dr. Wollaston—and William Stewart Rose—Coursing on
Newark Hill—Salmon Fishing—The Festival at Boldside—The Abbotsford Hunt—The
Kirm, &amp;c. 1820.</p>
<p >CHAP. II.—Publication of the Abbot—The Blair-Adam Club, Kelso—Walton Hall,
&amp;c.—Ballantyne's Novelist Library—Acquittal of Queen Caroline—Service of the
Duke of Buccleugh—Scott elected President of the Royal Society of Edinburgh—The Celtic
Society, &amp;c.—Kenilworth published—Letters to Lord Montagu—Cornet
Scott—Allan Cunningham, &amp;c. 1820-1821.</p>
<p >CHAP. III.—Visit to London—Project of the Royal Society of Literature—The 18th
Hussars—Marriage of Captain Adam Ferguson—Letters to Lord Sidmouth—Lord
Montagu—Allan Cunningham—Mrs. Lockhart—and Cornet Scott, 1821.</p>
<p >CHAP. IV.—Illness and Death of John Ballantyne—Extract from his Pocket
Book—Letters from Blair-Adam—Castle Campbell—Sir Samuel
Shepherd—“Bailie Mackay,” &amp;c.—Coronation of George
IV.—Correspondence with James Hogg and Lord Sidmouth—Letter on the
Coronation—Anecdotes—Allan Cunningham's Memoranda—Completion of Chantrey's Bust,
1821.</p>
<p >CHAP. V.—Publication of Mr. Adolphus' Letters on the Authorship of Waverley, 1821.</p>
<p >CHAP. VI.—New Buildings at Abbotsford—Chiefswood—William Erskine—Letter
to Countess Purgstall—Progress of the Pirate—Private Letters in the Reign of James
I.—Commencement of the Fortunes of Nigel—Second Sale of Copy Rights—Contract for
“Four Works of Fiction”—Enormous Profits of the Novelist, and Extravagant Projects
of Constable—The Pirate published—Lord Byron's Cain dedicated to Scott—Affair of
the Beacon Newspaper—Franck's Northern Memoirs—and Notes on Lord Fountainhall,
published, 1821.</p>
<p >CHAP. VII.—William Erskine promoted to the Bench—Joanna Baillie's
Miscellany—Halidon Hill, and Macduff's Cross—Letters to Lord Montagu—Last Portrait
by Raeburn—Constable's Letter on the appearance of the Fortunes of Nigel—Halidon Hill
published, 1822.</p>
<p >CHAP. VIII.—Repairs of Melrose Abbey—Letters to Lord Montagu—Blair-Adam,
&amp;c.—King George IV. arrives in Scotland—Celtic Mania—Mr. Crabbe in Castle
Street—Death of Lord Kinnedder—Letters to Joanna Baillie, &amp;c.—Departure of the
King—Letters from Mr. Peel and Mr. Croker, 1822.</p>
<p >CHAP. IX.—Mons Meg—Jacobite Peerages—Invitation from the Galasheils
Poet—Progress of Abbotsford House—Letters to Joanna Baillie—Terry—Lord
Montagu—Publication of Peveril of the Peak, 1822-23.</p>
<p >CHAP. X.—Quentin Durward in preparation—Letter to Dr. Dibdin on being elected a
Member of the Roxburgh Club—The Bannatyne Club—Scott elected President—Letters to
Terry—Lord Montagu—Publication of Quentin Durward—Criticism, 1823.</p>
<p >CHAP. XI.—Letters to Joanna Baillie—William Howison—Visit of Mr.
Adolphus—and of Miss Edgeworth at Abbotsford—Publication of St. Ronan's Well—The
St. Ronan's Border Games, 1823.</p>
<p >CHAP. XII.—Publication of Redgauntlet—Additions to the Library at
Abbotsford—Letters to Joanna Baillie—Terry—Lord Montagu—Southey and Charles
Scott—Extracts from Captain Hall's Journal of a Visit at Abbotsford, 1824.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p2"/>
<head >LIFE OF SIR WALTER SCOTT.
<lb/>CONTENTS OF VOLUMES I. II. III. &amp; IV.</head>
<div type="section">
<head >VOLUME I.</head>
<p >MEMOIRS OF THE EARLY LIFE or SIR WALTER SCOTT, WRITTEN BY HIMSELF.—Illustrations of the
Autobiography—Ancestry—Early Life at Edinburgh, Sandy Knowe, Bath,
Prestonpans—High School of Edinburgh—Kelso—Anecdotes of College
Life—Apprenticeship—Debating Societies—Studies for the Bar—Early
Correspondence—Excursions to the Highlands, Northumberland, Flodden Field, and to
Liddesdale—Call to the Bar—Disappointment in Love—Burger's Leonore—Ballads
from the German—Edinburgh Light Horse—Excursion to Cumberland—Anecdotes—Miss
Carpenter—Marriage—Lasswade Cottage—First Original Ballads, Glenfinlas,
&amp;c.—Appointed Sheriff of Selkirkshire—Richard Heber—John Leyden—William
Laidlaw—James Hogg—Publication of the Border Minstrelsy and of Sir Tristrem—Visit
to London and Oxford—Edinburgh Review—Visit of Wordsworth, . . . . . .
1771—1804.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >VOLUME II.</head>
<p >REMOVAL to Ashestiel—Mungo Park—Publication of the Lay of the Last
Minstrel—Partnership with James Ballantyne—Literary Projects—Criticism in the
Edinburgh Review—Commencement of Waverley—Mr. Skene's Reminiscences of
Ashestiel—Visit of Mr. Southey—Correspondence on Dryden with Ellis and
Wordsworth—Affair of the Clerkship of Session—Visit to London—Earl Spenser and Mr.
Fox—Caroline Princess of Wales—Joanna Baillie—Appointment as Clerk of
Session—Lord Melville's Trial—Dryden—Critical Pieces—Edition of Slingsby's
Memoirs—Visit to London—Ellis—Rose—Canning—Publication of
Marmion—Anecdotes—Edition of Dryden Published—Weber's Romances—Editions of
Queenhoo-Hall—Captain Carleton's Memoirs—The Memoirs of Robert Cary, Earl of
Monmouth—The Sadler Papers and Somers's Tracts—James Hogg—Mr. Morritt's
Reminiscences of Ashestiel—Scott's Domestic Life—Quarrel with Messrs. Constable and
Hunter—John Ballantyne established as a Bookseller in Edinburgh—The Edinburgh Annual
Register, &amp;c.—John Murray's Visit to Ashestiel—Correspondence concerning the
Quarterly Review—Scott in London—Morritt's Description of him as a Lion in
town—The Quarterly Review started—First Visit to Rokeby—Excursion to the Trosachs
and Loch Lomond—Death of Daniel Scott—Correspondence about Mr. Canning's Duel with Lord
Castlereagh—Theatrical Anecdotes—Publication of the Lady of the
Lake—Correspondence concerning versification with Ellis and Canning—Anecdotes from James
Ballantyne's MEMORANDA—First Excursion to the Hebrides—Life of Miss
Seward—Waverley resumed and again laid aside—Unfortunate Speculations of John Ballantyne
&amp; Co.—Death of Lord President Blair—and of Lord Melville—Publication of the
Vision of Don Roderick—First Purchase of Land; Abbotsford—Correspondence with Lord
Byron, . . . . . . . 1804-1814.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >VOLUME III.</head>
<p >THE “Flitting” to Abbotsford—Excursion to Flodden—Correspondence with
Crabbe—Life of Patrick Carey, &amp;c.—Publication of Rokeby, and of the Bridal of
Triermain—Affairs of John Ballantyne and Co.—Causes of their
derangement—Negotiations for relief with Messrs. Constable and Co.—New Purchase of
land—John Ballantyne's expresses—Application to the Duke of Buccleugh—Offer of the
Poet-Laureatship—Question of taxation on literary income—Letters to Mr. Morrit—Mr.
Southey—Mr. Richardson—Mr. Crabbe—Miss Baillie and Lord Byron—Insanity of
Henry Weber—Publication of Life and edition of Swift—Essays for the Supplement to the
Encyclopædia Britannica—Completion and Publication of Waverley—Voyage to the
Shetland Isles, &amp;c.—Scott's Diary kept on board the Light-house—Letters in verse
from Zetland and Orkney—Death of the Duchess of Buccleugh—Success of
Waverley—Letter from James Ballantyne to Miss Edgeworth—Rapid completion of the Lord of
the Isles—“Six weeks at Christmas”—“Refreshing the
Machine”—Publication of the Poem—and of Guy Mannering—Anecdotes by James
Ballantyne—Visit to London—Meeting with Lord Byron—Dinners at Carlton
House—Battle of Waterloo—Anecdotes of Scott at Paris—The Duke of
Wellington—The Emperor Alexander—Blucher—Platoff—London—Parting with
Lord Byron—Return to Abbotsford—Anecdotes by Mr. Skene, and James Ballantyne—Notes
on “The Field of Waterloo”—Revision of Paul's Letters, &amp;c.—Quarrel and
reconciliation with Hogg—Football match at Carterhaugh—Dinner at Bowhill—Letters
to the Duke of Buccleugh—Joanna Baillie and Mr. Morritt—The Durham Garland, . . . . . .
. 1812-1815.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >VOLUME IV.</head>
<p >PUBLICATION of Paul's Letters to his Kinsfolk—Guy Mannering
“Terryfied”—Publication of the Antiquary—History of 1814 for the Edinburgh
Annual Register—Publication of the first Tales of My Landlord—Anecdotes by Mr.
Train—Building at Abbotsford begun—Harold the Dauntless published—First attack of
Cramp in the Stomach—Story of the Doom of Devorgoil—John Kemble's retirement from the
Stage—Novel of Rob Roy projected—Excursion to the Lennox. Glasgow, and
Drumlanrig—Purchase of Toftfield—Visits of Washington Irving, Lady Byron, and Sir David
Wilkie—Rob Roy Published—The Scottish Regalia—Letters to the Duke of
Buccleugh—Correspondence on Rural Affairs with Mr. Laidlaw—And on the Buildings at
Abbotsford with Mr. Terry—Scott's Edinburgh Den—Details of his Domestic Life in
Castle-street—His Sunday Dinners—His Evening Drives—Dinners at John
Ballantyne's—And at James Ballantyne's, on the appearance of a New Novel—Anecdotes of
the Ballantynes and of Constable—Publication of the Heart of Mid-Lothian—Melrose
Abbey—Lion-hunters from America—Provincial Antiquities, &amp;c.—Extensive Sale of
Copyrights to Constable &amp; Co.—Scott receives and accepts the offer of a
Baronetcy—Rob Roy played at Edinburgh—Letter from Jedediah Cleishbotham to Mr. Charles
Mackay—Recurrence of Scott's Illness March and April 1819—Death of the Duke of
Buccleugh—Scott's sufferings while dictating The Bride of Lammermoor—Anecdotes by James
Ballantyne, &amp;c.—Appearance of the Third Series of Tales of my Landlord—Anecdote of
the Earl of Buchan—Gradual Re-establishment of Scott's Health—Scott's Correspondence
with his Son—Miscellaneous Letters—Abbotsford visited by Prince Leopold of
Saxe-Coburg—Political Alarms—The Radicals—Death of Scott's Mother—Her
Brother Dr. Rutherford—and her Sister Christian—Publication of Ivanhoe—The
Visionary—Scott's Saturday Excursions to Abbotsford—A Sunday there in
February—Constable—John Ballantyne—Prince Gustavus Vasa—Publication of the
Monastery—Scott revisits London—His Portrait by Laurence, and Bust by
Chantrey—Anecdotes by Allan Cunningham—Marriage of his Daughter—Visit of Prince
Gustavus Vasa at Abbotsford, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1816-1820.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p3"/>
<head >LIFE OF SIR WALTER SCOTT, </head>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head > VOLUME THE FIRST.
<lb/>PERIODICAL CRITICISM.</head>
<div type="section">
<head >A</head>
<p >The appearance of Lockhart's Life of Scott has been looked forward to with no ordinary degree of
expectation. The interest which its announcement was as general as it was intense. It is impossible
that the task of bringing out such a book could have fallen into better hands. J. G. Lockhart is a
man whose high character, independent of his relationship, insures the absence of every thing
improper or indecorous in a biographical work, and whose eminence as an author is a sufficient
guarantee for the good taste and ability with which the whole plan and details will be managed. If
anything were wanting to prove Mr. Lockhart's fitness for the duty which has devolved upon him, it
is to be found in his “Life of Burns.”—<hi rend="italics">Aberdeen
Herald.</hi></p>
<p >From the manner in which Mr. Lockhart has executed this part of his task, added to the interest
which the admirers of Sir Walter Scott, or, in other words, the whole reading world, must take in
the subject, and, considering also the avidity with which the most trifling anecdotes, and the most
unimportant circumstances connected with the names of eminent deceased literary men are sought after
by the public, there can be little doubt that this biography of Scott will be the most popular
publication that has appeared for many years past. The volume abounds throughout with the most
interesting materials.—<hi rend="italics">Aberdeen Journal.</hi></p>
<p >We are glad to acknowledge that we have suffered no sort of disappointment in our perusal of the
first volume of this. It is replete with valuable and well collated material illustrative of the
early life of its subject; and the comments that the various newly discovered MSS., letters, &amp;c.
have elicited, evince the sterling taste and judgment which Mr. Lockhart's previous literary
reputation allows him to possess. It is sure of commanding a prodigious sale; for of those who
possess a majority, or the whole of Sir Walter Scott's productions, thousands will greedily procure
this last, and by no means least wonderful monument of his genius, his worth, and his service to the
human race.—<hi rend="italics">Alexander's East India Magazine, April.</hi></p>
<p >This is the first volume of a biography which promises a rich harvest of amusement to the
admirers of the great Magician of the North. It is rich in correspondence, anecdotes, and traits of
character in the various literary men with whom Scott came into contact, Leyden, Ellis, Wordsworth,
Hogg, &amp;c. &amp;c. In short, if we end as we began, the biography will prove a rich
treat.—<hi rend="italics">Asiatic Journal, April.</hi></p>
<p >There has rarely appeared a book so admirably calculated to speak for itself; and it is
sufficient to say, that, as respects the interest of these memoirs of the earliest years of the
poet's life, and the new traits of character and anecdotes with which they are stored to
overflowing, our expectations have been more than satisfied.—<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >B</head>
<p >The fame of Scott is beyond the reach of criticism; he received, during his lifetime, a
popularity only second to that of Shakspeare, after the lapse of two centuries. His creations are
already “household words;” his poems are perused and reperused; his prose works almost
learned by heart. But when we have read them all, we begin to feel that something remains to satisfy
us—we desire to know the man, and to enquire whether our sympathy with the author is borne out
by his personal character. And to whom shall we look to have this want supplied? The delicacy of a
near relative with the discriminating friend, added to the talent which could develope, and the
kindred genius to appreciate the mighty works of the departed—these are requisites which the
most gifted of men can scarcely dare to hope for in their biographer. Sir Walter Scott's memory has
attained this singular good fortune, this <hi rend="italics">curiosa felicitas.—Berkshire
Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >This work has been received with an almost unanimous expression of approbation by the public and
the press.—<hi rend="italics">Berwick Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >The interest excited by the announcement of this work has been amply justified by the first
volume, which has just made its appearance. Its details of the greatest author of his
generation—as, taking him all in all, we hesitate not to pronounce Sir Walter Scott,—are
such as to raise still higher our admiration of the writer and the man; while the judgment displayed
by Mr. Lockhart in the execution of his task, are highly creditable to himself.—<hi rend="italics">Brighton Gazette.</hi></p>
<p >Whether it be owing to our own prepossession, or to the skill of the writer, we find its
execution immeasurably superior to that of any similar work that has of late years issued from the
press.—<hi rend="italics">Brighton Guardian.</hi></p>
<p >Few books have made their appearance in the world better adapted to obtain favourable notice from
it. Every one is willing to hear about Sir Walter Scott; and Mr. Lockhart has provided,—in the
memoirs which he gives of the poet's early life, and the notices <pb xml:id="p4"/> and anecdotes
which he everywhere scatters with the most liberal hand,—entertainment which will more than
satisfy all expectation.—<hi rend="italics">Bristol Mercury.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >C</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has done full and ample justice to the task imposed upon him by the last will and
testament of his talented and lamented relative.—<hi rend="italics">Cambrian.</hi></p>
<p >It is a work of high interest, and the first chapter contains an autobiographical fragment
written by Sir Walter, giving a delightful account of his early life to the period of his call to
the bar. Mr. Lockhart has performed his task in a manner worthy of the Editor of the <hi rend="italics">Quarterly Review.—Cambridge Chronicle and Journal.</hi></p>
<p >Sir Walter Scott, singularly fortunate in his living celebrity, has been fortunate in the hand to
which he has bequeathed its care when the grave should have sealed all his labours. Mr. Lockhart had
been not merely chosen for this purpose, but furnished with every material important to its
fulfilment,—memoranda by the author himself, his correspondence, and a vast variety of letters
from that crowd of the literary world, with whom he kept up an active intercourse for nearly a
quarter of a century.—<hi rend="italics">Colburn's New Monthly Magazine, April.</hi></p>
<p >Mr. Lockhart is, perhaps, the most competent person living to write the Life of Scott. So far as
this volume goes, he appears to have dedicated himself industriously to his labour of love, and we
are satisfied, from the specimen it affords of the whole, that the work will abundantly repay the
curiosity of the public. We cannot close the book without earnestly commending it to our readers. It
promises to afford a complete review of the life of our northern Ariosto; not merely a correct and
circumstantial account of incidents, but a developement of the progress of his studies, his projects
and his literary proceedings. Mr. Lockhart has performed his arduous labour with a skill and
assiduity commensurate to its demands, and the work is fairly entitled to take its place amongst the
best biographies in our language.—<hi rend="italics">Court Magazine and Monthly Critic,
April.</hi></p>
<p >We take our leave for the present of this interesting work, the complete success and speedy
completion of which must be desired by every reader of Scott—that is, by the entire British
public.—<hi rend="italics">Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >D</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has discharged the task imposed upon him by the will of Sir Walter with great tact
and ability.—<hi rend="italics">Derby Reporter.</hi></p>
<p >Of all the delightful volumes we have recently read, this is the most delightful; it constitutes
the best and most interesting Biography which modern times have produced.—<hi rend="italics">Dublin Evening Mail.</hi></p>
<p >This long and anxiously looked for work will not disappoint public expectation. The Life of Sir
Walter Scott is a gem in its class of literature which will impress its value upon every reader, and
sparkle with distinctive brilliancy in whatever light of intelligence it shall be placed.—<hi rend="italics">Dublin Standard.</hi></p>
<p >Amid the mass of ephemerals, such as have for the last six or seven years darkened rather than
brightened our literary atmosphere—brief in existence, and often as insignificant as insects
floating in the beams of a summer's sun—it is indeed refreshing and invigorating to inhale
such copious draughts of the richness and raciness contained in the work now before us, while the
contents too of its succeeding volumes, present a still richer bill of fare of literary
gratification awaiting and courting the appetite.</p>
<p >In the preface to this volume, Mr. Lockhart ha the names of upwards of a hundred individuals to
whom his acknowledgments are tendered for the communications of letters and other documents, and
those names include many of the <hi rend="italics">elite</hi> in station, literature, science, and
the arts. With such a subject, and such profusion of materials, from these and other sources, the
writer cannot fail to produce a literary biography more generally interesting and successful than
any other since the period of Boswell's life of Johnson, and in as far as the present volume enables
us to judge, he proceeds with his labours impartially and fearlessly.—<hi rend="italics">Dumfries and Galloway Courier.</hi></p>
<p >We have here a recurrence of that pleasing excitement, through all the reading world, which was
wont to attend the appearance of each new “Waverley novel.” The voice of the mighty
minstrel again rises, as it were, from the grave, and we cease for a time in the midst of the
anxious and feverish contentions of faction, to listen to the tones which delighted and astonished
our earlier years. This volume, indeed, unexpectedly possesses all the interest of a new sweep from
the lyre which was supposed for ever dumb.—<hi rend="italics">Dundee Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >It is a most instructive, amusing, and in every way satisfactory biography; and will in time be
as widely circulated, and universally read, as the works of the mighty “Wizard of the
North.”—<hi rend="italics">Dundee Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >E</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has, as was to be expected from his own eminent talents, performed the task confided
to him in a manner worthy of the subject. If Boswell's Life of Johnson has been pronounced the model
or <hi rend="italics">beau ideal</hi> of biography, the present work is equally entitled to the
compliment; as it resembles its predecessor in the minutiæ of its details, in its keeping the
hero perpetually upon the scene, in its never allowing the interest of the story to flag for one
moment, in its telling every thing the reader wishes to know, in short, in every particular except
in the dissimilarity between the characters of the biographers.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh
Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >This is one of the most interesting publications which has for a long time past issued from the
press, and will prove, if we judge from the specimen now given, a valuable accession to the
literature of the day. The subject is indeed one of great interest, as a memorial of the genius,
acquirements, and still more of the domestic habits and general dispositions of one of the most
illustrious literary characters of this or of any other age; but it derives additional interest from
the manner in which it is treated—from the talent, the taste, and sound judgment displayed by
the editor, Mr. Lockhart. The work is of great value, as giving such full details of the infancy and
boyish days of Sir Walter Scott—of the course of his studies—of his habits, and the
progress and maturity of his mind; <pb xml:id="p5"/> and though last, not least, of that enviable
equanimity and serenity of temper which he possessed,—those benevolent dispositions, and that
blameless conduct in all the relations of life, which gave so fine a finish of his character; and is
so different from others, in behalf of whose genius a sort of dispensation is claimed by their
admirers from all ordinary rules, even that of morality itself. To the taste and judgment, with
which the editor has made his selections, the work is indebted for much of its interest; if he has
erred on any side, it is certainly not on that of prolixity, either in his extracts from letters or
in his own remarks, which are always to the purpose, illustrative of some essential point, and
tending either to information or amusement.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Courant.</hi></p>
<p >This volume is, in every respect, calculated to gratify the admirers of Sir Walter Scott, and to
realise all the expectations which they may have formed with respect to the peculiar qualifications
of the biographer. The details are minute, copious, and characteristic. Every incident, adventure,
or saying, connected with Scott, in any way calculated to exhibit <hi rend="italics">the man,</hi>
is brought forward and related in a manner the most attractive. Mr. Lockhart displays that admirable
tact so indispensable in a biographer, which enables him to go along with his subject, <hi rend="italics">con amore,</hi> in every situation, and under every variety of circumstance. This
utter absence of pretension, indeed, forms one of the greatest charms of the work.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Evening Post.</hi></p>
<p >We shall at once express our unbounded approbation of this admirable book.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Caledonian Mercury.</hi></p>
<p >Never have we turned over the leaves of any production of the kind with more intense delight. Mr.
Lockhart has executed his task, so far as he has proceeded, in an admirable manner. Indeed, such a
performance was to be expected from the pen of him who wrote so admirable a biography of
Burns.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Observer.</hi></p>
<p >There has not been, we will venture to say, a work published the last quarter of a
century—perhaps we might, with all safety, double the period—which has been looked for
with a more general, more eager, and more intense curiosity, than that whose title stands at the
head of this notice. A feeling of impatience for its appearance, and of deep interest by
anticipation in its contents, pervaded all classes from the peer to the peasant.</p>
<p >With regard to the execution of the work, we shall only say,—and we could not say more in
effect although we were to write half a dozen columns on the subject—that it is, in every
respect, calculated to gratify all reasonable curiosity, and to satisfy all reasonable expectations,
and this most amply. The narrative is clear and unaffected, and, with great good taste and judgment
on the part of the writer, aims at presenting little more than a simple record of facts, pleasingly
told, but without the slightest effort after effect, or attempt at meretricious embellishment. Above
all things, let us remark its total freedom from that fulsome, and no less impertinent than fulsome,
laudation of the merits and genius of the subject, with which it is a common failing of the writers
of memoirs to lard over their narratives; thus becoming rather the eulogists than biographers of
those whose lives they record. From this sin, the work before us is entirely free.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Scotsman.</hi></p>
<p >Mr. Lockhart appears to us to have approached his task in the best possible spirit, and with a
sincere desire to convey to his readers at once, simply and directly, the various and extensive
information which circumstances have placed within his reach. There is nothing about this
commencement of the work which is in any way officious or egotistical. It is manly and unaffected
throughout, and will realize, we think, all the expectations that are likely to have been formed
about it.—<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p >Such a work as this requires no recommendation: the title-page alone is sufficient to gain for it
a rapid and most extensive sale. Mr. Lockhart had proceeded at some length in his labour, when to
his surprise “there was discovered, in an old cabinet at Abbotsford, an autobiographical
fragment, composed by him in 1808, shortly after the publication of his Marmion,” so that Mr.
Lockhart has remodelled his work from the <hi rend="italics">narrative of Sir Walter Scott
himself.</hi> This renders the work of additional interest and value.—<hi rend="italics">Exeter &amp; Plymouth (Woolmer's) Gazette.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >G</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart, by industriously collecting the fullest information, and digesting his materials
with proper caution, has produced a work worthy of the illustrious deceased, and which, we feel
confident, will add in no small degree to his own fame as an author. Mr. Lockhart has performed his
task with skill and fidelity.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Argus.</hi></p>
<p >This volume will add largely to Mr. Lockhart's reputation, and detract nothing from that of his
distinguished relative. Whatever judgment, scholarship, and cultivated taste may be capable of
effecting, have been accomplished by Mr. Lockhart. The tone of the book is manly and
unaffected—the style remarkable for its simplicity and energy; and, throughout the volume, not
an expression is to be met with which could mark the intimate relationship of the biographer to his
subject, so careful has he been to avoid even the appearance of undue partiality.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Courier.</hi></p>
<p >To-day, a delightful volume will be introduced to the notice of the reading public. The subject
of it is the Great Magician of the North, before he became the pride and boast of his country, when
he was yet the full-charged depositary of the romantic lore of the olden time, but had not asked the
public to drink at the well of his genius or of his acquisitions. The volume is a trying one for Mr.
Lockhart—he acquits himself nobly of his task.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Scots
Times.</hi></p>
<p >To say that this is the most interesting volume we have opened, since the “Waverley
Novels,” is merely to say that it really is what it purports to be, a faithful account of the
noble and simple character of its distinguished subject.—<hi rend="italics">Globe.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >H</head>
<p >This is a work for all times, and should be in the possession of every-body. In our opinion, it
must be impossible to read it without delight of the purest kind. Almost every page is fraught with
instruction, the value of which is greatly enhanced by the kindly, <pb xml:id="p6"/> generous, and
truly English spirit and style in which it is communicated.—<hi rend="italics">Hull
Packet.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >I</head>
<p >We opened this volume with great interest and anxiety, but not unmingled with fear as to the
result. So many disclosures have been made by Sir Walter Scott himself in his latter days; and such
a variety of information on almost every point bearing upon his history, literary and personal, has
appeared since in different forms and shapes, that we conceived Mr. Lockhart would have little now
to impart to the public. This, however, is far from being the case. The present volume has all the
freshness of novelty, and is so full of <hi rend="italics">heart,</hi> of life, and adventures, that
it stirs up almost like one of those romances with which the Great Magician himself, in days, alas!
never to return, held captive his countless readers.—<hi rend="italics">Inverness
Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >K</head>
<p >The work is in itself a literary treasure, full of incident and interesting facts, gathered from
the most authentic sources. The whole is cast in Lockhart's usual mould of elegance and
discrimination. When the work is completed, it will, we doubt not, be valued by all who can esteem
the efforts of genius.—<hi rend="italics">Kelso Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >We are certain that this work will obtain for Mr. Lockhart golden opinions from all; and not the
less so for the modest place which he constantly assumes to himself throughout its pages. In doing
this, he has avoided that error of overweening vanity which offends so much in Moore's Life of
Byron. Mr. Lockhart's better judgment has made this strictly a biography of his illustrious
relative; and we apprehend that he has executed it in such a way as will entitle it to rank in the
highest class of this department of literature.—<hi rend="italics">Kelso Mail.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >L</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart's “illustrations,” and the subsequent chapters of the volume, which
bring up the biography to the publication of “Sir Tristrem,” in 1804, just previous to
that of “the Lay of the Last Minstrel,” prove him fully adequate to the duty imposed on
him, and which he has undertaken <hi rend="italics">con amore.—Leeds Mercury.</hi></p>
<p >To most of our readers in England and Scotland, this review will be a pass-over; for, we dare
say, the charming volume has by this time been perused with pleasure by that literature-loving
majority.—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p >The ample means of obtaining authentic materials for the composition of these memoirs, by their
author, his acknowledged competence for his task, and, above all, the intense interest excited by
every thing relative to their illustrious subject, have combined to keep the public for a long time
“on the tiptoe of expectation.” This feeling is now in progress of being gratified by
the appearance of the first volume of the memoirs in question. It has been remarked, that highly
raised expectations are never completely realized by the object to which they are directed. In this
instance, however, an exception will be found to the general truth of the observation. The Memoirs,
so far, at least, as they yet extend, are calculated to gratify the most sanguine anticipations
which have been cherished respecting them.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >High as were the expectations formed, from the acknowledged ability of Mr. Lockhart, and the
ample sources of information at his command, the present specimen justifies us in saying that these
expectations will be exceeded, not disappointed.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool
Mercury.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >M</head>
<p >We congratulate the reading public on the appearance of this work. Mr. Lockhart has performed his
task with the judgment and ability which were expected from him; and, in his endeavour to do justice
to the character of his illustrious relative, he has increased his own reputation. Of the advantages
which he possessed in having access to the best sources of information, and of the communications
and the correspondence of the friends of the illustrious poet, he has made a good use; and he has
produced a volume of which almost every page teems with interest.—<hi rend="italics">Manchester Courier.</hi></p>
<p >The commencing volume of this anxiously expected work is now before us; the remainder being about
to appear at certain and not distant periods of time. But however high may have been the
anticipation formed regarding it, we feel assured that the present specimen will occasion no
disappointment.—<hi rend="italics">Monthly Review, April.</hi></p>
<p >It is related of Haydn, that when urged by his friends to bring to a conclusion his great work,
the oratorio of <hi rend="italics">The Creation,</hi> in the composition of which he had spent
several years, he used to say calmly, “I spend a long time upon it because I intend it to last
a a long time.” Mr. Lockhart has probably often made some such answer to expressions of
surprise and disappointment at the non-appearance of the long-expected life of his illustrious
father-in-law. But, independently of what he owed to his own reputation, he had to perform a sacred
duty to the great man who had intrusted it to him. That he has been sedulously engaged in the
performance of this duty, and that its execution will be worthy of his subject as well as of
himself, the volume now given to the public sufficiently shows. Sir Walter Scott was anything but a
secluded man of letters, known to the world solely by the productions of his pen. He was in habits
of intercourse with all that was great or distinguished in the literature and society of his time.
In order to do justice to his biography, it was requisite to collect material from a thousand
sources; and the labour, skill, and judgment necessary to extract from them the substance of a
narrative at once copious and well digested, must have been many times greater than even the
industry employed in accumulating so immense a mass. Sir Walter's correspondence, in particular, was
of extraordinary extent. Mr. Lockhart interweaves it with his narrative, and (to judge from the
volume before us) employs it in throwing light and interest over every part of Sir Walter's
history.—<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >Few modern publications have been anticipated with so much impatience as the Memoirs of Scott, by
Lockhart, and a rapid perusal of the first volume of the work has enabled us to predict with
confidence that still fewer are destined to be received with so much pleasure.—<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p7"/>
<head >N</head>
<p >This is the first of six, and, if all be as interesting as that before us, the work will be one
of the most valuable, as well as the most amusing and instructive, that have been published in the
present age.—<hi rend="italics">Newcastle Tyne Mercury.</hi></p>
<p >After an attentive perusal of this volume, we can say, without hesitation, that it has realised
all the hopes and wishes which we ever entertained. And these, we must say, were of no common
order.—<hi rend="italics">Northern Star and Caithness Advertiser.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >P</head>
<p >The first volume of this long-promised and expected work has at length made its appearance, and
its contents amply repay the delay. It is in every respect worthy of the subject, and of the high
literary character of its author.—<hi rend="italics">Perthshire Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >S</head>
<p >With a friendly hand and an affectionate heart, Mr. Lockhart has gone over every stage in the
Life of his illustrious relative; and, in plain, simple, and unaffected language, has endeavoured to
pourtray the leading peculiarities of a character of infinite interest. <hi rend="italics">Sheffield
Iris.</hi></p>
<p >We are convinced that the anticipations of the reading public will be amply realised by this
Biography of one of the most eminent authors of his age.—<hi rend="italics">Staffordshire
Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >Mr. Lockhart's Life of his illustrious relative, will not, so far as it has yet proceeded,
disappoint the expectations that have been formed of it. The dramatic form in which the work is
cast, greatly heightens its effect, for Mr. Lockhart does not put himself prominently forward, but
stands modestly in the background, leaving Sir Walter, assisted by the recollections of his own
personal friends, to be his own biographer.—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >T</head>
<p >The first volume of Mr. Lockhart's Life of Sir Walter Scott has been sent to us. We have not had
time to give more than a glance at it, but even in this cursory view we have seen that it is a book
which will interest every reader. Besides some new and curious matter furnished by Mr. Lockhart, the
volume contains an autobiographical memoir of the early life of the most popular of modern authors.
It is written in that graceful, unaffected, manly style, which characterises all the writings of Sir
Walter Scott, who, if not the first literary man of his age, had certainly the most healthy and
wholesome mind among all the whole tribe. His intellect was untained with the dandyism from which
Byron was not always free, or with the constantly ostentatious cant of the overrated Coleridge (we
purposely omit the names of living authors); it was alert and energetic; it sympathised, like
Shakspeare's, with every class of human existence, without the fantastical whining of Sterne, or the
unprincipled recklessness of Voltaire; and if it did not attain the higher flight of more
contemplative students, it was certainly not from want of strength of wing, but because the keen
observer and just thinker was disposed to see in the realities of life a more extended field for the
exercise of his great talents, and a more ample harvest of usefulness to his fellow-creatures, than
in the abstrusest theories of metaphysics, or the loftiest excursions of imagination.—<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >U</head>
<p >Here is the characteristic commencement of a life destined to be the most popular in British
Biography. The opening sample is delicious: authentic, characteristic, familiar, abounding with
anecdote and interest descriptive of striking scenes and congenial cronies, this volume is a feast.
Fortunately for posterity, Scott, with that intuitive foresight which gave prescience of his own
greatness, and rendered him jealous of misrepresentation, had taken the precaution to put together a
notice of his earlier years, which luckily fell into the hands of his son-in-law and biographer Mr.
Lockhart, at the critical moment. With this memorandum, which breathes of the frank and manly
character of its author, the present volume opens, and then proceeds with the illustrations and
additions of the biographer, who prosecutes his task in a spirit and style thoroughly harmonising
with his subject.—<hi rend="italics">United Service Journal.</hi></p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >VOLUME THE SECOND.
<lb/>PERIODICAL CRITICISM.</head>
<div type="section">
<head >A</head>
<p >THIS Volume opens with Sir Walter Scott's removal to Ashestiel, and the Publication of the
“Lay of the Last Minstrel” in 1804. We have subsequently an account of the unfortunate
partnership with Ballantyne, and the consequent literary projects,—a Visit to Southey, and
another to London,—Letters from Joanna Baillie, Canning, Ellis, Words-worth, Southey, Gifford,
and others,—particulars of the Establishment of the <hi rend="italics">Quarterly
Review,</hi>—Edinburgh theatrical anecdotes,—correspondence, &amp;c. relating to the
editions of Dryden and Swift,—and visit to the Hebrides; thus pleasantly bringing down the
narrative to 1812, when “Rokeby” was just planned, and Abbotsford just
purchased.—<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
<p >The Second Volume of this highly entertaining biography carries us through, perhaps, the most
critical part of Sir Walter's life, as well as that portion of contemporary literary history most
thickly sown with matters of interest.</p>
<p >We admire the impartial spirit in which Mr. Lockhart has treated the biography of his great
relative, as much as the ability which he has displayed in digesting the vast mass of materials, and
the style of the narrative.—<hi rend="italics">Asiatic Journal.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p8"/>
<head >B</head>
<p >The second volume of this work is even more interesting than the first; for it exhibits Scott in
the character of a popular author.—<hi rend="italics">Berwick Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >Our notice of this volume is a late one; but since its arrival politics—as well general as
local—have occupied so exclusively our attention, that we have been unable to do it the
justice we desired. The present volume is even more interesting than its predecessor. It continues
to furnish ample proof of that goodness of heart and amiable qualities, which a orned the talents of
Sir Walter Scott, and which distinguish him so favourably above most of his literary
compeers.—<hi rend="italics">Brighton Gazette.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >C</head>
<p >This volume of the Life of Sir W. Scott is by no means inferior in interest to its predecessor.
Sir Walter's “literary executor” has thrown over the pages of the second portion of his
work as great an abundance of literary anecdotes, correspondence, and particulars respecting Sir
Walter's publications, as delighted us in those of the first. Biography is the most attractive of
all reading, and we can imagine none more pleasing than Scott's.—<hi rend="italics">The
Cambrian.</hi></p>
<p >Of the second volume of this truly delightful work, it is not saying too much to assert that its
interest increases with its growth; and we become acquainted, by means of the extensive epistolary
correspondence of him whom every man of taste and feeling delighted to honour, with the habits,
pursuits, and opinions of the great “Wizard of the North.”</p>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has displayed great taste and discernment in the selections he has made from the
very voluminous correspondence in which Scott was engaged, and no person can take up the volume
without reading with pleasure and delight the letters to Joanna Baillie, Miss Seward, and others,
where lighter cares gave the opportunity of shewing an unaffected goodness of heart united with the
elegance and refinement of a cultivated mind. We could give numberless extracts, but we prefer
recommending the work itself to the perusal of every one who can appreciate the gratification we
have found, and who wishes to become better acquainted with the mighty master who so long occupied a
distinguished station in the literature of his country, and whose history will fill a niche in it
for generations yet to come.—<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Chronicle.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >D</head>
<p >However high may have been the expectations raised with respect to the manner in which Mr.
Lockhart would execute the task of biographer,—a task rendered, perhaps, more difficult by the
exalted station which the illustrious author occupied in the literary hemisphere; he has hitherto
performed the duties to which he has been assigned to the satisfaction of all,—to the
immediate friends of Sir Walter, and to his innumerable admirers in all parts of the world. Although
the quantity and quality of the materials which have been placed at his disposal, are both numerous
and valuable, the narrative is wholly removed from all affectation and vanity, evincing sound taste
and judgment, without an admixture of any thing partaking of an egotistical or fulsome nature. It is
minute without being tedious, and communicative without being dull.—<hi rend="italics">Doncaster Gazette.</hi></p>
<p >We can easily venture now to predict that Lockhart's Life of Scott, will be found equal, if not
superior in interest, to Boswell's Life of Johnson, which has hitherto been considered quite
unapproachable in the department of Biography; the spirit and tact with which he has used his
materials, and more especially his manly impartiality, are conspicuous throughout.—<hi rend="italics">Dumfries and Galloway Herald and Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >We have perused this volume without feeling any diminution of interest from what we experienced
from the perusal of the first. The interest is kept up without flagging, so ample and interesting
are the materials, and so skilfully are they managed. Scott's character is unfolded to us in every
capacity, whether as regards his Sheriffship, his Clerkship of Session, his authorship, or his
political partisanship. The domestic details are minute and interesting, and told in the way they
should be. Mr. Lockhart has proved himself admirably qualified for the duty he has been called upon
to discharge. His style is clear and manly. He does not obtrude his opinions, or cloy the reader
with misplaced or unnecessary eulogy. There is an air of candour too throughout the work which
satisfies us that Scott's inferior parts (and certainly they were of small amount) are as fairly
brought out as the brilliant parts. As a monument to the memory of our country's pride, this
undertaking, judging from what we have already seen, will, when completed, be more gratifying,
lasting, and useful, than any which can be reared by human hands.—<hi rend="italics">Dundee,
Perth, and Cupar Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p >The interest excited by the appearance of the first volume of the Life of the great Poet,
Historian, and Novelist, occasioned an anxious and very general desire for the second volume, which
is now before the world. Its contents are highly interesting, and cannot fail to gratify even the
most fastidious reader.—<hi rend="italics">Durham Advertiser.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >E</head>
<p >The first volume of this interesting Biography was calculated to give great promise of future
entertainment; nor do we think, judging from the present volume, that those expectations will be
disappointed. The progress of Sir Walter's Life, and the opening of that brilliant course which he
was destined to run, his multifarious literary schemes, his commercial connections, and the widening
circle of his acquaintance, afford ample topics to his biographer, which he handles with equal skill
and talent; and though last, not least, with impartiality; for he does not withhold censure when he
thinks censure due.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Courant.</hi></p>
<p >No preface is necessary on our part to bring before our readers the Second Volume of Mr.
Lockhart's Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott. It well sustains the promise of its predecessor;
and as we are carried into what may be regarded as one of the busiest and most important periods of
the Poet's History, the work increases proportionally in attraction.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Saturday Post.</hi></p>
<p >With regard to the Biographer's share of this volume, we need say no more than that all the
praise which we bestowed upon the first, is equally applicable to the second. It is most pleasantly
and most ably written.—<hi rend="italics">Scotsman (Edinburgh.)</hi></p>
<pb  xml:id="p9"/>
<p >The second volume of this valuable work is we think an improvement even on the first.—<hi rend="italics">Exeter Western Luminary.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >G</head>
<p >Need we say, that we strongly recommend this book to the public. In after years it will be one of
the classics of the language; at this moment it is one of the most readable and delightful works
which the present century has seen.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Courier.</hi></p>
<p >The Second Volume of this most interesting biography has just appeared, and it more than realises
the expectations which we were led to form of it, from the masterly execution of the
first.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Scots Times.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >I</head>
<p >In this volume Mr. Lockhart seems more at home than in the first, and there is more <hi rend="italics">breadth</hi> and freedom in his manner.—<hi rend="italics">Inverness
Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >K</head>
<p >If clearness of arrangement,—apt and interesting collection of a vast variety of
heterogeneous information,—authenticity of statements,—impartiality of
narration,—a thorough insight into the character of the “Great Unknown” when
breathing forth his inmost thoughts and feelings to his literary contemporaries, can recommend the
work before us, then we are assured the public will pronounce the performance complete.—<hi rend="italics">Kelso Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >The favourable opinion which we then formed of the literary merit of this publication, has been
confirmed and increased, rather then weakened and diminished, by a perusal of the second
volume.—<hi rend="italics">Kelso Mail.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >L</head>
<p >The continuation of this delightful literary treasure shews that, intense as was the interest
excited, it was far from being exhausted in the first volume; and, on the contrary, is maintained
with almost equal spirit, and certainly introducing persons and discussions of more universal
concern.—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p >The second volume of this most interesting work has just appeared, and, is, so far as we can
judge from a somewhat hasty perusal, in every way equal in merit to the first. We recommend the work
in the most unqualified manner to the notice of our readers.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool
Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >The qualifications of Mr. Lockhart for the task he has undertaken, or rather that has been
imposed upon him, become progressively more developed as the work advances. The abundance of his
materials is amply sufficient to satisfy the most craving curiosity, and the good taste of the
biographer in the selection of the materials, has ensured that curiosity shall not be thrown away.
Much that is new is brought out, and much that was already known has been put into a more clear and
connected form. We are fully warranted in saying, that this will be the most correct, as well as the
most complete life of Sir Walter Scott that has yet appeared.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool
Courier.</hi></p>
<p >The first volume of these most interesting memoirs of the Great Magician, has created such an
extraordinary sensation in the literary world, that we are sure the continuation in the present and
succeeding volumes, will be hailed with the most cordial satisfaction by the reading public in
general, not only in Great Britain, but in every part of the civilized world. Our readers will
peruse the work itself or their characters as persons of taste will be in jeopardy.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Standard.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >M</head>
<p >In this volume, there is, besides many interesting particulars respecting his literary labours, a
great deal of amusing anecdotes, and letters of himself and other distinguished individuals. In
short, the second volume is in no respect less interesting than the first, and the perusal of it
must produce an impression honourable to Scott, whether considered in his private character, or as
an author. There are many passages which, if we had room, we should gladly transfer to our
columns.—<hi rend="italics">Manchester Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >N</head>
<p >The interest of this attractive work grows with its growth, and the volume now before us is one
of the most delightful it was ever our good fortune to read. The natural taste and unaffected
elegance of Mr. Lockhart's mind, evince themselves in every page of the valuable narrative, while
the character and pursuits of the mighty master himself, are truly and admirably delineated in the
original correspondence. A more valuable addition to what may be called the contemporaneous history
of letters, can scarcely be desired.—<hi rend="italics">Newcastle Journal.</hi></p>
<p >This volume commences with Sir Walter's (then plain Walter's) removal to Ashestiel, and proceeds
to the history of his further literary efforts, his partnership with James Ballantyne, his obtaining
the office of clerk of the Court of Session, and the numerous and very interesting correspondence
into which he entered. His own letters, and those of his friends, convey a much more vivid and
characteristic account of his life than we could possibly have had from a mere dry detail. The
pleasure of accompanying the poet and novelist through his busy and enterprising career is greater
as we advance, and the modest and agreeable manner in which the narrative is carried on by the able
historian, gives a charm to the work which none who have not read it can possibly appreciate. To
enumerate the anecdotes related,—nay, to attempt to lay before our readers even a list of the
persons who figure in this delightful book, would occupy us too long, and would be rather fatiguing
than satisfactory. For the minutiæ we must refer the reader to the work itself. Suffice it to
say, that if the memoirs, as the author humbly calls them, continue as pleasing as we have found the
first two volumes, they will rank their author as one of the best biographical writers of this, or
indeed of any age. The present volume concludes with the beginning of Rokeby and Sir Walter's
correspondence with Lord Byron, bringing the life down to 1812. We purposely refrain from further
remark, that we may enable our readers to judge for themselves from the extracts we shall now make.
Before we conclude, however, we must observe, that the cheerful, happy enterprise of the poet, his
steady industry, his amiable disposition, his just and honourable conduct to <pb xml:id="p10"/>
all about him, are strikingly depicted, and form one of the finest “moral lessons,” to
all who desire to emulate Sir Walter, either in his virtues or his fame, that can possibly be
conceived. — <hi rend="italics">Newcastle Tyne Mercury.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >P</head>
<p >We will return to this delightful volume at another opportunity. Meantime, we will only add that
the interest of Mr. Lockhart's narrative rises with the progress of the work; and those, who, like
ourselves, anticipated at his hands a record worthy of his literary fame, as well as of his subject,
will find in this volume new evidence of its realization. — <hi rend="italics">Perthshire
Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >S</head>
<p >The present volume of the memoirs of this great man includes about eight years, from 1804 to
1812, a period during which his mind was in the fullest energy and vigour, and when he was laying
the foundation for his never dying fame. We like the present volume much better than its
predecessor. Mr. Lockhart appeared in the former volume to have been labouring under the impression
that he was engaging in a very serious and arduous undertaking. In the present his superior talents
are perceptible throughout the whole; the arrangement is much better than in the last, and
occasionally we have his own criticism on Sir Walter's productions, as well as on several others,
whose works are mentioned, given in that dignified and masterly style which he possesses when he
suffers his natural genius to have his own vent. Want of room prevents us from giving more extracts
from this interesting volume, which is rendered doubly so by being the life of so great a man as Sir
W. Scott, at a time when, as we have already said, he was laying the foundation of his great name;
but we recommend it to our readers as a rich intellectual treat.—<hi rend="italics">Sheffield
Iris.</hi></p>
<p >To any one who knew nothing of Scott but what he had gained from the earlier editions of his
works, it is probable that the first volume of Mr. Lockhart's work would be the most interesting. We
must confess, however, that we prefer the second, as fresher, and, consequently, more attractive in
its matter; and as exhibiting Scott in a new light in his maturer years, and when his character was
formed. Mr. Lockhart, moreover, appears to have improved in the execution of his task; and it would
be difficult to extol too highly the impartial spirit with which he has gone about it.—<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p>
<p >The pleasure derived in reading the first volume, is greatly enhanced in the second.—<hi rend="italics">Stirling Observer.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >T</head>
<p >The second volume of this valuable addition to the standard treasures of our literature embraces
the biographic details of eight years, namely, from 1804, the period when the <hi rend="italics">Lay
of the Last Minstrel</hi> was completed, to 1812, when <hi rend="italics">Rokeby</hi> was commenced.
If <hi rend="italics">Boswell's Life of Johnson,</hi> even in the present day, be read with avidity,
with how much more of interest and general sympathy must not that of Scott be read, whose biographer
is so far more eminent—whose life was so mixed up with popular adoration—whose works are
almost ubiquitous, and whose death is so comparatively recent? With biographers, in general, the <hi rend="italics">“nil nisi bonum”</hi> is rather too frequently observed; but the
insatiate feeling of the world requires impartiality as well as details, other than those of which
fame may have previously whispered, but not sufficiently expatiated upon. Mr. Lockhart, although a
relative, has had too much good sense to conceal that which was expected, and such details, handled
in the most judicious manner, are accordingly to be found in the book before us. The Editorship, as
far as it has been already exemplified, is as amply satisfactory to the personal friends of Sir
Walter, as it must be to the thousands and tens of thousands of admirers of his voluminous and
delightful works. Matter for extract abounds in almost every page of the work, and next week (if not
partially in this) we hope to afford our readers some very pleasant quotations.—<hi rend="italics">Taunton Courier.</hi></p>
<p >This is decidedly one of the most interesting publications of the day.—<hi rend="italics">The Yorkshireman.</hi></p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >VOLUME THE THIRD.
<lb/>PERIODICAL CRITICISM.</head>
<div type="section">
<head >A</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has treated this portion of Scott's life with all the ability which could have been
wished. The expectations formed from the first volume are fully realised, and a decided opinion
concerning the great merits of these memoirs may now be safely pronounced. The two volumes before us
are full of the most interesting anecdotes, told with great simplicity and effect. The criticisms
interspersed through the work are acute and judicious.—<hi rend="italics">Aberdeen
Journal.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >C</head>
<p >The contents of this volume occupy a period of three years, and is full as interesting as any of
the preceding ones.—<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Chronicle.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >D</head>
<p >The third volume of this charming Biography, gives us some of the most pleasing, as well as most
painful, passages in the life of the illustrious Scott. His pecuniary annoyances, from his deep
connexion with the bookselling shop of the Ballantynes, are positively humiliating. In the teeth of
all these mortifications, however,—nay, in the very midst of them, we find him carrying on his
literary labours with as great ease, as if his mind were wholly unruffled. In the volume now before
us, we have the history of the publication of Rokeby, The Bridal of Triermain, The Lord of the
Isles, The New Edition of Swift's Works, Paul's Letters, The Field of Waterloo, Waverley, and Guy
Mannering. It contains, also, much new and interesting <pb xml:id="p11"/> correspondence: besides
a Diary kept by Scott during a visit to Orkney and Shetland, and the Western Islands of Scotland.
The volume embraces a period from 1812 to 1815.—<hi rend="italics">Dumfries Herald.</hi></p>
<p >The middle of the volume now before us is the Diary of a voyage to the Shetland Islands in the
summer of 1814, from which we purpose in a future number to make some interesting extracts relative
to Staffa and Iona, and the other magnificent beauties of nature on the Scottish coast as seen by a
Poet's eye, and recorded fresh from a Poet's pen, while he looked</p>
<q ><p>“From Nature up to Nature's GOD.”</p></q>
<p >The political events of the year 1815, as connected with Scott, form the latter part of the
volume. These need only be mentioned to create intense interest.—<hi rend="italics">Dorset
County Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p >Our limits do not permit of a lengthened notice of this volume, but as we have already expressed
our high opinion of the work, this is unnecessary. The volume contains a period of three years from
1812 to 1815, during which time Sir Walter Scott produced Rokeby,—the Bridal of
Triermain,—the Lord of the Isles,—the Field of Waterloo,—Paul's Letters,—and
the novels of Waverley and Guy Mannering. We anticipated that this volume would be still more
animating than any of the preceding, and certainly there never was a task of a more difficult nature
than that performed by Mr. Lockhart, accomplished with such uniform and gratifying success. The
period mentioned above was an era in Sir Walter's life. He was plunged into society—the
admired of all admirers,—his private correspondence was voluminous, and his literary labours
Herculean, while the circumstances connected with his private life and transactions were such as
would have given to any ordinary mind sufficient space for thought and action. Complicated and
arduous as were his every day duties, it might naturally be thought next to impossible at this
distance of time, to expound every separate branch of the author of Waverley's undertakings. But the
biographer, a man of deep research and excellent judgment, has been gifted with ability to perform
the melancholy duty to his departed relative, of handing down to posterity all that is known of his
history. He has given in the work copious and continuous extracts from Sir Walter's correspondence,
and elucidates whatever is obscure in the happiest style. Brilliant passages connect the letters
inserted, and we have interspersed throughout the volumes, the collated memoranda of Scott's
surviving associates. Nothing is, therefore, wanting to complete the idea of the Poet's character
obtained from his works. We are transported from the perusal of his imperishable thoughts to his
parlour, where we view him as the simple, kind-hearted, and humourous Laird of Abbotsford. We are
carried with him to the court and the palace, and there is no change, his virtue is unassailable by
flattery, and his actions unswayed by influence. But while a sufficient space is devoted to the
reminiscences of his private and public life, we are not allowed for one moment to lose sight of his
literary labours, the progress of which are, as they ought to be, a chief object in the biography.
We have already made large extracts from this volume, and subjoin one or two more.—<hi rend="italics">Dundee Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >E</head>
<p >All the various matters of this volume are full of interest. The narrative of them is
interspersed with amusing anecdotes; and the biographer still executes his task with unabated
vigour. The portrait which he gives of Sir Walter is altogether pleasing, yet he appears to adhere
strictly to truth and impartiality. The ease, simplicity, and playfulness of his character, is
admirably depicted. As far as the work has yet gone, it is an excellent specimen of biography, and
presents a lively view of Sir Walter's character, both moral and intellectual—of his amiable
virtues in domestic life—and of the modesty and propriety of his general deportment in
whatever situation he was placed. We indulge in the most sanguine expectations of entertainment from
the succeeding volumes, seeing that the story must increase in interest as the celebrity of the hero
gradually extends.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Courant.</hi></p>
<p >The third volume is in some respects more interesting than either of the two previously
published, and, from ample materials in the shape of correspondence, which must be within the reach
of Mr. Lockhart's arm, it will form one of the most delightful biographies ever published—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Observer.</hi></p>
<p >The present volume of these charmingly written and most interesting Memoirs contains some of the
brightest, as well as darkest passages in the life of Sir Walter Scott. Beginning with the
“flitting” of the poet's family from Ashestiel to Abbotsford, with the characteristic
details of so important an event, the literary progress and personal fortunes of Sir Walter are
minutely related in the succeeding chapters; the publication of Rokeby, the Bridal of Triermain, the
Lord of the Isles, and, greater than all, Waverley and Guy Mannering. The <hi rend="italics">interior</hi> history of these popular works, particularly the novels, is full of the deepest
interest, and nothing could be better calculated to satisfy the reader's curiosity than the thorough
unfolding of the author's proceedings, which has been done in Mr. Lockhart's happiest manner. Five
chapters of the present volume are occupied with the Diary kept by Sir Walter Scott during a voyage
to the Shetland Isles. It is full of curious and characteristic matter, containing the poet's
personal observations in the course of the voyage. It was intended for a circle of friends, but,
nevertheless, it possesses every quality which could render such a record interesting to the public.
Indeed the <hi rend="italics">real man</hi> is nowhere more clearly unfolded than in the almost
unpremediated memoranda of which the Diary is composed.—<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Evening
Post.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >G</head>
<p >Mr. Lockhart has amply redeemed the pledge which his first volume gave, and, so far from there
being any falling off, either in the execution or interest of the narrative, there is a marked
improvement at every step we take.—<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Argus.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >H</head>
<p >Another delightful volume. It brings the narrative down to the year 1815; and contains a little
world of character, fact, and anecdote made yet more interesting by the good taste with which it is
presented. A diary of a visit to Stromness, the Hebrides, and other places in the north, shows how
completely the mind of Sir Walter Scott was able to invest an apparently barren subject with strong
interest.—<hi rend="italics">Hull Packet.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p12"/>
<head >I</head>
<p >The interest of this biography continues undiminished; for no cloud has yet come over the
brilliant career of Scott, and he is engaged in a thousand schemes, full of life, hope, business,
imagination, or pleasure. Here we have him, in the short space of three years, (1812 to 1815),
planting and improving at Abbotsford, (he has now become a laird, and discharges all his family and
social duties with exemplary kindness and hospitality), but we find him first a Clerk of the Court
of Session—publishing his poems of Rokeby and the Bridal of Triermain—refusing the
Poet-Laureateship—writing letters to Byron, Joanna Baillie, Crabbe, and fifty
others—publishing his edition of Swift—(a trifle of nineteen volumes)—writing
Essays for the Encyclopedia—publishing Waverley—(having written the second and third
volumes in <hi rend="italics">three weeks!</hi>)—making a voyage to Shetland and
Orkney—publishing the Lord of the Isles—writing in <hi rend="italics">six weeks</hi> the
novel of Guy Mannering—visiting Brussels, and writing Paul's Letters, and his poem of the
Field of Waterloo, &amp;c. &amp;c. When was so much of mind, of inventive genius and observation,
and of stirring life, crowded into three years of one man's existence? We were prepared by the
comments of some periodical critics to find this volume not so good as the two first, but we can
honestly say, that in the perusal we discovered no falling off. Mr. Lockhart certainly does not do
much himself, but his materials are admirably disposed for effect, and they are so rich in
themselves that they require no setting at the hands of another.—<hi rend="italics">Inverness
Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >K</head>
<p >This work, as it progresses, grows upon our affections. The literary associations with which it
is conversant, and the ever-varying scintillations of a genius such as Scott's, must render the
perusal of the valuable correspondence contained in it a matter both of delight and of instruction,
and, we will not say to Scotsmen, but to Britons, of honest pride, that Sir Walter was one of us.
Every Borderer should make himself master of a copy of this publication.—<hi rend="italics">Kelso Chronicle.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >L</head>
<p >This third volume of the Memoirs of Sir Walter Scott, comprises the important and critical period
of his life, from 1812 to 1815, commencing with his removal from Ashestiel to Abbotsford, and
including the publication of the first of the “Waverley Novels.” A large proportion of
the volume is occupied with the embarrassments arising from the derangement of the affairs of
Messrs. Ballantyne and Co., which began, it would appear, as early as 1812. Notwithstanding the
anxiety naturally superinduced by this constantly depressing cause, we find Scott, instead of
relaxing his literary labours, continuing them with redoubled zeal and energy, and producing a
succession of works, both in prose and poetry, which proved the indomitable ardour of his mind, the
Herculean strength of his frame, and the inexhaustible resources of his genius. One portion of the
present volume has afforded us very great pleasure in the perusal. We allude to the interesting
Diary of his voyage in the lighthouse yacht to Nova Zembla, “and the Lord knows where.”
It is an exquisite specimen of what might have been expected from him in the character of a
traveller. We need scarcely add, that it is our conviction that the present volume will be read with
increasing interest. The work is destined to become a part of the standard literature of Great
Britain, and, as such, will occupy a place in every library of consequence in the world.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Standard.</hi></p>
<p >This volume comprises about three years of the poet's life, viz. from 1812 to 1815, a period
short as to time but rich in events, both with respect to the hero and the world in general, since
it included the publication of Waverley and Guy Mannering, the escape of Buonaparte from Elba, and
his final defeat at Waterloo. We mention these events in conjunction, because in some of the
charming correspondence with which the biography is enriched, Scott expresses his opinions on
passing political events with all the zeal and fervour of his nature. The volume contains Scott's
diary of a trip to the Orkney and Shetland Isles, which abounds in touches of descriptive incident
and character, just such as we should expect from such an observer on such a voyage. Lockhart's Life
of Scott is likely to be, if it proceeds as it has begun, one of the best executed and most
interesting pieces of biography in the language.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool
Mercury.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >M</head>
<p >The third volume continues this most entertaining Memoir from 1812 to 1815, and embraces an
account of a highly interesting portion of Scott's life. The most interesting portion is Sir
Walter's diary of a voyage to the Shetland and Orkney islands, which occupied the whole month of
August and part of September 1814. “It affords,” says his biographer, “such a
complete and artless portraiture of the man, as he was in himself, and as he mingled with his
friends and companions, at one of the most interesting periods of his life, that I am persuaded
every reader will be pleased to see it printed in its original state.” Besides this, the
volume contains excellent letters to various correspondents, and an account of Sir Walter's
excursion to the field of Waterloo, &amp;c.—<hi rend="italics">Manchester Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >N</head>
<p >This volume commences with Sir Walter's removal to Abbotsford, and proceeds to give an account of
his correspondence with Crabbe, and the publication of Rokeby and the Bridal of Triermain. We have
then narrated the troubles in which Sir Walter became involved by his connection with Ballantyne,
further interesting correspondence, the insanity of Weber, with the very kind treatment of him by
Scott; the publication of Swift and of Waverley. The poet then took a voyage to the Shetland Isles,
the Orknies, and the neighbourhood, of which the author judiciously gives us the whole of Sir
Walter's diary. As a part of his life, the idea was excellent to copy the whole into the present
volume; and beyond this, it has all the interest and effect of a separate work. The diary occupies
about five chapters, and is so replete with information, and so delightful with varied interest,
that it is to us matter of astonishment it never came before the public in a corrected state till
this time. The Field of Waterloo was next published, and then come Paul's Letters to his Kinsfolk.
The volume ends with 1815, and contains, we should not forget, an appendix of the Durham
Garland.—<hi rend="italics">Newcastle Tyne Mercury.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >P</head>
<p >Among the interesting passages which crowd every <pb xml:id="p13"/> page of this volume, it is
almost impossible to give a preference; the following refers to his introduction to the Prince
Regent in 1815, and to a very current anecdote regarding his disclaimer of the authorship of the
Novels..... This brings us to the close of the volume. The work increases in interest as it
proceeds, and this portion of it is enriched by the insertion of a larger quantity of Scott's MSS,
than either of its predecessors.—<hi rend="italics">Perthshire Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >S</head>
<p >The interest excited by the perusal of the two preceding volumes of this work is still kept up,
we may say increased, by the present. We congratulate Mr. Lockhart on the discrimination displayed
by him in selecting materials for these volumes, and we would recommend all the admirers of the once
<hi rend="italics">Great Unknown</hi> to place this alongside his works on the shelves of their
library. In these will be found, as it were, the main spring which guided the hand now withering in
the dust, at whose beckon, knowledge opened her treasury, antiquity her locked-up stores, and formed
them into shapes for the amusement, instruction, and admiration of the world.—<hi rend="italics">Sheffield Iris.</hi></p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="page_of_senior_bio">
<head >VOLUME THE FOURTH.
<lb/>PERIODICAL CRITICISM.</head>
<div type="section">
<head >A</head>
<p >The interest of this work increases so deeply as it proceeds, that the prospect of its
termination excites pain and regret. We never remember to have read a biography which more strongly
enchained the attention, or exhibited so distinct and vivid a picture of the original. Scott has,
indeed, in his letters, unconsciously employed his inimitable skill in sketching characters upon
himself; and we doubt very much, whether the most perfect master of biography could have brought out
the character of Sir Walter Scott with half the force and strength of outline with which it is
reflected from his own correspondence. The fourth volume introduces his biographer, Mr. Lockhart, as
an actor on the scene, and his description of Scott is highly graphic.—<hi rend="italics">Asiatic Journal.</hi></p>
<p >The novelist's letters to his friends on these and other subjects, form one of the greatest
charms of the work. Indeed, he seems to have been a most indefatigable letter-writer, so much so,
that it is difficult to comprehend how he found any time at all to devote to authorship, even
allowing, which appears to be the case, that he attended to his voluminous correspondence whilst
sitting in the Court of Session, and supposed to be listening to the speeches of learned counsel at
the Bar. Besides an account of the negotiations for bringing out certainly by far the best batch of
his novels, the fourth volume contains many interesting incidents of his private history, among
others the death of some of his near and dear friends, his own illness, a visit to London, and his
elevation to a baronetcy. Such of our readers as can afford to purchase the work should hasten to do
so. They will read it with some portion of that pleasure with which, in days of yore, they coned
over the damp sheets of Ivanhoe or the Antiquary; and with every person of good taste it will appear
a <hi rend="italics">desideratum</hi> to have it placed on the same shelf with the never-dying works
of the great man, the incidents of whose life and death it details.—<hi rend="italics">Aberdeen Herald.</hi></p>
<p >We have characterised this Volume as more interesting than its predecessors. The cause may be,
that during the time to which it refers, the biographer became personally acquainted with “The
Great Unknown,” and is therefore able to link together the correspondence it contains (which
also is Scott's best) by a richer chain of anecdote and personal reminiscence, than he could command
for the earlier portion of his work. We find plenteous notices, too, of the increasing splendour of
Abbotsford, delightfully intermixed with glimpses of Scott's benevolence and consideration as a
landlord and a master.—<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >C</head>
<p >This volume comprises an interesting portion of Sir Walter's life from the year 1816 to 1820,
when we find him in the full vigour of his genius, and though labouring under a painful disease,
which attacked him occasionally for more than a twelvemonth, yet pouring forth with unabated
prodigality, the treasures of his mind, and contributing, during this short space, a larger stock to
the public amusement than other writers during a lifetime. The biography also derives additional
interest from the circumstance, that it has now attained to that period where the writer describes
from his own observations; and his sketch of Sir Walter, with his favourites of the brute creation
gambolling around him, and of his manner of conversing, of his tastes, his habits, and the aspect of
his study, is peculiarly lively and graphic. Nor less amusing, and equally just is his estimate of
his conversational powers. The interest of the work is fully maintained in this volume, which
contains much amusing detail, abundance of anecdote, and the most characteristic illustrations of
the manners and mind of the great literary hero of modern times, related, too, in an easy,
agreeable, and popular style.—<hi rend="italics">Courant (Edinburgh.).</hi></p>
<p >This volume, owing to many circumstances, is fully more entertaining on the whole than its
immediate predecessor. It contains more of domestic and personal detail—next to those which
relate to Scott's literary speculations, by far the most interesting portions of these memoirs.
These details include some curious festive scenes, in which the Ballantynes, who have acquired
altogether in the course of the narrative a sort of amusing importance, perform a distinguished
part. All this portion of the volume is exceedingly entertaining.</p>
<pb  xml:id="p14"/>
<p >Amongst the personal details of particular interest is an account of the attentions of the Prince
Regent to Scott. His offer of the laureatship, which the poet declined, and subsequently
successfully employed his interest to procure for Southey—his promotion to a baronetcy, and
some notices of a severe illness with which Scott was attacked in 1817, and which subjected him from
time to time, for a long while afterward's, to great bodily suffering. Such is a sketch of a few, a
very few, of the most striking points in these two interesting volumes. They, of course, convey but
an inadequate idea of their multifarious contents; but to give a fuller, would require a much
greater space than we can afford. We must, therefore, refer the reader to the ample bill of fair,
served up under the title of “contents,” or better still, to the work itself.</p>
<p >We cannot, however, dismiss these volumes without adverting for a moment to one or two general
impressions which a perusal of them will not fail to make on the reader. He will be struck with the
amazing amount of literary labour which Scott's unwearying industry was capable of accomplishing,
with the extraordinary elasticity of mind which enabled him to seize on subject after subject with
unpausing rapidity, and unabating energy, and with that still more wonderful facility of
composition, which enabled him to accomplish in a few weeks what any other man would have thought
cleverly done in as many months. Such an instance, in short, of rapidity of conception, with
facility of execution, is wholly unparalleled in the history of literary exertion. The reader will
not fail, also, to be struck with the singular and beautiful simplicity of character, the
unpretending manners and benevolence of nature which is associated with these astonishing powers,
nor to remark that there is not, throughout the whole of these two volumes, [3 and 4,] one single
harsh or discordant note—one single circumstance to disturb the perfect harmony of fine moral
associations.</p>
<p >Lastly, the reader will be struck with the fulness and frankness of the biographer's disclosures,
and will acknowledge that they leave no reasonable curiosity ungratified. Mr. Lockhart has not had a
very great deal to do in the case of these two volumes; but what he has had to do, he has done
admirably.—<hi rend="italics">Scotsman.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >D</head>
<p >Each succeeding volume of these highly interesting Memoirs affords the clearest evidence of the
single-heartedness of purpose possessed by this gifted being, the emanation of whose vivid fancy and
enlightened mind will live and triumph as long as the fascinating charms of imagination hold theirs
way over the human breast.</p>
<p >As far as he has proceeded, Mr. Lockhart has proved himself fully equal to the important work he
has undertaken; and, jealously watchful as we might be of the absence of the most minute incident in
the life of him whom from infancy we have loved, we could not select a single portion of the four
published volumes with which we could disagree or cavil. They indeed</p>
<q ><p>“Hold the mirror up to nature;”</p></q>
<p >and whether describing Scott as the “lion” of the London “magnates,” or
the contented centre of his own happy family circle—his books, his children, and what, as he
did himself, we may class with his family, his noble dogs, they are equally felicitous. The letters
which he has given us, written by the “Lion of the North,” and; his entire
correspondence with the leading literary, scientific, and political characters of the day, are rife
with interest of the most pleasing description; and we look for the appearance of the volume almost
with as much anxiety as we did of yore for the appearance of a new triumph in romance, bearing on
its title-page the thrilling announcement, “By the author of Waverley.”—<hi rend="italics">Dublin Evening Packet.</hi></p>
<p >Lockhart's personal reminiscences of Scott come into play in this volume, and give a fresh and
vivid interest to the work, beyond anything to be found in the three preceding volumes. Such a
sketcher as Peter Morris, with such subjects as Wilson, Blackwood, Constable, the Ballantynes,
&amp;c. cannot but be highly piquant. Another feature of great interest in this volume, lies in the
letters written by Scott to his son after he joined his regiment, which form an admirable model of
paternal counsel, conveyed with all the frank and easy confidence of one man writing to another as
his bosom companion. The rest of the correspondence throughout this volume is also superior, upon
the whole, we think, to what the three first volumes bear. If we add to all this that the literary
history of the works produced by Scott, during the period which this volume embraces, possesses in
many instances a new and profound interest, from the circumstance that some of the best of those
works were dictated amidst the pains and groans of a subduing malady, we have still only imperfectly
stated the attractions of a volume which we think is almost without a rival in the annals of our
literature.—<hi rend="italics">Dumfries Herald.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >E</head>
<p >What is there in literature that more interests us than that department which treats of the
actions and fortunes of individuals? In truth, the incidents of the life of an eminent man, is not
unfrequently the history of his times and nation; and if ever this were true of any individual, it
undoubtedly is so of Scott. If, too, the great end of biography is to make us acquainted with the
nature of man, what can better conduce to it than faithful portraits? This then admitted, and we
think it will scarcely be contested, we have in the work before us a grouping of characters, such as
in the most effectual way enables us to make progress in this branch of knowledge. The opening
volume, of which we have before spoken, was ample, its successors have all the marks of
authenticity, and abound alike with anecdote and incident. A manly character runs through the whole,
and there is something delightful in the perusal.—<hi rend="italics">Exeter Flying
Post.</hi></p>
<p >The fourth volume of this work, is, we think, of more general interest than the preceding ones.
Its contents embrace Scott's correspondence, referring to the chief events of his life from the
years 1816 to 1820, and are plesingly interspersed with Mr. Lockhant's own remimiscences of him, and
many of his contemporaries. The chief attraction of the present volume appears to be, that it places
the character of the man in its proper colours before the reader. We have him divested of all
reserve or ceremony, such as he appeared in the bosom of his family, and it may be readily supposed,
that as his biographer proceeds further with his personal recollection of the bard, who was destined
afterwards to be his father-in-law, he will bring additional spirit to his undertaking.—<hi rend="italics">Excter Western Luminary.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb  xml:id="p15"/>
<head >I</head>
<p >The value of this volume, like that of its predecessors, consists chiefly in the richness of its
gathered materials,—it is Scott that speaketh. Mr. Lockhart, however, has added some personal
reminiscences and anecdotes, worthy of preservation, with some interesting details of the poet's
habits—his great Sunday dinners and drives—his love of hearty breakfasts, and
old-fashioned dishes at dinner, &amp;c. There is a very humourous description of the dinners usually
given by James Ballantyne on the appearance of a new novel of the Waverley series. The demeanour of
Scott, the meek solemnity of Ballantyne, and the toasting of the Great Unknown, &amp;c., are all
admirably let off. We admire also the frankness with which he has dealt with his subject. There is
apparently no suppression for the sake of saving his hero—no fastidious dryness in burrying
into light all his private tastes, opinions, and transactions. In this manner the book will form a
counterpart to Boswell's inimitable biography, both as regards the chief actor in the scene, and all
his illustrious contemporaries.—<hi rend="italics">Inverness Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >L</head>
<p >The fourth volume of this delightful biography shows Sir Walter Scott in the height of his fame
and fortune, publishing with wonderful rapidity the tales which fascinated the world, and at the
same time carrying on a correspondence so extensive, a friendly and literary intercourse so wide,
and improvements in his estate at Abbotsford so various, that these alone would have filled up the
whole time of any man of ordinary industry. This volume still increases the impression produced by
the former of Scott's exceeding amiableness of character, and of his almost boundless versatility.
At this period of his life he was attacked by a most painful and formidable complaint, cramp in the
stomach, which disabled him from writing his novels with his own hand, as in former and subsequent
periods; but in the midst of agonies of pain he often dictated with indomitable energy; and the
following is one of the most remarkable instances in the history of literature, of the triumph of
imagination and genius over the extreme of bodily anguish.—<hi rend="italics">Leeds
Mercury.</hi></p>
<p >Our interest is increased as we proceed with the perusal of these admirable memoirs. The present
volume unfolds to us a very important portion of the history of the illustrious Scott, including the
period from 1816 to 1820, during which time his different publications appeared in very rapid
succession, and contributed to increase his popularity, as well as to stimulate the curiosity of the
public as to the identity of the mysterious author. It gives a minute account of the publication of
“Paul's Letters to his Kinsfolk”—“Guy Mannering”—“The
Antiquary”—“Tales of My Landlord”—“Harold the
Dauntless”—“Rob Roy”—“The Heart of
Mid-Lothian”—“The Bride of Lammermoor”—“Ivanhoe”—The
Visionary”—and “The Monastery,” together with a great number of smaller
works. The letters here published are very numerous, and possessed of great attractions. Extensive
as Scott's correspondence was, it is not a matter of surprise that this department of the Memoirs
should be one of the most edifying and amusing. The anecdotes related are as varied and
characteristic as those dispersed through the preceding volumes. We shall endeavour to make room for
several extracts in our succeeding numbers. In the meantime we can do no better than recommend our
readers to purchase the volume for themselves.—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Standard.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >M</head>
<p >This is the most interesting volume that has yet been published of these admirable Memoirs. The
correspondence of Scott in this volume is highly interesting, and for the most part entertaining;
and the same may be said of the anecdotes of his domestic life, and of his intercourse with society,
with which the volume abounds. Amongst the most striking events recorded in this part of the work,
are the visits of Washington Irving, Lady Byron, and Sir David Wilkie, to Abbotsford—the
former of whom has given a spirited sketch of his visit, strikingly illustrative of the poet's
habits and tastes. The account of his <hi rend="italics">Den</hi> in Edinburgh, and of his mode of
spending his time in Modern Athens, forms a highly entertaining chapter of the work: indeed every
page of the volume will repay perusal.—<hi rend="italics">Manchester Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >P</head>
<p >The fourth volume of this most fascinating of works and lives, takes up the narrative at the
publication of Paul's Letters in 1816, and concludes shortly after the period of his elevation to
the Baronetcy in 1820. The interval includes but a short space of time, but a mass of literary
labour, besides his usual abundant contributions to the periodical literature of the day, with the
addition of his extensive private correspondence, of which the present volume almost entirely
consists. The latter is more of a domestic character than hitherto, to which his severe illness in
1819, and the departure of his eldest son “from the nest—to wing his own way against the
storm,” mainly contributed. But in whatever view the correspondence runs, its character is
equally fascinating and equally beyond criticism.—<hi rend="italics">Perthshire
Courier.</hi></p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head >S</head>
<p >In this volume Mr. Lockhart appears upon the scene speaking of matters within his own knowledge;
painting domestic details, of course with greater freshness, and describing collateral things, such
as the various society of Edinburgh in which Scott mixed, with a portrait-like reality. His picture
of the brothers BALLANTYNE, and of the party given by JAMES when a new Waverley novel was on the
tapis, is richly ludicrous.—<hi rend="italics">The Spectator.</hi></p>
<closer >ROBERT CADELL, Edinburgh: JOHN MURRAY, and WHITTAKER &amp; Co. London.</closer>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pxvi"/>
<head >1837.
<lb/> SIR WALTER SCOTT'S WORKS COMPLETE.</head>
<p >I. WAVERLEY NOVELS, 48 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO, 96 ENGRAVINGS.</p>
<p >II. POETICAL WORKS, 12 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO, 24 ENGRAVINGS.</p>
<p >III. PROSE WORKS, 28 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO, 56 ENGRAVINGS.</p>
<p ><hi rend="italics">All done up in Cloth Boards, very handsomely, with gilt Back Titles.</hi></p>
<p >IV. SELECT POETRY, 6 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO.</p>
<p >THE SAME, 6 VOLS. 24mo. POCKET EDITION.</p>
<p >V. BIOGRAPHICAL MEMOIRS, 4 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO.</p>
<p >VI. LIFE OF NAPOLEON, 9 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO.</p>
<p >VII. PERIODICAL CRITICISM, 5 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO.</p>
<p >VIII. TALES OF A GRANDFATHER, (SCOTLAND,) 5 VOLS. SMALL OCTAVO.</p>
<p ><hi rend="italics">All likewise done up in Cloth Boards, very handsomely, with gilt Back
Titles.</hi></p>
<p >SEPARATE.</p>
<p >IX. LAY OF THE LAST MINSTREL, SMALL OCTAVO or 24mo.</p>
<p >MARMION, SMALL OCTAVO or 24mo.</p>
<p >LADY OF THE LAKE, OCTAVO or 24mo.</p>
<p >ROKEBY, SMALL OCTAVO or 24mo.</p>
<p >LORD OF THE ISLES, SMALL OCTAVO or 24mo.</p>
<p >TRIERMAIN. AND OTHER POEMS, 24mo. (only.)</p>
<p >All done up in <hi rend="italics">Cloth, Silk, Roan,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Morocco.</hi></p>
<p >The above contain the INTRODUCTIONS, NOTES, and VARIOUS READINGS, and form,
<lb/> together or separately, appropriate</p>
<p >LITERARY PRESENTS.</p>
<p >X. HISTORY OF SCOTLAND, (TALES OF A GRANDFATHER)
<lb/> SCHOOL COPY, 2 THICK VOLS. WITH COLOURED MAP, BOUND.</p>
<div type="section">
<head >CAPTAIN BASIL HALL'S WRITINGS.</head>
<p >I. SCHLOSS HAINFELD, OR A WINTER IN LOWER STYRIA. 3d Edition.</p>
<p >II. FRAGMENTS OF VOYAGES AND TRAVELS. 1st, 2d, &amp; 3d SERIES. Each 3 Vols.</p>
<p >III. NORTH AMERICA. 3d Edition, &amp; Vol. of Etchings in 4to.</p>
<p >IV. NAPOLEON IN COUNCIL, by BARON PELET, (de la Lozère.) Translated by CAPTAIN BASIL HALL,
R.N.</p>
<p >STUART'S NORTH AMERICA. 3d Edit. 2 Vols.</p>
<p >MRS. DALGAIRNS' COOKERY, a New Edition.</p>
<p >THE COOK'S ORACLE, a New Edition, containing a Complete System of Cookery for Catholic
Families.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">In the Press, Small Octavo,</hi></opener>
<head > TALES ABOUT WALES, </head>
<p ><hi rend="italics">New Edition,</hi> Edited by Capt. BASIL HALL. R.N.</p>
<p >ROBERT CADELL, Edinburgh: WHITTAKER &amp; Co. London.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pxvii"/>
<opener >FOURTH EDITION.
<lb/><hi rend="italics">In One Volume, small octavo, price Three Shillings boards,</hi></opener>
<head >SKETCHES OF YOUNG LADIES;</head>
<p > IN WHICH
<lb/> THESE INTERESTING MEMBERS OF THE ANIMAL KINGDOM ARE CLASSIFIED ACCORDING
<lb/> TO THEIR INSTINCTS, HABITS, AND GENERAL CHARACTERISTICS.</p>
<p >BY “QUIZ.”</p>
<p >WITH SIX ILLUSTRATIONS
<lb/> BY “PHIZ.”</p>
<list  type="simple">
<item>THE BUSY YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE ROMANTIC YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE MATTER-OF-FACT YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE YOUNG LADY WHO SINGS.</item>
<item>THE PLAIN YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE EVANGELICAL YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE MANLY YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE LITERARY YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE YOUNG LADY WHO IS ENGAGED.</item>
<item>THE PETTING YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE NATURAL HISTORIAN YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE INDIRECT YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE STUPID YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE HYPERBOLICAL YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE INTERESTING YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE ABSTEMIOUS YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE WHIMSICAL YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE SINCERE YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE AFFIRMATIVE YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE NATURAL YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE CLEVER YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE MYSTERIOUS YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE LAZY YOUNG LADY.</item>
<item>THE YOUNG LADY FROM SCHOOL.</item>
</list>
<p >“Here you shall see ‘the Sex’ classed and characterised with a keen pen, and
some of them sketched by a whimsical pencil. The little book before us offers itself as a <hi rend="italics">vade mecum</hi> to all gallant bachelors; and the most fastidious must surely find
some one to his taste among the varieties of that delicate and interesting species who are drawn as
‘lively as life’ in its pages.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">Publishing once a fortnight, price Sixpence each,</hi></opener>
<head >WEBSTER'S ACTING NATIONAL DRAMA,
<lb/> UNDER THE AUSPICES OF
<lb/> THE DRAMATIC AUTHORS' SOCIETY.</head>
<p >The Edition of the Drama will comprise every popular New Play, Farce, Melodrama, Opera, Burletta,
or Burlesque presented to the London Public, correctly printed from the Prompting Copy, with the
cast of characters, costume, and sides of entrance and exit, relative position of the Dramatis
Peronæ during the various incidents of the piece, and the time occupied in its
representation.</p>
<p >EDITED BY
<lb/> BENJAMIN WEBSTER, COMEDIAN,
<lb/> OF THE THEATRES ROYAL DRURY LANE, COVENT GARDEN, AND HAYMARKET,
<lb/> MEMBER OF THE DRAMATIC AUTHORS' SOCIETY.</p>
<p >VOLUME I., price Seven Shillings in cloth, is just completed, containing
<lb/> THE BRIDAL,
<lb/>
</p>
<list  type="simple">
<item>THE TWO FIGAROS,</item>
<item>THE QUEER SUBJECT,</item>
<item>THE MODERN ORPHEUS,</item>
<item>WALTER TYRREL,</item>
<item>MY YOUNG WIFE AND MY OLD UMBRELLA,</item>
<item>THE COUNTRY SQUIRE,</item>
<item>THE SENTINEL,</item>
<item>A PECULIAR POSITION,</item>
<item>THE TIGER AT LARGE,</item>
<item>THE MIDDLE TEMPLE,</item>
<item>RIQUET WITH THE TUFT.</item>
</list>
<p >WITH A PORTRAIT OF J. R. PLANCHE, ESQ.
<lb/>AND A SCENIC ILLUSTRATION OF EACH PLAY BY
<lb/> PIERCE EGAN THE YOUNGER.</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<opener ><hi rend="italics">In the press,</hi></opener>
<p > A QUARTER TO NINE—BLANCHE OF JERSEY—COURT FAVOUR—THE BOTTLE IMP—THE MAID
OF CROISSEY.</p>
<closer >LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement">
<pb  xml:id="pxviii"/>
<opener >THE NOBILITY, GENTRY, &amp; THEIR GARDENERS,
<lb/> Are recommended to peruse the New
<lb/><hi rend="italics">Horticultural Newspaper,</hi>
<lb/>CALLED THE</opener>
<head >GARDENERS'
<lb/> GAZETTE,</head>
<p > A WEEKLY JOURNAL OF
<lb/> SCIENCE, LITERATURE,
<lb/> And General Information,
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
<lb/> Published on Saturday,
<lb/> CONTAINING
<lb/> FORTY-EIGHT COLUMNS
<lb/> Of interesting matter, equal in quantity to that of any First Class Journal. Admitted by the
Provincial Press to be the most complete, well-arranged, and unexceptionable Newspaper for Families
that has yet been printed in London.</p>
<p >SOLD BY ALL NEWSMEN,
<lb/> AND SENT POSTAGE FREE
<lb/><hi rend="italics">To every part of the Kingdom; the Continents of Europe and</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italics">America; the British Colonies, &amp;c.</hi></p>
<p >OFFICE for receiving Orders and Advertisements, Books, Prints,
<lb/> &amp;c., for Review, and all Communications for the Editor,
<lb/> No. 343, STRAND.</p>
<closer >BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
