<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc ><titleStmt><title><emph>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. XV:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name><name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name><name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name><name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name></respStmt><funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt><resp>Text transcribed  by</resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp><name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp><name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Harris Henderson, and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>ca. 225K</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher><date>2002.</date><availability status="unknown"><p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title>title_pageThe Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. XV</title><title type="cover"/><author>Boz</author><respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp><name>Phiz</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>     54 p., ill.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">LONDON:CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher><date>MDCCCXXXVI</date><authority/></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Call number Dickens 13 pt. 15 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc ><editorialDecl><p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p><p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p><p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p><p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p><p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p><p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p><p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p><p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p><p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc ><langUsage><language ident="eng">English</language><language ident="fre">French</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc ><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-12-09"> Jill Kuhn Sexton finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-10-02">Harris Henderson finished TEI/SGML encoding</change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" when="2002-08-01">Apex Data Services, Inc. finished transcribing the text.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text ><front><titlePage><titlePart type="main"> No. XV.]</titlePart><docEdition>[PRICE  1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition><docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE <lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PICKWICK CLUB <lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE <lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES <lb/> AND <lb/> Sporting Transactions <lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS. </titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor>
EDITED BY “BOZ.”
</docAuthor><docEdition>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVI</docDate>
</docImprint></titlePage><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pii"/><opener ><hi rend="italics">Just Published, price One Shilling each, Parts I. and II., containing eight Engravings on</hi><lb/><hi rend="italics">Steel, of</hi></opener><head >SAMUEL WELLER'S <lb/> ILLUSTRATIONS <lb/> TO <lb/> THE PICKWICK CLUB.</head><p >THE ENGRAVINGS WILL BE BEAUTIFULLY ETCHED ON STEEL, AND ADAPTED <lb/> FOR BINDING WITH THE WORK.</p><p >TO BE COMPLETED IN TEN PARTS; <lb/> THE LAST OF WHICH WILL APPEAR IN DECEMBER.</p><p >A QUARTO EDITION, WITH PROOFS ON INDIA PAPER, PRICE TWO SHILLINGS.</p><p >A few of the criticisms to Part I. are subjoined. It is confidently expected the future Parts <lb/> will considerably extend the fame of the Artist.</p><p >“These delineations are imputed to no less a person than <hi rend="italics">Sam Weller</hi> himself; the characters are graphically conceived, and their features well preserved; the local scenery is said to be sketched on the spot. The drollness and spirit of these illustrations make us anxious to see more of the artist.”—<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p><p >“We hail with satisfaction the commencement of a series of illustrations to this popular work by Samuel Weller himself. Judging from his natural shrewdness, and these his earliest pencillings, we feel confident they will prove a very popular addition to the work; indeed the first part justifies us in expecting an inimitable series of etchings.”—<hi rend="italics">Observer.</hi></p><p >“The characters of this now celebrated club are well preserved in the various scenes illustrated, and in some there is much humour.”—<hi rend="italics">Guide.</hi></p><p >“In the first part Pickwick and Wardell are beyond praise; Sam Weller is a great hit, but his figure is too aristocratic; the whole group is admirably illustrative of the letter-press. In the last plate, Dr. Slammer and old Pickwick are immense, the person to the left is the <hi rend="italics">beau ideal</hi> of <hi rend="italics">Dr. Cantwell,</hi> in the play of the <hi rend="italics">Hypocrite;</hi> this plate is very fine. The artist must be a great man; should he live; he has nothing of the caricature of George Cruikshank, which pervades all that artist's best performances: his pencil is more Hogarth-like and dramatical, each figure is a study, and the combinations are exquisitely good.”—<hi rend="italics">Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“This is a clever work, in which the characters in the celebrated Pickwick Papers are graphically delineated by a talented artist, who has ‘taken the idea,’ and embodied it in a masterly manner.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p><p >“These illustrations are very clever and humorous.”—<hi rend="italics">Bell's Weekly Messenger.</hi></p><p >E. GRATTAN, 51, PATERNOSTER-ROW.</p><p >Sold by all Booksellers, Stationers, and Printsellers.</p><p > The Trade will find these Illustrations meet with certain sale to the various Subscribers of the PICKWICK PAPERS; and many of the thousands who read, but do not purchase the work, will, it is confidently expected, be anxious to possess these Gems.</p><div type="section"><opener >E. J. has just published a very fine Portrait of</opener><head > HIS LATE MAJESTY WILLIAM THE FOURTH, <lb/> IN HIS CORONATION ROBES.</head><p >The size of this beautiful Engraving is 12 inches by 9; the Price only 6d.</p></div></div></front><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piii"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill1"/>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="piv"/><p >
<figure xml:id="ill2"/>
</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="section"><pb  xml:id="p1"/><opener >186, STRAND, <hi rend="italics">June</hi> 30, 1837.</opener><head >ADDRESS.</head><p >THE author is desirous to take the opportunity afforded him by his resumption of this work, to state once again what he thought had been stated sufficiently emphatically before, namely, that its publication was interrupted by a severe domestic affliction of no ordinary kind; that this was the sole cause of the non-appearance of the present number in the usual course; and that henceforth it will continue to be published with its accustomed regularity.</p><p >However superfluous this second notice may appear to many, it is rendered necessary by various idle speculations and absurdities which have been industriously propagated during the past month; which have reached the author's ears from many quarters, and have pained him exceedingly. By one set of intimate acquaintances, especially well informed, he has been killed outright; by another, driven mad; by a third, imprisoned for debt; by a fourth, sent per steamer to the United States; by a fifth, rendered incapable of any mental exertion for evermore—by all, in short, represented as doing anything but seeking in a few weeks' retirement the restoration of that cheerfulness and peace of which a sad bereavement had temporarily deprived him.</p><div type="section"><head >NOTICE TO CORRESPONDENTS.</head><p >WE receive every month an immense number of communications, purporting to be “suggestions” for the Pickwick Papers. We have no doubt that they are forwarded with the kindest intentions; but as it is wholly out of our power to make use of any such hints, and as we really have no time to peruse anonymous letters, we hope the writers will henceforth spare themselves a great deal of unnecessary and useless trouble.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p2"/><head >NEW WORKS <lb/> PUBLISHED BY CHAPMAN AND HALL.</head><div type="section"><opener ><hi rend="italics">In One Volume, small octavo, price Three Shillings boards,</hi></opener><head > SKETCHES OF YOUNG LADIES;</head><p > IN WHICH <lb/> THESE INTERESTING MEMBERS OF THE ANIMAL KINGDOM <lb/> Are Classified, <lb/> ACCORDING TO <lb/> THEIR INSTINCTS, HABITS, AND GENERAL CHARACTERISTICS.</p><p >BY “QUIZ.”</p><p >WITH SIX ILLUSTRATIONS</p><p >BY “PHIZ.”</p><list  type="simple"><item>THE BUSY YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE ROMANTIC YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE MATTER-OF-FACT YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE YOUNG LADY WHO SINGS.</item><item>THE PLAIN YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE EVANGELICAL YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE MANLY YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE LITERARY YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE YOUNG LADY WHO IS ENGAGED.</item><item>THE PETTING YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE NATURAL HISTORIAN YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE INDIRECT YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE STUPID YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE HYPERBOLICAL YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE INTERESTING YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE ABSTEMIOUS YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE WHIMSICAL YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE SINCERE YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE AFFIRMATIVE YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE NATURAL YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE CLEVER YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE MYSTERIOUS YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE LAZY YOUNG LADY.</item><item>THE YOUNG LADY FROM SCHOOL.</item></list></div><div type="section"><opener ><hi rend="italics">Price One Shilling.</hi></opener><head >A FEW WORDS ON A FEW WINES.</head><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >CHAPTER I.—CHOICE OF WINE.</head><p >PORT IN THE WOOD.—GOOD WINE.—WHAT IT SHOULD NOT BE.—WHAT IT SHOULD BE.—HOW TO OBTAIN WHAT YOU WANT.—MATURITY.—BOTTLED WINE.—CONDITION.—BEES-WING.—CLARETY PORT.—THE WAY TO PURCHASE.—THE BEST SORT.—KNOW YOUR OWN MIND.—WHITE WINE.—ACIDITY.—SHERRY.—MADEIRA.</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >CHAPTER II.—MANAGEMENT OF WINE.</head><p >DIRECTIONS FOR.—FINING PORT.—CONDITION.—WHEN FIT TO BOTTLE.—WHITE WINE FINING.—DIRECTIONS FOR BOTTLING.—BOTTLES.—CORKS.—IMPLEMENTS.—PIERCING.—DRAWING.—CORKING.—PACKING.—THE CELLAR.</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >CHAPTER III.—TREATMENT OF BOTTLED WINE.</head><p >CORKSCREW.—DRAWING THE CORK.—DECANTING THE WINE.—WINE STRAINERS</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >CHAPTER IV.—DRINKING WINE.</head><p >TOO MUCH.—ENOUGH.—USE OF WINE.—ABUSE OF WINE.—DINING AT HOME.—DINING OUT.—LIGHT WINE.—ICING WINE.—WINE COOLERS.—WINE GLASSES.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p3"/><p >MESSRS. CHAPMAN &amp; HALL beg to announce that they have purchased the entire Stock and Copyright of the highly popular Works by the Author of the PICKWICK PAPERS.</p><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >I. <lb/> SKETCHES BY “BOZ;”</head><p > THE FIRST SERIES,—IN TWO VOLUMES, PRICE ONE GUINEA.</p><p >THIRD EDITION.</p><p >
<list type="simple"><head>CONTENTS OF VOL. I.</head><item>I. THE PARISH.</item><item>II. MISS EVANS AND “THE EAGLE.”</item><item>III.  SHOPS AND THEIR TENANTS.</item><item>IV.  THOUGHTS ABOUT PEOPLE.</item><item>V.  A VISIT TO NEWGATE.</item><item>VI.  LONDON RECREATIONS.</item><item>VII.  THE BOARDING-HOUSE.</item><item>VIII.  HACKNEY-COACH STANDS.</item><item>IX.  BROKERS AND MARINE-STORESHOPS.</item><item>X.  THE BLOOMSBURY CHRISTENING.</item><item>XI.  GIN-SHOPS.</item><item>XII.  PUBLIC DINNERS.</item><item>XIII.  ASTLEY'S.</item><item>XIV.  GREENWICH FAIR.</item><item>XV.  THE PRISONERS' VAN.</item><item>XVI.  A CHRISTMAS DINNER.</item></list>
</p><p >
<list type="simple"><head>CONTENTS OF VOL. II.</head><item>I.  PASSAGE IN THE LIFE OF MR. WATKINS TOTTLE.</item><item>II.  THE BLACK VEIL.</item><item>III.  SHABBY-GENTEEL PEOPLE.</item><item>IV.  HORATIO SPARKINS.</item><item>V.  THE PAWNBROKER'S SHOP.</item><item>VI.  THE DANCING ACADEMY.</item><item>VII.  EARLY COACHES.</item><item>VIII.  THE RIVER.</item><item>IX.  PRIVATE THEATRES.</item><item>X.  THE GREAT WINGLEBURY DUEL.</item><item>XI.  OMNIBUSES.</item><item>XII.  MRS. JOSEPH PORTER.</item><item>XIII.  THE STEAM EXCURSION.</item><item>XIV.  SENTIMENT.</item></list>
</p><p >EMBELLISHED WITH SIXTEEN HIGHLY CHARACTERISTIC DESIGNS BY <lb/> GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >II. <lb/> SKETCHES BY “BOZ;”</head><p > THE SECOND SERIES, COMPLETE IN ONE VOLUME, PRICE 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >SECOND EDITION.</p><list  type="simple"><head>CONTENTS:</head><item>THE STREETS BY MORNING.</item><item>THE STREETS BY NIGHT.</item><item>MAKING A NIGHT OF IT.</item><item>CRIMINAL COURTS.</item><item>SCOTLAND YARD.</item><item>THE NEW-YEAR.</item><item>MEDITATIONS IN MONMOUTH-STREET.</item><item>OUR NEXT-DOOR NEIGHBOURS.</item><item>THE HOSPITAL PATIENT.</item><item>SEVEN DIALS.</item><item>THE MISTAKEN MILLINER.</item><item>DOCTORS' COMMONS.</item><item>MR. JOHN DOUNCE'S ATTACHMENT.</item><item>VAUXHALL GARDENS BY DAY.</item><item>PARLIAMENTARY SKETCHES.</item><item>MR. MINNS AND HIS COUSIN.</item><item>LAST CAB DRIVER AND FIRST OMNIBUSCAD.</item><item>THE PARLOUR ORATOR.</item><item>THE FIRST OF MAY.</item><item>THE DRUNKARD'S DEATH.</item></list><p >WITH TWELVE PLATES BY GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="pv"/><head >WORKS IN THE PRESS.</head><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >I. <lb/> A VISIT TO <lb/> THE BRITISH MUSEM,</head><p > CONTAINING A <lb/> FAMILIAR DESCRIPTION OF EVERY OBJECT OF INTEREST IN <lb/> THE VARIOUS DEPARTMENTS OF THAT ESTABLISHMENT.</p><p >WITH <lb/> Numerous Illustratíons.</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >II. <lb/> <hi rend="italics">In One Volume, square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo.</hi></opener><head >MORALS FROM THE CHURCH-YARD</head><p > IN <lb/> A SERIES OF CHEERFUL FABLES FOR THE YOUTH OF BOTH <lb/> SEXES.</p><p >WITH <lb/> Beautifully engraved Illustrations on Wood.</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >III. <lb/><hi rend="italics">In One Volume, square</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo</hi></opener><head >  TALES &amp; STORIES FOR YOUNG PEOPLE;</head><p >  CONTRIBUTED TO THE “JUVENILE FORGET ME NOT,” <lb/> With Additions.</p><p >BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p><p >EMBELLISHED WITH SIX ENGRAVINGS ON STEEL.</p></div></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="text"><pb  xml:id="p435"/><head >[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XL.</head><head >
WHAT BEFEL MR. PICKWICK WHEN HE GOT INTO THE FLEET; WHAT DEBTORS HE SAW THERE; AND HOW HE PASSED THE NIGHT.
</head><p >Mr. TOM ROKER, the gentleman who had accompanied Mr. Pickwick into the prison, turned sharp round to the right when he got to the bottom of the little flight of steps, and led the way through an iron gate which stood open, and up another short flight of steps, into a long narrow gallery, dirty and low, paved with stone, and very dimly lighted by a window at each remote end.</p><p >“This,” said the gentleman, thrusting his hands into his pockets, and looking carelessly over his shoulder to Mr. Pickwick, “This here is the hall flight.”</p><p >“Oh,” replied Mr. Pickwick, looking down a dark and filthy staircase, which appeared to lead to a range of damp and gloomy stone vaults beneath the ground, “and those, I suppose, are the little cellars where the prisoners keep their small quantities of coals. Ah! unpleasant places to have to go down to; but very convenient, I dare say.”</p><p >“Yes, I shouldn't wonder if they was convenient,” replied the gentleman, “seeing that a few people live there pretty snug. That's the Fair, that is.”</p><p >“My friend,” said Mr. Pickwick, “you don't really mean to say that human beings live down in those wretched dungeons?”</p><p >“Don't I?” replied Mr. Roker, with indignant astonishment; “why shouldn't I?”</p><p >“Live!—live down there!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Live down there! yes, and die down there, too, wery often!” replied Mr. Roker; “and what of that? Who's got to say anything agin it? Live down there!—yes, and a wery good place it is to live in, ain't it?”</p><p >As Roker turned somewhat fiercely upon Mr. Pickwick in saying this, and moreover muttered, in an excited fashion, certain unpleasant in vocations concerning his own eyes, limbs, and circulating fluids, the latter gentleman deemed it advisable to pursue the discourse no further. Mr. Roker then proceeded to mount another staircase, as dirty as that which led to the place which had just been the subject of discussion, in which ascent he was closely followed by Mr. Pickwick and Sam.</p><p >“There,” said Mr. Roker, pausing for breath when they reached another gallery of the same dimensions as the one below, “this is the coffee-room flight: the one above's the third, and the one above that's the top; and the room where you're a going to sleep to-night is the warden's room, and it's this way—come on.” Having said all this in a
<pb xml:id="p436"/>
breath, Mr. Roker mounted another flight of stairs, with Mr. Pickwick and Sam Weller following at his heels.</p><p >These staircases received light from sundry windows placed at some little distance above the floor, and looking into a gravelled area bounded by a high brick wall, with iron <foreign xml:lang="fre"><hi rend="italics">chevaux-de-frise</hi></foreign> at the top. This area, it appeared from Mr. Roker's statement, was the racket-ground; and it further appeared, on the testimony of the same gentleman, that there was a smaller area in that portion of the prison which was nearest Farringdon-street, denominated and called “the Painted Ground,” from the fact of its walls having once displayed the semblances of various men-of-war in full sail, and other artistical effects, achieved in bygone times by some imprisoned draughtsman in his leisure hours.</p><p >Having communicated this piece of information, apparently more for the purpose of discharging his bosom of an important fact, than with any specific view of enlightening Mr. Pickwick, the guide, having at length reached another gallery, led the way into a small passage at the extreme end; opened a door, and disclosed an apartment of an appearance by no means inviting, containing eight or nine iron bedsteads.</p><p >“There,” said Mr. Roker, holding the door open, and looking triumphantly round at Mr. Pickwick, “There's a room!”</p><p >Mr. Pickwick's face, however, betokened such a very trifling portion of satisfaction at the appearance of his lodging, that Mr. Roker looked for a reciprocity of feeling into the countenance of Samuel Weller, who, until now, had observed a dignified silence.</p><p >“There's a room, young man,” observed Mr. Roker.</p><p >“I see it,” replied Sam, with a placid nod of the head.</p><p >“You wouldn't think to find such a room as this, in the Farringdon Hotel, would you?” said Mr. Roker, with a complacent smile.</p><p >To this Mr. Weller replied with an easy and unstudied closing of one eye; which might be considered to mean, either that he would have thought it, or that he would not have thought it, or that he had never thought anything at all about it, just as the observer's imagination suggested. Having executed this feat, and re-opened his eye, Mr. Weller proceeded to inquire which was the individual bedstead that Mr. Roker had so flatteringly described as an out-and-outer to sleep in.</p><p >“That's it,” replied Mr. Roker, pointing to a very rusty one in a corner. “It would make any one go to sleep, that bedstead would, whether they wanted to or not.”</p><p >“I should think,” said Sam, eyeing the piece of furniture in question with a look of excessive disgust, “I should think poppies was nothin' to it.”</p><p >“Nothing at all,” said Mr. Roker.</p><p >“And I s'pose,” said Sam, with a sidelong glance at his master, as if to see whether there were any symptoms of his determination being shaken by what passed, “I s'pose the other gen'l'men as sleeps here, <hi rend="italics">are</hi> gen'l'men.”</p><p >“Nothing but it,” said Mr. Roker. “One of 'em takes his twelve pints of ale a-day, and never leaves off smoking, even at his meals.”</p><pb  xml:id="p437"/><p >“He must be a first-rater,” said Sam.</p><p >“A, 1,” replied Mr. Roker.</p><p >Nothing daunted, even by this intelligence, Mr. Pickwick smilingly announced his determination to test the powers of the narcotic bedstead for that night; and Mr. Roker, after informing him that he could retire to rest at whatever hour he thought proper without any further notice or formality, walked off, leaving him standing with Sam in the gallery.</p><p >It was getting dark; that is to say, a few gas jets were kindled in this place, which was never light, by way of compliment to the evening, which had set in outside. As it was rather warm, some of the tenants of the numerous little rooms which opened into the gallery on either hand, had set their doors ajar. Mr. Pickwick peeped into them as he passed along, with great curiosity and interest. Here, four or five great hulking fellows, just visible through a cloud of tobacco-smoke, were engaged in noisy and riotous conversation over half-emptied pots of beer, or playing at all-fours with a very greasy pack of cards. In the adjoining room, some solitary tenant might be seen, poring, by the light of a feeble tallow candle, over a bundle of soiled and tattered papers, yellow with dust and dropping to pieces from age, writing, for the hundredth time, some lengthened statement of his grievances, for the perusal of some great man whose eyes it would never reach, or whose heart it would never touch. In a third, a man, with his wife and a whole crowd of children, might be seen making up a scanty bed on the ground, or upon a few chairs, for the younger ones to pass the night in. And in a fourth, and a fifth, and a sixth, and a seventh, the noise, and the beer, and the tobacco-smoke, and the cards, all came over again in greater force than before.</p><p >In the galleries themselves, and more especially on the staircases, there lingered a great number of people, who came there, some because their rooms were empty and lonesome; others because their rooms were full and hot; and the greater part because they were restless and uncomfortable, and not possessed of the secret of exactly knowing what to do with themselves. There were many classes of people here, from the labouring man in his fustian jacket, to the broken down spendthrift in his shawl dressing-gown, most appropriately out at elbows; but there was the same air about them all—a kind of listless, jail-bird, careless swagger; a vagabondish who's-afraid sort of bearing, which is wholly indescribable in words; but which any man can understand in one moment if he wishes, by just setting foot in the nearest debtors' prison, and looking at the very first group of people he sees there, with the same interest as Mr. Pickwick did.</p><p >“It strikes me, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, leaning over the iron-rail at the stair-head, “It strikes me, Sam, that imprisonment for debt is scarcely any punishment at all.”</p><p >“Think not, Sir?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“You see how these fellows drink, and smoke, and roar,” replied Mr. Pickwick. “It's quite impossible that they can mind it much.”</p><p >“Ah, that's just the wery thing, Sir,” rejoined Sam, “<hi rend="italics">they</hi> don't
<pb xml:id="p438"/>
mind it; it's a reg'lar holiday to them—all porter and skettles. It's the t'other vuns as gets done over vith this sort o' thing: them down-hearted fellers as can't svig avay at the beer, nor play skettles neither; them as vould pay if they could, and gets low by being boxed up. I'll tell you wot it is, Sir; them as is always a idlin' in public houses it don't damage at all, and them as is alvays a vorkin' ven they can, it damages too much. ‘It's unekal,’ as my father used to say ven his grog worn't made half-and-half—‘It's unekal, and that's the fault on it.’ ”</p><p >“I think you're right, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, after a few moments' reflection, “quite right.”</p><p >“P'raps, now and then, there's some honest people as likes it,” observed Mr. Weller, in a ruminative tone, “but I never heerd o' one as I can call to mind, 'cept the little dirty-faced man in the brown coat, and that was force of habit.”</p><p >“And who was he?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Vy, that's just the wery point as nobody never know'd,” replied Sam.</p><p >“But what did he do?”</p><p >“Vy he did wot many men as has been much better know'd has done in their time, Sir,” replied Sam, “he run a match agin the constable, and vun it.”</p><p >“In other words, I suppose,” said Mr. Pickwick, “he got into debt?”</p><p >“Just that, Sir,” replied Sam, “and in course o' time he come here in consekens. It warn't much—execution for nine pound nothin', multiplied by five for costs; but hows'ever here he stopped for seventeen year. If he got any wrinkles in his face, they was stopped up vith the dirt, for both the dirty face and the brown coat wos just the same at the end o' that time as they wos at the beginnin'. He wos a wery peaceful inoffendin' little creetur, and wos alvays a bustlin' about for somebody, or playin' rackets and never vinnin'; till at last the turnkeys they got quite fond on him, and he wos in the lodge ev'ry night, a chattering vith 'em, and tellin' stories, and all that 'ere. Vun night he wos in there as usual, alone vith a wery old friend of his, as wos on the lock, ven he says all of a sudden, ‘I ain't seen the market outside, Bill,’ he says (Fleet Market wos there at that time)—‘I ain't seen the market outside, Bill,’ he says, ‘for seventeen year.’ ‘I know you ain't,’ says the turnkey, smoking his pipe. ‘I should like to see it for a minit, Bill,’ he says. ‘Wery probable,’ says the turnkey, smoking his pipe wery fierce, and making believe he warn't up to wot the little man wanted. ‘Bill,’ says the little man, more abrupt than afore, ‘I've got the fancy in my head. Let me see the public street once more afore I die; and if I ain't struck with apoplexy, I'll be back in five minits by the clock.’ ‘And wot 'ud become o' me if you <hi rend="italics">wos</hi>struck with apoplexy?’ said the turnkey. ‘Vy,’ says the little creetur, ‘whoever found me, 'ud bring me home, for I've got my card in my pocket, Bill,’ he says, ‘No. 20, Coffee-room Flight:’ and that wos true, sure enough, for ven he wanted to make the acquaintance of any new comer, he used to pull out a little limp card vith them words on it and nothin' else; in consideration o'
<pb xml:id="p439"/>
vich, he wos alvays called Number Tventy. The turnkey takes a fixed look at him, and at last he says in a solemn manner, ‘Tventy,’ he says, ‘I'll trust you; you won't get your old friend into trouble.’ ‘No, my boy; I hope I've somethin’ better behind here,’ says the little man, and as he said it, he hit his little veskit wery hard, and then a tear started out o' each eye, which wos wery extraordinary; for it wos supposed as water never touched his face. He shook the turnkey by the hand; out he vent——”</p><p >“And never came back again,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Wrong for vunce, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller, “for back he come two minits afore the time, a bilin' vith rage, sayin' how he'd been nearly run over by a hackney coach; that he warn't used to it, and he wos blowed if he wouldn't write to the Lord Mayor. They got him pacified at last; and for five year arter that, he never even so much as peeped out o' the lodge-gate.”</p><p >“At the expiration of that time he died, I suppose,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“No he didn't, Sir,” replied Sam. “He got a curiosity to go and taste the beer at a new public-house over the way, on the premises; and it wos such a wery nice parlour, that he took it into his head to go there every night, which he did for a long time, alvays comin' back reg'lar about a quarter of an hour afore the gate shut, which wos all wery snug and comfortable. At last he began to get so precious jolly, that he used to forget how the time vent, or care nothin' at all about it, and he vent on gettin' later and later, till vun night his old friend wos just a shuttin' the gate—had turned the key in fact—ven he come up. ‘Hold hard, Bill,’ he says. ‘Wot, ain't you come home yet, Tventy?’ says the turnkey, ‘I thought you was in long ago.’ ‘No I wasn',’ says the little man, vith a smile. ‘Vell then, I'll tell you wot it is, my friend,’ says the turnkey, openin' the gate wery slow and sulky, ‘it's my 'pinion as you've got into bad company o' late, which I'm wery sorry to see. Now I don't wish to do anything harsh,’ he says, ‘but if you can't confine yourself to steady circles, and find your vay back at reg'lar hours, as sure as you're a standin' there, I'll shut you out altogether!’ The little man was seized vith a wiolent fit o' tremblin', and never vent outside the prison walls artervards!”</p><p >As Sam concluded, Mr. Pickwick slowly retraced his steps down stairs. After a few thoughtful turns in the Painted Ground, which, as it was now dark, was nearly deserted, he intimated to Mr. Weller that he thought it high time for him to withdraw for the night; requesting him to seek a bed in some adjacent public house, and return early in the morning, to make arrangements for the removal of his master's wardrobe from the George and Vulture. This request Mr. Samuel Weller prepared to obey, with as good a grace as he could assume, but with a very considerable show of reluctance nevertheless. He even went so far as to essay sundry ineffectual hints regarding the expediency of stretching himself on the gravel for that night; but finding Mr. Pickwick obstinately deaf to any such suggestions, finally with-drew.</p><pb  xml:id="p440"/><p >There is no disguising the fact that Mr. Pickwick felt very low-spirited and uncomfortable—not for lack of society, for the prison was very full, and a bottle of wine would at once have purchased the utmost good-fellowship of a few choice spirits, without any more formal ceremony of introduction; but he was alone in the coarse vulgar crowd, and felt the depression of spirit and sinking of heart, naturally consequent upon the reflection that he was cooped and caged up without a prospect of liberation. As to the idea of releasing himself by ministering to the sharpness of Dodson &amp; Fogg, it never for an instant entered his thoughts.</p><p >In this frame of mind he turned again into the coffee-room gallery, and walked slowly to and fro. The place was intolerably dirty, and the smell of tobacco smoke perfectly suffocating. There was a perpetual slamming and banging of doors as the people went in and out, and the noise of their voices and footsteps echoed and re-echoed through the passages constantly. A young woman, with a child in her arms, who seemed scarcely able to crawl, from emaciation and misery, was walking up and down the passage in conversation with her husband, who had no other place to see her in. As they passed Mr. Pickwick, he could hear the female sob bitterly; and once she burst into such a passion of grief, that she was compelled to lean against the wall for support, while the man took the child in his arms, and tried to soothe her.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick's heart was really too full to bear it, and he went up stairs to bed.</p><p >Now, although the warden's room was a very uncomfortable one, being, in every point of decoration and convenience, several hundred degrees inferior to the commonest infirmary of a county gaol, it had at present the merit of being wholly deserted, save by Mr. Pickwick himself. So, he sat down at the foot of his little iron bedstead, and began to wonder how much a year the warden made out of the dirty room. Having satisfied himself, by mathematical calculation, that the apartment was about equal in annual value to the freehold of a small street in the suburbs of London, he took to wondering what possible temptation could have induced a dingy-looking fly that was crawling over his pantaloons, to come into a close prison, when he had the choice of so many airy situations—a course of meditation which led him to the irresistible conclusion that the insect was insane. After settling this point, he began to be conscious that he was getting sleepy; where-upon he took his nightcap out of the pocket in which he had had the precaution to stow it in the morning, and, leisurely undressing himself, got into bed, and fell asleep.</p><p >“Bravo! Heel over toe—cut and shuffle—pay away at it, Zephyr! I'm smothered if the Opera House isn't your proper hemisphere. Keep it up. Hooray!” These expressions, delivered in a most boisterous tone, and accompanied with loud peals of laughter, roused Mr. Pickwick from one of those sound slumbers which, lasting in reality some half hour, seem to the sleeper to have been protracted for about three weeks or a month.</p><p >The voice had no sooner ceased than the room was shaken with such
<pb xml:id="p441"/>
violence that the windows rattled in their frames, and the bedsteads trembled again. Mr. Pickwick started up, and remained for some minutes fixed in mute astonishment at the scene before him.</p><p >On the floor of the room, a man in a broad-skirted green coat, with corderoy knee smalls and grey cotton stockings, was performing the most popular steps of a hornpipe, with a slang and burlesque caricature of grace and lightness, which, combined with the very appropriate character of his costume, was inexpressibly absurd. Another man, evidently very drunk, who had probably been tumbled into bed by his companions, was sitting up between the sheets, warbling as much as he could recollect of a comic song, with the most intensely sentimental feeling and expression; while a third, seated on one of the bedsteads, was applauding both performers with the air of a profound connoisseur, and encouraging them by such ebullitions of feeling as had already roused Mr. Pickwick from his sleep.</p><p >This last man was an admirable specimen of a class of gentry which never can be seen in full perfection but in such places;—they may be met with, in an imperfect state, occasionally about stable-yards and public houses; but they never attain their full bloom except in these hot-beds, which would almost seem to be considerately provided by the Legislature for the sole purpose of rearing them.</p><p >He was a tall fellow, with an olive complexion, long dark hair, and very thick bushy whiskers meeting under his chin. He wore no neckerchief, as he had been playing rackets all day, and his open shirt collar displayed their full luxuriance. On his head he wore one of the common eighteenpenny French skull-caps, with a gawdy tassel dangling therefrom, very happily in keeping with a common fustian coat. His legs, which, begin long, were afflicted with weakness, graced a pair of Oxford-mixture trousers, made to show the full symmetry of the limbs. Being somewhat negligently braced, however, and, moreover, but imperfectly buttoned, they fell in a series of not the most graceful folds over a pair of shoes sufficiently down at heel to display a pair of very soiled white stockings. There was a rakish vagabond smartness, and a kind of boastful rascality, about the whole man, that was worth a mine of gold.</p><p >This figure was the first to perceive that Mr. Pickwick was looking on; upon which he winked to the Zephyr, and entreated him, with mock gravity, not to wake the gentleman.</p><p >“Why, bless the gentleman's honest heart and soul!” said the Zephyr, turning round and affecting the extremity of surprise; “the gentleman <hi rend="italics">is</hi> awake. Hem; Shakspeare. How do you do, Sir? How is Mary and Sarah, Sir? and the dear old lady at home, Sir—eh, Sir? Will you have the kindness to put my compliments into the first little parcel you're sending that way, Sir, and say that I would have sent 'em before, only I was afraid they might be broken in the waggon, Sir?”</p><p >“Don't overwhelm the gentleman with ordinary civilities when you see he's anxious to have something to drink,” said the gentleman with the whiskers, with a jocose air. “Why don't you ask the gentleman what he'll take?”</p><pb  xml:id="p442"/><p >“Dear me—I quite forgot,” replied the other. “What <hi rend="italics">will</hi> you take, Sir? Will you take port wine, Sir, or sherry wine, Sir? I can recommend the ale, Sir; or perhaps you'd like to taste the porter, Sir? Allow me to have the felicity of hanging up your nightcap, Sir.”</p><p >With this, the speaker snatched that article of dress from Mr. Pickwick's head, and fixed it in a twinkling on that of the drunken man, who, firmly impressed with the belief that he was delighting a numerous assembly, continued to hammer away at the comic song in the most melancholy strains imaginable.</p><p >Taking a man's nightcap from his brow by violent means, and adjusting it on the head of an unknown gentleman of dirty exterior, however ingenious a witticism in itself, is unquestionably one of those which come under the denomination of practical jokes. Viewing the matter precisely in this light, Mr. Pickwick, without the slightest intimation of his purpose, sprang vigorously out of bed; struck the Zephyr so smart a blow in the chest, as to deprive him of a considerable portion of the commodity which sometimes bears his name; and then, recapturing his nightcap, boldly placed himself in an attitude of defence.</p><p >“Now,” said Mr. Pickwick, gasping no less from excitement than from the expenditure of so much energy, “come on—both of you—both of you.” And with this liberal invitation the worthy gentleman communicated a revolving motion to his clenched fists, by way of appalling his antagonists with a display of science.</p><p >It might have been Mr. Pickwick's very unexpected gallantry, or it might have been the complicated manner in which he had got himself out of bed, and fallen all in a mass upon the hornpipe man, that touched his adversaries. Touched they were; for, instead of then and there making an attempt to commit manslaughter, as Mr. Pickwick implicitly believed they would have done, they paused, stared at each other a short time, and finally laughed outright.</p><p >“Well; you're a trump, and I like you all the better for it,” said the Zephyr. “Now jump into bed again, or you'll catch the rheumatics. No malice, I hope?” said the man, extending a hand about the size of the yellow clump of fingers which sometimes swings over a glover's door.</p><p >“Certainly not,” said Mr. Pickwick, with great alacrity; for, now that the excitement was over, he began to feel father cool about the legs.</p><p >“Allow me the honour, Sir?” said the gentleman with the whiskers, presenting his dexter hand, and aspirating the h.</p><p >“With much pleasure, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick; and having executed a very long and solemn shake, he got into bed again.</p><p >“My name is Smangle, Sir,” said the man with the whiskers.</p><p >“Oh,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Mine is Mivins,” said the man in the stockings.</p><p >“I am delighted to hear it, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Hem,” coughed Mr. Smangle.</p><p >“Did you speak, Sir?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“No, I did not, Sir,” said Mr. Smangle.</p><pb  xml:id="p443"/><p >“I thought you did, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >All this was very genteel and pleasant; and, to make matters still more comfortable, Mr. Smangle assured Mr. Pickwick a great many times that he entertained a very high respect for the feelings of a gentleman; which sentiment, indeed, did him infinite credit, as he could be in no wise supposed to understand them.</p><p >“Are you going through the Court, Sir?” inquired Mr. Smangle.</p><p >“Through the what?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Through the Court—Portugal Street—the Court for the Relief of—you know.”</p><p >“Oh, no,” replied Mr. Pickwick. “No, I am not.”</p><p >“Going out, perhaps?” suggested Mivins.</p><p >“I fear not,” replied Mr. Pickwick. “I refuse to pay some damages, and am here in consequence.”</p><p >“Ah,” said Mr. Smangle, “paper has been my ruin.”</p><p >“A stationer, I presume, Sir?” said Mr. Pickwick, innocently.</p><p >“Stationer! No, no; confound and curse me!—not so low as that. No trade. When I say paper, I mean bills.”</p><p >“Oh, you use the word in that sense. I see,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Damme! a gentleman must expect reverses,” said Smangle. “What of that? Here am I in the Fleet Prison. Well; good. What then? I'm none the worse for that, am I?”</p><p >“Not a bit,” replied Mr. Mivins. And he was quite right; for, so far from Mr. Smangle being any the worse for it, he was something the better, inasmuch as to qualify himself for the place, he had attained gratuitous possession of certain articles of jewellery, which, long before that, had found their way to the pawnbroker's.</p><p >“Well; but come,” said Mr. Smangle; “this is dry work. Let's rinse our mouths with a drop of burnt sherry; the last comer shall stand it, Mivins shall fetch it, and I'll help to drink it. That's a fair and gentlemanlike division of labour, any how—curse me!”</p><p >Unwilling to hazard another quarrel, Mr. Pickwick gladly assented to the proposition, and consigned the money to Mr. Mivins, who, as it was nearly eleven o'clock, lost no time in repairing to the coffee-room on his errand.</p><p >“I say,” whispered Smangle, the moment his friend had left the room; “what did you give him?”</p><p >“Half a sovereign,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“He's a devilish pleasant gentlemanly dog,” said Mr. Smangle:— “internal pleasant. I don't know anybody more so; but—” Here Mr. Smangle stopped short, and shook his head dubiously.</p><p >“You don't think there is any probability of his appropriating the money to his own use?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Oh, no — mind, I don't say that; I expressly say that he's a devilish gentlemanly fellow,” said Mr. Smangle. “But I think, perhaps, if somebody went down, just to see that he didn't drop his beak into the jug by accident, or make some confounded mistake in losing the money as he came up stairs, it would be as well. Here, you Sir, just run down stairs, and look after that gentleman, will you?”</p><pb  xml:id="p444"/><p >This request was addressed to a little, timid-looking, nervous man, whose appearance bespoke great poverty, and who had been crounching on his bedstead all this while, apparently quite stupified by the novelty of his situation.</p><p >“You know where the coffee-room is,” said Smangle; “just run down, and tell that gentleman you've come to help him up with the jug. Or—stop—I'll tell you what—I'll tell you how we'll do him,” said Smangle, with a cunning look.</p><p >“How?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Send down word that he's to spend the change in cigars. Capital thought. Run and tell him that; d'ye hear? They shan't be wested,” continued Smangle, turning to Mr. Pickwick. “<hi rend="italics">I'll</hi> smoke 'em.”</p><p >This manoeuvring was so exceedingly ingenious, and, withal, performed with such immoveable composure and coolness, that Mr. Pickwick would have had no wish to disturb it, even if he had had the power. In a short time Mr. Mivins returned, bearing the sherry, which Mr. Smangle dispensed in two little cracked mugs; considerately remarking, with reference to himself, that a gentleman must not be particular under such circumstances, and, for his part, he was not too proud to drink out of the jug; in which, to show his sincerity, he forth-with pledged the company in a daught which half emptied it.</p><p >An excellent understanding having been, by these means, promoted, Mr. Smangle proceeded to entertain his hearers with a relation of divers romantic adventures in which he had been from time to time engaged, involving various interesting anecdotes of a thorough-bred horse, and a magnificent Jewess, both of surpassing beauty, and much coveted by the nobility and gentry of these kingdoms.</p><p >Long before these elegant extracts from the biography of a gentleman were concluded, Mr. Mivins had betaken himself to bed, and set in snoring for the night: leaving the timid stranger and Mr. Pickwick to the full benefit of Mr. Smangle's experiences.</p><p >Nor were the two last-named gentlemen as much edified as they might have been by the moving passages which were narrated. Mr. Pickwick had been in a state of slumber for some time, when he had a faint perception of the drunken man bursting out afresh with the comic song, and receiving from Mr. Smangle a gentle intimation, through the medium of the water jug, that his audience were not musically disposed. He then once again dropped off to sleep, with a confused consciousness that Mr. Smangle was still engaged in relating a long story, the chief point of which appeared to be, that, on some occasion particularly stated and set forth, he had “done” a bill and a gentleman at the same time.</p></div><div type="chapter"><pb  xml:id="p445"/><head >CHAPTER XLI.</head><head >
ILLUSTRATIVE, LIKE THE PRECEDING ONE, OF THE OLD PROVERB, THAT ADVERSITY BRINGS A MAN ACQUAINTED WITH STRANGE BED-FELLOWS. LIKEWISE CONTAINING MR. PICKWICK'S EXTRAORDINARY AND STARTLING ANNOUNCEMENT TO MR. SAMUEL WELLER.
</head><p >WHEN Mr. Pickwick opened his eyes next morning, the first object upon which they rested was Samuel Weller, seated upon a small black portmanteau, intently regarding, apparently in a condition of profound abstraction, the stately figure of the dashing Mr. Smangle, while Mr. Smangle himself, who was already partially dressed, was seated on his bedstead, occupied in the desperately hopeless attempt of staring Mr. Weller out of countenance. We say desperately hopeless, because Sam, with a comprehensive gaze, which took in Mr. Smangle's cap, feet, head, face, legs, and whiskers, all at the same time, continued to look steadily on with every demonstration of lively satisfaction, but with no more regard to Mr. Smangle's personal sentiments on the subject, than he would have displayed had he been inspecting a wooden statue, or a straw-embowelled Guy Faux.</p><p >“Well; will you know me again?” said Mr. Smangle, with a frown.</p><p >“I'd svear to you any veres, Sir,” replied Sam, cheerfully.</p><p >“Don't be impertinent to a gentleman, Sir,” said Mr. Smangle.</p><p >“Not on no account,” replied Sam. “If you'll tell me ven he wakes, I'll be upon the wery best extra-super behaviour!” This observation, having a remote tendency to imply that Mr. Smangle was no gentleman, rather kindled his ire.</p><p >“Mivins!” said Mr. Smangle, with a passionate air.</p><p >“What's the office?” replied that gentleman from his couch.</p><p >“Who the devil is this fellow?”</p><p >“Gad,” said Mr. Mivins, looking lazily out from under the bedclothes, “I ought to ask <hi rend="italics">you</hi> that. Hasn't he any business here?”</p><p >“No,” replied Mr. Smangle.</p><p >“Then knock him down stairs, and tell him not to presume to get up till I come and kick him,” rejoined Mr. Mivins; and with this prompt advice, that excellent gentleman again betook himself to slumber.</p><p >The conversation exhibiting these unequivocal symptoms of rather verging on the personal, Mr. Pickwick deemed it a fit point at which to interpose.</p><p >“Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Sir,” rejoined that gentleman.</p><p >“Has anything new occurred since last night?”</p><p >“Nothin partickler, Sir,” replied Sam, glancing at Mr. Smangle's whiskers; “the late prewailance of a close and confined atmosphere has
<pb xml:id="p446"/>
been rayther favourable to the growth of veeds, of an alarmin' and sangvinary natur; but vith that 'ere exception things is quiet enough.”</p><p >“I shall get up,” said Mr. Pickwick; “give me some clean things.”</p><p >Whatever hostile intentions Mr. Smangle might have entertained, his thoughts were speedily diverted by the unpacking of the portmanteau; the contents of which appeared to impress him at once with a most favourable opinion, not only of Mr. Pickwick, but of Sam also, who, he took an early opportunity of declaring, in a tone of voice loud enough for that eccentric personage to overhear, was a regular thorough-bred original, and consequently the very man after his own heart. As to Mr. Pickwick, the affection he conceived for him knew no limits.</p><p >“Now is there anything I can do for you, my dear Sir?” said Smangle.</p><p >“Nothing that I am aware of, I am obliged to you,” replied Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“No linen that you want sent to the washerwoman's? I know a delightful washerwoman outside, that comes for my things twice a week, and, by Jove!—how devilish lucky!—this is the very day she calls. Shall I put any of those little things up with mine? Don't say anything about the trouble. Confound and curse it! if one gentleman under a cloud is not to put himself a little out of the way to assist another gentleman in the same condition, what's human nature?”</p><p >Thus spake Mr. Smangle, edging himself meanwhile as near as possible to the portmanteau, and beaming forth looks of the most fervent and disinterested friendship.</p><p >“There's nothing you want to give out for the man to brush, my dear creature, is there?” resumed Smangle.</p><p >“Nothin' whoever, my fine feller,” rejoined Sam, taking the reply into his own mouth. “P'raps if vun of us wos to brush, without troubling the man, it'ud be more agreeable for all parties, as the school-master said ven the young gentlemen objected to being flogged by the butler.”</p><p >“And there's nothing that I can send in my little box to the washer-woman's, is there?” said Smangle, turning from Sam to Mr. Pickwick with an air of some discomfiture.</p><p >“Nothin' whatever, Sir,” retorted Sam; “I'm afeerd the little box must be chock full o' your own as it is.”</p><p >This speech was accompanied with such a very expressive look at that particular portion of Mr. Smangle's attire, by the appearance of which the skill of laundresses in getting up gentlemen's linen is generally tested, that he was fain to turn upon his heel, and, for the present at any rate, to give up all design on Mr. Pickwick's purse and wardrobe. He accordingly retired in dudgeon to the racket-ground, where he made a light and wholesome breakfast upon a couple of the cigars which had been purchased on the previous night.</p><p >Mr. Mivins, who was no smoker, and whose account for small articles of chandlery had also reached down to the bottom of the slate, and been “carried over” to the other side, remained in bed, and, in his own words, “took it out in sleep.”</p><pb  xml:id="p447"/><p >After breakfasting in a small closet attached to the coffee-room, which bore the imposing title of the Snuggery, the temporary inmate of which, in consideration of a small additional charge, has the unspeakable advantage of overhearing all the conversation in the coffee-room aforesaid; and after despatching Mr. Weller on some necessary errands, Mr. Pickwick repaired to the Lodge, to consult Mr. Roker concerning his future accommodation.</p><p >“Accommodation, eh?” said that gentleman, consulting a large book; “Plenty of that, Mr. Pickvick. Your chummage ticket will be on twenty-seven, in the third.”</p><p >“Oh,” said Mr. Pickwick. “My what, did you say?”</p><p >“Your chummage ticket,” replied Mr. Roker; “you're up to that?”</p><p >“Not quite,” replied Mr. Pickwick, with a smile.</p><p >“Why,” said Mr. Roker, “it's as plain as Salisbury. You'll have a chummage ticket upon twenty-seven in the third, and them as is in the room will be your chums.”</p><p >“Are there many of them?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, dubiously.</p><p >“Three,” replied Mr. Roker.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick coughed.</p><p >“One of 'em 's a parson,” said Mr. Roker, filling up a little piece of paper as he spoke, “another's a butcher.”</p><p >“Eh?” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“A butcher,” repeated Mr. Roker, giving the nib of his pen a tap on the desk to cure it of a disinclination to mark. “What a thorough-paced goer he used to be sure-ly! You remember Tom Martin, Neddy?” said Roker, appealing to another man in the lodge, who was paring the mud off his shoes with a five-and-twenty bladed pocket knife.</p><p >“I should think so,” replied the party addressed, with a strong emphasis on the personal pronoun.</p><p >“Bless my dear eyes,” said Mr. Roker, shaking his head slowly from side to side, and gazing abstractedly out of the grated window before him, as if he were fondly recalling some peaceful scene of his early youth; “it seems but yesterday that he whopped the coal-heaver down Fox-under-the-Hill by the wharf there. I think I can see him now, a coming up the Strand between the two street-keepers, a little sobered by the bruising, with a patch o' winegar and brown paper over his right eyelid, and that 'ere lovely bull-dog, as pinned the little boy arterwards, a following at his heels. What a rum thing time is, ain't it, Neddy?”</p><p >The gentleman to whom these observations were addressed, who appeared of a taciturn and thoughtful cast, merely echoed the inquiry and Mr. Roker, shaking off the poetical and gloomy train of thought into which he had been betrayed, descended to the common business of life, and resumed his pen.</p><p >“Do you know what the third gentleman is?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, not very much gratified by this description of his future associates.</p><p >“What is that Simpson, Neddy?” said Mr. Roker, turning to his companion.</p><pb  xml:id="p448"/><p >“What Simpson?” said Neddy.</p><p >“Why him in twenty-seven in the third, that this gentleman's going to be chummed on.”</p><p >“Oh, him!” replied Neddy: “he's nothing exactly. He <hi rend="italics">was</hi> a horse chaunter: he's a leg now.”</p><p >“Ah, so I thought,” rejoined Mr. Roker, closing the book, and placing the small piece of paper in Mr. Pickwick's hands—“That's the ticket, Sir.”</p><p >Very much perplexed by this summary disposition of his person, Mr. Pickwick walked back into the prison, revolving in his mind what he had better do. Convinced, however, that before he took any other steps it would be advisable to see, and hold personal converse with, the three gentlemen with whom it was proposed to quarter him, he made the best of his way to the third flight.</p><p >After groping about in the gallery for some time, attempting in the dim light to decipher the numbers on the different doors, he at length appealed to a potboy, who happened to be pursuing his morning occupation of gleaning for pewter.</p><p >“Which is twenty-seven, my good fellow?” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Five doors further on,” replied the potboy. “There's the likeness of a man being hung, and smoking a pipe the while, chalked outside the door.”</p><p >Guided by this direction, Mr. Pickwick proceeded slowly along the gallery until he encountered the “portrait of a gentleman,” above described, upon whose countenance he tapped, with the knuckle of his fore-finger—gently at first, and then more audibly. After repeating this process several times without effect, he ventured to open the door and peep in.</p><p >There was only one man in the room, and he was leaning out of window as far as he could without over-balancing himself, endeavouring with great perseverance to spit upon the crown of the hat of a personal friend on the parade below. As neither speaking, coughing, sneezing, knocking, nor any other ordinary mode of attracting attention, made this person aware of the presence of a visiter, Mr. Pickwick, after some delay, stepped up to the window, and pulled him gently by the coattail. The individual brought in his head and shoulders with great swiftness, and surveying Mr. Pickwick from head to foot, demanded in a surly tone what the—something beginning with a capital H—he wanted.</p><p >“I believe,” said Mr. Pickwick, consulting his ticket, “I believe this is twenty-seven in the third.”</p><p >“Well?” replied the gentleman.</p><p >“I have come here in consequence of receiving this bit of paper,” rejoined Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Hand it over,” said the gentleman.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick complied.</p><p >“I think Roker might have chummed you somewhere else,” said Mr. Simpson (for it was the leg), after a very discontented sort of a pause.</p><pb  xml:id="p449"/><p >Mr. Pickwick thought so also; but, under all the circumstances, he considered it a matter of sound policy to be silent.</p><p >Mr. Simpson mused for a few moments after this, and then, thrusting his head out of the window, gave a shrill whistle, and pronounced some word aloud several times. What the word was, Mr. Pickwick could not distinguish; but he rather inferred that it must be some nickname which distinguished Mr. Martin, from the fact of a great number of gentlemen on the ground below, immediately proceeding to cry “Butcher,” in imitation of the tone in which that useful class of society are wont diurnally to make their presence known at area railings.</p><p >Subsequent occurrences confirmed the accuracy of Mr. Pickwick's impression; for, in a few seconds, a gentleman, prematurely broad for his years, clothed in a professional blue jean frock, and top-boots with circular toes, entered the room nearly out of breath, closely followed by another gentleman in very shabby black, and a seal-skin cap. The latter gentleman, who fastened his coat all the way up to his chin by means of a pin and a button alternately, had a very coarse red face, and looked like a drunken chaplain, which, indeed, he was.</p><p >These two gentlemen having by turns perused Mr. Pickwick's billet, the one expressed his opinion that it was “a rig,” and the other his conviction that it was “a go.” Having recorded their feelings in these very intelligible terms, they looked at Mr. Pickwick and each other in awkward silence.</p><p >“It's an aggravating thing, just as we got the beds so snug,” said the chaplain, looking at three dirty mattresses, each rolled up in a blanket, which occupied one corner of the room during the day, and formed a kind of slab, on which were placed an old cracked basin, ewer, and soapdish, of common yellow earthenware, with a blue flower: “Very aggravating.”</p><p >Mr. Martin expressed the same opinion, in rather stronger terms; Mr. Simpson, after having let a variety of expletive adjectives loose upon society without any substantive to accompany them, tucked up his sleeves, and began to wash the greens for dinner.</p><p >While this was going on, Mr. Pickwick had been eyeing the room, which was filthily dirty, and smelt intolerably close. There was no vestige of either carpet, curtain, or blind. There was not even a closet in it. Unquestionably there were but few things to put away, if there had been one; but, however few in number, or small in individual amount, still remnants of loaves, and pieces of cheese, and damp towels, and scraps of meat, and articles of wearing apparel, and mutilated crockery, and bellows without nozzles, and toasting-forks without prongs, <hi rend="italics">do</hi> present something of an uncomfortable appearance when they are scattered about the floor of a small apartment, which is the common sitting and sleeping room of three idle men.</p><p >“I suppose this can be managed somehow,” said the butcher after a pretty long silence. “What will you take to go out?”</p><p >“I beg your pardon,” replied Mr. Pickwick. “What did you say? I hardly understand you.”</p><p >“What will you take to be paid out?” said the butcher. “The regular chummage is two-and-sixpence. Will you take three bob?”</p><pb  xml:id="p450"/><p >“—And a bender,” suggested the clerical gentleman.</p><p >“Well, I don't mind that; it's only twopence a-piece more,” said Mr. Martin. “What do you say now? We'll pay you out for three-and-sixpence a week. Come.”</p><p >“And stand a gallon of beer down,” chimed in Mr. Simpson. “There.”</p><p >“And drink it on the spot,” said the chaplain. “Now.”</p><p >“I really am so wholly ignorant of the rules of this place,” returned Mr. Pickwick, “that I do not yet comprehend you. <hi rend="italics">Can</hi> I live anywhere else? I thought I could not.”</p><p >At this inquiry Mr. Martin looked with a countenance of excessive surprise at his two friends, and then each gentleman pointed with his right thumb over his left shoulder. This action, imperfectly described in words by the very feeble term of “over the left,” when performed by any number of ladies or gentlemen who are accustomed to act in unison, has a very graceful and airy effect; its expression is one of light and playful sarcasm.</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Can</hi> you!” repeated Mr. Martin, with a smile of pity.</p><p >“Well, if I knew as little of life as that, I'd eat my hat and swallow the buckle,” said the clerical gentleman.</p><p >“So would I,” added the sporting one, solemnly.</p><p >After this introductory preface, the three chums informed Mr. Pickwick in a breath, that money was, in the Fleet, just what money was out of it; that it would instantly procure him almost anything he desired; and that, supposing he had got it, and had no objection to spend it, if he only signified his wish to have a room to himself, he might take possession of one, furnished and fitted to boot, in half an hour's time.</p><p >With this, the parties separated, very much to their mutual satisfaction; Mr. Pickwick once more retracing his steps to the lodge, and the three companions adjourning to the coffee-room, there to expend the five shillings which the clerical gentleman had, with admirable prudence and foresight, borrowed of him for the purpose.</p><p >“I knowed it!” said Mr. Roker, with a chuckle, when Mr. Pickwick stated the object with which he had returned. “Didn't I say so, Neddy?”</p><p >The philosophical owner of the universal penknife growled an affirmative.</p><p >“I knowed you'd want a room for yourself, bless you!” said Mr. Roker. “Let me see. You'll want some furniture. You'll hire that of me, I suppose? That's the reg'lar thing.”</p><p >“With great pleasure,” replied Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“There's a capital room up in the coffee-room flight, that belongs to a Chancery prisoner,” said Mr. Roker. “It'll stand you in a pound a-week. I suppose you don't mind that?”</p><p >“Not at all,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Just step there with me,” said Roker, taking up his hat with great alacrity; “the matter's settled in five minutes. Lord! why didn't you say at first that you was willing to come down handsome?”</p><pb  xml:id="p451"/><p >The matter was soon arranged, as the turnkey had foretold. The Chancery prisoner had been there long enough to have lost friends, fortune, home, and happiness, and to have acquired the right of having a room to himself. As he laboured, however, under the slight inconvenience of often wanting a morsel of bread, he eagerly listened to Mr. Pickwick's proposal to rent the apartment; and readily covenanted and agreed to yield him up the sole and undisturbed possession thereof, in consideration of the weekly payment of twenty shillings; from which fund he furthermore contracted to pay out any person or persons that might be chummed upon it.</p><p >As they struck the bargain, Mr. Pickwick surveyed him with a painful interest. He was a tall, gaunt, cadaverous man, in an old great coat and slippers, with sunken cheeks, and a restless, eager eye. His lips were bloodless, and his bones sharp and thin. God help him! the iron teeth of confinement and privation had been slowly filing them down for twenty years.</p><p >“And where will you live meanwhile, Sir?” said Mr. Pickwick, as he laid the amount of the first week's rent in advance on the tottering table.</p><p >The man gathered up the money with a trembling hand, and replied that he didn't know yet; he must go and see where he could move his bed to.</p><p >“I am afraid, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick, laying his hand gently and compassionately on his arm;—“I am afraid you will have to live in some noisy crowded place. Now, pray, consider this room your own when you want quiet, or when any of your friends come to see you.”</p><p >“Friends!” interposed the man, in a voice which rattled in his throat. “If I lay dead at the bottom of the deepest mine in the world, tight screwed down and soldered in my coffin, rotting in the dark and filthy ditch that drags its slime along beneath the foundations of this prison, I could not be more forgotten or unheeded than I am here. I am a dead man—dead to society, without the pity they bestow on those whose souls have passed to judgment. Friends to see <hi rend="italics">me!</hi> My God! I have sunk from the prime of life into old age in this place, and there is not one to raise his hand above my bed, when I lie dead upon it, and say, ‘It is a blessing he is gone!’”</p><p >The excitement, which had cast an unwonted light over the man's face while he spoke, subsided as he concluded; and, pressing his withered hands together in a hasty and disordered manner, he shuffled from the room.</p><p >“Rides rather rusty,” said Mr. Roker, with a smile. “Ah! they're like the elephants;, they feel it now and then, and it makes 'em wild!”</p><p >Having made this deeply-sympathising remark, Mr. Roker entered upon his arrangements with such expedition, that in a short time the room was furnished with a carpet, six chairs, a table, a sofa bedstead, a tea-kettle, and various small <hi rend="italics">et ceteras,</hi> on hire, at the very reasonable rate of seven-and-twenty shillings and sixpence per week.</p><p >“Now, is there anything more we can do for you?” inquired Mr.
<pb xml:id="p452"/>
Roker, looking round with great satisfaction, and gaily chinking the first week's hire in his closed fist.</p><p >“Why, yes,” said Mr. Pickwick, who had been musing deeply for some time. “Are there any people here who run on errands, and so forth?”</p><p >“Outside, do you mean?” inquired Mr. Roker.</p><p >“Yes; I mean who are able to go outside. Not prisoners.”</p><p >“Yes, there is,” said Roker. “There's an unfortunate devil, who has got a friend on the poor side, that's glad to do anything of that sort. He's been running odd jobs, and that, for the last two months. Shall I send him?”</p><p >“If you please,” rejoined Mr. Pickwick. “Stay;—no. The poor side, you say. I should like to see it;—I'll go to him myself.”</p><p >The poor side of a debtor's prison is, as its name imports, that in which the most miserable and abject class of debtors are confined. A prisoner having declared upon the poor side, pays neither rent nor chummage. His fees, upon entering and leaving the gaol, are reduced in amount, and he becomes entitled to a share of some small quantities of food; to provide which, a few charitable persons have, from time to time, left trifling legacies in their wills. Most of our readers will remember, that, until within a very few years past, there was a kind of iron cage in the wall of the Fleet Prison, within which was posted some man of hungry looks, who, from time to time, rattled a money-box, and exclaimed, in a mournful voice, “Pray, remember the poor debtors; pray, remember the poor debtors.” The receipts of this box, when there were any, were divided among the poor prisoners, and the men on the poor side relieved each other in this degrading office.</p><p >Although this custom has been abolished, and the cage is now boarded up, the miserable and destitute condition of these unhappy persons remains the same. We no longer suffer them to appeal at the prison gates to the charity and compassion of the passers by; but we still leave unblotted in the leaves of our statute book, for the reverence and admiration of succeeding ages, the just and wholesome law which declares that the sturdy felon shall be fed and clothed, and that the penniless debtor shall be left to die of starvation and nakedness. This is no fiction. Not a week passes over our heads but, in every one of our prisons for debt, some of these men must inevitably expire in the slow agonies of want, if they were not relieved by their fellow-prisoners.</p><p >Turning these things in his mind, as he mounted the narrow staircase at the foot of which Roker had left him, Mr. Pickwick gradually worked himself to the boiling-over point; and so excited was he with his reflections on this subject, that he had burst to the room to which he had been directed, before he had any distinct recollection either of the place in which he was, or of the object of his visit.</p><p >The general aspect of the room recalled him to himself at once; but he had no sooner cast his eyes on the figure of a man who was brooding over the dusty fire, than, letting his hat fall on the floor, he stood perfectly fixed and immoveable with astonishment.</p><pb  xml:id="p453"/><p >Yes, in tattered garments, and without a coat; his common calico shirt yellow and in rags; his hair hanging over his face; his features changed with suffering, and pinched with famine,—there sat Mr. Alfred Jingle; his head resting upon his hand, his eyes fixed upon the fire, and his whole appearance denoting misery and dejection!</p><p >Near him, leaning listlessly against the wall, stood a strong-built countryman, flicking with a worn-out hunting-whip the top-boot that adorned his right foot: his left being thrust into an old slipper. Horses, dogs, and drink had brought him there pell-mell. There was a rusty spur on the solitary boot, which he occasionally jerked into the empty air, at the same time giving the boot a smart blow, and muttering some of the sounds by which a sportsman encourages his horse. He was riding, in imagination, some desperate steeple-chace at that moment. Poor wretch! he never rode a match on the swiftest animal in his costly stud, with half the speed at which he had torn along the course that ended in the Fleet.</p><p >On the opposite side of the room an old man was seated on a small wooden box, with his eyes rivetted on the floor, and his face settled into an expression of the deepest and most hopeless despair. A young girl—his little grand-daughter—was hanging about him, endeavouring, with a thousand childish devices, to engage his attention; but the old man neither saw nor heard her. The voice that had been music to him, and the eyes that had been light, fell coldly on his senses. His limbs were shaking with disease, and the palsy had fastened on his mind.</p><p >There were two or three other men in the room, congregated in a little knot, and noisily talking among themselves. There was a lean and haggard woman, too—a prisoner's wife—who was watering, with great solicitude, the wretched stump of a dried-up, withered plant, which, it was plain to see, could never send forth a green leaf again;—too true an emblem, perhaps, of the office she had come there to discharge.</p><p >Such were the objects which presented themselves to Mr. Pickwick's view, as he looked round him in amazement. The noise of some one stumbling hastily into the room roused him. Turning his eyes towards the door, they encountered the new comer; and in him, through all his rags, and dirt, and misery, he recognised the familiar features of Mr. Job Trotter.</p><p >“Mr. Pickwick!” exclaimed Job aloud.</p><p >“Eh?” said Jingle, starting from his seat.</p><p >“Mr.——! So it is—queer place—strange thing—serves me right—very.” And with this Mr. Jingle thrust his hands into the place where his trousers pocket used to be, and, dropping his chin upon his breast, sunk back into his chair.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick was affected; the two men looked so very miserable The sharp involuntary glance Jingle had cast at a small piece of raw loin of mutton, which Job had brought in with him, said more of their reduced state than two hours' explanation could have done. He looked mildly at Jingle, and said:—</p><pb  xml:id="p454"/><p >“I should like to speak to you in private. Will you step out for an instant?”</p><p >“Certainly,” said Jingle, rising hastily. “Can't step far—no danger of over-walking yourself here—spike park—grounds pretty—romantic, but not extensive—open for public inspection—family always in town—housekeeper desperately careful—very.”</p><p >“You have forgotten your coat,” said Mr. Pickwick, as they walked out to the staircase, and closed the door after them.</p><p >“Eh?” said Jingle. “Spout—dear relation—uncle Tom—couldn't help it—must eat, you know. Wants of nature—and all that.”</p><p >“What do you mean?”</p><p >“Gone, my dear Sir—last coat—can't help it. Lived on a pair of boots—whole fortnight. Silk umbrella—ivory handle—week—fact—honour—ask Job—knows it.”</p><p >“Lived for three weeks upon a pair of boots and a silk umbrella with an ivory handle!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, who had only heard of such things in shipwrecks, or read of them in Constable's Miscellany.</p><p >“True,” said Jingle, nodding his head. “Pawnbroker's shop—duplicates here—small sums—mere nothing—all rascals.”</p><p >“Oh,” said Mr. Pickwick, much relieved by this explanation; “I understand you. You have pawned your wardrobe.”</p><p >“Every thing—Job's too—all shirts gone—never mind—saves washing. Nothing soon—lie in bed—starve—die—Inquest—little bonehouse—poor prisoner—common necessaries—hush it up—gentlemen of the jury—warden's tradesmen—keep it snug—natural death—coroner's order—workhouse funeral—serve him right—all over—drop the curtain.”</p><p >Jingle delivered this singular summary of his prospects in life with his accustomed volubility, and with various twitches of the countenance to counterfeit smiles. Mr. Pickwick easily perceived that his recklessness was assumed, and looking him full, but not unkindly, in the face, saw that his eyes were moist with tears.</p><p >“Good fellow,” said Jingle, pressing his hand, and turning his head away. “Ungrateful dog—boyish to cry—can't help it—bad fever—weak—ill—hungry. Deserved it all; but suffered much—very.” Wholly unable to keep up appearances any longer, and perhaps rendered worse by the effort he had made, the dejected stroller sat down on the stairs, and, covering his face with his hands, sobbed like a child.</p><p >“Come, come,” said Mr. Pickwick, with considerable emotion, “we'll see what can be done when I know all about the matter. Here, Job; where is that fellow?”</p><p >“Here, Sir,” replied Job, presenting himself on the staircase. We have described him, by-the-bye, as having deeply-sunken eyes in the best of times; in his present state of want and distress, he looked as if those features had gone out of town altogether.</p><p >“Here, Sir,” said Job.</p><p >“Come here, Sir,” said Mr. Pickwick, trying to look stern, with four large tears running down his waistcoat. “Take that, Sir.”</p><p >Take what? In the ordinary acceptation of such language, it should have been a blow. As the world runs, it ought to have been a sound,
<pb xml:id="p455"/>
hearty cuff; for Mr. Pickwick had been duped, deceived, and wronged by the destitute outcast who was now wholly in his power. Must we tell the truth? It was something from Mr. Pickwick's waistcoat-pocket, which chinked as it was given into Job's hand: and the giving which, somehow or other imparted a sparkle to the eye, and a swelling to the heart of our excellent old friend, as he hurried away.</p><p >Sam had returned when Mr. Pickwick reached his own room, and was inspecting the arrangements that had been made for his comfort, with a kind of grim satisfaction which was very pleasant to look upon. Having a decided objection to his master's being there at all, Mr. Weller appeared to consider it a high moral duty not to appear too much pleased with anything that was done, said, suggested, or proposed.</p><p >“Well, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Well, Sir,” replied Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Pretty comfortable now, eh, Sam?”</p><p >“Pretty vell, Sir,” responded Sam, looking round him in a disparaging manner.</p><p >“Have you seen Mr. Tupman and our other friends?”</p><p >“Yes, I <hi rend="italics">have</hi> seen 'em, Sir, and they're a comin' to-morrow, and wos wery much surprised to hear they warn't to come to-day,” replied Sam.</p><p >“You have brought the things I wanted?”</p><p >Mr. Weller in reply pointed to various packages which he had arranged as neatly as he could, in a corner of the room.</p><p >“Very well, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, after a little hesitation; “listen to what I am going to say, Sam.”</p><p >“Cert'nly, Sir,” rejoined Mr. Weller, “fire avay, Sir.”</p><p >“I have felt from the first, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, with much solemnity, “that this is not the place to bring a young man to.”</p><p >“Nor an old 'un neither, Sir,” observed Mr. Weller.</p><p >“You're quite right, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick; “but old men may come here through their own heedlessness and unsuspicion, and young men may be brought here by the selfishness of those they serve. It is better for those young men, in every point of view, that they should not remain here. Do you understand me, Sam?”</p><p >“Vy no, Sir, I do not,” replied Mr. Weller, doggedly.</p><p >“Try, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Vell, Sir,” rejoined Sam, after a short pause, “I think I see your drift; and if I do see your drift, it's my ‘pinion that you're a comin’ it a great deal too strong, as the mail-coachman said to the snow storm, ven it overtook him.”</p><p >“I see you comprehend me, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick. “Independently of my wish that you should not be idling about a place like this for years to come, I feel that for a debtor in the Fleet to be attended by his man-servant is a monstrous absurdity.—Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, “for a time you must leave me.”</p><p >“Oh, for a time, eh, Sir?” rejoined Mr. Weller, rather sarcastically.</p><p >“Yes, for the time that I remain here,” said Mr. Pickwick. “Your wages I shall continue to pay. Any one of my three friends will be happy to take you, were it only out of respect to me. And if I ever do
<pb xml:id="p456"/>
leave this place, Sam,” added Mr. Pickwick, with assumed cheerfulness—“if I do, I pledge you my word that you shall return to me instantly.”</p><p >“Now I'll tell you wot it is, Sir,” said Mr. Weller, in a grave and solemn voice, “This here sort o' thing von't do at all, so don't let's hear no more about it.”</p><p >“I am serious, and resolved, Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“You air, air you, Sir?” inquired Mr. Weller, firmly. “Wery good, Sir: then so am I.”</p><p >Thus speaking, Mr. Weller fixed his hat on his head with great precision, and abruptly left the room.</p><p >“Sam,” said Mr. Pickwick, calling after him, “Sam. Here.”</p><p >But the long gallery ceased to re-echo the sound of footsteps. Sam Weller was gone.</p></div><div type="chapter"><head >CHAPTER XLII.</head><head >
SHOWING HOW MR. SAMUEL WELLER GOT INTO DIFFICULTIES.
</head><p >IN a lofty room, badly lighted and worse ventilated, situate in Portugal-street, Lincoln's Inn-fields, there sit nearly the whole year round, one, two, three, or four gentlemen in wigs, as the case may be, with little writing desks before them, constructed after the fashion of those used by the judges of the land, barring the French polish; a box of barristers on their right hand; an inclosure of insolvent debtors on their left; and an inclined plane of most especially dirty faces in their front. These gentlemen are the Commissioners of the Insolvent Court, and the place in which they sit is the Insolvent Court itself.</p><p >It is, and has been, time out of mind, the remarkable fate of this Court to be somehow or other held and understood by the general consent of all the destitute shabby-genteel people in London, as their common resort, and place of daily refuge. It is always full. The steams of beer and spirits perpetually ascend to the ceiling, and, being condensed by the heat, roll down the walls like rain: there are more old suits of clothes in it at one time, than will be offered for sale in all Houndsditch in a twelvemonth; and more unwashed skins and grizzly beards than all the pumps and shaving-shops between Tyburn and Whitechapel could render decent between sunrise and sunset.</p><p >It must not be supposed that any of these people have the least shadow of business in, or the remotest connexion with, the place they so indefatigably attend. If they had, it would be no matter of surprise, and the singularity of the thing would cease at once. Some of them sleep during the greater part of the sitting; others carry small portable dinners wrapped in pocket handkerchiefs or sticking out of their wornout pockets, and munch and listen with equal relish; but no one among them was ever known to have the slightest personal interest in any
<pb xml:id="p457"/>
case that was ever brought forward. Whatever they do, there they sit from the first moment to the last. When it is heavy rainy weather, they all come in wet through; and at such times the vapours of the Court are like those of a fungus-pit.</p><p >A casual visitor might suppose this place to be a temple dedicated to the Genius of Seediness. There is not a messenger or process-server attached to it, who wears a coat that was made for him; not a tolerably fresh, or wholesome-looking man in the whole establishment, except a little white-headed apple-faced tipstaff, and even he, like an ill-conditioned cherry preserved in brandy, seems to have artificially dried and withered up into a state of preservation, to which he can lay no natural claim. The very barristers' wigs are ill-powdered, and their curls lack crispness.</p><p >But the attorneys, who sit at a large bare table below the Commissioners, are, after all, the greatest curiosities. The professional establishment of the more opulent of these gentlemen, consists of a blue bag and a boy: generally a youth of the Jewish persuasion. They have no fixed offices, their legal business being transacted in the parlours of public houses, or the yards of prisons, whither they repair in crowds, and canvass for customers after the manner of omnibus cads. They are of a greasy and mildewed appearance; and if they can be said to have any vices at all, perhaps drinking and cheating are the most conspicuous among them. Their residences are usually on the outskirts of “the Rules,” chiefly lying within a circle of one mile from the obelisk in St. George's Fields. Their looks are not prepossessing, and their manners are peculiar.</p><p >Mr. Solomon Pell, one of this learned body, was a fat flabby pale man, in a surtout which looked green one minute, and brown the next, with a velvet collar of the same cameleon tints. His forehead was narrow, his face wide, his head large, and his nose all on one side, as if Nature, indignant with the propensities she observed in him in his birth, had given it an angry tweak which it had never recovered. Being short-necked and asthmatic, however, he respired principally through this feature; so, perhaps, what it wanted in ornament it made up in usefulness.</p><p >“I'm sure to bring him through it,” said Mr. Pell.</p><p >“Are you though?” replied the person to whom the assurance was pledged.</p><p >“Certain sure,” replied Pell; “but if he'd gone to any irregular practitioner, mind you, I wouldn't have answered for the consequences.”</p><p >“Ah!” said the other, with open mouth.</p><p >“No, that I wouldn't,” said Mr. Pell; and he pursed up his lips, frowned, and shook his head mysteriously.</p><p >Now the place where this discourse occurred, was the public-house just opposite to the Insolvent Court; and the person with whom it was held was no other than the elder Mr. Weller, who had come there to comfort and console a friend, whose petition to be discharged under the act was to be that day heard, and whose attorney he was at that moment consulting.</p><p >“And vere is George?” inquired the old gentleman.</p><pb  xml:id="p458"/><p >Mr. Pell jerked his head in the direction of a back parlour, whither Mr. Weller at once repairing, was immediately greeted in the warmest and most flattering manner by some half-dozen of his professional brethren, in token of their gratification at his arrival. The insolvent gentleman, who had contracted a speculative but imprudent passion for horsing long stages, which had led to his present embarrassments, looked extremely well, and was soothing the excitement of his feelings with shrimps and porter.</p><p >The salutation between Mr. Weller and his friends was strictly confined to the freemasonry of the craft; consisting of a jerking round of the right wrist, and a tossing of the little finger into the air at the same time. We once knew two famous coachmen (they are dead now, poor fellows) who were twins, and between whom an unaffected and devoted attachment existed. They passed each other on the Dover road every day, for twenty-four years, never exchanging any other greeting than this; and yet, when one died, the other pined away, and soon afterwards followed him!</p><p >“Vell, George,” said Mr. Weller, senior, taking off his upper coat, and seating himself with his accustomed gravity. “How is it? All right behind, and full inside?”</p><p >“All right, old feller,” replied the embarrassed gentlemen.</p><p >“Is the grey mare made over to any body?” inquired Mr. Weller, anxiously.</p><p >George nodded in the affirmative.</p><p >“Vell, that's all right,” said Mr. Weller. “Coach taken care on, also?”</p><p >“Con-signed in a safe quarter,” replied George, wringing the heads off half-a-dozen shrimps, and swallowing them without any more ado.</p><p >“Wery good, wery good,” said Mr. Weller. “Alvays see to the drag ven you go down hill. Is the vay-bill all clear and straight for'erd?”</p><p >“The schedule, Sir,” said Pell, guessing at Mr. Weller's meaning, “the schedule is as plain and satisfactory as pen and ink can make it.”</p><p >Mr. Weller nodded in a manner which bespoke his inward approval of these arrangements; and then, turning to Mr. Pell, said, pointing to his friend George,—</p><p >“Ven do you take his cloths off?”</p><p >“Why,” replied Mr. Pell, “he stands third on the opposed list, and I should think it would be his turn in about half an hour. I told my clerk to come over and tell us when there was a chance.”</p><p >Mr. Weller surveyed the attorney from head to foot with great admiration, and said emphatically,—</p><p >“And what'll you take, Sir?”</p><p >“Why, really,” replied Mr. Pell, “you're very—. Upon my word and honour, I'm not in the habit of—. It's so very early in the morning, that, actually, I am almost—. Well, you may bring me three penn'orth of rum, my dear.”</p><p >The officiating damsel, who had anticipated the order before it was given, set the glass of spirits before Pell, and retired.</p><pb  xml:id="p459"/><p >“Gentlemen,” said Mr. Pell, looking round upon the company, “Success to your friend. I don't like to boast, gentlemen; it's not my way; but I can't help saying, that, if your friend hadn't been fortunate enough to fall into hands that—but I won't say what I was going to say. Gentlemen, my service to you.” Having emptied the glass in a twinkling, Mr. Pell smacked his lips, and looked complacently round on the assembled coachmen, who evidently regarded him as a species of divinity.</p><p >“Let me see,” said the legal authority—“What was I a-saying, gentlemen?”</p><p >“I think you was remarkin' as you wouldn't have no objection to another o' the same, Sir,” said Mr. Weller, with grave facetiousness.</p><p >“Ha, ha!” laughed Mr. Pell. “Not bad, not bad. A professional man, too! At this time of the morning it would be rather too good a—. Well, I don't know, my dear—you <hi rend="italics">may</hi> do that again, if you please. Hem!”</p><p >This last sound was a solemn and dignified cough, in which Mr. Pell, observing an indecent tendency to mirth in some of his auditors, considered it due to himself to indulge.</p><p >“The late Lord Chancellor, gentlemen, was very fond of me,” said Mr. Pell.</p><p >“And wery creditable in him, too,” interposed Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Hear, hear,” assented Mr. Pell's client. “Why shouldn't he be?”</p><p >“Ah—why, indeed!” said a very red-faced man, who had said nothing yet, and who looked extremely unlikely to say anything more. “Why shouldn't he?”</p><p >A murmur of assent ran through the company.</p><p >“I remember, gentlemen,” said Mr. Pell, “dining with him on one occasion;—there was only us two, but every thing as splendid as if twenty people had been expected; the great seal on a dumb-waiter at his right hand, and a man in a bag-wig and suit of armour guarding the mace with a drawn sword and silk stockings, which is perpetually done, gentlemen, night and day; when he said, ‘Pell,’ he said; ‘no false delicacy, Pell. You're a man of talent; you can get any body through the Insolvent Court, Pell; and your country should be proud of you.’ Those were his very words.—‘My Lord,’ I said, ‘you flatter me.’—‘Pell,’ he said, ‘if I do, I'm damned.‘ ”</p><p >“Did he say that?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“He did,” replied Pell.</p><p >“Vell, then,” said Mr. Weller, “I say Parliament ought to ha' taken it up; and if he'd been a poor man, they would ha' done it.”</p><p >“But, my dear friend,” argued Mr. Pell, “it was in confidence.”</p><p >“In what?” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“In confidence.”</p><p >“Oh! wery good,” replied Mr. Weller, after a little reflection. “If he damned his-self in confidence, o' course that was another thing.”</p><p >“Of course it was,” said Mr. Pell. “The distinction's obvious, you will perceive.”</p><p >“Alters the case entirely,” said Mr. Weller. “Go on, Sir.”</p><pb  xml:id="p460"/><p >“No; I will not go on, Sir,” said Mr. Pell, in a low and serious tone. “You have reminded me, Sir, that this conversation was private—private and confidential, gentlemen. Gentlemen, I am a professional man. It may be that I am a good deal looked up to, in my profession—it may be that I am not. Most people know. I say nothing. Observations have already been made, in this room, injurious to the reputation of my noble friend. You will excuse me, gentlemen; I was imprudent. I feel that I have no right to mention this matter without his concurrence. Thank you, Sir; thank you.” Thus delivering himself, Mr. Pell thrust his hands into his pockets, and, frowning grimly around, rattled three-halfpence with terrible determination.</p><p >This virtuous resolution had scarcely been formed, when the boy and the blue bag, who were inseparable companions, rushed violently into the room, and said (at least the boy did; for the blue bag took no part in the announcement) that the case was coming on directly. The intelligence was no sooner received than the whole party hurried across the street, and began to fight their way into Court—a preparatory ceremony, which has been calculated to occupy, in ordinary cases, from twenty-five minutes to thirty.</p><p >Mr. Weller being stout, cast himself at once into the crowd, with the desperate hope of ultimately turning up in some place which would suit him. His success was not quite equal to his expectations, for having neglected to take his hat off, it was knocked over his eyes by some unseen person, upon whose toes he had alighted with considerable force. Apparently this individual regretted his impetuosity immediately afterwards, for, muttering an indistinct exclamation of surprise, he dragged the old man out into the hall, and, after a violent struggle, released his head and face.</p><p >“Samivel!” exclaimed Mr. Weller, when he was thus enabled to behold his rescuer.</p><p >Sam nodded.</p><p >“You're a dutiful and affectionate little boy, you are, ain't you?” said Mr. Weller, “to come a bonnetin' your father in his old age?”</p><p >“How should I know who you wos?” responded the son. “Do you s'pose I wos to tell you by the weight o' your foot?”</p><p >“Vell, that's wery true, Sammy,” replied Mr. Weller, mollified at once; “but wot are you a doin' on here? Your gov'nor can't do no good here, Sammy. They von't pass that werdict; they von't pass it, Sammy.” And Mr. Weller shook his head with legal solemnity.</p><p >“Wot a perwerse old file it is!” exclaimed Sam, “alvays a goin' on about werdicts and alleybis, and that. Who said anything about the werdict?”</p><p >Mr. Weller made no reply, but once more shook his head most learnedly.</p><p >“Leave off rattlin' that 'ere nob o' yourn, if you don't want it to come off the springs altogether,” said Sam impatiently, “and behave reasonable. I vent all the vay down to the Markis o' Granby arter you last night.”</p><pb  xml:id="p461"/><p >“Did you see the Marchionness o' Granby, Sammy?” inquired Mr. Weller, with a sigh.</p><p >“Yes, I did,” replied Sam.</p><p >“How wos the dear creetur lookin'?”</p><p >“Wery queer,” said Sam. “I think she's a injurin' herself gradivally vith too much o' that 'ere pine-apple rum, and other strong medicines o' the same natur.”</p><p >“You don't mean that, Sammy?” said the senior, earnestly.</p><p >“I do, indeed,” replied the junior.</p><p >Mr. Weller seized his son's hand, clasped it, and let it fall. There was an expression on his countenance in doing so—not of dismay or apprehension, but partaking more of the sweet and gentle character of hope. A gleam of resignation, and even of cheerfulness, passed over his face too, as he slowly said—“I ain't quite certain, Sammy; I wouldn't like to say I wos altogether positive, in case of any subsekent disappintment, but I rayther think, my boy—I rayther think that the shepherd's got the liver complaint!”</p><p >“Does he look bad?” inquired Sam.</p><p >“He's uncommon pale,” replied his father, “ 'cept about the nose, vich is redder than ever. His appetite is wery so-so, but he imbibes wunderful.”</p><p >Some thoughts of the rum appeared to obtrude themselves on Mr. Weller's mind as he said this, for he looked gloomy and thoughtful; but very shortly recovered, as was testified by a perfect alphabet of winks, in which he was only wont to indulge when particularly pleased.</p><p >“Vell, now,” said Sam, “about my affair. Just open them ears o' yourn, and don't say nothin' till I've done.” With this brief preface, Sam related, as succinctly as he could, the last memorable conversation he had had with Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“Stop there by himself, poor creetur!” exclaimed the elder Mr. Weller, “without nobody to take his part! It can't be done, Samivel, it can't be done.”</p><p >“O' course it can't,” asserted Sam; “I know'd that afore I came.”</p><p >“Vy, they'll eat him up alive, Sammy,” exclaimed Mr. Weller.</p><p >Sam nodded his concurrence in the opinion.</p><p >“He goes in rayther raw, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller metaphorically, “and he'll come out done so ex-ceedin' brown, that his most formiliar friends won't know him. Roast pigeon's nothin' to it, Sammy.”</p><p >Again Sam Weller nodded.</p><p >“It oughtn't to be, Samivel,” said Mr. Weller, gravely.</p><p >“It mustn't be,” said Sam.</p><p >“Cert'nly not,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Vell now,” said Sam, “you've been a prophecyin' avay wery fine, like a red-faced Nixon, as the sixpenny books gives picters on.”</p><p >“Who wos he, Sammy?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Never mind who he was,” retorted Sam; “he warn't a coachman, that's enough for you.”</p><p >“I know'd a ostler o' that name,” said Mr. Weller, musing.</p><p >“It warn't him,” said Sam. “This here gen'lm'n was a prophet.”</p><pb  xml:id="p462"/><p >“Wot's a prophet?” inquired Mr. Weller, looking sternly on his son.</p><p >“Vy, a man as tells what's a goin' to happen,” replied Sam.</p><p >“I wish I'd know'd him, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller. “P'raps he might ha' throw'd a small light on that 'ere liver complaint as we wos a speakin' on just now. Hows'ever, if he's dead, and ain't left the bisness to nobody, there's an end on it. Go on, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller, with a sigh.</p><p >“Vell,” said Sam, “you're been a prophecyin' avay about wot'll happen to the gov'nor if he's left alone. Don't you see any vay o'takin' care on him?”</p><p >“No, I don't, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller, with a reflective visage.</p><p >“No vay at all?” inquired Sam.</p><p >“No vay,” said Mr. Weller, “unless”—and a gleam of intelligence lighted up his countenance as he sunk his voice to a whisper, and applied his mouth to the ear of his offspring—“unless it is getting him out in a turn-up bedstead, unbeknown to the turnkeys, Sammy, or dressin' him up like an old'ooman vith a green wail.”</p><p >Sam Weller received both of these suggestions with unexpected contempt, and again propounded his question.</p><p >“No,” said the old gentleman; “if he von't let you stop there, I see no vay at all. Its no thoroughfare, Sammy—no thoroughfare.”</p><p >“Well, then, I'll tell you wot it is,” said Sam, “I'll trouble you for the loan of five-and-tventy pound.”</p><p >“Wot good'ull that do?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Never mind,” replied Sam. “P'raps you may ask for it five minits artervards; p'raps I may say I von't pay, and cut up rough. You von't think o' arrestin' your own son for the money, and sendin' him off to the Fleet will you, you unnat'ral wagabond?”</p><p >At this reply of Sam's, the father and son exchanged a complete code of sly telegraphic nods and gestures, after which, the elder Mr. Weller sat himself down on a stone step, and laughed till he was purple.</p><p >“Wot a old image it is!” exclaimed Sam, indignant at this loss of time. “What are you a settin' down there for, con-wertin' your face into a street-door knocker, ven there's so much to be done. Vere's the money?”</p><p >“In the boot, Sammy, in the boot,” replied Mr. Weller, composing his features. “Hold my hat, Sammy.”</p><p >Having divested himself of this incumbrance, Mr. Weller gave his body a sudden wrench to one side, and, by a dexterous twist, contrived to get his right hand into a most capacious pocket, from whence, after a great deal of panting and exertion, he extricated a pocket-book of the large octavo size, fastened by a huge leather strap. From thence he drew forth a couple of whip-lashes, three or four buckles, a little samplebag of corn, and finally a small roll of very dirty bank-notes, from which he selected the required amount, which he handed over to Sam.</p><p >“And now, Sammy,” said the old gentleman, when the whip-lashes, and the buckles, and the sample, had been all put back, and the book once more deposited at the bottom of the same pocket, “Now, Sammy, I know a gen'lm'n here, as'll do the rest o' the bisness for us, in no time
<pb xml:id="p463"/>
—a limb o' the law, Sammy, as has got brains like the frogs, dispersed all over his body, and reachin' to the wery tips of his fingers; a friend of the Lord Chancellorship's, Sammy, who'd only have to tell him what he wanted, and he'd lock you up for life, if that wos all.”</p><p >“I say,” said Sam, “none o' that.”</p><p >“None o' wot?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Vy, none o' them unconstitootional ways o' doin' it,” retorted Sam.</p><p >“The have-his-carcase, next to the perpetual motion, is vun o' the blessedest things as wos ever made. I've read that 'ere in the newspapers wery of'en.”</p><p >“Well, wot's that got to do vith it?” inquired Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Just this here,” said Sam, “that I'll patronise the inwention, and go in, that vay. No visperin's to the Chancellorship—I don't like the notion. It mayn't be altogether safe, vith reference to the gettin' out again.”</p><p >Deferring to his son's feeling upon this point, Mr. Weller at once sought the erudite Solomon Pell, and acquainted him with his desire to issue a writ instantly for the sum of twenty-five pounds, and costs of process, to be executed without delay upon the body of one Samuel Weller; the charges thereby incurred to be paid in advance to Solomon Pell.</p><p >The attorney was in high glee, for the embarrassed coach-horser was ordered to be discharged forthwith. He highly approved of Sam's attachment to his master; declared that it strongly reminded him of his own feelings of devotion to his friend, the Chancellor; and at once led the elder Mr. Weller down to the Temple, to swear the affidavit of debt, which the boy, with the assistance of the blue bag, had drawn up on the spot.</p><p >Meanwhile Sam, having been formally introduced to the whitewashed gentleman and his friends, as the offspring of Mr. Weller, of the Belle Sauvage, was treated with marked distinction, and invited to regale himself with them in honour of the occasion—an invitation which he was by no means backward in accepting.</p><p >The mirth of gentlemen of this class is of a grave and quiet character usually; but the present instance was one of peculiar festivity, and they relaxed in proportion. After some rather tumultuous toasting of the Chief Commissioner and Mr. Solomon Pell, who had that day displayed such transcendant abilities, a mottled-faced gentleman in a blue shawl proposed that somebody should sing a song. The obvious suggestion was, that the mottled-faced gentleman, being anxious for a song, should sing it himself; but this the mottled-faced gentleman sturdily, and somewhat offensively, declined to do; upon which, as is not unusual in such cases, a rather angry colloquy ensued.</p><p >“Gentlemen, said the coach-horser, “rather than disturb harmony of this delightful occasion, perhaps Mr. Samuel Weller will oblige the company.”</p><p >“Raly, gentlemen,” said Sam, “I'm not wery much in the habit o' singin' vithout the instrument; but anythin' for a quiet life, as the man said ven he took the sitivation at the light-house.”</p><pb  xml:id="p464"/><p >With this prelude, Mr. Samuel Weller burst at once into the following wild and beautiful legend, which, under the impression that it is not generally known, we take the liberty of quoting. We would beg to call particular attention to the monosyllable at the end of the second and fourth lines, which not only enables the singer to take breath at those points, but greatly assists the metre.</p><lg  type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><head>Romance.</head><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><head>I.</head><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Bold Turpin vunce, on Hounslow Heath,</l><l part="N">His bold mare Bess bestrode—er;</l><l part="N">Ven there he see'd the Bishop's coach</l><l part="N">A-comin' along the road—er.</l><l part="N">So he gallops close to the orse's legs,</l><l part="N">And he claps his head vithin;</l><l part="N">And the Bishop says, “Sure as eggs is eggs,</l><l part="N">This here's the bold Turpin!”</l><l part="N">(CHORUS.) <hi rend="italics">And the Bishop says, “Sure as eggs is eggs,</hi></l><l part="N"><hi rend="italics">This here's the bold Turpin!”</hi></l></lg></lg><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><head>II.</head><lg type="song" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><l part="N">Says Turpin, “You shall eat your words,</l><l part="N">With a sarse of leaden b<hi rend="italics">u</hi>l—let;”</l><l part="N">So he puts a pistol to his mouth,</l><l part="N">And he fires it down his gul—let,</l><l part="N">The coachman, he not likin' the job,</l><l part="N">Set off at a full gal-lop,</l><l part="N">But Dick put a couple of balls in his nob,</l><l part="N">And perwailed on him to stop.</l><l part="N">(CHORUS <hi rend="italics">sarcastically.</hi>) <hi rend="italics">But Dick put a couple of balls in his nob,</hi></l><l part="N"><hi rend="italics">And perwailed on him to stop.</hi></l></lg></lg></lg><p >“I maintain that that 'ere song's personal to the cloth,” said the mottled-faced gentleman, interrupting it at this point. “I demand the name o' that coachman.”</p><p >“Nobody know'd,” replied Sam. “He hadn't got his card in his pocket.”</p><p >“I object to the introduction o' politics,” said the mottled-faced gentleman. “I submit that, in the present company, that 'ere song's political; and, wot's much the same, that it ain't true. I say that that coachman did <hi rend="italics">not</hi> run avay; but that he died game—game as pheasants; and I won't hear nothin' said to the contrairey.”</p><p >As the mottled-faced gentleman spoke with great energy and determination, and as the opinions of the company seemed divided on the subject, it threatened to give rise to fresh alteraction, when Mr. Weller and Mr. Pell most opportunely arrived.</p><p >“All right, Sammy,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“The officer will be here at four o'clock,” said Mr. Pell. “I suppose you won't run away meanwhile—eh? Ha! ha!”</p><pb  xml:id="p465"/><p >“P'raps my cruel pa 'ull relent afore that,” replied Sam, with a broad grin.</p><p >“Not I,” said the elder Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Do,” said Sam.</p><p >“Not on no account,” replied the inexorable creditor.</p><p >“I'll give bills for the amount at sixpence a month,” said Sam.</p><p >“I won't take 'em,” said Mr. Weller.</p><p >“Ha, ha, ha! very good, very good,” said Mr. Solomon Pell, who was making out his little bill of costs; “a very amusing incident indeed. Benjamin, copy that,” and Mr. Pell smiled again, as he called Mr. Weller's attention to the amount.</p><p >“Thank you, thank you,” said the professional gentleman, taking up another of the greasy notes as Mr. Weller took it from the pocket-book. “Three ten and one ten is five. Much obliged to you, Mr. Weller. Your son is a most deserving young man, very much so indeed, Sir. It's a very pleasant trait in a young man's character—very much so,” added Mr. Pell, smiling smoothly round, as he buttoned up the money.</p><p >“Wot a game it is!” said the elder Mr. Weller, with a chuckle. “A reg'lar prodigy son!”</p><p >“Prodigal—prodigal son, Sir,” suggested Mr. Pell, mildly.</p><p >“Never mind, Sir,” said Mr. Weller, with dignity. “I know wot's o'clock, Sir. Ven I don't, I'll ask you, Sir.”</p><p >By the time the officer arrived, Sam had made himself so extremely popular, that the congregated gentlemen determined to see him to prison in a body. So off they set; the plaintiff and defendant walking arm-in-arm, the officer in front, and eight stout coachmen bringing up the rear. At Sergeants' Inn Coffee-house the whole party halted to refresh; and, the legal arrangements being completed, the procession moved on again.</p><p >Some little commotion was occasioned in Fleet Street by the pleasantry of the eight gentlemen in the flank, who persevered in walking four abreast; and it was also found necessary to leave the mottled-faced gentleman behind, to fight a ticket-porter, it being arranged that his friends should call for him as they came back. Nothing but these little incidents occurred on the way. When they reached the gate of the Fleet, the cavalcade, taking the time from the plaintiff, gave three tremendous cheers for the defendant; and, after having shaken hands all round, left him.</p><p >Sam having been formally delivered into the warden's custody, to the intense astonishment of Roker, and to the evident emotion of even the phlegmatic Neddy, passed at once into the prison, walked straight to his master's room, and knocked at the door.</p><p >“Come in,” said Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >Sam appeared, pulled off his hat, and smiled.</p><p >“Ah, Sam, my good lad,” said Mr. Pickwick, evidently delighted to see his humble friend again; “I had no intention of hurting your feelings yesterday, my faithful fellow, by what I said. Put down your hat, Sam, and let me explain my meaning a little more at length.”</p><p >“Won't presently do, Sir?” inquired Sam.</p><pb  xml:id="p466"/><p >“Certainly,” said Mr. Pickwick; “but why not now?”</p><p >“I'd rayther not now, Sir,” rejoined Sam.</p><p >“Why?” inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p><p >“'Cause,” said Sam, hesitating.</p><p >“Because of what?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, alarmed at his follower's manner. “Speak out, Sam.”</p><p >“'Cause,” rejoined Sam; “'cause I've got a little bisness as I want to do.”</p><p >“What business?” inquired Mr. Pickwick, surprised at Sam's confused manner.</p><p >“Nothin' partickler, Sir,” replied Sam.</p><p >“Oh, if it's nothing particular,” said Mr. Pickwick, with a smile, “you can speak with me first.”</p><p >“I think I'd better see arter it at once,” said Sam, still hesitating.</p><p >Mr. Pickwick looked amazed, but said nothing.</p><p >“The fact is—” said Sam, stopping short.</p><p >“Well!” said Mr. Pickwick. “Speak out, Sam.”</p><p >“Why, the fact is,” said Sam, with a desperate effort, “P'raps I'd better see arter my bed afore I do anythin' else.”</p><p >“<hi rend="italics">Your bed!”</hi> exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, in astonishment.</p><p >“Yes, my bed, Sir,” replied Sam. “I'm a prisoner. I was arrested this here wery arternoon for debt.”</p><p >“You arrested for debt!” exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, sinking into a chair.</p><p >“Yes, for debt, Sir,” replied Sam; “and the man as put me in 'ull never let me out, till you go yourself.”</p><p >“Bless my heart and soul!” ejaculated Mr. Pickwick. “What do you mean?”</p><p >“Wot I say, Sir,” rejoined Sam. “If it's forty year to come, I shall be a pris'ner, and I'm very glad on it; and if it had been Newgate, it vould ha' been just the same. Now the murder's out, and, damme, there's an end on it.”</p><p >With these words, which he repeated with great emphasis and violence, Sam Weller dashed his hat upon the ground, in a most unusual state of excitement; and then, folding his arms, looked firmly and fixedly in his master's face.</p></div></div></body><back><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1a"/><opener >ESTABLISHED 1820.</opener><head >JOHN JAMES RIPPON'S <lb/> FURNISHING IRONMONGERY WAREHOUSES,</head><p >WELLS STREET, OXFORD STREET, LONDON.</p><p >CATALOGUE of ARTICLES, which, if purchased for Town, must be paid for on delivery; if for the Country, or for Exportation, the money must be remitted, postage free, with the order. On any other terms JOHN JAMES RIPPON respectfully declines doing business at the Prices herein named.</p><p >The Frequent ROBBERIES of PLATE <lb/> Have induced JOHN JAMES RIPPON to manufacture BRITISH PLATE of such a superior quality, that it requires the strictest scrutiny to distinguish it from silver, than which it is much more durable; it improves with use, and is warranted to stand the test of aquafortis. The prices will be found about one-half those usually charged.</p><div type="section"><head >BRITISH PLATE.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Table Spoons &amp; Forks, per doz.</cell><cell>£0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Table Spoons &amp; Forks, very strong</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Dessert Spoons and Forks</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Dessert Spoons and Forks, very strong</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Tea Spoons</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Tea Spoons, very strong</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Gravy Spoons, each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Salt and Mustard Spoons</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Salt and Mustard, with gilt bowls</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Sauce Ladles</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Soup Ladles</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Fish Knives</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Butter Knives</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Sugar Bows, per pair</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Fiddle-handle Sugar Bows, very strong</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Ivory handle Fish Knives, each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Ivory handle Butter Knives</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Pearl handle Butter Knives</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Cruet Frames, with 5 rich cut glasses, shell mountings, and feet, each</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Cruet, Frames, with 5 rich cut glasses, 7 glasses</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Liquor Frames, with 3 richly cut glasses</cell><cell>£4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Round Waiters, with rich shell mountings and feet, centre elegantly chased, 10 in. diameter</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Round Waiters, with rich shell mountings and feet, centre elegantly chased, 12 in. diameter</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Round Waiters, with rich shell mountings and feet, centre elegantly chased, 16 in. diameter</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table Candlesticks, 9 inches high, per pair</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table Candlesticks, with gadroon mountings, 8 inches high</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table with gadroon mountings, 10 inches high</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table, with shell mountings, 8 inches high</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table, with shell mountings, 10 inches high</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Table, Antique Silver Pattern, 10 inches high</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Chamber Candlesticks, with Snuffers and Extinguisher, and gadroon mountings, each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Snuffers, per pair from 5s. 6d. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Snuffer Trays, with gadroon mountings each</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Snuffer Trays, with shell with gadroon mountings &amp; richly chased centres, 10s. to</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Skewers per, inch</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell></row></table>
</p><p >CAUTION.—The unprecedented demand which JOHN JAMES RIPPON has had for this Metal has induced others to use the name of British Plate to an inferior composition; but the genuine improved British Plate can only be obtained at the Manufactory, Wells-street, Oxford-street.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Superior Table Cutlery.</head><p >
<table><row><cell><hi rend="italics">Every Knife and Fork warranted Steel, and exchanged if not found good.</hi></cell><cell>Table Knives, per doz.</cell><cell>Table Forks, per doz.</cell><cell>Dessert Knives, per doz.</cell><cell>Dessert Forks, per doz.</cell><cell>Carvers, per pair.</cell><cell>The set of 50 pieces.</cell></row><row><cell>3½-inch Octagon Ivory Handles, with Rimmed Shoulders</cell><cell>14s. </cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>7s.</cell><cell> 0d.</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell> 0d.</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell> 0d.</cell><cell>4s.</cell><cell> 6d.</cell><cell>£2 </cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell> 0d.</cell></row><row><cell>The same size to balance</cell><cell>16</cell><cell> 0</cell><cell>8 </cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14 </cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell> 0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>3¾-inch Octagon Ivory Handles, with Rimmed Shoulders</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The same size to balance</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The same, with Waterloo Balance Shoulders</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>The same Transparent Ivory, with Shield, and Silver Ferrules</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>White Bone octagon shape Handles</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>White Bone octagon shape Handles, with Rimmed Shoulders</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black Horn octagon shape Handles</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black Horn octagon shape Handles, with Rimmed Shoulders</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Very strong Rough Bone Handles</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Black Wood Handles</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Oval shape White Bone Handles</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p ><hi rend="italics">The Forks priced in the above Scale are all forged Steel. Cast Steel Forks would be</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s. per doz. less.</hi></p><p >Richly carved MAHOGANY CASES, containing, of Transparent Ivory Handles, with Shields and Silver Ferrules, <lb/> Two dozen Table Knives, two dozen Dessert Knives, two pair of full size Carvers with <lb/> French pattern Forks, one pair of Poultry Carvers, and one Steel £10. 10s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >DISH COVERS.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>Inches long</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>Set of 6.</cell><cell>Set of 7.</cell></row><row><cell>The commonest are in sets of the six first sizes, which cannot be separated</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>£0</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell>0d</cell><cell>...</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>6d</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>9d</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>0d</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>6d</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>3d</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>6d</cell><cell>5s.</cell><cell>6d</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>£0</cell><cell>17s.</cell><cell>0d</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin Anti-Patent shape</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin, O. G. shape</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin, Patent Imperial Silver shape. The Tops raised in one piece</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin, the very best made, except Plated or Silver</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Wove Wire Fly-proof, tin rims, japanned</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p2a"/><p >
<table><row><cell>Shower Baths, Japanned Bamboo, with Brass Force-pump attached, to throw the water into the shower cistern, &amp; curtains complete</cell><cell>£4</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Shower Baths, the very best made, with copper conducting tubes, brass force-pump, and curtains .</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Hot Water Baths, self-heating, slipper shaped, full size, japanned wainscot, with copper fire-place, so attached that the Bath may, with the greatest safety, be heated in any room in 20 minutes</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Hip Baths, Japanned Bamboo</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Spunging Baths, Round, 30 inches diameter, 7 inches deep</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Open Baths, 3 ft. 6 in. long, 30s.; 4 ft. long, 35s.; 4ft. 6in. long, 50s.; 5 ft. long, 60s.; 5 ft. 6 in.long, 70s.</p><p >Feet Baths, Japanned Bamboo, small size, 6s. 6d.; large, 7s 6d.; tub shape, with hoops, 11s.</p><p >Bottle Jacks, Japanned, 7s. 6d.; Brass, 9s. 6d. each.</p><p >Brass Stair Rods, per doz. 21 incheslong, 3s. 6d.; 24 in. 4s. 3d.; 27 in. 5s.; 30 in. 5s. 6d.</p><p >Brass Curtain Poles, warranted solid, 1½ inch diameter, 1s. 6d. per foot; 2 in. 2s. 2d. per foot.</p><p >Brass Poles, complete with end ornaments, rings, hooks &amp; brackets, 3ft. long, 15s.; 3ft. 6 in. 17s.; 4ft. 20s.</p><p >Brass Curtain Bands, 1¼ in. wide, 2s, 6d. per pair, 1½ in. 3s.; 2 in. 4s. Richer patterns, 1½ in. 4s.; 2 in. 5s.</p><p >Finger Plates for Doors, newest and richest patterns, long, 1s. 4d.; short, 1s. each.</p><p >Copper Coal Scoops, small, 10s. 6d.; middle, 13s. large, 14s. 6d.. Helmet Shape, 14s. 6d., 18s., 20s.; Square Shape, with Hand Scoop, 28s.</p><p >Copper Tea Kettles, Oval Shape, very strong, with barrel handle, 2 quarts, 5s. 6d.; 3 quarts, 6s.; 4 quarts, 7s. The strongest quality made, 2 quarts 8s.; 3 quarts, 10s.; 4 quarts, 11s.</p><p >Copper Stewpans; Soup or Stock Pots, and Fish Kettles, with Brazing Pan; Saucepans &amp; Preserving Pans; Cutlet Pans, Frying Pans, and Omelette Pans, at prices proportionate with the above.</p><p >Copper Warming Pans, with handles, for fire, 6s. 6d. to 9s. 6d.; Ditto, for water, 25s.</p><p >
<table><head>Fire Irons.</head><row><cell>Large strong Wrought Iron, for Kitchens, 5s. 6d. to</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Wrought Iron, suitable for Servants' Bed Rooms</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Small Polished Steel, for better Bed Rooms</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large Polished Steel, for Libraries</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large Polished Steel, for Dining Rooms</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Large Polished Steel, with Cut Heads, for ditto</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Large very highly polished Steel, plain good pattern</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Large very highly polished, richly cut 25s. to</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Cruet Frames, Black Japanned, with 3 Glasses, 3s. 8d.; 4 Glasses, 4s. 9d.; 5 Glasses, 6s.; 6 Glasses, 7s.</p><p >Corkscrews, Patent, 3s. 6d. each; Common ditto, 6d., 9d., 1s., 1s. 6d., and 2s.</p><p >Smoke Jack, with Chains and Spit, £6. Superior Self-acting do. with Dangle and Horizontal Spit, £10.</p><p >N.B. Experienced Workmen employed to clean, repair, and oil Smoke Jacks, which are so constantly put out of order by the treatment they meet with from chimney sweepers.</p><p >Family Weighing Machines, or Balances, complete, with weights from ¼ oz. to 14lbs., 26s.</p><p >Britannia Metal Goods.</p><p >Amongst the most useful articles that are made of this metal, may be named,—Teapots, Coffee Biggins, Cream Ewers, Sugar Basins, Table Candlesticks, Chamber Candlesticks complete with Snuffers and Extinguishers, Hot Water Dishes, Hot Water Plates, Pepper Castors, Mustard and Salt Cellars; of all of which an immense variety are kept, at prices of which the following may be safely taken as a criterion:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>To hold</cell><cell>1½</cell><cell>Pts.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Qt.</cell><cell>2½</cell><cell>Pts.</cell></row><row><cell>Teapots, with Black Handles and Black Knobs</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell></row><row><cell>Teapots, very strong</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Teapots, with Pearl Knobs</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Teapots with Pearl Knobs and Metal Handles</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Coffee Biggins, 1s. 6d. each size extra.</p><p >Table Candlesticks, 8 in. 3s. per pair; 9 in. 4s. 6d.; 10 in. 6s.</p><p >Chamber Candlesticks with Extinguishers, 2s. each.</p><p >Chamber Candlesticks with Gadroon Edges, complete with Snuffers and Extinguisher, 4s. each.</p><p >Mustards, with Blue Earthen Lining, 1s. each.</p><p >Salt Cellars with Blue Earthen Lining, 1s. 4d. per pair.</p><p >Pepper Boxes, 1s. each.</p><p >Britannia Metal Hot Water Dishes, with wells for gravy, and gadroon edges, 16 inches long, 30s.; 18in., 35s.; 20 in., 42s.; 22 in., 50s.; 24 in., 55s. Hot Water Plates, 6s. 6d. each.</p><p >Plated Table Candlesticks, with Silver Mountings, 8½ inches high, 8s. 6d. per pair; 9 inches 12s. 6d.; 10 in. 16s. 6d.</p><p >Reading Candlesticks, with Shade and Light to slide, one light, 6s.; two lights, 8s.</p><p >Coffee Filterers, for making Coffee without boiling.</p><p >
<table><row><cell>To hold</cell><cell>1½</cell><cell>Pts.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Qt.</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Pts.</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Qts.</cell></row><row><cell>Best Block Tin</cell><cell>4s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>5s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>7s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell></row><row><cell>Bronzed</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Etnas, for boiling a Pint of Water in three minutes, 3s. each.</p><p >Coffee and Pepper Mills, small, 3s.; middle, 4s.; large, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6d.</p><p >Ditto, to fix, small, 4s. 6d.; middle, 5s. 6d,; large, 6s. 6d.</p><p >Iron Digesters, for making Soup, to hold 2 galls. 9s.; 3 galls. 10s. 6d.; 4 galls. 16s.</p><p >Tea Urns, Globe shape. to hold four quarts. 27s. each.</p><p >Modern Shapes, to hold 6 quarts, 45s. to 60s. each.</p><p >Improved Wove Wire Gauze Window Blinds, in mahogany frames, made to any size, and painted to any shade of colour, 2s. 3d. per square foot.</p><p >Ornamenting with shadedlines, 1s. 6d. each blind.</p><p >Ditto, with lines and corner ornaments, 2s. 6d. each blind.</p><p >Blinds, ornamented with landscape, in mahogany frames, 4s. per square foot.</p><p >Old Blind Frames filled with new wire, and painted any colour, at 1s. 4d. per square foot.</p><p >Servants' Wire Lanterns, Open Tops, with Doors, 1s. 6d. each. Closed Tops, with Doors, 2s.</p><p >Rush Safes, Open Tops, 2s. 3d. each. Closed Tops, with Doors, 2s. 9d. each.</p><p >Captains' Cabin Lamps, with 1 quart kettles, 6s.</p><p >Fire Guards, painted Green, with Dome Tops, 14 inch, 1s. 6d.; 16 in. 1s. 9d.; 18 in. 2s. 3d. Brass Wire, 6s., 6s. 6d., and 7s. 6d.</p><p >Egg Whisks, Tinned Wire, 9d. each.</p></div><div type="section"><head >Iron Coal Scoops and Boxes.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>14 in. long.</cell><cell>16 in. long.</cell><cell>18 in. long.</cell></row><row><cell>Coal Boxes, Japanned with Covers, ornamented with Gold Lines</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>14s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>16s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell></row><row><cell>Coal Scoops, Iron, for Kitchen Use</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Coal Scoops, lined with Zinc, the most serviceable article of the kind ever made</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Upright Hods</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p3a"/><head >FENDERS.</head><p >The immense variety which the Show Rooms contain, and the constant change of patterns of Fenders, render it impossible to give the prices of but a small portion of them. The following Scale, however, may be taken as a guide, and the prices generally will be found about 25 per cent. below any other house whatever.</p><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>3 Feet.</cell><cell>3 Feet 3.</cell><cell>3 Feet 6.</cell><cell>3 Feet 9.</cell><cell>4 Feet.</cell></row><row><cell>Green, with Brass Top, suitable for Bed Rooms</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>4s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>All Brass</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>15s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell></row><row><cell>Black Iron for Dining Rooms or Libraries</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Bronzed for Dining Rooms or Libraries</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Bronzed, with bright Steel Tops</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Bronzed, very handsome, with Steel Tops and Steel Bottom Moulding</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Very rich Pattern, with Scroll Centre, Steel Rod and Steel Ends, for Drawing Rooms [all sizes]</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>50</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Green painted Wire Nursery Guard Fenders, Brass Tops, 1S in. high</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Green painted, 24 inches high</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Strong Iron Kitchen Fenders, with Sliding Bars</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Strong Iron Kitchen fenders, extra strong, for long sizes</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >STOVES.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>Inches wide</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell>Elliptic or Rumford Stoves, for Bed Rooms</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell>8d.</cell><cell>7s.</cell><cell>4d.</cell><cell>8s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>8s.</cell><cell>8d.</cell><cell>9s.</cell><cell>4d.</cell><cell>10s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>10s.</cell><cell>8d</cell><cell>11s.</cell><cell>4d</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>0d</cell></row><row><cell>Common half register Stoves</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Best Common half bold Fronts and Bannister Bars</cell><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>28</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Register Stoves of superior patterns</cell><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>-</cell><cell/><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >Register Stoves, fine Cast, 3 feet wide, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, and 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi>—Ground Bright Front Register Stoves with Bronzed and Steel Ornaments, and with bright and black bars, 3 feet wide, 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi>. and 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >Ironing Stoves for Laundries, complete, with Frame and Ash Pan, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="section"><head >KITCHEN RANGES.</head><p >The very high prices charged and obtained for Kitchen Ranges, under a pretence of having made improvements in them, but which, in most cases, have proved quite the reverse, owing to the complicated manner in which they are made for the sake of showing an apparent alteration, induce JOHN JAMES RIPPON strongly to recommend those that are the most simple in their construction, which he has invariably found to answer. The prices are:—</p><p >
<table><row><cell>To fit an opening of</cell><cell>3 Ft.</cell><cell>3 Ft. 3.</cell><cell>3 Ft. 6.</cell><cell>3 Ft. 9.</cell><cell>4 Ft.</cell><cell>4 Ft. 6.</cell><cell>5 Ft.</cell></row><row><cell>With Oven and Boiler</cell><cell>50s.</cell><cell>54s.</cell><cell>58s.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Self-acting Boiler, with Oven and Boiler, Sliding Check, and Wrought Iron Bars (recommended)</cell><cell>90</cell><cell>95</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>105s.</cell><cell>110s.</cell><cell>126s.</cell><cell>140s.</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >Iron Saucepans and Tea Kettles.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>1 pint.</cell><cell>1½ pint.</cell><cell>1 Quart.</cell><cell>3 pint.</cell><cell>2 Quart.</cell><cell>3 Quart.</cell><cell>4 Quart.</cell><cell>6 Quart.</cell><cell>8 Quart.</cell></row><row><cell>Iron Saucepan and Cover</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>2d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>4d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>8d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>10d</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>3d.</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>4s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell></row><row><cell>Iron Stewpan and Cover</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Round Iron Tea Kettles</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Oval Tea Kettles</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >Iron Boiling Pots.</head><p >
<table><row><cell/><cell>2½ Gall.</cell><cell>3 Gall.</cell><cell>3½ Gall.</cell><cell>4 Gall.</cell><cell>5 Gall.</cell><cell>6 Gall.</cell></row><row><cell>Oval Iron Boiling Pot and Cover</cell><cell>5s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>6s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>7s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>9s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>11s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>12s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell></row><row><cell>Tea Kitchens, or Water Fountains, with Brass Pipe &amp; Cock</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >Japanned Goods.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>Inches long</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>TEA TRAYS, good common quality</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>3d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>3d.</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>3d.</cell><cell>3s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell></row><row><cell>TEA TRAYS, best common quality</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>TEA TRAYS, paper shape, black</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>TEA TRAYS, Gothic paper shape, black</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>TEA TRAYS, Gothic, Marone, ornamented all over</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><list  type="simple"><item>Bread and Knife Trays, common, 9d., 1s. &amp; 1s. 6d. each.</item><item>Middle quality Knife, at 2s. and 2s. 6d.</item><item>Best Middle quality Knife, Gothic shape, 3s. 6d., 4s. 6d. and 5s. 6d. each.</item><item>Tea Trays, paper, Gothic shape, in sets of one each of 18, 24, and 30 inches, £3. 10s.</item><item>Tea Trays, ornamented, the set, £4. 5s.</item><item>Tea Trays, richest patterns, the set, £5. 5s. and £6.</item><item>Toast Racks, plain black, 1s. 6d. Ornamented. 2s.</item><item>Toast Racks, marone or green, ornamented all over, 2s. 9d.</item><item>Cheese Trays, 2s., 2s. 6d., 3s., and 3s. 6d.</item><item>Snuffer Trays, 6d., 9d., 1s., 1s. 3d., and 1s. 6d.</item><item>Paper Snuffer Trays, 2s., 2s. 6d., 3s., 3s. 6d., and 4s.</item><item>Paper Decanter Stands, plain black, 3s. 6d. per pair.</item><item>Paper Decanter Stands, plain black, red, 4s. per pair.</item><item>Paper Decanter Stands, ornamented black or marone, 4s. 6d. per pair.</item><item>Plate Warmers, upright shade, with gilt lines, 18s.</item><item>Plate Warmers, long shape, £1. 5s.</item><item>Toilet Cans and Toilet Pails, 7s. 6d. each.</item><item>Chamber Slop Pails, japanned green outside and red inside, small, 3s.; middle, 4s.; large, 5s. 6d.</item><item>Chamber Candlesticks, complete, with Snuffers and Extinguisher, 6d. Ditto, better, 9d. to 3s.</item><item>Cash Boxes, with Tumbler Locks, small size, 5s. 6d.</item><item>Cash Boxes, with Tumbler Locks, middle size, 6s. 6d.; large size, 7s. 6d.</item><item>Cash Boxes, with Tumbler Locks, with Patent Locks, 10s. 6d.</item><item>Deed Boxes, Japanned Brown, with Locks, 12 inches long, 9s.; 14 in. 13s.; 16 in. 15s.; 18 in. 18s.</item><item>Candle Boxes, 1s. 4d. each.</item><item>Candle or Rush Safes, 2s. 6d. each.</item><item>Cinder Pails or Sifters, Japanned Brown, 11s. each.</item></list></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p4"/><head >TIN GOODS.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>To hold</cell><cell>1 Pt.</cell><cell>1 Qt.</cell><cell>3 Pt.</cell><cell>2 Qt.</cell><cell>3 Qt.</cell><cell>4 Qt.</cell><cell>6 Qt.</cell><cell>8 Qt.</cell><cell>9 Qt.</cell><cell>10 Qt.</cell></row><row><cell>SAUCEPANS, strong common, with Covers</cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell>4d</cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell>5d</cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell>6d</cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell>8d</cell><cell>0s.</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>2d</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>3d</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>4d</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>8d</cell><cell>2s.</cell><cell>0d</cell></row><row><cell>Strongest Tin, Iron Handles, not Blocked</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Saucepans and Steamers</cell><cell>—</cell><cell/><cell>—</cell><cell/><cell>—</cell><cell/><cell>—</cell><cell/><cell>2</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row></table>
</p><list  type="simple"><item>Coffee and Chocolate Pots, Block Tin, to hold 1 quart, 1s. 4d.; 3 pints, 1s. 10d.; 2 quarts, 2s. 3d</item><item>Colanders, small, 1s.; large, 1s. 6d.</item><item>Colanders, Block Tin, small, 3s. 6d.; large, 4s. 6d.</item><item>Dripping Pans, with wells, small, 3s.; mid., 5s.; large, 7s.</item><item>Fish Kettles, small, 4s. 6d.; middle, 5s. 6d.; large, 6s. 6d.</item><item>Turbot Pans, or Kettles, Turbot shape, 21s.</item><item>Meat Screens for Bottle Jacks, 15s. each.</item><item>Meat Screens, Wood, Elliptic Shape, lined with Tin, upon Rollers, with Shelf and Door, 3 feet wide, £1. 5s. Larger sizes in proportion.</item><item>Stomach Warmers, each 2s. 6d.</item></list><p >
<table><row><cell>To hold</cell><cell>3 Pts.</cell><cell>2 Qts.</cell><cell>3 Qts.</cell><cell>4 Qts.</cell></row><row><cell>TEA KETTLES, Oval shape, strong Common Tin</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>2d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>3d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell><cell>1s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell></row><row><cell>TEA KETTLES, strongest Tin</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Block Tin, with Iron Handles and Iron Spouts</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Oblong shape, with round Barrel Handles and Iron Spout</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table>
</p></div><div type="section"><head >JOHN JAMES RIPPON'S Prices of STRONG SETS of IRON and TIN <lb/> KITCHEN FURNITURE.</head><p >
<table><row><cell>Small Set.</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bread Grater</cell><cell>0<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pair Brass Candlesticks</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bottle Jack</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tin Candlestick</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Candle Box</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>1 Meat Chopper</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Cinder Sifter</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Coffee Pot</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Colander</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dripping Pan &amp; Stand</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dust Pan</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Slice</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fish Kettle</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Flour Box</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>2 Flat Irons</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fryingpan</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>1 Gridiron</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Mustard Pot</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Salt Cellar</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pepper Box</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Block Tin Butter Saucepan</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>2 Iron Saucepans</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>2 Iron Stewpans</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Boiling Pot, Iron</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Set of Skewers</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 Knives and Forks</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>3 Spoons</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Pot and 1 Tea Tray</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Toasting Fork</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Kettle</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>£3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Middle Set.</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bread Grater</cell><cell>1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pair Brass Candlesticks</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bottle Jack</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pair of Bellows</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>2 Tin Candlesticks</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Candle Box</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>1 Cheese Toaster</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>1 Chopper</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>1 Cinder Sifter</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Coffee Pot</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Colander</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dripping Pan &amp; Stand</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dust Pan</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fish Slice</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fish Kettle</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Pepper and Flour Boxes</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3 Flat Irons</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fryingpan</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>1 Gridiron</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>2 Jelly Moulds</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Mustard Pot</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Salt Cellar</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Plate Basket</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>2 Block Tin Saucepans</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>3 Iron Saucepans</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Saucepan and Steamer</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Large Boiling Pot</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>3 Stewpans</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Set of Skewers</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 Knives and Forks</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 Iron Spoons</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Pot &amp; 1 Tea Tray</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Toasting Fork</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Kettle</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>£5</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >
<table><row><cell>Large Set.</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bread Grater</cell><cell>1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pair Brass Candlesticks</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bottle Jack</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pair of Bellows</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>2 Deep Tin Candlesticks</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Candle Box</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>1 Cheese Toaster</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>1 Chopper, for Meat</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Cinder Sifter</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Coffee Pot</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Coal Shovel</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Colander</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dripping Pan and Stand</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Dust Pan</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Egg Slice</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Fish Slice</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>2 Fish Kettles</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Flour Box</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>3 Flat Irons</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>2 Fryingpans</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Gridiron, with fluted Bars</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Wood Meat Screen</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>3 Jelly Moulds</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Mustard Pot</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Salt Cellar</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>1 Pepper Box</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Wicker Plate Basket, lined with Tin</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>3 Block Tin Saucepans</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>4 Iron Saucepans</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1 Saucepan and Steamer</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Large Boiling Pot, Iron</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>4 Stewpans, Iron</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>2 Sets of Skewers</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>6 Knives and Forks</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>6 Iron Spoons</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Pot</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Tray</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Toasting Fork</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1 Egg Whisk</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>1 Tea Kettle</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>£8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table>
</p><p >In submitting to the Public the foregoing Catalogue, JOHN JAMES RIPPON begs to state, that he will continue to offer Articles of the VERY BEST MANUFACTURE only, as he has hitherto done, at prices which, when compared with others of the same quality, will be found much lower than any that have ever yet been quoted. The knowledge which JOHN JAMES RIPPON has obtained by his long connexion with the largest Manufacturers, and the principle upon which he conducts his business, afford great advantages to the purchaser; all Articles being bought in very large quantities for Cash, and marked for sale at Cash prices, which are not subject to discount or abatement of any kind; thus giving the ready money purchaser all the advantages that can be obtained over the plan usually adopted by others, of marking their goods at prices which will enable them to give credit, and pay for that credit which they take; allowing those, who pay cash, 5 per cent. discount from prices 25 per cent. higher than they should fairly be charged. The many years JOHN JAMES RIPPON'S business has been established, and the very extensive patronage he has met with, will be some proof that the public have not been deceived by him; but, as a further security against the impositions practised by many, JOHN JAMES RIPPON will continue to exchange, or return the money for every article that is not approved of, if returned in good condition and free of expense within one month of the time it was purchased.</p><p >J. Bradley, Printer, 78, Great Titchfield, London.</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p1b"/><opener >
“TO SOFTER PROSPECTS TURN WE NOW THE VIEW, <lb/> TO LAURELL'D SCIENCE, ARTS, AND PUBLIC WORKS”—<hi rend="italics">Thomson.</hi>
<lb/>IN PARTS, ROYAL QUARTO, EVERY ALTERNATE WEEK, <lb/> PRICE HALF-A-CROWN, <lb/> EDITED BY JAMES DUNCAN, ESQ. M. W. S., &amp;c. &amp;c.
</opener><head >
THE <lb/> ARTIST'S PORTFOLIO:
</head><p >CONTAINING <lb/> ELABORATE ENGRAVINGS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PRINCIPAL PRODUCTIONS OF THE DIFFERENT <lb/> Schools of Painting, <lb/> AND THE MOST INTERESTING REMAINS OF <lb/> ANCIENT SCULPTURE:</p><p >WITH HISTORICAL, DESCRIPTIVE, AND BIOGRAPHICAL NOTICES.</p><p >LONDON:</p><p >PUBLISHED BY ALLAN BELL AND CO., WARWICK SQUARE.</p><p >ACKERMANN AND CO., STRAND; AND H. WASHBOURNE, SALISBURY SQUARE.</p><p >EDINBURGH:—FRASER AND CO.</p><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p2b"/><head >ADVERTISEMENT.</head><p >THE “ARTIST'S PORTFOLIO” is intended to comprise the elaborate productions, formerly constituting the NAPOLEON GALLERY, in the NATIONAL MUSEUM OF FRANCE, which have been engraved by a number of the most talented Foreign Artists, from the Original Pictures by the following celebrated Masters: <hi rend="italics">viz.</hi>:—</p><list  type="simple"><item>ALBANO,</item><item>ANGELO, MICH.</item><item>BACKHUYSEN,</item><item>BARTOLOMEO,</item><item>BASSANO,</item><item>BERGHEM,</item><item>BLOEMART,</item><item>BOTH,</item><item>BREUGHEL,</item><item>BRILL,</item><item>CARAVAGLIA,</item><item>CANALLETTA,</item><item>CARACCI,</item><item>CHAMPAGNI,</item><item>CIGNANI,</item><item>CLAUDE,</item><item>CORREGGIO,</item><item>CORTONA,</item><item>COYPEL,</item><item>CUYP,</item><item>DEL SARTO,</item><item>DEL VAGA,</item><item>DIETRICH,</item><item>COLCI,</item><item>DOMENICHENI,</item><item>DOW, G.</item><item>DU JARDIN,</item><item>FETI,</item><item>FLINCK,</item><item>FOREST,</item><item>GAROFOLO,</item><item>GIORGIONE,</item><item>GLAUBER,</item><item>GUERCINO,</item><item>GIORGONE,</item><item>GUERIN,</item><item>GUIDO,</item><item>HALS,</item><item>HOLBEIN,</item><item>HOOGE,</item><item>JAN STEEN,</item><item>JOSEPIN,</item><item>JOUVENET,</item><item>LAIRESSE,</item><item>LANA,</item><item>LANFRANC,</item><item>LAURI,</item><item>LE BRUN,</item><item>LE DIEU,</item><item>LE SUEUR,</item><item>LOTTO,</item><item>MARATTI,</item><item>METZU,</item><item>MIERS,</item><item>MIGNARD,</item><item>MOLA,</item><item>MURILLO,</item><item>NEEFS,</item><item>NETSCHER,</item><item>NICCOLO,</item><item>OSTADE,</item><item>PARMESAN,</item><item>PATEL,</item><item>PIOMBO,</item><item>POLENBURG,</item><item>POLIDOR,</item><item>POTTER,</item><item>POUSSIN,</item><item>PYNACKER,</item><item>RAFFAEL,</item><item>REMBRANDT,</item><item>ROMANO,</item><item>ROOS,</item><item>ROTTENHAMER,</item><item>RUBENS,</item><item>RUYSDAEL,</item><item>SALVATOR ROSA,</item><item>SCHALKEN,</item><item>SCHIDONE,</item><item>SILVESTER,</item><item>SPADA,</item><item>SPAGNOLETTI,</item><item>SWANEVELDT,</item><item>TENIERS,</item><item>TERBURG,</item><item>TINTORETTI,</item><item>TITIAN,</item><item>VAN DER HELST,</item><item>VAN DER HEYDEN,</item><item>VAN DER MEULEN,</item><item>VAN DER POEL,</item><item>VAN DER VELDE,</item><item>VAN DYCK,</item><item>VAN EYCK,</item><item>VAN GOYEN,</item><item>VAN HAYSUM,</item><item>VAN LOO,</item><item>VALENTIN,</item><item>VENEZIANO,</item><item>VERONESE,</item><item>VERNET,</item><item>VINCI, (LEON. DA)</item><item>VOUET,</item><item>WOUVERMANS,</item><item>WYNANTS.</item></list><p >The entire Work will comprise upwards of SEVEN HUNDRED PLATES, and be completed in about SEVEN VOLUMES, ROYAL QUARTO.</p><p >*** A NUMBER, PRICE FIVE SHILLINGS, containing FOUR PLATES, COLOURED in a superior style, with the requisite Descriptive Letter-press, in a neat Wrapper, will also be published occasionally.</p></div><div type="section"><head >EXTRACT FROM THE EDITOR'S PREFACE.</head><p >THE Work which we now lay before the Public, contains representations of many of the most celebrated Paintings found in Europe, as well as the most valuable remains of the sister art which have been transmitted from ancient times. The series of Plates composing it is of great extent, and they are executed in the most skilful and elaborate manner by the best artists that could be obtained in France. The favourable circumstances under which we have been enabled to reprint them in their present form, and the general nature of the publication now presented to the lovers of the Fine Arts, a very few words will be sufficient to explain.</p><p >It is well known that Napoleon Buonaparte, during his successful career, used every exertion to form a Gallery of Pictures in Paris; and that the assemblage which he brought together in the Louvre, soon surpassed, in value and extent, every thing of that kind that had previously been witnessed. The account of the plans taken to amass and preserve this unparalleled collection, forms a curious and interesting episode in the history of Napoleon's life. Amidst the din of war, and the progress of operations which decided the fate of nations, this object was never overlooked, and the surrender of pictures and statues was often made an indispensable condition in treaties which affected the lives and welfare of thousands. Certainly an equal number of these invaluable objects could not have been obtained by any other method than that adopted by Napoleon, and that method, as obviously, could never have been carried into effect, except under the peculiar combination of circumstances which then happened to exist. The works of the great masters are regarded as reflecting honour on the country which gave them birth, and to alienate or dispose of them as ordinary commodities of marketable value, is considered little short of national degradation. But Napoleon had no desire to purchase them, even if that had been practicable; the fortune of war had placed them completely within his reach. The steps of his victorious armies were attended by crowds of commissioners, artists, and savans, whose business it was to select what was most valuable; and Europe witnessed, with equal surprise and indignation, the appropriation of a species of property which the established usage of modern warfare had hitherto held sacred. The different Italian campaigns transferred to the French the best productions of the mother country of modern art: every Gallery of importance was laid under contribution; the delivery of such as were public property, was expressly stipulated in treaties for peace; and the violation of all the principles of international law was a consideration little likely to prevent the victorious general from seizing whatever suited his purposes in the possession of private individuals. A similar system was acted upon in every subsequent campaign made by the French, and their invasions extended to almost every country where the arts had flourished. The collection formed by such means was necessarily of great extent, and its value was such as scarcely to admit of calculation. In making these unusual exactions, it is probable that Napoleon acted at first under instructions from the Directory, and these were too much in unison with his own schemes of policy, to be afterwards abandoned when he had the liberty of choice. They enabled him to present continual trophies of his victories to the eyes of the French nation,—to evince the advantages of military greatness,—and to raise a continual cloud of incense to the national vanity: they supplied one of the means by which his consummate genius “wielded at will the fierce democracy,” whose authority was paramount at the outset of his career, and long continued too formidable not to be conciliated. It may, at the same time, be admitted, that he was actuated by a real desire to improve the arts of his own country. When the duke of Modena offered £80,000 to redeem the celebrated St. Jerome of Corregio, and Buonaparte's generals urged him to prefer the money: “No,” said he, “the duke's two millions of francs would soon be spent; but his Corregio will remain for ages to adorn Paris, and inspire the arts of France.”</p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p3b"/><head >LITERARY NOVELTIES</head><p >GOT UP EXPRESSLY <lb/> As Presents to the Junior Classes, <lb/> IN WHICH ARE BLENDED <lb/> INSTRUCTION, AMUSEMENT, AND ATTRACTION.</p><div type="section"><opener >I. <lb/> Dedicated to Her Ropal Highness the Princess Victoria.<lb/>
In 7 Pocket Volumes, exquisitely bound in crimson Cloth, and richly ornamented in Gold, <lb/> IN A CASE, 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; and in elegant Turkey Morocco, in a SILK CASE, 45<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >SHAKSPEARE'S DRAMATIC WORKS,</head><p > SPLENDIDLY ILLUSTRATED FROM ORIGINAL DRAWINGS, BY A FIRST-RATE ARTIST, <lb/> Each Play being embellished with a highly-finished Vignette, printed in Colours, and a <lb/> Steel Plate printed on Enamelled Paper.</p></div><div type="section"><opener >II. <lb/> Dedicated to Her Royal Highness the Duchess of Kent.<lb/>
In 4 Volumes, 24mo. Printed in a superior manner, and bound in the style of the “Illustrated <lb/> Classics,” richly gilt, Price 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; or in elegant Turkey Morocco, 35<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head >GOLDSMITH'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND, <lb/> FROM THE EARLIEST TIMES TO THE DEATH OF GEORGE THE SECOND;</head><p >With numerous Original Notes, and a Continuation to the Year 1836, inclusive, <lb/> BY EDMUND BELLCHAMBERS, <lb/> Editor of a “General Biographical Dictionary,” “The Scripture Cabinet,” “Apology for the Life of Cibber,” &amp;c.</p><p >The Work is Embellished with about SIXTY STEEL PLATES, comprising Portraits of all the Sovereigns, including their present Majesties, WILLIAM IV. and QUEEN ADELAIDE and many other Historical Illustrations, from Original Drawings made expressly for <lb/> this Work.</p></div><div type="section"><head >CRITICAL NOTICES.</head><p >“These volumes are gems outside as well as inside. They are really as beautiful as green-binding and golden adornment can make them—with the royal arms impressed so as to form a climax to entice the young who have a little pocket-money to lay out on intellectual treasures, which can never be wasted or become old. All this external neatness, tasteful <hi rend="italics">getting up,</hi> and richness, can only be regarded as the suitable index of the contents. Goldsmith's England is too well known to require a word of recommendation
<pb xml:id="p4a"/>
from us to juvenile readers. But we must add, that the Continuation dovetails admirably with the model, and that the notes are abundant, and judiciously inserted as well as dictated. When, with all these circumstances, we regard the portraits and other illustrations that embellish such gemlike yet substantial volumes, it cannot be too much to say, that they are unique in the history of typography, and the arts of elegant condensation.”—<hi rend="italics">Monthly Review, June,</hi> 1837.</p><p >“* * * * The Work can only be appreciated fully by being seen. IT IS SO TASTEFUL, THAT IT WOULD FORM A PRESENT WORTHY EVEN THE HIGHEST AND THE MOST OPULENT TO GIVE AND TO RECEIVE.”—<hi rend="italics">Metropolitan Mag.</hi></p><p >“This is a neat Edition of GOLDSMITH'S ENGLAND, and Mr. Bellchambers has edited the original portion of the work with care; the new matter brings the history down to our own time. THE LATTER WILL BE READ WITH MUCH INTEREST.”—<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><p >“A beautiful little Edition of Goldsmith's History has just been published by Bell and Co. Of Dr. Goldsmith's part we are not called on to speak; the reader will remember that he was an old contributor to this paper, having introduced in the <hi rend="italics">Public Ledger</hi> of 1760, some letters (almost as entertaining as “Boz”) under the signature of the “CHINESE PHILOSOPHER.” It would look like a partiality in us to praise a person of our own establishment, and we must therefore speak of Mr. Bellchamber's share of the History. This embraces the histories of the three last reigns; the disasters of the war of American independence, the victories in the war with Napoleon, the conjugal battle of George IV., and the struggle and conquest of reform in our own day. The reader, <hi rend="italics">young or old,</hi> cannot have a more instructive book, and the critic can but applaud the style in which it is done. At the close of the two last volumes are to be found some admirable statistical accounts, which render the work of double utility; a history of the United States, and a statistical survey of the population, the manufactures, and the wealth of this country * * *.—We never saw four volumes which deserve such a general popularity.”—<hi rend="italics">Constitutional.</hi></p><p >“Quite a Bijou in a sweet livery of green and gold, appropriately super-added to which are the Royal arms; we have rarely or never seen the poet and the historian of nature, youth's favourite author, Oliver Goldsmith, in so beautiful an attire. * * * * * * The notes, by the editor, are <hi rend="italics">copious, judicious,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">well-digested;</hi> and the illustrations are numerous and well executed. We shall therefore dismiss the work with this observation, THAT THERE IS NOT A YOUNG LADY OR GENTLEMAN IN THE LAND WHOSE LIBRARY OUGHT TO BE CONSIDERED COMPLETE WITHOUT A COPY OF IT.”—<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser.</hi></p><p >“Here are four very pretty little volumes handsomely bound, illustrated with numerous engravings, and embodying a new edition of Goldsmith's History of England, with notes, and a ‘continuation’ up to the present time, by Mr. E. Bellchambers. The work also contains an Appendix, conveying a great deal of useful information on subjects of national importance, and we may safely recommend it as a most admirable production—equally creditable to the talents of Mr. Bellchambers, and the taste and spirit of the publishers. To show the style in which the ‘continuation’ is written, we cannot do better than by quoting the following eloquent and truly liberal passage from the ‘Introduction.’—‘For the latter moiety of these volumes, the Editor is proud to hold himself personally responsible. It contains an <hi rend="italics">original</hi> and <hi rend="italics">exclusive</hi> notice of public affairs, as they transpired subsequent to the period at which Goldsmith relinquished them, and they have been treated, it is hoped, in a tone of which no enlightened or impartial Englishman will disapprove. Placing himself upon an eminence, with the clouds of party prejudice rolling at his feet, the Editor has attempted to take that clear view of men and things, which could not have been gained from a less elevated station. Among other great topics which are treated in this spirit of freedom and independence, he ventures to rank the American war, which, reflecting and writing like a citizen of the world, has been described without regret for the baffled ambition of his native country, or displeasure at the triumph of an antagonist power. The fundamental rights of the whole human race were comprehended in that mighty struggle; and he who can fail to rejoice at their preeminence, by whatever sacrifice of interest or of glory a particular region might be attended, wants the first and best of those philosophic sympathies, which teach us to find individual happiness in its extension to the whole of mankind. Seldom has a moral lesson of such magnitude been taught to the potentates of this haughty hemisphere: and let us pray that in this happy land, at least, the arms of oppressed and embittered freemen will never again be raised to repeat the blow that has already been inflicted!’ * * * * “The general tone of Mr. Bellchambers' writings is most decidedly liberal—on the side of the people—in the cause of reform, and, consequently, in accordance with the spirit of the age. In fact, this is almost exactly <hi rend="italics">the</hi> HISTORY of ENGLAND WHICH OUGHT TO BE STUDIED BY THE RISING GENERATION.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Dispatch.</hi></p><p >“* * * * The continuator has most amply performed his duty to the work:—indeed, we will make bold to say <hi rend="italics">that his part of the work is the cream of the whole.</hi> The improved form in which Goldsmith now appears, will, we hope, do good. * * * We especially recommend the fourth volume, as being on the whole the most interesting part of the work.”—<hi rend="italics">Monthly Magazine.</hi></p><p >“We have here Goldsmith's popular History of England, republished in four of the most elegant little duodecimos that have appeared for years past, and carried down to 1836. The new matter comprises just two volumes, and is written in an easy and perspicuous style. It is also accurate in its facts; and so far as we have been able to judge from a hasty glance, temperate and impartial in its tone. The Editor has acquitted himself of a difficult task with skill and judgment * * * * *. It would form a capital prize-book for schools.”—<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p5"/><head >ALLAN BELL &amp; CO.'S <lb/> UNIQUE ILLUSTRATED CLASSICAL LIBRARY; </head><p > IN A CASE, WITH LOCK AND KEY, <lb/> FIFTEEN VOLUMES, splendidly bound and richly gilt, <lb/> Price £2. in extra Cloth; or in elegant purple Morocco, £3 : 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
</p><list  type="simple"><head>CONTENTS:</head><item>MILTON'S POETICAL WORKS, embellished with 24 Illustrations, from Original Drawings, complete in 2 vols.</item><item>THOMSON'S POETICAL WORKS, 24 Illustrations, complete in 2 vols.</item><item>GOLDSMITH'S MISCELLANEOUS WORKS, 30 Illustrations, complete in 5 vols.</item><item>COWPER'S POETICAL WORKS, 24 Illustrations, complete in 2 vols.</item><item>BUTLER'S HUDIBRAS and MISCELLANEOUS POEMS, complete in 2 vols. with 12 Illustrations.</item><item>POPE'S HOMER'S ILIAD, complete in 2 vols. Embellished with 24 Illustrations.</item></list><p > Each Author may also be had <hi rend="italics">separately,</hi> in the same elegant style of binding as the above, at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> a volume; or 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in Morocco.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><opener >In Ten Volumes, neatly bound, extra gilt, in a Case, Price 15s.</opener><head >ABBOTT'S JUVENILE LIBRARY;</head><p > COMPRISING <lb/> HIS EXCELLENT, POPULAR, AND INSTRUCTIVE PRODUCTIONS.</p><list  type="simple"><head>CONTENTS:</head><item>THE YOUNG CHRISTIAN; being a Familiar Illustration of the Principles of Christian Duty, &amp;c.</item><item>THE MOTHER AT HOME; or, the Principles of Paternal Duty familiarly illustrated.</item><item>THE CHILD AT HOME; or, the Principles of Filial Duty familiarly illustrated.</item><item>PARENTAL DUTIES in the Promotion of early Piety.</item><item>THE LITTLE PHILOSOPHER; designed for the use of Juvenile Reasoners, &amp;c.</item><item>THE FIRE-SIDE; or, the Duties and Enjoyments of Family Religion.</item><item>THE TEACHER; or, Moral Influences employed in the Instruction and Government of the Young.</item><item>EVERY DAY DUTY; illustrated by Sketches of Childish Character and Conduct.</item><item>CHINA AND THE ENGLISH; or, the Character and Manners of the Chinese, &amp;c.</item><item>THE CORNER STONE; or, a Familiar Illustration of the Principles of Christian Truth.</item></list><p > Separate Volumes, in same extra gilt binding, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; or in Fancy Boards, at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p6"/><head >DIAMOND POCKET EDITIONS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> HOLY BIBLE, COMMON PRAYER,</head><p >  New Testament, and Proper Lessons, <lb/> ALL WITH PRACTICAL AND EXPLANATORY NOTES, <lb/> BY <lb/> THE REV. HENRY STEBBING, A.M., M.R.S.L., &amp;c.</p><p >The peculiar features which distinguish the Rev. Mr. STEBBING's Pocket Editions of the Sacred Scriptures render them particularly suitable for the junior branches of Christian Families. The text is a faithful reprint of the authorized version. The NOTES, which comprise about one-fifth of the entire reading, are chiefly of a practical and devotional character, but they also embody, in a condensed form, a clear and lucid exposition of all difficult passages, and a selection of references to parallel parts of Scripture adapted to elucidate the text.</p><p >The publishers, therefore, feel confident that no other Pocket Edition of the Scriptures will be found so replete with instructive and explanatory annotations, and that the high reputation which the Rev. Author has obtained as a theological writer, not only among the members of the established church, but also among the different bodies of orthodox dissenters, cannot fail to recommend these Editions to very general attention, <hi rend="italics">as adapted in an eminent degree for the improvement, especially the younger branches,</hi> of the great mass of Christian families.</p><p >The BOOK OF COMMON PRAYER, and the PROPER LESSONS, have also copious Notes by the same Author, fully explaining and elucidating the solemn services of the Church, in a manner which cannot fail to render them more interesting and instructive to the youthful mind.</p><p >“THE NAME OF MR. STEBBING IS A SECURITY THAT THE NOTES ARE SENSIBLE, JUDICIOUS, AND ORTHODOX.—<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p><p >“Extremely neat volumes; appropriately illustrated by Engravings after celebrated pictures, and by still more valuable Notes by the able Editor, who has also consulted the highest sources for his contributions.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gaz.</hi></p><p >“This Diamond Edition of the Bible is indeed a Gem. The Notes, as far as we have perused them, are highly valuable.”—<hi rend="italics">Evangelical Register.</hi></p><div type="section"><p >Royal 24mo. Size.</p><list  type="simple"><item>1. STEBBING'S BIBLE, Illustrated with 14 Plates, including PRESENTATION PLATE and Engraved Title Page, Turkey Morocco, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; Morocco Extra, with Illuminated Title and Frontispiece, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item><item>2. STEBBING'S BIBLE with the BOOK of COMMON PRAYER, complete in 1 Volume, 14 Plates, &amp;c., Turkey Morocco, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Morocco extra, with Illuminated Title and Frontispiece, 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></item><item>3. STEBBING'S “CHURCH SERVICE,” comprising the BOOK OF COMMON PRAYER, NEW TESTAMENT, and PROPER LESSONS, complete in One Volume, Morocco, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; extra Morocco, &amp;c. 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item></list><list  type="simple"><head>Demy 32mo. Size.</head><item>4. STEBBING'S DIAMOND BIBLE, illustrated with 36 Plates, from the OLD MASTERS, and a PRESENTATION PLATE, 2 Volumes (or in One Volume, with Albata Clasp) <hi rend="italics">Morocco,</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; ditto, Morocco extra, with Illuminated Titles and Frontispiece, 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></item><item>5. STEBBING'S BIBLE, PRAYER, AND TESTAMENT, 2 Volumes, with 50 Illustrations and Presentation Plate, Morocco, in a Morocco Case, 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; Ditto extra Illuminated Title and Frontispiece, 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item></list><list  type="simple"><pb xml:id="p7"/><item>6. STEBBING'S “CHURCH SERVICE,” comprising the BOOK OF COMMON PRAYER and PROPER LESSONS, 25 Illustrations and PRESENTATION PLATE, 2 Volumes, Morocco, in a Morocco Case, 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; 2 Volumes, Morocco extra, ditto, 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; I Volume, Morocco, <hi rend="italics">Tuck,</hi> or with Lock, 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; 1 Volume, Embossed Roan gilt, Tuck, or with Lock, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item><item>7. STEBBING'S COMMON PRAYER, (including the NEW VERSION OF THE PSALMS,) with 12 Illustrations and a PRESENTATION PLATE, Roan, gilt edges, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Morocco extra, with Illuminated Title and Frontispiece, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item><item>8. STEBBING'S NEW TESTAMENT, with 12 Illustrations and a PRESENTATION PLATE, Roan, gilt edges, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Morocco Extra, &amp;c. &amp;c. 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item></list></div><div type="section"><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In 32mo. A beautiful Diamond Edition, with Thirteen Plates.</opener><head >LE NOUVEAU TESTAMENT DE NOTRE SEIGNEUR JESUS CHRIST;</head><p > the New Testament in French, Revised and Corrected by W. CLAPPERTON, Esq., Cloth, gilt edges, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; Embossed Roan, gilt, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In 32mo. Beautifully printed on fine paper,</opener><head > THE SCRIPTURE CABINET; </head><p > comprehending the Principal Events recorded in the OLD AND NEW TESTAMENTS. Edited by E. BELLCHAMBERS, embellished with above 30 Scriptural Illustrations, besides Maps of Canaan and of Jerusalem, engraved on Steel by LIZARS, Fancy Boards, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Embossed Roan, extra gilt, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >“We strongly recommend this book to teachers, and ail who are charged with the important task of educating <lb/> young persons.”—<hi rend="italics">Monthly Magazine.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In 32mo. Embellished with 320 Portraits, engraved on Steel,</opener><head > BELLCHAMBERS' BIOGRAPHICAL DICTIONARY;</head><p >containing LIVES OF THE MOST EMINENT PERSONS of all Ages and Nations, complete in 4 Volumes, extra Cloth, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Cloth, gilt edges, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Embossed roan, gilt extra, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >“A little library of lives. This is a Biographical Dictionary <hi rend="italics">per se.”—Atlas.</hi></p><p >“This work cannot fail to interest every one. It will be found useful in Schools, and as a book of reference in the library. The lives of the Poet, the Statesman, the Scholar, the Soldier, and the Philosopher of all ages and nations are given, not merely as we see them in the world, but, wherever opportunity offered, as in the case of Napoleon Buonaparte, with reference to their habits and pursuits in private.”—<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p><p >“This is a very excellent Biography, and has been compiled with so much care, that it is an interesting as well as useful book of reference.”—<hi rend="italics">London Courier.</hi></p><p >“One of the neatest and most correct works on Biography that have recently issued from the press. * * * Sufficient information of every eminent character is given, to furnish to the reader a very comprehensive view of his virtues or frailties, his mental strength or weakness, and of the prominent actions of his life. The work is an elegant specimen of typography.”—<hi rend="italics">Manchester Times.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In Post 8vo. a New Edition, enlarged, beautifully printed with Coloured Borders</opener><head >WOODROW'S BIOGRAPHICAL PORTRAIT GALLERY,</head><p >consisting of upwards of 330 PORTRAITS, engraved on Steel in a superior style by Lizars; with DESCRIPTIVE NOTICES, prepared expressly for this Work by G. WOODROW. Printed in corresponding pages with the Portraits; extra Cloth Boards, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Turkey Morocco, extra, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><pb  xml:id="p8"/><opener >In One beautifully got-up Pocket Volume, illustrated by Thirteen Characteristic Steel Engravings, <lb/> from Original Drawings,</opener><head > THE COMPLETE WORKS OF ROBERT BURNS.</head><p >This compact and incomparably cheap Volume embraces all the matter, viz. the POEMS, LETTERS, LIFE, &amp;c. of the Genuine Edition, edited by Dr. CURRIE, and published in Four 8vo. Vols. at 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; extra Cloth Boards, gilt tops, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Roan, extra gilt, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p><p >“This is one of the marvels of Diamond Editions. We have here in one volume eighteens, verbatim, the whole substance of the Prose and Poetry of ‘Scotland's glory and shame,’ Robert Burns, whom genius made immortal, <lb/> and the Scottish nobility made an Exciseman.”—<hi rend="italics">Leigh Hunt.</hi> VIDE <hi rend="italics">True Sun.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In One Volume, Royal 8vo. adapted for the Drawing-room,</opener><head >THE MUSICAL CYCLOPÆDIA;</head><p >comprising a Collection of ENGLISH, SCOTTISH, and IRISH SONGS, with appropriate Music, adapted to the Voice, Pianoforte, &amp;c. by JAMES WILSON, Esq.: to which is prefixed <hi rend="italics">an elaborate Essay on the First Principles of Music</hi> by WILLIAM GRIER, A. M. Fancy Boards, gilt tops, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Fancy Cloth, extra gilt, 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“Here is a well-printed 8vo. work of ENGLISH, SCOTTISH, and IRISH SONGS, with appropriate music; to which is prefixed a scientific, but very intelligent Essay on the First Principles of Music, by W. GRIER, A. M. Those who are acquainted with this delightful science will find the Essay well worth their careful study, while to the learner it will be found extremely serviceable. To the amateur, and especially the admirer of the delightful songs and ballads of the United Kingdom, the collection will be esteemed a perfect treasure. Scarcely one established favourite is omitted from this ample and very judicious collection, and the music, which is adapted to the voice, pianoforte, &amp;c., has been arranged with great taste and skill.”—<hi rend="italics">Weekly Dispatch.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >In 48mo. Fifth Edition,</opener><head >THE DIAMOND GAZETTEER OF GREAT BRITAIN &amp; IRELAND,</head><p > embellished with Three Maps, &amp;c. &amp;c.: to which is now appended, a COMPLETE STRANGER'S GUIDE THROUGH LONDON, &amp;c., with an additional Map of London beautifully engraved by DOWER, extra Cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Turkey Morocco, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“This is truly an example of the <hi rend="italics">multum in parvo;</hi> an excellent, though concise Gazetteer, about the size of a snuff box, with the population of 1831, travelling routes, and useful commercial and statistical tables. We have hardly ever seen so neat and complete a work of this diamond kind: for tourists and travellers it is the very thing.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><p >“This is a very useful and neat little volume, adapted to the waistcoat pocket of the traveller and man of business. It contains a vast deal of information in the smallest imaginable compass—truly a <hi rend="italics">multum in parvo.</hi> It is in short one of those little works which confer so much honor on the spirit and taste of modern publishers, who seem determined to leave the world nothing to desire, that can administer to its information.”—<hi rend="italics">Metropolitan.</hi></p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><opener >A New Edition, 48mo.</opener><head >THE COMMERCIAL VADE MECUM, &amp;c.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">greatly extended and improved,</hi> comprising a greater quantity of Mercantile Information, essential, more or less, to every man in business, than any work of the kind extant. In neat Cloth, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Roan, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p><p >“A neat little well-compiled volume, that no man ought to be without. It contains a great deal of useful information in the smallest possible compass.”—<hi rend="italics">Athenceum.</hi></p><p >“A TOM-THUMB of a book, but as full of commercial knowledge, as if it were a GIANT FOLIO.”—<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p><closer >LONDON:—ALLAN BELL AND CO., WARWICK SQUARE; <lb/> SOLD BY <lb/> T. TEGG AND SON, CHEAPSIDE; ACKERMANN AND CO., STRAND; <lb/> H. WASHBOURNE, SALISBURY SQUARE; <lb/> TEGG AND CO., DUBLIN; FRASER AND CO., AND STIRLING, KENNY &amp; CO., EDINBURGH.<lb/>
Balne, Printer, Gracechurch street.</closer></div></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="p9"/><head >THE POPULAR WORKS OF MR. PETER PARLEY, <lb/> VOYAGER, TRAVELLER, AND STORY-TELLER.</head><p >“IN the evening of a long toilsome life, if a man were to be obliged solemnly to declare what, without any exception, has been the most lovely thing which, on the surface of this earth, it has been his good fortune to witness, I conceive that, without hesitation, he might reply, ‘THE MIND OF A YOUNG CHILD.’</p><p >“We observe with what delight a Child beholds light—colours—flowers—fruit, and every new object that meets his eye; and we all know, that (before his judgment be permitted to interfere) for many years he feels—or rather suffers—a thirst which is almost insatiable.</p><p >“He desires, and very naturally desires, to know what the Moon is?—What are the Stars?—Where the rain, wind, and frost come from?—With innocent simplicity, he asks, what becomes of the light of a candle, when it is blown out? Any story, or any history, he greedily devours.”</p><div type="section"><head >COPY OF A LETTER TO PETER PARLEY.</head><quote><floatingText><body ><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="quote"><salute >TO MR. PETER PARLEY,
HAMPSTEAD,</salute><docDate ><hi rend="italics">January,</hi> 1837.</docDate><p ><hi rend="italics">Somewhere in London.</hi></p><p >“DEAR SIR,—I write this to tell you a story about myself. I have read your “Tales about Animals”—also, your “Tales about Europe, Asia, Africa, and America”—and your “Tales about Great Britain”—likewise your “Tales about the Sea, and the Islands in the Pacific Ocean”—and your “Tales about the Sun, Moon, and Stars”—as well as your “Tales about Greece;” but I want to see you very much. I learnt from your Books a great deal that I did not know before; and I thought if I could see you, you would fell me something more. Besides, I want to know how you look, and hear you talk (for I am told that you are now in London); and I thought you would let me sit down with the little boys and girls that come to hear your stories, and then I should have been very happy.</p><p >Well, I asked my mother to let me go to London and see you; so she put me into the omnibus, and told the driver to put me down at Mr. Parley's house, and bring me back at night. I was very impatient till we got to where the omnibus stops: the driver inquired for your house, but nobody could tell any thing about it. I went to my uncle's, but he was not at home; however, his son, Ben, told me that you lived in the City Road, and that he would go with me and find you. He was the more willing to go, as he wished to get a peep at you himself.</p><p >So we set out, and went up one street and down another, for two hours: we asked about at several places, but nobody could tell us any thing about you. At last we saw an old man coming along with a cane; he was gray and lame, and looked very much like your picture in the little books. Now, thought I, here is Mr. Parley himself! Never was I more happy: I thought I was about to talk with a friend, and that my journey would not be in vain, after all.</p><p >With eager eyes, and with our hands squeezed in each other, Ben and I stood a little aside, waiting till you should come up. I thought I saw your very face, and read in your countenance a welcome smile to my companion and me. I took heart to speak, and asked if his name was Mr. Parley? O dear! how much was I disappointed at the answer! “No,” said the good old man, smiling; “no, my boy; my name is not Parley, it is Williams; though I have been taken for Peter Parley before.” He then walked along, as if he had a great deal of business to do.</p><p >We asked a young man, with a book in his hand, if he knew where Mr. Parley lived. “I wish I did,” said he; “I would go from one end of London to the other to see him.” We then asked a girl, and she said you was in every body's house, yet you was no where to be found. We asked at the post office, they told us we should find out your place of abode by inquiring of Mr. Tegg, in Cheapside.</p><p >We went to Mr. Tegg's warehouse, which was stocked with nice books; but he was not at home. I was, at last, obliged to return home at night, sick at heart and disappointed; and now I write this letter, hoping that it may have better luck in its journey after you than I had myself. Should it reach you, I pray you be so kind as tell me where you live, so that I may some day, during the holidays, go and see you. I am, dear sir, a reader of all your books,</p><signed >FRANK HOWARD.</signed></div></body></floatingText></quote><p > This little friendly letter having come into Messrs. Tegg's hands, it is deemed proper to remark, that although, at No. 73, Cheapside, we converse with Mr. Peter Parley very often, we do not know where he lives. It is said that during his present visit to London (collecting materials for New Tales), he inhabits a little Brown House, in the City Road; but we could never find it. His books are all that he chooses to exhibit to the Public, and perhaps our little friend must be content with them; though we are not at all surprised at his anxiety to see and talk with the good old gentleman who has wound himself round our hearts; in truth, nothing has been so much the subject of our daily thoughts and nightly dreams as PETER PARLEY.</p><closer >LONDON:<lb/>
PRINTED FOR THOMAS TEGG AND SON, WHOLESALE BOOK MARCHANTS, <lb/> NO. 73, CHEAPSIDE: AND SOLD BY TEGG AND CO. DUBLIN; <lb/> R. GRIFFIN AND CO. GLASGOW; AND ALL OTHER BOOKSELLERS.</closer></div><div type="section"><pb  xml:id="p10"/><head >A LIST OF THE POPULAR WORKS OF MR. PETER PARLEY, <lb/> VOYAGER, TRAVELLER, AND STORY-TELLER.</head><p >Comprising Pieces adapted to all stages of the youthful faculties, written in a familiar manner, that they who read may have <hi rend="italics">delight;</hi>—that they who are desirous to commit to memory may have <hi rend="italics">ease;</hi>—and that all into whose hands they come may have <hi rend="italics">profit.</hi> These books may pass from hand to hand in the family circle, and the Parents will not disdain to find amusement in what they are called upon to explain to their Children. Young people will not regard them as things they <hi rend="italics">must</hi> read as a task; but which they will love to consult as a companion and friend; in short, the reading of which may be permitted as a reward of good conduct, but the denial felt as a punishment for bad.</p><p >The encomiums on the Works of Mr. PETER PARLEY are so numerous and so laudatory, that the Publishers find no small difficulty in determining which to present for the attention of the Public. The following are the opinions of some of the first journals of the present day.</p><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >1. TALES OF ANIMALS.</head><p >Comprising QUADRUPEDS, BIRDS, FISHES, REPTILES, and INSECTS. The Sixth Edition, embellished with Two Hundred and Eighty Cuts. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth boards.</p><p >“Natural History is a subject which affords more amusing details and more astonishing facts, and suggests more deep and important reflections, than any other in the whole range of natural science. The matter in this volume is very excellently adapted to the capacity and the wants of children. The style is simple, neat, and perspicuous; the subjects are well selected and happily treated.”</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >2. TALES ABOUT EUROPE, ASIA, AFRICA, and AMERICA.</head><p >A New Edition, with great Additions. Embellished with One Hundred and Thirty-six Cuts. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in fancy boards.</p><p >“The execution of this work, as respects typography and arrangement, is admirable and attractive; the wood cuts are of uncommon excellence. Here is that specific kind of literature for youth, combining information with amusement, which is adapted to counteract the taste for silly tales, awaken a laudable curiosity, and gratify an intelligent youth in a manner and to an extent which mere fiction never can.”</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >3. TALES ABOUT GREAT BRITAIN AND IRELAND.</head><p >A New Edition, greatly improved, and embellished with upwards of One Hundred Cuts. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in fancy boards.</p><p >“These volumes by Peter Parley are now universally admitted into every family, and particularly among the Quakers, whose method of using them is interesting; one of the children reads some interesting fact, the rest sit still and hear; sometimes they are requested to repeat the substance of their reading <hi rend="italics">verbally</hi> (by word of mouth), at others they write it on slates. Thus by these means a habit is formed of attending to what they hear and read; a habit of great importance, but very much neglected. In this way they cultivate the faculties of <hi rend="italics">attention</hi> and <hi rend="italics">memory.</hi> And to relate a story in this way, which we have heard or read, what is it but learning to <hi rend="italics">compose?</hi> More than all, they learn to THINK. And if there be any one thing which should be urged upon the young again and again, it is LEARN TO THINK.”</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >4. TALES ABOUT THE SEA, AND THE ISLANDS IN THE <lb/> PACIFIC OCEAN.</head><p >The Second Edition, enlarged. Embellished with numerous Cuts. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> fancy bds.</p><p >“The recent boisterous weather, and its calamitous results on our shores, make us take up this volume in the hope of soothing our anxiety for those whose ‘march is on the mountain waves, and home upon the deep.’ The charm of its graphic descriptions and fascinating tales fell on us with all the power of enchantment. It is a lively little volume, well adapted for the instruction and amusement of children.”</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >5. TALES ABOUT ANCIENT AND MODERN GREECE.</head><p >Embellished with One Hundred Cuts. Price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> in fancy boards.</p><p >“The works of Peter Parley will need no puffing to insure success, they are really the most ingenious and taking conceits yet developed to aid the cause of education; they are full of simple and substantial food for the juvenile mind, and add to the many claims of the benevolent Peter to the gratitude both of parents and children.”</p></div><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >6. TALES ABOUT THE SUN, MOON, STARS, AND COMETS.</head><p >A New and very greatly improved Edition. With 130 Cuts. Price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> fancy bds.</p><p >“This beautiful volume is extremely well adapted to convey a knowledge of astronomical science to the youthful understanding. Peter is so bland and earnest in his manner, that he never fails to win attention and raise curiosity: he then uses such familiar terms in gratifying it, that the rudiments of astronomy are insensibly impressed upon the mind, and an abstruse science rendered a pleasing study. We wish that Peter had lived and written in the days of our boyhood! The young of both sexes are bound to pray for length of days to so engaging an instructor.</p><p >The Works published under the title of PETER PARLEY'S TALES consist chiefly of matters of fact. Truth and knowledge are presented in a guise as attractive to the youthful mind as that in which fiction has generally been arrayed; and no expense has been spared in getting them up, both as regards the literary or graphic departments, men of first rate abilities having been engaged in the completion of this Series of popular Works for Youth. A Volume will be published about every three Months, until the whole are completed.</p></div></div></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pvii"/><head >SPLENDIDLY ILLUSTRATED WORK.</head><p >CUNNINGHAM'S GALLERY <lb/> OF PICTURES, <lb/> BY THE FIRST MASTERS OF <lb/> ENGLISH AND FOREIGN SCHOOLS, <lb/> FORMING A COMPREHENSIVE DISPLAY <lb/> OF THE WORKS OF <lb/> TITIAN, CARACCI, CLAUDE, CORREGGIO, CUYP, DOMENICHINO, GUIDO, JAN STEEN, MURILLO, OSTADE, PAUL POTTER, G. POUSSIN, RAPHAEL, LEO DA VINCI, REMBRANDT, RUBENS, RUYSDAEL, BERGHEM, HONDE-KOETER, TENIERS, TERBURG, VANDEVELDE, VANDYKE, VANGOOL, PAUL VERONESE, WATTEAU, WOUVERMANS, LAWRENCE, REYNOLDS, WEST, WILKIE, LOUTHERBOURG, WILSON, BEAUMONT, GAINSBOROUGH, MORLAND, MORTIMER, CROME, COPLEY, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p >NEARLY FIFTY OF THEM FOR THE FIRST TIME ENGRAVED, <lb/> (BY SPECIAL PERMISSION) IN THE LINE MANNER BY <lb/> STOTHARD, R. A., WARREN, CHEVALIER, RICHARDSON, WATT, HAVELL, WEDGWOOD, ROBINSON, NICHOLSON, SMITH, W. R. SMITH, RADCLIFFE, HEATH, RADDON, MARR, TAYLOR, WORTHINGTON, KERNOT, SHENTON, MANSELL, DUNCAN, PINE, AND OTHER <lb/> Eminent Artists, <lb/> WITH HISTORICAL AND CRITICAL DISSERTATIONS AND <lb/> BIOGRAPHICAL NOTICES, <lb/> BY ALLAN CUNNINGHAM.</p><p >“A magnificent work, and treasury of instructive criticism.”—<hi rend="italics">Dr. Dibdin's Reminiscences.</hi></p><p >“The most extraordinary production of modern art.”—<hi rend="italics">Standard.</hi></p><p >“A delightful table book for the family circle.”—<hi rend="italics">Suffolk Chronicle.</hi></p><p >“The subjects are the first in art, the engravings most excellently executed.”—<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Journal.</hi></p><p >“We refer to the brilliant clearness and softness, and to the powerful execution of the subjects, as a justification of our unqualified praise.”—<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p><p >LONDON:</p><p >GEORGE AND WILLIAM NICOL, AND HODGSON AND GRAVES, PALL MALL. AND SOLD BY EVERY BOOK AND PRINTSELLER IN THE EMPIRE.</p><p >Rayner and Hodges,]</p><p >[Shoe Lane, Fleet Street.</p></div><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="advertisement"><pb  xml:id="pviii"/><head >J. SANGER'S <lb/> GENUINE PATENT &amp; PUBLIC MEDICINE WAREHOUSE,</head><p >150, OXFORD STREET, OPPOSITE BOND STREET.</p><p >MR. SANGER offers his most respectful acknowledgments to the NOBILITY, GENTRY, and PUBLIC, for the liberal support he has received, and begs to inform them, he continues to adhere most strictly to the same principles on which his House was established (fifty years since) by the late MR. BACON, viz. of vending only such Public Medicines as are made by the Original Inventors, or prepared from the Genuine Recipes of deceased Proprietors.</p><p >Ladies and Gentlemen, residing in the Country, wishing to have their Medicines direct from Mr. S.'s Warehouse, can transmit their orders per post, inclosing a remittance in Cash, or an order on a London Banker, and they may depend on having them most promptly attended to.</p><p >The Proprietors of the following long established and highly esteemed articles have requested MR. SANGER to draw the public attention more directly to them, and he trusts they will be found well deserving a liberal patronage.</p><div type="section"><head >PARKER'S ORIGINAL GRECIAN COMPOUND,</head><p ><hi rend="italics">For changing Red or Gray Hair to Beautiful and Natural Shades of Black or Brown.</hi></p><p >Fifty years' experience has convinced the Public that this Compound is the most effectual article for Dyeing the Hair; the simplicity and ease with which it is applied, requiring very little care and trouble, places it as one of the first articles ever invented for that purpose. Sold in Bottles at 3s. 6d., 6s., and 10s. 6d.</p></div><div type="section"><head >THE ANTI-CALLOSITY, OR RUSSIAN CORN AND BUNION <lb/> PLAISTER, </head><p > Will be found the most certain cure for all callous swellings on the Feet that has ever been presented to the Public. By the use of this Plaister immediate benefit will be found, and in a short time a radical cure will be effected, not by cutting (which is generally attended with danger), but by gradually dispersing the hard or soft corn, and entirely removing those painful throbbings, so severely felt at every change of weather. Sold, with full directions for use, in Boxes, 1s. 1½d. and 2s.</p></div><div type="section"><head >THE BLOOM OF NINON DE L'ENCLOS.</head><p >This incomparable Bloom will be found superior to any thing yet discovered, for rendering the Skin soft, smooth, and beautiful; its wonderful effects in removing Freckles, Morphews, Worms, &amp;c. justly entitle it to that preference so long bestowed on it by the most elegant beauties in this kingdom. It is particularly recommended for the Hands and Arms, bestowing on them a delicacy and whiteness unrivalled. Sold in Bottles at 4s. 6d. each.</p></div><div><head >KEARSLEY'S ORIGINAL AND ONLY GENUINE WIDOW WELCH'S <lb/> FEMALE PILLS,</head><p >So long and justly celebrated for their peculiar virtues, are strongly recommended to the notice of every Lady, having obtained the sanction and approbation of most Gentlemen of the Medical Profession, as a safe and valuable Medicine, in effectually removing obstructions, and relieving all other inconveniences to which the Female Frame is liable, especially those which, at an early period of life, frequently arise from want of Exercise and general debility of the System, they create an appetite, correct indigestion, remove Giddiness and Nervous Headache, and are eminently useful in Windy Disorders, Pains in the Stomach, Shortness of Breath, and Palpitations of the Heart; being perfectly innocent, may be used with safety in all seasons and climates. Sold in Boxes at 2s. 9d.</p><p >CAUTION.—The late CATHERINE KEARSLEY, of Fleet Street, London, Widow, the <hi rend="italics">Legal Proprietor</hi> of the Recipe for making “Welch's Female Pills,” found it absolutely necessary to preserve her property from infringement, and to prevent the Public being imposed on by spurious compositions, to make the following affidavit in the year 1798:—</p><div type="page_of_senior_bio"><head >AFFIDAVIT.</head><p ><hi rend="italics">First.</hi>—That she is in possession of the Recipe for making Welch's Female Pills, which was bequeathed to her by her late Husband.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Second.</hi>—That this Recipe was purchased by her late husband of the Widow Welch, in the year 1787 for a valuable consideration, and with a view for making the medicine for public sale.</p><p ><hi rend="italics">Third.</hi>—That she, CATHERINE KEARSLEY, is also in possession of the Receipt signed by the said Widow Welch, acknowledging the having received the money of the said Mr. George Kearsley, for the purchase of the absolute property of the said Recipe. C. KEARSLEY.</p><p >Sworn at the Mansion House, London, the 3d Day of November, 1798, before me, ANDERSON, <hi rend="italics">Mayor.</hi></p><p >The above articles may also be procured at the following respectable Medicine Venders:—Barclay, Farringon Street; Sutton, Bow Church-yard; Newberry and Edwards, St. Paul's Church-yard; Butler, 4, Cheapside; Johnston, 68, Cornhill; Low, 330, Strand; Gattie and Pierce, New Bond Street, Hawkins, 13, King's Road, Brighton; Shillitoe, Birmingham; Brodie and Co., Canal, Salisbury; and one or more Chemists and Druggists in every country town in England.</p></div></div></div></back></text></TEI>