<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. IV:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 165  K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. IV</title>
<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent> 46 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1849</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>


<change>
<date>2002-11-11, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-27, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>




<titlePage>

<docTitle><titlePart> No. IV. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> AUGUST.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) 
</titlePart></docTitle>

<byline>BY</byline>

<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>

<docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'CLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of Bedding, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest stock and greatest variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES, <lb/> Of which they were the Original Introducers: these Mattresses are made of the finest material, quite equal to the best made in Paris. Also, <lb/> GERMAN SPRING MATTRESSES.</p>
<p>These HEAL and SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are selling at a much lower price than any other house, and can recommend one of them, with a FRENCH MATTRESS on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>And also the PATENT CORK FIBRE MATTRESS. FOR THE PRESERVATION OF LIFE AT SEA.</p>
<p>THE EIDER DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen <hi rend="italics">only</hi> at their House. It is the warmest, the lightest, and the most elegant covering ever introduced, suitable to the <hi rend="italics">Bed,</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Couch,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">Carriage.</hi> All who have travelled on the Continent are aware that no covering produces such extreme warmth with the same weight; so that for Invalids they are perfect luxury. Their <lb/> BED FEATHERS <lb/> are also PURIFIED BY STEAM, WITH PATENT MACHINERY, by which the offensive properties of the quill are evaporated and carried off, without subjecting the Feathers to the unpleasant smell of the stove, to which all Feathers dressed in the ordinary way are liable.</p>
<p>OLD FEATHER-BEDS re-dressed by this process are perfectly freed from all impurities; and, by expanding the Feathers, the bulk is greatly increased, and the Bed consequently rendered much fuller and softer, at 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb.</p>
<p>OLD AND MOTHY MATTRESSES effectually cured and re-made.</p>
<p>Every description of BLANKETS, QUILTS, and SHEETINGS.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S LIST OF BEDDING.</head>
<p>It contains full particulars of WEIGHTS, SIZES, and PRICES, of every description of Bedding, and is so arranged that purchasers are enabled to judge of the articles best suitable to make a comfortable Bed. Sent free by post on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196, (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL,) <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb id="p1" n="[1]"/>
<opener>No. IV.&mdash;AUGUST, 1849.</opener><head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<head>THE LITERARY GAZETTE, <lb/> ESTABLISHED 1817; ENLARGED 1846.</head>
<p>PUBLISHED EVERY SATURDAY AT THE LITERARY GAZETTE OFFICE, <lb/> 300, STRAND, LONDON.</p>
<p>Price Fourpence; Stamped, Fivepence, to go free by Post, <lb/> AND IN TIME FOR TRANSMISSION TO ALL PARTS OF THE COUNTRY BY THE EARLY <lb/> TRAINS OR MORNING MAILS OF THE SAME DAY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">(Monthly Parts, containing Four or Five Numbers, 1s. 4d. or 1s. 8d.)</hi></p>
<p>So long held in high public estimation, the LITERARY GAZETTE continues to afford a complete view and record of the National Literature, Science, and the Fine Arts, with the addition of Foreign Intelligence on the same subjects from every part of the Civilised World. It has, also, of late, made liberal improvements in the various branches which its plan has embraced. In every department of Literature peculiar to Learned Research, Medical Practice, Philosophy, important Works in Foreign Languages, &amp;c. &amp;c., in addition to Publications of more general character:&mdash;in Science, Voyages, Travels, History, Poetry, the Fine Arts, Dramatic and Musical Criticism, Gentlemen of ability and experience in these matters have been incorporated with the regular staff of the JOURNAL OF BELLES LETTERS, and under the same Editorial supervision which has, from 1817, sustained its Reputation and Influence, and it is consequently hoped that increased energy and talent will be manifest throughout the whole, and a Weekly Sheet acknowledged which may justly challenge comparison with the greatest and best of Periodical Publications.</p>
<p>During the current year, the most interesting Papers on the Earliest Records of the Human Race, Philological investigations of the highest importance, and Antiquarian discoveries and proceedings at home and abroad, have formed a very prominent feature in nearly every Weekly Number.</p>
<p>Of these, and all other Literary matters, this Journal is, in fact, the only comprehensive Exponent in the Periodical Press; and Members of Literary and Scientific Societies, as well as intelligent readers of every class, who reside in remote parts, may through its columns be promptly made acquainted with everything that is done or heard of at Head Quarters. For rising families it is peculiarly adapted, as it conveys instruction of every practical and intellectual kind, mingled with the more amusing literature which is calculated to attract and interest youthful minds, till they are filled with the information and knowledge of the passing time.</p>
<p>May be ordered of any Bookseller or Newsman in Town or Country, or at the LITERARY GAZETTE Publishing and Advertising Office, No. 300, Strand, London; where also the yearly subscription of 21s. 8d., or, half-yearly, 10s. 10d. may be paid, by Post-Office Order or Town reference, and the LITERARY GAZETTE, stamped for the Country or Colonies, will be regularly forwarded by post; or, if in Monthly Parts, at 17s. 4d. per annum, with the monthly periodicals.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In the Press, and shortly will be Published,</hi></opener><head>THE SOLITARY, AND OTHER POEMS, <lb/> WITH THE CAVALIER. A PLAY.</head>
<p>BY CHARLES WHITEHEAD.</p>
<closer>LONDON: RICHARD BENTLEY, NEW BURLINGTON STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p><hi rend="italics">This Day is Published, in small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</p>
<p>A Fairy Tale for Little People.</p>
<p>BY MARK LEMON.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The moral of the Tale is unexceptionable, and one that is always welcome, and the thanks of that important minikin public for which the great Newbury laboured in days of yore, are due to Mr. Lemon for this little book.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This Day is Published, in Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> A SHORT INQUIRY INTO <lb/> THE HISTORY OF AGRICULTURE, <lb/> IN ANCIENT, MEDI&AElig;VAL, AND MODERN TIMES.</p>
<p>BY CHANDOS WREN HOSKYNS, ESQ.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This Day is Published, in Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE <lb/> POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</p>
<p>REVISED AND ARRANGED EXPRESSLY FOR YOUNG PERSONS AND SCHOOLS.</p>
<p>BY W. C. MACREADY.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FOR THE USE OF SCHOOLS AND YOUNG PERSONS.</head>
<p>A Third Edition of the Epitome of <lb/> ALISON'S HISTORY OF EUROPE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Price Seven Shillings and Sixpence, strongly bound in cloth.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We perceive the traces of some masterly hand employed upon the laborious and responsible task of selection and compression. . . . . A work which cannot be too widely disseminated, but especially adapted for those to whose service it professes to be dedicated&mdash;schools and young persons,&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<closer>WILLIAM BLACKWOOD AND SONS, EDINBURGH AND LONDON.</closer>
<trailer>Sold by all Booksellers.</trailer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now Ready, Volume I.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth.</hi></opener>
<head>CONFESSIONS OF CON CREGAN, <lb/> THE IRISH GIL BLAS.</head>
<p>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS ON WOOD AND STEEL, BY H. K. BROWNE (PHIZ).</p>
<p>&ldquo;The manner of the writer happily corresponds with his matter. An easier flow of narration, without obtrusive familiarity, or a yet more offensive untidiness, does not occur to us than we find in Con Cregan.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athen&oelig;um.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: WM. S. ORR AND CO., AMEN CORNER.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In One Large Volume, with Forty Original Designs, engraved on Wood, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF <lb/> OLIVER GOLDSMITH.</head>
<p>A BIOGRAPHY: IN FOUR BOOKS.</p>
<list>
<item>BOOK<lb/>1. THE SIZAR, STUDENT, TRAVELLER, APOTHECARY'S JOURNEYMAN, USHER, AND POOR PHYSICIAN.</item>
<item>2. AUTHORSHIP BY COMPULSION.</item>
<item>3. AUTHORSHIP BY CHOICE.</item>
<item>4. THE FRIEND OF JOHNSON, BURKE AND REYNOLDS: DRAMATIST, NOVELIST, AND POET.</item>
</list>
<p>BY JOHN FORSTER, <lb/> Of the Inner Temple, Barrister, Author of &ldquo;Lives of Statesmen of the Commonwealth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A fitting, and we think, a permanent companion to the works of the author whose career it commemorates:&mdash;a gentle but a manly apology for the life, which it tracks through each pathetic transition of light and shadow: written in that spirit of which Goldsmith himself would have approved&mdash;pleasing while it instructs us, mild without tameness, earnest without acerbity.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p>
<closer>Bradbury &amp; Evans, 11, Bouverie Street; and Chapman &amp; Hall, 186, Strand.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>ELECTRO-PLATE SUPERSEDED BY RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK'S PURE NICKEL SILVER.&mdash;</head><p>This Incomparable Metal possesses all the richness of Silver in appearance, with all its durability and hardness, and is warranted to stand the test of aquafortis.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="7">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Thread Pattern. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Victoria and King's Pattern. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 25 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>R. &amp; J. S. beg to caution the public against several spurious imitations of their articles. The genuine are to be had only at their establishment, 336, Strand, where may be inspected the most extensive assortment of Furnishing Ironmongery in London, at prices 30 per cent, under any other house; the money returned for any article not approved of. Their book, containing drawings and prices of every article, may be had gratis, or sent free to any part. RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK, 336, Strand, opposite Somerset House, established in 1818.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FORD'S <lb/> &lsquo;EUREKA&rsquo; <lb/>SHIRT</head><p>185. STRAND.</p>
<p>The attention of gentlemen is solicited to this truly unique article, being the only perfect fitting shirt made.</p>
<p>Six very superior Shirts for 30<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> also all the new patterns in Coloured Shirts, six for 27<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Detailed catalogues, with patterns and directions for self-measurement, sent post-free.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TOILET of BEAUTY</head><p>furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy, and sustaining its brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.&mdash;&ldquo;Robert Shaw, London,&rdquo; is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>AMPUTATION AGAIN PREVENTED BY HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>Extract of a letter from Mr. S. Smith, 69, Capel Street, Dublin, dated March 13, 1849:&mdash;&ldquo;To Professor Holloway.&mdash;Dear Sir,&mdash;I think it only my duty to inform you and the public of the wonderful cure your Ointment and Pills have effected on me. For three years I had a dreadful wound in my leg. I tried all the faculty in this city, but to no purpose; they informed me that nothing could save my life but amputation. I was then advised by a celebrated doctor to use your remedies, which in a brief period have healed my leg, and made it as strong as it formerly was.&rdquo; Sold by all vendors of Medicine, and at Professor Holloway's establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>COPY YOUR LETTERS.</head>
<p>No man of business should write a letter, or transmit any document of importance, without keeping a copy of it. The additional labour of copying by hand, caused by the introduction of cheap postage, may be entirely saved; as twenty letters may be copied in five minutes; by WATERLOW &amp; SONS' <lb/> Improved Patent Copying Machines, <lb/> The Working Parts manufactured of Steel, and finished with the greatest accuracy.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="13">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Lever Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Mach. wrt. iron beam. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Damping Boxes. </cell>
<cell> Copying Books. 4to, Type-Paged. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> LARGE 4to </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 0s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 10s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 3s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 15s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11s. </cell>
<cell> 500 leaves, 8s. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> FOOLSCAP FOLIO </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 750 leaves, 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> POST FOLIO </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 1,000 leaves, 12 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The above Presses, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and <lb/> will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p>
<closer>WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, &amp; 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>USE <lb/> KIRBY, BEARD &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">O'S</hi>
<lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES. <lb/></p>
<p>Sold by every Draper, &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>TO secure Household Linen and Wearing Apparel against Loss or Mistake, use</opener><head>BOND'S PERMANENT MARKING INK.</head>
<p>The Original, and by far the best, requiring no preparation.</p>
<p>Prepared by the Inventor, JOHN BOND, 28, Long Lane, West Smithfield, City, and sold by most Chemists, Stationers, and Medicine Vendors.</p>
<p>Price One Shilling a bottle.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However, debilitated the system, or deep rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>UNDER HER MAJESTY'S ROYAL LETTERS PATENT.</opener><head>LOCOCK'S FEMALE PILLS.</head>
<p>SOLD BY ALL ESTABLISHED MEDICINE VENDORS.</p>
<p>LOCOCK'S FEMALE PILLS.<lb/>PRICE 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>A single trial of this Medicine ever proves it &ldquo;the Best and Safest Medicine for Ladies.&rdquo; Imitation in fanciful shapes and all counterfeits, must be guarded against, by observing the words &ldquo;Locock's Female Pills,&rdquo; engraved on the government stamp of the original medicine, and pasted outside each box.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p>and all other medicines of a nauseous character may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT ORGANIC CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHEE, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p>
<p>Ask for the Patent Flexible Capsules.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<opener>Under Royal Patronage.<lb/>INSTANT RELIEF AND A RAPID CURE OF ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, <lb/> COUGHS, COLDS, AND ALL DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS, <lb/> ARE INSURED BY</opener><head>DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated Testimonials, may be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">had from every Agent.</hi></p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>Important Testimonials.</head>
<opener>
<dateline>Mr. W. J. Cooper, Surgeon, Canterbury, <lb/> Medical Hall, Jan. 1, 1845.</dateline>
</opener><p>Gentlemen,&mdash;Having heard your Wafers very highly spoken of by several persons who had taken them with decided benefit, I have recommended them in several cases of confirmed asthma, and their good effects have been truly astonishing. I now recommend them in all obstinate cases.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) W. J. COOPER, Surgeon.</signed>
</closer>
</div3><div3>
<head>Cure of a Fourteen Years' Asthmatic <lb/> Cough.</head>
<opener>
<dateline>Nov. 3, 1848.</dateline>
</opener><p>I, Thomas Carter, Egremont, Cheshire, had an asthmatic cough for fourteen years; nothing ever gave me relief until I commenced taking Dr. Locock's Pulmonic Wafers, three boxes of which have entirely cured me.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) THOMAS CARTER.</signed>
</closer><trailer>Witness, Mr. Geo. H. Howell, <lb/> Chemist, Dale-street, Liverpool.</trailer>
</div3><div3>
<p>TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p>
<p>They have a pleasant taste. Price 1s. 1&frac12;d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p>
<p>AGENTS: DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors.</p>
<p>PROTECTED BY ROYAL LETTERS PATENT. <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S <lb/> (HAVE NO TASTE OF MEDICINE.) <lb/> FEMALE WAFERS.</p>
<p>PRICE, 1s. 1&frac12;d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p>
<p>The only Medicine recommended to be <lb/> taken by Females!</p>
<p>BEWARE OF IMITATIONS! <lb/> Unprincipled Persons Counterfeit this medicine in the form of PILLS, &amp;c. Purchasers must therefore observe that none are Genuine but &ldquo;WAFERS,&rdquo; and that the words <lb/> &ldquo;DR. LOCOCK'S WAFERS&rdquo; <lb/> are in the Stamp outside each Box.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">There are various Counterfeit Medicines, having words on the Stamp so</hi> NEARLY RESEMBLING THESE, <hi rend="italics">as to mislead the unwary. Purchasers must therefore strictly observe the above Caution.</hi></p>
<p>Prepared only by the Proprietor's Agents, DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride Lane, Fleet St., London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors.</p>
<p>DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS FORTIFY the CONSTITUTION at all PERIODS of LIFE, and IN ALL NERVOUS AFFECTIONS act like a Charm. They remove HEAVINESS, FATIGUE ON SLIGHT EXERTION, PALPITATION OF THE HEART, LOWNESS OF SPIRITS, WEAKNESS, and ALLAY PAIN.</p>
<p>They create Appetite, and remove INDIGESTION, HEART-BURN, WIND, HEAD-ACHES, GIDDINESS, &amp;c.</p>
<p>In HYSTERICAL DISEASES, a proper perseverance in the use of this Medicine will be found to effect a cure after all other means have failed.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Full Directions are given with every Box.</hi></p>
<p>NOTE.&mdash;These Wafers do not contain any Mineral, and may be taken either dissolved in water, or whole.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>TRELOAR'S COCOA-NUT FIBRE WAREHOUSE,</head><p>42, LUDGATE HILL.</p>
<p>The articles made from COCOA-NUT FIBRE consist of Matting, Hearth-rugs, Door-mats, Mattresses, Cushions, Hassocks, Netting for sheep folds, Clothes-lines, Cordage, Scrubbing Brushes, and Brushes for stable use. To ensure good quality at the lowest prices, apply direct to the Manufacturer, T. TRELOAR, 42, Ludgate Hill.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE INVISIBLE VENTILATING HEADS OF HAIR.</head>
<p>ROSS &amp; SON'S METHOD OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Round of the Head </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From Ear to Ear </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From Forehead to Poll </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>These inimitable works of art, for both Ladies and Gentlemen, from One Guinea-and-a-half upwards.</p>
<p>THE ATRAPILATORY, OR LIQUID HAIR DYE, the only Dye that really answers for all colours. Ross &amp; SONS can recommend the above Dye as infallible.</p>
<p>BOTANIC WATER AND BEAR'S GREASE. When the Hair is becoming thin, and falling off, the only effectual remedy is the use of the above-named articles, applied alternately; the Botanic Water to cleanse and stimulate, and the Bear's Grease to nourish it.</p>
<p>THE NEW TOOTH-PICK TOOTH-BRUSH, thoroughly cleansing between the Teeth when used up and down, and polishing the surface when used crossways, the hair warranted never to come out. In four strengths, viz., No. 1, hard; No. 2, less hard; No. 3, medium; No. 4, soft.</p>
<p>THE DOUBLE ANTI-PRESSURE NAIL BRUSH; THE TRIPLE HAIR BRUSH; THE MEDIUM SHAVING BRUSH; THE &ldquo;RENOVATOR&rdquo; CLOTHES BRUSH. These articles being the inventions of Ross &amp; SONS, the public are requested to observe their names stamped on each.</p>
<p>If you wish to avoid all the torture &ldquo;which Shaving has entailed upon your chins,&rdquo; try ROSS &amp; SON'S RAILWAY STROP AND RAZOR, and if Travellers, supply yourselves with the ROSSIAN DRESSING CASE, which contains the largest number of conveniences in the smallest compass.</p>
<closer>Address, ROSS &amp; SON'S, 119 and 120, Bishopsgate Street, London.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head>
<p>THE economy both in the cost and wear of this Umbrella has been freely borne out by the experience of these last 18 months, during which time so many thousands have been sold. They may be obtained of most Umbrella Dealers in the United Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Patentees, 140, Regent-street, <lb/> 94, Fleet-street, <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</p>
<p>CHEAP SILK UMBRELLAS, from 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p>
<p>N.B. Certain parties who are not licensed by the Patentees of the Alpaca Umbrella have been selling an inferior imitation of it. The public are therefore requested to observe that the Patentees' names are affixed inside each Umbrella.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>WARREN'S SKETCHES OF CHARACTER.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, WESTMINSTER, who has become so celebrated for his DELINEATION OF THE CHARACTER of Individuals, as derived from their HANDWRITING, continues his interesting experiments. Specimens of writing, with the fee of 13 postage stamps, and a mention of the applicant's sex, to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, ONLY &pound;1 10s.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<opener>NO MORE PILLS NOR ANY OTHER MEDICINE.&mdash;DYSPEPSIA (INDIGESTION), HABITUAL CONSTIPATION, DIARRH&OElig;A, NERVOUS, BILIOUS, LIVER COMPLAINTS and GENERAL DEBILITY, effectually removed, without Pills or any other Medicine, by</opener><head>DU BARRY'S REVALENTA ARABICA FOOD.</head>
<p>Analysis by the celebrated Professor of Chemistry and Analytical Chemist, Andrew Ure, M.D., F.R.S., &amp;c. :&mdash; <lb/> &ldquo;London, 24, Bloomsbury-square, June 8, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hereby certify that having examined &lsquo;Du Barry's Revalenta Arabica,&rsquo; I find it to be a pure vegetable Farina, perfectly wholesome, easily digestible, likely to promote a healthy action of the stomach and bowels, and thereby to counteract dyspepsia, constipation, and their nervous consequences.</p>
<p>&ldquo;ANDREW URE, M.D., F.R.S., &amp;c., Analytical Chemist.&rdquo; <lb/> This light delicious farinaceous Breakfast Food, without medicine of any kind, without inconvenience, and without expense, as it saves other more costly food, speedily and permanently removes Dyspepsia (Indigestion), Constipation, and Diarrh&oelig;a, the main causes of Nervousness, Biliousness, Liver Complaint, Flatulency, Distension, Palpitation of the Heart, Nervous Headache, Deafness, Noises in the Head and Ears, Pains in almost every part of the Body, Inflammation and Cancer in the Stomach. Asthma, Eruptions on the Skin, Scrofula, Consumption, Dropsy, Rheumatism, Gout, Heartburn, Nausea and Vomiting during Pregnancy, after Eating, or at Sea, Low Spirits, Spasms, Spleen, General Debility, Cough, Inquietude, Sleeplessness, Involuntary Blushing, Tremors, Dislike to Society, Unfitness for Study, Loss of Memory, Delusions, Vertigo, Blood to the Head, Exhaustion, Melancholy, Groundless Fear, Indecision, Wretchedness, Thoughts of Self-Destruction, and Insanity. The best food for infants and invalids generally, as, unlike arrowroot and other artificial substances, it never turns acid on the weakest stomach, but imparts a healthy relish for lunch and dinner, and restores the faculty of digestion, and nervous and muscular energy, to the most enfeebled.</p><div3>
<head>CASES.</head>
<p>From the Right Hon. the Lord Stuart De Decies. &ldquo;Dromana, Capoquin, County Waterford, Feb. 15, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen, I have derived much benefit from the use of the &lsquo;Revalenta Food.&rsquo; It is only due to yourselves and to the public to state, that you are at liberty to make any use of this communication which you may think proper. I remain, gentlemen, your obedient servant, <lb/> &ldquo;STUART DE DECIES.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;4, Park Walk, Little Chelsea, London, Oct. 2, 1848.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twenty-seven years' dyspepsia, from which I had suffered great pain and inconvenience, and for which I had consulted the advice of many, has been effectually removed by your excellent &lsquo;Revalenta Arabica Food&rsquo; in six weeks' time, &amp;c. </p>
<p>&ldquo;PARKER D. BINGHAM, Captain, Royal Navy.&rdquo; <lb/> William Hunt, Esq., Barrister-at-law, King's College, Cambridge, has thanked us for the general benefit he has derived from our &ldquo;Revalenta Arabica Food.&rdquo; At the age of eighty-three he obtained effectual relief from functional disorders of long standing, and overcame a recent attack of erysipelas, by confining his diet entirely to this excellent Food,&mdash;to the exclusion of all other remedies. We extract the following lines from one of his last letters :&mdash; <lb/> &ldquo;I now consider myself a stranger to all complaints, excepting a hearty old age. I am as well as ever I was, and quite free from the vexatious and troublesome annoyance of an eruption of the skin, from which I had suffered for years, and which my medical attendant had declared incurable at my time of life.&rdquo;<lb/> &ldquo;12, Patrick-street, Cork, 4th April, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Respected Friends,&mdash;I have given your &lsquo;Arabica Food&rsquo; to a girl of fifteen, who during the last seven years had not been a day without vomiting fifteen or sixteen times, and sometimes oftener. The fourth day after she commenced your Food, vomiting ceased altogether, and she has not thrown up since; her health is improving wonderfully. </p>
<p>&ldquo;WILLIAM MARTIN.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Bromley, Middlesex, March 31st, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;The lady for whom I ordered your Food is six months advanced in pregnancy, and was suffering severely from indigestion, constipation, throwing up her meals shortly after eating them, having a great deal of heartburn, and being constantly obliged to resort to physic or the enema, and sometimes both. I am happy to inform you that your Food produced immediate relief. She has never been sick since, had but little heartburn, and the functions are more regular,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
<p>&ldquo;THOS. WOODHOUSE.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Bromley, Middlesex, 11th June, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear Sirs,&mdash;I am very happy to have to inform you, that on Tuesday last the lady mentioned in my previous letter was safely delivered of a son; and you will no doubt be glad to learn, that they are both doing exceedingly well. She has had a much better &lsquo;time&rsquo; than formerly, and the child is very strong and healthy. Not satisfied with any thanks that I can give you, she begs I will express to you her gratitude for this favourable change, which she entirely attributes to the &lsquo;Revalenta,&rsquo; and to following strictly the advice which you have been so very kind as to give her from time to time.&mdash;I am, gentlemen, very truly yours, <lb/> &ldquo;THOMAS WOODHOUSE.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;3, Sidney Terrace, Reading, Berks, Dec. 3, 1847.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;I am happy to be able to inform you that the person for whom the former quantity was procured has derived very great benefit from its use; distressing symptoms of long standing have been removed, and a feeling of restored health induced. </p>
<p>&ldquo;JAMES SHORLAND, late Surgeon, 96th Regiment.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;21, Broad Street, Golden Square, London, Nov. 20, 1847.</p>
<p>(Details of nineteen years' dyspepsia, nervousness, sickness at the stomach, with spasms and vomiting, and liver complaint, and three weeks' Revalenta treatment.)&mdash;&ldquo;I humbly and sincerely thank God, and yourselves, as His instruments, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;ISABELLA GRELLIERE.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Athol-street, Perth, May 2, 1848.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some time has now elapsed since the lady (who had been an invalid for thirteen years from want of digestion, accompanied with cough and general prostration of strength) for whom I procured your &lsquo;Arabica&rsquo; Food, has been using it daily as directed, and I am happy to say that it has produced a most salutary change in her system, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;JAMES PORTER.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Haddington, East Lothian, March, 3, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear Sir,&mdash;Your excellent &lsquo;Arabica Food&rsquo; has completely restored my stomach, nerves, and liver, which had been disordered for nearly twenty years past, and my health is now everything I could wish, and has been so these three months past, &amp;c. </p>
<p>&ldquo;ANDREW FRASER.&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;2, Princess-street, Manchester, 3rd Month, 19th, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Respected Friend.&mdash;........ I think no one who had received or seen so much good and comfort result from it as in my mother's case, would be without it in sickness. Thou art at liberty to use this letter as thou thinkest best, and I will cheerfully answer any inquiries.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am, thy friend, <lb/>&ldquo;EDWARD CORBETT, Sanitary Engineer,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>In canisters of 4 lb. at 11<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> 10lb. at 22<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> super-refined quality, 8lb., 33<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and 4lb. 22<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> suitably packed for all climates, 8lb. and 10lb. canisters forwarded by DU BARRY and Co., on receipt of Post-office or bankers' orders (carriage free) to any town or railroad station connected by rail with London, or to any port in Scotland or Ireland connected with London by steam or sailing vessels. Shipments abroad attended to. Their amount may be sent in a bill or banker's order on London, or placed to the credit of Messrs. DU BARRY and Co.'s account at Messrs. COUTTS and Co., Bankers, London.</p>
<p>A popular Treatise on &ldquo;Indigestion and Constipation,&rdquo; entitled &ldquo;The Natural Regenerator of the Digestive Organs without Medicine,&rdquo; by De BARRY and Co., forwarded by them, post free, on receipt of letter stamps for 8<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> also at WHITTAKER and Co.; SIMPKIN, MARSHALL and Co.; and all Booksellers.</p>
<closer>Agents and the Trade will please apply to Messrs. DU BARRY and Co., 127, New Bond-street, London.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Mrs. Gummidge casts a damp on our departure.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">My magnificent order at the public-house.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>


<div1 type="narrative">
<pb id="p97" n="97"/>
<head>[THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head>


<div2 type="chapter"><head>CHAPTER X. <lb/> I BECOME NEGLECTED, AND AM PROVIDED FOR.</head>
<p>THE first act of business Miss Murdstone performed when the day of the solemnity was over, and light was freely admitted into the house, was to give Peggotty a month's warning. Much as Peggotty would have disliked such a service, I believe she would have retained it, for my sake, in preference to the best upon earth. She told me we must part, and told me why; and we condoled with one another, in all sincerity.</p>
<p>As to me or my future, not a word was said, or a step taken. Happy they would have been, I dare say, if they could have dismissed me at a month's warning too. I mustered courage once, to ask Miss Murdstone when I was going back to school; and she answered dryly, she believed I was not going back at all. I was told nothing more. I was very anxious to know what was going to be done with me, and so was Peggotty; but neither she nor I could pick up any information on the subject.</p>
<p>There was one change in my condition, which, while it relieved me of a great deal of present uneasiness, might have made me, if I had been capable of considering it closely, yet more uncomfortable about the future. It was this. The constraint that had been put upon me, was quite abandoned. I was so far from being required to keep my dull post in the parlor, that on several occasions, when I took my seat there, Miss Murdstone frowned to me to go away. I was so far from being warned off from Peggotty's society, that, provided I was not in Mr. Murdstone's, I was never sought out or inquired for. At first I was in daily dread of his taking my education in hand again, or of Miss Murdstone's devoting herself to it; but I soon began to think that such fears were groundless, and that all I had to anticipate was neglect.</p>
<p>I do not conceive that this discovery gave me much pain then. I was still giddy with the shock of my mother's death, and in a kind of stunned state as to all tributary things. I can recollect, indeed, to have speculated, at odd times, on the possibility of my not being taught any more, or cared for any more; and growing up to be a shabby moody man, lounging an idle life away, about the village; as well as on the feasibility of my getting rid of this picture by going away somewhere, like the hero in a story, to seek my fortune: but these were transient visions, day dreams I sat looking at sometimes, as if they were faintly painted or written on the wall of my room, and which, as they melted away, left the wall blank again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Peggotty,&rdquo; I said in a thoughtful whisper, one evening, when I was warming my hands at the kitchen fire, &ldquo;Mr. Murdstone likes me less than he used to. He never liked me much, Peggotty; but he would rather not even see me now, if he can help it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps it's his sorrow,&rdquo; said Peggotty, stroking my hair.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure, Peggotty, I am sorry too. If I believed it was his sorrow, I should not think of it at all. But it's not that; oh, no, it's not that.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="98" id="p98"/>
<p>&ldquo;How do you know it's not that?&rdquo; said Peggotty, after a silence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, his sorrow is another and quite a different thing. He is sorry at this moment, sitting by the fireside with Miss Murdstone; but if I was to go in, Peggotty, he would be something besides.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What would he be?&rdquo; said Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Angry,&rdquo; I answered, with an involuntary imitation of his dark frown.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If he was only sorry, he wouldn't look at me as he does. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> am only sorry, and it makes me feel kinder.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Peggotty said nothing for a little while; and I warmed my hands, as silent as she.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Davy,&rdquo; she said at length.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Peggotty?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have tried, my dear, all ways I could think of&mdash;all the ways there are, and all the ways there ain't, in short&mdash;to get a suitable service here, in Blunderstone; but there's no such a thing, my love.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what do you mean to do, Peggotty?&rdquo; says I, wistfully. &ldquo;Do you mean to go and seek your fortune?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I expect I shall be forced to go to Yarmouth,&rdquo; replied Peggotty, &ldquo;and live there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You might have gone farther off,&rdquo; I said, brightening a little, &ldquo;and been as bad as lost. I shall see you sometimes, my dear old Peggotty, there. You won't be quite at the other end of the world, will you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Contrary ways, please God!&rdquo; cried Peggotty, with great animation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As long as you are here, my pet, I shall come over every week of my life to see you. One day, every week of my life!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt a great weight taken off my mind by this promise; but even this was not all, for Peggotty went on to say:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'm a going, Davy, you see, to my brother's, first for another fortnight's visit&mdash;just till I have had time to look about me, and get to be something like myself again. Now, I have been thinking, that perhaps, as they don't want you here at present, you might be let to go along with me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If anything, short of being in a different relation to every one about me, Peggotty excepted, could have given me a sense of pleasure at that time, it would have been this project of all others. The idea of being again surrounded by those honest faces, shining welcome on me; of renewing the peacefulness of the sweet Sunday morning, when the bells were ringing, the stones dropping in the water, and the shadowy ships breaking through the mist; of roaming up and down with little Em'ly, telling her my troubles, and finding charms against them in the shells and pebbles on the beach; made a calm in my heart. It was ruffled next moment, to be sure, by a doubt of Miss Murdstone's giving her consent; but even that was set at rest soon, for she came out to take an evening grope in the store-closet while we were yet in conversation, and Peggotty, with a boldness that amazed me, broached the topic on the spot.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The boy will be idle there,&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, looking into a pickle-jar, &ldquo;and idleness is the root of all evil. But, to be sure, he would be idle here&mdash;or anywhere, in my opinion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Peggotty had an angry answer ready, I could see; but she swallowed it for my sake, and remained silent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Humph!&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, still keeping her eye on the pickles;
<pb n="99" id="p99"/>
&ldquo;it is of more importance than anything else&mdash;it is of paramount importance&mdash;that my brother should not be disturbed or made uncomfortable. I suppose I had better say yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thanked her, without making any demonstration of joy, lest it should induce her to withdraw her assent. Nor could I help thinking this a prudent course, when she looked at me out of the pickle-jar, with as great an access of sourness as if her black eyes had absorbed its contents. However, the permission was given, and was never retracted; for when the month was out, Peggotty and I were ready to depart.</p>
<p>Mr. Barkis came into the house for Peggotty's boxes. I had never known him to pass the garden-gate before, but on this occasion he came into the house. And he gave me a look as he shouldered the largest box and went out, which I thought had meaning in it, if meaning could ever be said to find its way into Mr. Barkis's visage.</p>
<p>Peggotty was naturally in low spirits at leaving what had been her home so many years, and where the two strong attachments of her life&mdash;for my mother and myself&mdash;had been formed. She had been walking in the churchyard, too, very early; and she got into the cart, and sat in it with her handkerchief at her eyes.</p>
<p>So long as she remained in this condition, Mr. Barkis gave no sign of life whatever. He sat in his usual place and attitude, like a great stuffed figure. But when she began to look about her, and to speak to me, he nodded his head and grinned several times. I have not the least notion at whom, or what he meant by it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's a beautiful day, Mr. Barkis!&rdquo; I said, as an act of politeness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It ain't bad,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, who generally qualified his speech, and rarely committed himself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Peggotty is quite comfortable now, Mr. Barkis,&rdquo; I remarked, for his satisfaction.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is she, though!&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis.</p>
<p>After reflecting about it, with a sagacious air, Mr. Barkis eyed her, and said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Are</hi> you pretty comfortable?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Peggotty laughed, and answered in the affirmative.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But really and truly, you know. Are you?&rdquo; growled Mr. Barkis, sliding nearer to her on the seat, and nudging her with his elbow. &ldquo;Are you? Really and truly pretty comfortable? Are you? Eh?&rdquo; At each of these inquiries Mr. Barkis shuffled nearer to her, and gave her another nudge; so that at last we were all crowded together in the left-hand corner of the cart, and I was so squeezed that I could hardly bear it.</p>
<p>Peggotty calling his attention to my sufferings, Mr. Barkis gave me a little more room at once, and got away by degrees. But I could not help observing that he seemed to think he had hit upon a wonderful expedient for expressing himself in a neat, agreeable, and pointed manner, without the inconvenience of inventing conversation. He manifestly chuckled over it for some time. By-and-by he turned to Peggotty again, and repeating, &ldquo;Are you pretty comfortable though?&rdquo; bore down upon us as before, until the breath was nearly wedged out of my body. By-and-by he made another descent upon us with the same inquiry, and the same result. At length, I got up whenever I saw him
<pb n="100" id="p100"/>
coming, and standing on the footboard, pretended to look at the prospect; after which I did very well.</p>
<p>He was so polite as to stop at a public-house, expressly on our account, and entertain us with broiled mutton and beer. Even when Peggotty was in the act of drinking, he was seized with one of those approaches, and almost choked her. But as we drew nearer to the end of our journey, he had more to do and less time for gallantry; and when we got on Yarmouth pavement, we were all too much shaken and jolted, I apprehend, to have any leisure for any thing else.</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty and Ham waited for us at the old place. They received me and Peggotty in an affectionate manner, and shook hands with Mr. Barkis, who, with his hat on the very back of his head, and a shame-faced leer upon his countenance, and pervading his very legs, presented but a vacant appearance, I thought. They each took one of Peggotty's trunks, and we were going away, when Mr. Barkis solemnly made a sign to me with his forefinger to come under an archway.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I say,&rdquo; growled Mr. Barkis, &ldquo;it was all right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I looked up into his face, and answered, with an attempt to be very profound: &ldquo;Oh!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It didn't come to a end there,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, nodding confidentially. &ldquo;It was all right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Again I answered: &ldquo;Oh!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You know who was willin',&rdquo; said my friend. &ldquo;It was Barkis, and Barkis only.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I nodded assent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's all right,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, shaking hands; &ldquo;I'm a friend of your'n. You made it all right, first. It's all right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In his attempts to be particularly lucid, Mr. Barkis was so extremely mysterious, that I might have stood looking in his face for an hour, and most assuredly should have got as much information out of it as out of the face of a clock that had stopped, but for Peggotty's calling me away. As we were going along, she asked me what he had said; and I told her he had said it was all right.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Like his impudence,&rdquo; said Peggotty, &ldquo;but I don't mind that! Davy dear, what should you think if I was to think of being married?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why&mdash;I suppose you would like me as much then, Peggotty, as you do now?&rdquo; I returned, after a little consideration.</p>
<p>Greatly to the astonishment of the passengers in the street, as well as of her relations going on before, the good soul was obliged to stop and embrace me on the spot, with many protestations of her unalterable love.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tell me what should you say, darling?&rdquo; she asked again, when this was over, and we were walking on.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you were thinking of being married&mdash;to Mr. Barkis, Peggotty?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should think it would be a very good thing. For then you know, Peggotty, you would always have the horse and cart to bring you over to see me, and could come for nothing, and be sure of coming.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The sense of the dear!&rdquo; cried Peggotty. &ldquo;What I have been thinking of, this month back! Yes, my precious; and I think I should be more independent altogether, you see; let alone my working with a better heart in my own house, than I could in anybody else's now. I
<pb n="101" id="p101"/>
don't know what I might be fit for, now, as a servant to a stranger. And I shall be always near my pretty's resting-place,&rdquo; said Peggotty musing, &ldquo;and able to see it when I like; and when <hi rend="italics">I</hi> lie down to rest, I may be laid not far off from my darling girl!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We neither of us said anything for a little while.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But I wouldn't so much as give it another thought,&rdquo; said Peggotty, cheerily, &ldquo;if my Davy was anyways against it&mdash;not if I had been asked in church thirty times three times over, and was wearing out the ring in my pocket.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Look at me, Peggotty,&rdquo; I replied; &ldquo;and see if I am not really glad, and don't truly wish it!&rdquo; As indeed I did, with all my heart.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my life,&rdquo; said Peggotty, giving me a squeeze, &ldquo;I have thought of it night and day, every way I can, and I hope the right way; but I'll think of it again, and speak to my brother about it, and in the meantime we'll keep it to ourselves, Davy, you and me. Barkis is a good plain creetur',&rdquo; said Peggotty, &ldquo;and if I tried to do my duty by him, I think it would be my fault if I wasn't&mdash;if I wasn't pretty comfortable,&rdquo; said Peggotty, laughing heartily.</p>
<p>This quotation from Mr. Barkis was so appropriate, and tickled us both so much, that we laughed again and again, and were quite in a pleasant humour when we came within view of Mr. Peggotty's cottage.</p>
<p>It looked just the same, except that it may, perhaps, have shrunk a little in my eyes; and Mrs. Gummidge was waiting at the door as if she had stood there ever since. All within was the same, down to the seaweed in the blue mug in my bedroom. I went into the out-house to look about me; and the very same lobsters, crabs, and crawfish possessed by the same desire to pinch the world in general, appeared to be in the same state of conglomeration in the same old corner.</p>
<p>But there was no little Em'ly to be seen, so I asked Mr. Peggotty where she was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She's at school, sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, wiping the heat consequent on the porterage of Peggotty's box from his forehead; &ldquo;she'll be home,&rdquo; looking at the Dutch clock, &ldquo;in from twenty minutes to half-an-hour's time. We all on us feel the loss of her, bless ye!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Gummidge moaned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cheer up, Mawther!&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I feel it more than anybody else,&rdquo; said Mrs. Gummidge; &ldquo;I'm a lone lorn creetur', and she used to be a'most the only think that didn't go contrairy with me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Gummidge, whimpering and shaking her head, applied herself to blowing the fire. Mr. Peggotty, looking round upon us while she was so engaged, said in a low voice, which he shaded with his hand: &ldquo;The old 'un!&rdquo; From this I rightly conjectured that no improvement had taken place since my last visit in the state of Mrs. Gummidge's spirits.</p>
<p>Now, the whole place was, or it should have been, quite as delightful a place as ever; and yet it did not impress me in the same way. I felt rather disappointed with it. Perhaps it was because little Em'ly was not at home. I knew the way by which she would come, and presently found myself strolling along the path to meet her.</p>
<p>A figure appeared in the distance before long, and I soon knew it to be Em'ly, who was a little creature still in stature, though she was grown. But when she drew nearer, and I saw her blue eyes looking bluer, and her dimpled
<pb n="102" id="p102"/>
face looking brighter, and her whole self prettier and gayer, a curious feeling came over me that made me pretend not to know her, and pass by as if I were looking at something a long way off. I have done such a thing since in later life, or I am mistaken.</p>
<p>Little Em'ly didn't care a bit. She saw me well enough; but instead of turning round and calling after me, ran away laughing. This obliged me to run after her, and she ran so fast that we were very near the cottage before I caught her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, it's you, is it?&rdquo; said little Em'ly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you knew who it was, Em'ly,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And didn't <hi rend="italics">you</hi> know who it was?&rdquo; said Em'ly. I was going to kiss her, but she covered her cherry lips with her hands, and said she wasn't a baby now, and ran away, laughing more than ever, into the house.</p>
<p>She seemed to delight in teasing me, which was a change in her I wondered at very much. The tea-table was ready, and our little locker was put out in its old place, but instead of coming to sit by me, she went and bestowed her company upon that grumbling Mrs. Gummidge: and on Mr. Peggotty's inquiring why, rumpled her hair all over her face to hide it, and would do nothing but laugh.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A little puss, it is!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, patting her with his great hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So sh' is! so sh' is!&rdquo; cried Ham. &ldquo;Mas'r Davy bo', so sh' is!&rdquo; and he sat and chuckled at her for some time, in a state of mingled admiration and delight, that made his face a burning red.</p>
<p>Little Em'ly was spoiled by them all, in fact; and by no one more than Mr. Peggotty himself, whom she could have coaxed into anything, by only going and laying her check against his rough whisker. That was my opinion, at least, when I saw her do it; and I held Mr. Peggotty to be thoroughly in the right. But she was so affectionate and sweet-natured, and had such a pleasant manner of being both sly and shy at once, that she captivated me more than ever.</p>
<p>She was tender-hearted, too; for when, as we sat round the fire after tea, an allusion was made by Mr. Peggotty over his pipe to the loss I had sustained, the tears stood in her eyes, and she looked at me so kindly across the table, that I felt quite thankful to her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, taking up her curls, and running them over his hand like water, &ldquo;here's another orphan, you see, sir. And here,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, giving Ham a back-handed knock in the chest, &ldquo;is another of 'em, though he don't look much like it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If I had you for my guardian, Mr. Peggotty,&rdquo; said I, shaking my head, &ldquo;I don't think I should <hi rend="italics">feel</hi> much like it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well said, Mas'r Davy bo'!&rdquo; cried Ham, in an ecstasy. &ldquo;Hoorah! Well said! Nor more you wouldn't! Hor! Hor!&rdquo;&mdash;Here he returned Mr. Peggotty's back-hander, and little Em'ly got up and kissed Mr. Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how's your friend, sir?&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Steerforth?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the name!&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty, turning to Ham. &ldquo;I knowed it was something in our way.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You said it was Rudderford,&rdquo; observed Ham, laughing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well?&rdquo; retoried Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;And ye steer with a rudder, don't ye? It ain't fur off. How is he, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="103" id="p103"/>
<p>&ldquo;He was very well indeed when I came away, Mr. Peggotty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's a friend!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, stretching out his pipe. &ldquo;There's a friend, if you talk of friends! Why, Lord love my heart alive, if it ain't a treat to look at him!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is very handsome, is he not?&rdquo; said I, my heart warming with this praise.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Handsome!&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;He stands up to you like&mdash;like a &mdash;why, I don't know what he <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> stand up to you like. He's so bold!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes! That's just his character,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;He's as brave as a lion, and you can't think how frank he is, Mr. Peggotty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I do suppose, now,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, looking at me through the smoke of his pipe, &ldquo;that in the way of book-learning he'd take the wind out of a'most anything.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said I, delighted; &ldquo;he knows everything. He is astonishingly clever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's a friend!&rdquo; murmured Mr. Peggotty, with a grave toss of his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing seems to cost him any trouble,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;He knows a task if he only looks at it. He is the best cricketer you ever saw. He will give you almost as many men as you like at draughts, and beat you easily.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty gave his head another toss, as much as to say: &ldquo;Of course he will.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is such a speaker,&rdquo; I pursued, &ldquo;that he can win anybody over; and I don't know what you'd say if you were to hear him sing, Mr. Peggotty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty gave his head another toss, as much as to say: &ldquo;I have no doubt of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, he's such a generous, fine, noble fellow,&rdquo; said I, quite carried away by my favorite theme, &ldquo;that it's hardly possible to give him as much praise as he deserves. I am sure I can never feel thankful enough for the generosity with which he has protected me, so much younger and lower in the school than himself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was running on, very fast indeed, when my eyes rested on little Em'ly's face, which was bent forward over the table, listening with the deepest attention, her breath held, her blue eyes sparking like jewels, and the color mantling in her cheeks. She looked so extraordinarily earnest and pretty, that I stopped in a sort of wonder; and they all observed her at the same time, for, as I stopped, they laughed and looked at her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Em'ly is like me,&rdquo; said Peggotty, &ldquo;and would like to see him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Em'ly was confused by our all observing her, and hung down her head, and her face was covered with blushes. Glancing up presently through her stray curls, and seeing that we were all looking at her still (I am sure, I, for one, could have looked at her for hours), she ran away, and kept away till it was nearly bedtime.</p>
<p>I lay down in the old little bed in the stern of the boat, and the wind came moaning on across the flat as it had done before. But I could not help fancying, now, that it moaned of those who were gone; and instead of thinking that the sea might rise in the night and float the boat away, I thought of the sea that had risen, since I last heard those sounds, and drowned my happy home. I recollect, as the wind and water began to
<pb n="104" id="p104"/>
sound fainter in my ears, putting a short clause into my prayers, petitioning that I might grow up to marry little Em'ly, and so dropping lovingly asleep.</p>
<p>The days passed pretty much as they had passed before, except&mdash;it was a great exception&mdash;that little Em'ly and I seldom wandered on the beach now. She had tasks to learn, and needle-work to do; and was absent during a great part of each day. But I felt that we should not have had those old wanderings, even if it had been otherwise. Wild and full of childish whims as Em'ly was, she was more of a little woman than I had supposed. She seemed to have got a great distance away from me, in little more than a year. She liked me, but she laughed at me, and tormented me; and when I went to meet her, stole home another way, and was laughing at the door when I came back, disappointed. The best times were when she sat quietly at work in the doorway, and I sat on the wooden step at her feet, reading to her. It seems to me, at this hour, that I have never seen such sunlight as on those bright April afternoons; that I have never seen such a sunny little figure as I used to see, sitting in the doorway of the old boat; that I have never beheld such sky, such water, such glorified ships sailing away into golden air.</p>
<p>On the very first evening after our arrival, Mr. Barkis appeared in an exceedingly vacant and awkward condition, and with a bundle of oranges tied up in a handkerchief. As he made no allusion of any kind to this property, he was supposed to have left it behind him by accident when he went away; until Ham, running after him to restore it, came back with the information that it was intended for Peggotty. After that occasion he appeared every evening at exactly the same hour, and always with a little bundle, to which he never alluded, and which he regularly put behind the door, and left there. These offerings of affection were of a most various and eccentric description. Among them I remember a double set of pig's trotters, a huge pin-cushion, half a bushel or so of apples, a pair of jet earrings, some Spanish onions, a box of dominoes, a canary bird and cage, and a leg of pickled pork.</p>
<p>Mr. Barkis's wooing, as I remember it, was altogether of a peculiar kind. He very seldom said anything; but would sit by the fire in much the same attitude as he sat in, in his cart, and stare heavily at Peggotty, who was opposite. One night, being, as I suppose, inspired by love, he made a dart at the bit of wax-candle she kept for her thread, and put it in his waistcoat-pocket and carried it off. After that, his great delight was to produce it when it was wanted, sticking to the lining of his pocket, in a partially-melted state, and pocket it again when it was done with. He seemed to enjoy himself very much, and not to feel at all called upon to talk. Even when he took Peggotty out for a walk on the flats, he had no uneasiness on that head, I believe; contenting himself with now and then asking her if she was pretty comfortable; and I remember that sometimes, after he was gone, Peggotty would throw her apron over her face, and laugh for half-an-hour. Indeed, we were all more or less amused, except that miserable Mrs. Gummidge, whose courtship would appear to have been of an exactly parallel nature, she was so continually reminded by these transactions of the old one.</p>
<p>At length, when the term of my visit was nearly expired, it was given out that Peggotty and Mr. Barkis were going to make a day's holiday together, and that little Em'ly and I were to accompany them. I had
<pb n="105" id="p105"/>
but a broken sleep the night before, in anticipation of the pleasure of a whole day with Em'ly. We were all astir betimes in the morning; and while we were yet at breakfast, Mr. Barkis appeared in the distance, driving a chaise-cart towards the object of his affections.</p>
<p>Peggotty was drest as usual, in her neat and quiet mourning; but Mr. Barkis bloomed in a new blue coat, of which the tailor had given him such good measure, that the cuffs would have rendered gloves unnecessary in the coldest weather, while the collar was so high that it pushed his hair up on end on the top of his head. His bright buttons, too, were of the largest size. Rendered complete by drab pantaloons and a buff waistcoat, I thought Mr. Barkis a phenomenon of respectability.</p>
<p>When we were all in a bustle outside the door, I found that Mr. Peggotty was prepared with an old shoe, which was to be thrown after us for luck, and which he offered to Mrs. Gummidge for that purpose.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. It had better be done by somebody else, Dan'l,&rdquo; said Mrs. Gummidge. &ldquo;I'm a lone lorn creetur' myself, and everythink that reminds me of creetur's that ain't lone and lorn, goes contrairy with me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come, old gal!&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;Take and heave it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, Dan'l,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Gummidge, whimpering and shaking her head. &ldquo;If I felt less, I could do more. You don't feel like me, Dan'l; thinks don't go contrairy with you, nor you with them; you had better do it yourself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But here Peggotty, who had been going about from one to another in a hurried way, kissing everybody, called out from the cart, in which we all were by this time (Em'ly and I on two little chairs, side by side), that Mrs. Gummidge must do it. So Mrs. Gummidge did it; and, I am sorry to relate, cast a damp upon the festive character of our departure, by immediately bursting into tears, and sinking subdued into the arms of Ham, with the declaration that she knowed she was a burden, and had better be carried to the House at once. Which I really thought was a sensible idea, that Ham might have acted on.</p>
<p>Away we went, however, on our holiday excursion; and the first thing we did was to stop at a church, where Mr. Barkis tied the horse to some rails, and went in with Peggotty, leaving little Em'ly and me alone in the chaise. I took that occasion to put my arm round Em'ly's waist, and propose that as I was going away so very soon now, we should determine to be very affectionate to one another, and very happy, all day. Little Em'ly consenting, and allowing me to kiss her, I became desperate; informing her, I recollect, that I never could love another, and that I was prepared to shed the blood of anybody who should aspire to her affections.</p>
<p>How merry little Em'ly made herself about it! With what a demure assumption of being immensely older and wiser than I, the fairy little woman said I was &ldquo;a silly boy;&rdquo; and then laughed so charmingly that I forgot the pain of being called by that disparaging name, in the pleasure of looking at her.</p>
<p>Mr. Barkis and Peggotty were a good while in the church, but came out at last, and then we drove away into the country. As we were going along, Mr. Barkis turned to me, and said, with a wink,&mdash;by-the-by, I should hardly have thought, before, that he <hi rend="italics">could</hi> wink:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What name was it as I wrote up in the cart?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="106" id="p106"/>
<p>&ldquo;Clara Peggotty,&rdquo; I answered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What name would it be as I should write up now, if there was a tilt here?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Clara Peggotty, again?&rdquo; I suggested.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Clara Peggotty, BARKIS!&rdquo; he returned, and burst into a roar of laughter that shook the chaise.</p>
<p>In a word, they were married, and had gone into the church for no other purpose. Peggotty was resolved that it should be quietly done; and the clerk had given her away, and there had been no witnesses of the ceremony. She was a little confused when Mr. Barkis made this abrupt announcement of their union, and could not hug me enough in token of her unimpaired affection; but she soon became herself again, and said she was very glad it was over.</p>
<p>We drove to a little inn in a bye road, where we were expected, and where we had a very comfortable dinner, and passed the day with great satisfaction. If Peggotty had been married every day for the last ten years, she could hardly have been more at her ease about it; it made no sort of difference in her: she was just the same as ever, and went out for a stroll with little Em'ly and me before tea, while Mr. Barkis philosophically smoked his pipe, and enjoyed himself, I suppose, with the contemplation of his happiness. If so, it sharpened his appetite; for I distinctly call to mind that, although he had eaten a good deal of pork and greens at dinner, and had finished off with a fowl or two, he was obliged to have cold boiled bacon for tea, and disposed of a large quantity without any emotion.</p>
<p>I have often thought, since, what an odd, innocent, out-of-the-way kind of wedding it must have been! We got into the chaise again soon after dark, and drove cosily back, looking up at the stars, and talking about them. I was their chief exponent, and opened Mr. Barkis's mind to an amazing extent. I told him all I knew, but he would have believed anything I might have taken it into my head to impart to him; for he had a profound veneration for my abilities, and informed his wife in my hearing, on that very occasion, that I was &ldquo;a young Roeshus&rdquo;&mdash;by which I think he meant, prodigy.</p>
<p>When we had exhausted the subject of the stars, or rather when I had exhausted the mental faculties of Mr. Barkis, little Em'ly and I made a cloak of an old wrapper, and sat under it for the rest of the journey. Ah, how I loved her! What happiness (I thought) if we were married, and were going away anywhere to live among the trees and in the fields, never growing older, never growing wiser, children ever, rambling hand in hand through sunshine and among flowery meadows, laying down our heads on moss at night, in a sweet sleep of purity and peace, and buried by the birds when we were dead! Some such picture, with no real world in it, bright with the light of our innocence, and vague as the stars afar off, was in my mind all the way. I am glad to think there were two such guileless hearts at Peggotty's marriage as little Em'ly's and mine. I am glad to think the Loves and Graces took such airy forms in its homely procession.</p>
<p>Well, we came to the old boat again in good time at night; and there Mr. and Mrs. Barkis bade us good-bye, and drove away snugly to their own home. I felt then, for the first time, that I had lost Peggotty. I should have gone to bed with a sore heart indeed under any other roof but that which sheltered little Em'ly's head.</p>
<pb n="107" id="p107"/>
<p>Mr. Peggotty and Ham knew what was in my thoughts as well as I did, and were ready with some supper and their hospitable faces to drive it away. Little Em'ly came and sat beside me on the locker, for the only time in all that visit; and it was altogether a wonderful close to a wonderful day.</p>
<p>It was a night tide; and soon after we went to bed, Mr. Peggotty and Ham went out to fish. I felt very brave at being left alone in the solitary house, the protector of Em'ly and Mrs. Gummidge, and only wished that a lion or a serpent, or any ill-disposed monster, would make an attack upon us, that I might destroy him, and cover myself with glory. But as nothing of the sort happened to be walking about on Yarmouth flats that night, I provided the best substitute I could by dreaming of dragons until morning.</p>
<p>With morning came Peggotty; who called to me, as usual, under my window as if Mr. Barkis the carrier had been from first to last a dream too. After breakfast she took me to her own home, and a beautiful little home it was. Of all the moveables in it, I must have been most impressed by a certain old bureau of some dark wood in the parlor (the tile-floored kitchen was the general sitting-room), with a retreating top which opened, let down, and became a desk, within which, was a large quarto edition of Fox's Book of Martyrs. This precious volume, of which I do not recollect one word, I immediately discovered and immediately applied myself to; and I never visited the house afterwards, but I kneeled on a chair, opened the casket where this gem was enshrined, spread my arms over the desk, and fell to devouring the book afresh. I was chiefly edified, I am afraid, by the pictures, which were numerous, and represented all kinds of dismal horrors; but the Martyrs and Peggotty's house have been inseparable in my mind ever since, and are now.</p>
<p>I took leave of Mr. Peggotty, and Ham, and Mrs. Gummidge, and little Em'ly, that day; and passed the night at Peggotty's, in a little room in the roof (with the crocodile-book on a shelf by the bed's head) which was to be always mine, Peggotty said, and should always be kept for me in exactly the same state.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Young or old, Davy dear, as long as I am alive and have this house over my head,&rdquo; said Peggotty, &ldquo;you shall find it as if I expected you here directly minute. I shall keep it every day, as I used to keep your old little room, my darling; and if you was to go to China, you might think of it as being kept just the same, all the time you were away.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt the truth and constancy of my dear old nurse, with all my heart, and thanked her as well as I could. That was not very well, for she spoke to me thus, with her arms round my neck, in the morning, and I was going home in the morning, and I went home in the morning, with herself and Mr. Barkis in the cart. They left me at the gate, not easily or lightly; and it was a strange sight to me to see the cart go on, taking Peggotty away, and leaving me under the old elm-trees looking at the house, in which there was no face to look on mine with love or liking any more.</p>
<p>And now I fell into a state of neglect, which I cannot look back upon without compassion. I fell at once into a solitary condition,&mdash;apart from all friendly notice, apart from the society of all other boys of my own age,
<pb n="108" id="p108"/>
apart from all companionship but my own spiritless thoughts,&mdash;which seems to cast its gloom upon this paper as I write.</p>
<p>What would I have given, to have been sent to the hardest school that ever was kept!&mdash;to have been taught something, anyhow, anywhere! No such hope dawned upon me. They disliked me; and they sullenly, sternly, steadily, overlooked me. I think Mr. Murdstone's means were straitened at about this time; but it is little to the purpose. He could not bear me; and in putting me from him he tried, as I believe, to put away the notion that I had any claim upon him&mdash;and succeeded.</p>
<p>I was not actively ill-used. I was not beaten, or starved; but the wrong that was done to me had no intervals of relenting, and was done in a systematic, passionless manner. Day after day, week after week, month after month, I was coldly neglected. I wonder sometimes, when I think of it, what they would have done if I had been taken with an illness; whether I should have lain down in my lonely room, and languished through it in my usual solitary way, or whether anybody would have helped me out.</p>
<p>When Mr. and Miss Murdstone were at home, I took my meals with them; in their absence, I ate and drank by myself. At all times I lounged about the house and neighbourhood quite disregarded, except that they were jealous of my making any friends: thinking, perhaps, that, if I did, I might complain to some one. For this reason, though Mr. Chillip often asked me to go and see him (he was a widower, having, some years before that, lost a little small light-haired wife, whom I can just remember connecting in my own thoughts with a pale tortoise-shell cat), it was but seldom that I enjoyed the happiness of passing an afternoon in his closet of a surgery; reading some book that was new to me, with the smell of the whole pharmacop&oelig;ia coming up my nose, or pounding something in a mortar under his mild directions.</p>
<p>For the same reason, added no doubt to the old dislike of her, I was seldom allowed to visit Peggotty. Faithful to her promise, she either came to see me, or met me somewhere near, once every week, and never empty-handed; but many and bitter were the disappointments I had, in being refused permission to pay a visit to her at her house. Some few times, however, at long intervals, I was allowed to go there; and then I found out that Mr. Barkis was something of a miser, or as Peggotty dutifully expressed it, was &ldquo;a little near,&rdquo; and kept a heap of money in a box under his bed, which he pretended was only full of coats and trousers. In this coffer, his riches hid themselves with such a tenacious modesty, that the smallest instalments could only be tempted out by artifice; so that Peggotty had to prepare a long and elaborate scheme, a very Gunpowder Plot, for every Saturday's expenses.</p>
<p>All this time I was so conscious of the waste of any promise I had given, and of my being utterly neglected, that I should have been perfectly miserable, I have no doubt, but for the old books. They were my only comfort; and I was as true to them as they were to me, and read them over and over I don't know how many times more.</p>
<p>I now approach a period of my life, which I can never lose the remembrance of, while I remember any thing; and the recollection of which has often, without my invocation, come before me like a ghost, and haunted happier times.</p>
<pb n="109" id="p109"/>
<p>I had been out, one day, loitering somewhere, in the listless, meditative manner that my way of life engendered, when, turning the corner of a lane near our house, I came upon Mr. Murdstone walking with a gentleman. I was confused, and was going by them, when the gentleman cried:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What! Brooks!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, sir, David Copperfield,&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't tell me. You are Brooks,&rdquo; said the gentleman. &ldquo;You are Brooks of Sheffield. That's your name.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At these words, I observed the gentleman more attentively. His laugh coming to my remembrance too, I knew him to be Mr. Quinion, whom I had gone over to Lowestoft with Mr. Murdstone to see, before&mdash;it is no matter&mdash;I need not recall when.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how do you get on, and where are you being educated, Brooks?&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion.</p>
<p>He had put his hand upon my shoulder, and turned me about, to walk with them. I did not know what to reply, and glanced dubiously at Mr. Murdstone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is at home at present,&rdquo; said the latter. &ldquo;He is not being educated anywhere. I don't know what to do with him. He is a difficult subject.&rdquo;</p>
<p>That old, double look was on me for a moment; and then his eye darkened with a frown, as it turned, in its aversion, elsewhere.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Humph!&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion, looking at us both, I thought. &ldquo;Fine weather!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Silence ensued, and I was considering how I could best disengage my shoulder from his hand, and go away, when he said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose you are a pretty sharp fellow still? Eh, Brooks?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye! He is sharp enough,&rdquo; said Mr. Murdstone, impatiently. &ldquo;You had better let him go. He will not thank you for troubling him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On this hint, Mr. Quinion released me, and I made the best of my way home. Looking back as I turned into the front garden, I saw Mr. Murdstone leaning against the wicket of the churchyard, and Mr. Quinion talking to him. They were both looking after me, and I felt that they were speaking of me.</p>
<p>Mr. Quinion lay at our house that night. After breakfast, the next morning, I had put my chair away, and was going out of the room, when Mr. Murdstone called me back. He then gravely repaired to another table, where his sister sat herself at her desk. Mr. Quinion, with his hands in his pockets, stood looking out of window; and I stood looking at them all.</p>
<p>&ldquo;David,&rdquo; said Mr. Murdstone, &ldquo;to the young this is a world for action; not for moping and droning in.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&mdash;&ldquo;As you do,&rdquo; added his sister.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Jane Murdstone, leave it to me, if you please. I say, David, to the young this is a world for action, and not for moping and droning in. It is especially so for a young boy of your disposition, which requires a great deal of correcting; and to which no greater service can be done than to force it to conform to the ways of the working world, and to bend it and break it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For stubbornness won't do here,&rdquo; said his sister. &ldquo;What it wants, is, to be crushed. And crushed it must be. Shall be, too!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="110" id="p110"/>
<p>He gave her a look, half in remonstrance, half in approval, and went on:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose you know, David, that I am not rich. At any rate, you know it now. You have received some considerable education already. Education is costly; and even if it were not, and I could afford it, I am of opinion that it would not be at all advantageous to you to be kept at a school. What is before you, is a fight with the world; and the sooner you begin it, the better.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think it occurred to me that I had already begun it, in my poor way: but it occurs to me now, whether or no.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have heard &lsquo;the counting-house&rsquo; mentioned sometimes,&rdquo; said Mr. Murdstone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The counting-house, sir?&rdquo; I repeated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of Murdstone and Grinby, in the wine trade,&rdquo; he replied.</p>
<p>I suppose I looked uncertain, for he went on hastily:</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have heard the &lsquo;counting-house&rsquo; mentioned, or the business, or the cellars, or the wharf, or something about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think I have heard the business mentioned, sir,&rdquo; I said, remembering what I vaguely knew of his and his sister's resources. &ldquo;But I don't know when.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It does not matter when,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;Mr. Quinion manages that business.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I glanced at the latter deferentially as he stood looking out of window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Quinion suggests that it gives employment to some other boys, and that he sees no reason why it shouldn't, on the same terms, give employment to you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He having,&rdquo; Mr. Quinion observed in a low voice, and half turning round, &ldquo;no other prospect, Murdstone.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Murdstone, with an impatient, even an angry gesture, resumed, without noticing what he had said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Those terms are, that you will earn enough for yourself to provide for your eating and drinking, and pocket-money. Your lodging (which I have arranged for) will be paid by me. So will your washing&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash;Which will be kept down to my estimate,&rdquo; said his sister.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your clothes will be looked after for you, too,&rdquo; said Mr. Murdstone; &ldquo;as you will not be able, yet awhile, to get them for yourself. So you are now going to London, David, with Mr. Quinion, to begin the world on your own account.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In short, you are provided for,&rdquo; observed his sister; &ldquo;and will please to do your duty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Though I quite understood that the purpose of this announcement was to get rid of me, I have no distinct remembrance whether it pleased or frightened me. My impression is, that I was in a state of confusion about it, and, oscillating between the two points, touched neither. Nor had I much time for the clearing of my thoughts, as Mr. Quinion was to go upon the morrow.</p>
<p>Behold me, on the morrow, in a much-worn little white hat, with a black crape round it for my mother, a black jacket, and a pair of hard stiff corduroy trousers&mdash;which Miss Murdstone considered the best armour for the legs in that fight with the world which was now to come off: behold me so attired, and with my little worldly all before me in a small trunk, sitting, a lone lorn child (as Mrs. Gummidge might have said), in the postchaise
<pb n="111" id="p111"/>
that was carrying Mr. Quinion to the London coach at Yarmouth! See, how our house and church are lessening in the distance; how the grave beneath the tree is blotted out by intervening objects; how the spire points upward from my old playground no more, and the sky is empty!</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XI. <lb/> I BEGIN LIFE ON MY OWN ACCOUNT, AND DON'T LIKE IT.</head>
<p>I KNOW enough of the world now, to have almost lost the capacity of being much surprised by anything; but it is matter of some surprise to me, even now, that I can have been so easily thrown away at such an age. A child of excellent abilities, and with strong powers of observation, quick, eager, delicate, and soon hurt bodily or mentally, it seems wonderful to me that nobody should have made any sign in my behalf. But none was made; and I became, at ten years old, a little labouring hind in the service of Murdstone and Grinby.</p>
<p>Murdstone and Grinby's warehouse was at the water side. It was down in Blackfriars. Modern improvements have altered the place; but it was the last house at the bottom of a narrow street, curving down hill to the river, with some stairs at the end, where people took boat. It was a crazy old house with a wharf of its own, abutting on the water when the tide was in, and on the mud when the tide was out, and literally over-run with rats. Its panelled rooms, discolored with the dirt and smoke of a hundred years, I dare say; its decaying floors and staircase; the squeaking and scuffling of the old grey rats down in the cellars; and the dirt and rottenness of the place; are things, not of many years ago, in my mind, but of the present instant. They are all before me, just as they were in the evil hour when I went among them for the first time, with my trembling hand in Mr. Quinion's.</p>
<p>Murdstone and Grinby's trade was among a good many kinds of people, but an important branch of it was the supply of wines and spirits to certain packet ships. I forget now where they chiefly went, but I think there were some among them that made voyages both to the East and West Indies. I know that a great many empty bottles were one of the consequences of this traffic, and that certain men and boys were employed to examine them against the light, and reject those that were flawed, and to rinse and wash them. When the empty bottles ran short, there were labels to be pasted on full ones, or corks to be fitted to them, or seals to be put upon the corks, or finished bottles to be packed in casks. All this work was my work, and of the boys employed upon it I was one.</p>
<p>There were three or four of us, counting me. My working place was established in a corner of the warehouse, where Mr. Quinion could see me, when he chose to stand up on the bottom rail of his stool in the counting-house, and look at me through a window above the desk.
<pb n="112" id="p112"/>
Hither, on the first morning of my so auspiciously beginning life on my own account, the oldest of the regular boys was summoned to show me my business. His name was Mick Walker, and he wore a ragged apron and a paper cap. He informed me that his father was a bargeman, and walked, in a black velvet head-dress, in the Lord Mayor's Show. He also informed me that our principal associate would be another boy whom he introduced by the&mdash;to me&mdash;extraordinary name of Mealy Potatoes. I discovered, however, that this youth had not been christened by that name, but that it had been bestowed upon him in the warehouse, on account of his complexion, which was pale or mealy. Mealy's father was a waterman, who had the additional distinction of being a fireman, and was engaged as such at one of the large theatres; where some young relation of Mealy's&mdash;I think his little sister&mdash;did Imps in the Pantomimes.</p>
<p>No words can express the secret agony of my soul as I sunk into this companionship; compared these henceforth every-day associates with those of my happier childhood&mdash;not to say with Steerforth, Traddles, and the rest of those boys; and felt my hopes of growing up to be a learned and distinguished man, crushed in my bosom. The deep remembrance of the sense I had, of being utterly without hope now; of the shame I felt in my position; of the misery it was to my young heart to believe that day by day what I had learned, and thought, and delighted in, and raised my fancy and my emulation up by, would pass away from me, little by little, never to be brought back any more; cannot be written. As often as Mick Walker went away in the course of that forenoon, I mingled my tears with the water in which I was washing the bottles; and sobbed as if there were a flaw in my own breast, and it were in danger of bursting.</p>
<p>The counting-house clock was at half-past twelve, and there was general preparation for going to dinner, when Mr. Quinion tapped at the counting-house window, and beckoned to me to go in. I went in, and found there a stoutish, middle-aged person, in a brown surtout and black tights and shoes, with no more hair upon his head (which was a large one, and very shining) than there is upon an egg, and with a very extensive face, which he turned full upon me. His clothes were shabby, but he had an imposing shirt-collar on. He carried a jaunty sort of a stick, with a large pair of rusty tassels to it; and a quizzing-glass hung outside his coat,&mdash;for ornament, I afterwards found, as he very seldom looked through it, and couldn't see anything when he did.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This,&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion, in allusion to myself, &ldquo;is he.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;This,&rdquo; said the stranger, with a certain condescending roll in his voice, and a certain indescribable air of doing something genteel, which impressed me very much, &ldquo;is Master Copperfield. I hope I see you well, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said I was very well, and hoped he was. I was sufficiently ill at ease, Heaven knows; but it was not in my nature to complain much at that time of my life, so I said I was very well, and hoped he was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am,&rdquo; said the stranger, &ldquo;thank Heaven, quite well. I have received a letter from Mr. Murdstone, in which he mentions that he would desire me to receive into an apartment in the rear of my house, which is at present unoccupied&mdash;and is, in short, to be let as a&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said the stranger, with a smile and in a burst of confidence, &ldquo;as a bed-room&mdash;the young beginner whom I have now the pleasure to&mdash;&rdquo; and the stranger waved his hand, and settled his chin in his shirt collar.</p>
<pb n="113" id="p113"/>
<p>&ldquo;This is Mr. Micawber,&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ahem!&rdquo; said the stranger, &ldquo;that is my name.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Micawber,&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion, &ldquo;is known to Mr. Murdstone. He takes orders for us on commission, when he can get any. He has been written to by Mr. Murdstone, on the subject of your lodgings, and he will receive you as a lodger.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My address,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;is Windsor Terrace, City Road. I&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, with the same genteel air, and in another burst of confidence&mdash;&ldquo;I live there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I made him a bow.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Under the impression,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;that your peregrinations in this metropolis have not as yet been extensive, and that you might have some difficulty in penetrating the arcana of the Modern Babylon in the direction of the City Road&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, in another burst of confidence, &ldquo;that you might lose yourself&mdash;I shall be happy to call this evening, and install you in the knowledge of the nearest way.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thanked him with all my heart, for it was friendly in him to offer to take that trouble.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At what hour,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;shall I&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At about eight,&rdquo; said Mr. Quinion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At about eight,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber. &ldquo;I beg to wish you good day, Mr. Quinion. I will intrude no longer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So he put on his hat, and went out with his cane under his arm: very upright, and humming a tune when he was clear of the counting-house.</p>
<p>Mr. Quinion then formally engaged me to be as useful as I could in the warehouse of Murdstone and Grinby, at a salary, I think, of six shillings a week. I am not clear whether it was six or seven. I am inclined to believe, from my uncertainty on this head, that it was six at first and seven afterwards. He paid me a week down (from his own pocket, I believe), and I gave Mealy sixpence out of it to get my trunk carried to Windsor Terrace at night: it being too heavy for my strength, small as it was. I paid sixpence more for my dinner, which was a meat pie and a turn at a neighbouring pump; and passed the hour which was allowed for that meal, in walking about the streets.</p>
<p>At the appointed time in the evening, Mr. Micawber reappeared. I washed my hands and face, to do the greater honour to his gentility, and we walked to our house, as I suppose I must now call it, together; Mr. Micawber impressing the names of streets, and the shapes of corner houses upon me, as we went along, that I might find my way back, easily, in the morning.</p>
<p>Arrived at his house in Windsor Terrace (which I noticed was shabby like himself, but also, like himself, made all the show it could), he presented me to Mrs. Micawber, a thin and faded lady, not at all young, who was sitting in the parlor (the first floor was altogether unfurnished, and the blinds were kept down to delude the neighbours), with a baby at her breast. This baby was one of twins; and I may remark here that I hardly ever, in all my experience of the family, saw both the twins detached from Mrs. Micawber at the same time. One of them was always taking refreshment.</p>
<p>There were two other children; Master Micawber, aged about four, and Miss Micawber, aged about three. These, and a dark-complexioned
<pb n="114" id="p114"/>
young woman, with a habit of snorting, who was servant to the family, and informed me, before half-an-hour had expired, that she was &ldquo;a Orfling,&rdquo; and came from St. Luke's workhouse, in the neighbourhood, completed the establishment. My room was at the top of the house, at the back: a close chamber; stencilled all over with an ornament which my young imagination represented as a blue muffin; and very scantily furnished.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never thought,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, when she came up, twin and all, to show me the apartment, and sat down to take breath, &ldquo;before I was married, when I lived with papa and mama, that I should ever find it necessary to take a lodger. But Mr. Micawber being in difficulties, all considerations of private feeling must give way.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said: &ldquo;Yes, ma'am.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Micawber's difficulties are almost overwhelming just at present,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber; &ldquo;and whether it is possible to bring him through them, I don't know. When I lived at home with papa and mama, I really should have hardly understood what the word meant, in the sense in which I now employ it, but experientia does it&mdash;as papa used to say.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I cannot satisfy myself whether she told me that Mr. Micawber had been an officer in the Marines, or whether I have imagined it. I only know that I believe to this hour that he <hi rend="italics">was</hi> in the Marines once upon a time, without knowing why. He was a sort of town traveller for a number of miscellaneous houses, now; but made little or nothing of it, I am afraid.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If Mr. Micawber's creditors <hi rend="italics">will not</hi> give him time,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;they must take the consequences; and the sooner they bring it to an issue the better. Blood cannot be obtained from a stone, neither can anything on account be obtained at present (not to mention law expenses) from Mr. Micawber.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I never can quite understand whether my precocious self-dependence confused Mrs. Micawber in reference to my age, or whether she was so full of the subject that she would have talked about it to the very twins if there had been nobody else to communicate with, but this was the strain in which she began, and she went on accordingly all the time I knew her.</p>
<p>Poor Mrs. Micawber! She said she had tried to exert herself; and so, I have no doubt, she had. The centre of the street-door was perfectly covered with a great brass-plate, on which was engraved &ldquo;Mrs. Micawber's Boarding Establishment for Young Ladies:&rdquo; but I never found that any young lady had ever been to school there; or that any young lady ever came, or proposed to come; or that the least preparation was ever made to receive any young lady. The only visitors I ever saw or heard of, were creditors. <hi rend="italics">They</hi> used to come at all hours, and some of them were quite ferocious. One dirty-faced man, I think he was a boot-maker, used to edge himself into the passage as early as seven o'clock in the morning, and call up the stairs to Mr. Micawber&mdash;&ldquo;Come! You ain't out yet, you know. Pay us, will you? Don't hide, you know; that's mean. I wouldn't be mean if I was you. Pay us, will you? You just pay us, d'ye hear? Come!&rdquo; Receiving no answer to these taunts, he would mount in his wrath to the words &ldquo;swindlers&rdquo; and &ldquo;robbers;&rdquo; and these being ineffectual too, would sometimes go to the extremity of crossing the street, and roaring up at the windows of the second floor, where he knew Mr. Micawber was. At these times, Mr. Micawber would be transported with grief and mortification, even to the length (as I was once
<pb n="115" id="p115"/>
made aware by a scream from his wife) of making motions at himself with a razor; but within half an hour afterwards, he would polish up his shoes with extraordinary pains, and go out, humming a tune with a greater air of gentility than ever. Mrs. Micawber was quite as elastic. I have known her to be thrown into fainting fits by the king's taxes at three o'clock, and to cat lamb-chops, breaded, and drink warm ale (paid for with two teaspoons that had gone to the pawnbroker's) at four. On one occasion, when an execution had just been put in, coming home through some chance as early as six o'clock, I saw her lying (of course with a twin) under the grate in a swoon, with her hair all torn about her face; but I never knew her more cheerful than she was, that very same night, over a veal-cutlet before the kitchen fire, telling me stories about her papa and mama, and the company they used to keep.</p>
<p>In this house, and with this family, I passed my leisure time. My own exclusive breakfast of a penny loaf and a pennyworth of milk, I provided myself. I kept another small loaf, and a modicum of cheese, on a particular shelf of a particular cupboard, to make my supper on when I came back at night. This made a hole in the six or seven shillings, I know well; and I was out at the warehouse all day, and had to support myself on that money all the week. From Monday morning until Saturday night, I had no advice, no counsel, no encouragement, no consolation, no assistance, no support, of any kind, from any one, that I can call to mind, as I hope to go to heaven!</p>
<p>I was so young and childish, and so little qualified&mdash;how could I be otherwise?&mdash;to undertake the whole charge of my own existence, that often, in going to Murdstone and Grinby's, of a morning, I could not resist the stale pastry put out for sale at half-price at the pastrycook's doors, and spent in that, the money I should have kept for my dinner. Then, I went without my dinner, or bought a roll or a slice of pudding. I remember two pudding-shops, between which I was divided, according to my finances. One was in a court close to St. Martin's Church&mdash;at the back of the church,&mdash;which is now removed altogether. The pudding at that shop was made of currants, and was rather a special pudding, but was dear, twopennyworth not being larger than a pennyworth of more ordinary pudding. A good shop for the latter was in the Strand&mdash;somewhere in that part which has been rebuilt since. It was a stout pale pudding, heavy and flabby, and with great flat raisins in it, stuck in whole at wide distances apart. It came up hot at about my time every day, and many a day did I dine off it. When I dined regularly and handsomely, I had a saveloy and a penny-loaf, or a fourpenny plate of red beef from a cook's shop; or a plate of bread and cheese and a glass of beer, from a miserable old public-house opposite our place of business, called the Lion, or the Lion and something else that I have forgotten. Once, I remember carrying my own bread (which I had brought from home in the morning) under my arm, wrapped in a piece of paper, like a book, and going to a famous alamode beef-house near Drury Lane, and ordering a &ldquo;small plate&rdquo; of that delicacy to eat with it. What the waiter thought of such a strange little apparition coming in all alone, I don't know; but I can see him now, staring at me as I ate my dinner, and bringing up the other waiter to look. I gave him a halfpenny for himself, and I wish he hadn't taken it.</p>
<pb n="116" id="p116"/>
<p>We had half-an-hour, I think, for tea. When I had money enough, I used to get half-a-pint of ready-made coffee and a slice of bread and butter. When I had none, I used to look at a venison-shop in Fleet-street; or I have strolled, at such a time, as far as Covent Garden Market, and stared at the pine-apples. I was fond of wandering about the Adelphi, because it was a mysterious place, with those dark arches. I see myself emerging one evening from some of these arches, on a little public-house close to the river, with an open space before it, where some coal-heavers were dancing; to look at whom, I sat down upon a bench. I wonder what they thought of me!</p>
<p>I was such a child, and so little, that frequently when I went into the bar of a strange public-house for a glass of ale or porter, to moisten what I had had for dinner, they were afraid to give it me. I remember one hot evening I went into the bar of a public-house, and said to the landlord:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is your best&mdash;your <hi rend="italics">very best</hi>&mdash;ale a glass?&rdquo; For it was a special occasion. I don't know what. It may have been my birth-day.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twopence-halfpenny,&rdquo; says the landlord, &ldquo;is the price of the Genuine Stunning ale.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then,&rdquo; says I, producing the money, &ldquo;just draw me a glass of the Genuine Stunning, if you please, with a good head to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The landlord looked at me in return over the bar, from head to foot, with a strange smile on his face; and instead of drawing the beer, looked round the screen and said something to his wife. She came out from behind it, with her work in her hand, and joined him in surveying me. Here we stand, all three, before me now. The landlord in his shirt sleeves, leaning against the bar window-frame; his wife looking over the little half-door; and I, in some confusion, looking up at them from outside the partition. They asked me a good many questions; as, what my name was, how old I was, where I lived, how I was employed, and how I came there. To all of which, that I might commit nobody, I invented, I am afraid, appropriate answers. They served me with the ale, though I suspect it was not the Genuine Stunning; and the landlord's wife, opening the little half-door of the bar, and bending down, gave me my money back, and gave me a kiss that was half admiring and half compassionate, but all womanly and good, I am sure.</p>
<p>I know I do not exaggerate, unconsciously and unintentionally, the scantiness of my resources or the difficulties of my life. I know that if a shilling were given me by Mr. Quinion at any time, I spent it in a dinner or a tea. I know that I worked, from morning until night, with common men and boys, a shabby child. I know that I lounged about the streets, insufficiently and unsatisfactorily fed. I know that, but for the mercy of God, I might easily have been, for any care that was taken of me, a little robber or a little vagabond.</p>
<p>Yet I held some station at Murdstone and Grinby's too. Besides that Mr. Quinion did what a careless man so occupied, and dealing with a thing so anomalous, could, to treat me as one upon a different footing from the rest, I never said, to man or boy, how it was that I came to be there, or gave the least indication of being sorry that I was there. That I suffered in secret, and that I suffered exquisitely, no one ever knew but I. How much I suffered, it is, as I have said already, utterly beyond my power to tell. But I kept my own counsel, and I did my work. I knew
<pb n="117" id="p117"/>
from the first, that, if I could not do my work as well as any of the rest, I could not hold myself above slight and contempt. I soon became at least as expeditious and as skilful as either of the other boys. Though perfectly familiar with them, my conduct and manner were different enough from theirs to place a space between us. They and the men generally spoke of me as &ldquo;the little gent,&rdquo; or &ldquo;the young Suffolker.&rdquo; A certain man named Gregory, who was foreman of the packers, and another named Tipp, who was the carman, and wore a red jacket, used to address me sometimes as &ldquo;David:&rdquo; but I think it was mostly when we were very confidential, and when I had made some efforts to entertain them, over our work, with some results of the old readings; which were fast perishing out of my remembrance. Mealy Potatoes uprose once, and rebelled against my being so distinguished; but Mick Walker settled him in no time.</p>
<p>My rescue from this kind of existence I considered quite hopeless, and abandoned, as such, altogether. I am solemnly convinced that I never for one hour was reconciled to it, or was otherwise than miserably unhappy; but I bore it; and even to Peggotty, partly for the love of her and partly for shame, never in any letter (though many passed between us) revealed the truth.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber's difficulties were an addition to the distressed state of my mind. In my forlorn state I became quite attached to the family, and used to walk about, busy with Mrs. Micawber's calculations of ways and means, and heavy with the weight of Mr. Micawber's debts. On a Saturday night, which was my grand treat,&mdash;partly because it was a great thing to walk home with six or seven shillings in my pocket, looking into the shops and thinking what such a sum would buy, and partly because I went home early,&mdash;Mrs. Micawber would make the most heart-rending confidences to me; also on a Sunday morning, when I mixed the portion of tea or coffee I had bought over-night, in a little shaving pot, and sat late at my breakfast. It was nothing at all unusual for Mr. Micawber to sob violently at the beginning of one of these Saturday night conversations, and sing about Jack's delight being his lovely Nan, towards the end of it. I have known him come home to supper with a flood of tears, and a declaration that nothing was now left but a jail; and go to bed making a calculation of the expense of putting bow-windows to the house, &ldquo;in case anything turned up,&rdquo; which was his favourite expression. And Mrs. Micawber was just the same.</p>
<p>A curious equality of friendship, originating, I suppose, in our respective circumstances, sprung up between me and these people, notwithstanding the ludicrous disparity in our years. But I never allowed myself to be prevailed upon to accept any invitation to eat and drink with them out of their stock (knowing that they got on badly with the butcher and baker, and had often not too much for themselves), until Mrs. Micawber took me into her entire confidence. This she did one evening as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;I make no stranger of you, and therefore do not hesitate to say that Mr. Micawber's difficulties are coming to a crisis.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It made me very miserable to hear it, and I looked at Mrs. Micawber's red eyes with the utmost sympathy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With the exception of the heel of a Dutch cheese&mdash;which is not adapted to the wants of a young family&rdquo;&mdash;said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;there is really not
<pb n="118" id="p118"/>
a scrap of anything in the larder. I was accustomed to speak of the larder when I lived with papa and mama, and I use the word almost unconsciously. What I mean to express, is, that there is nothing to eat in the house.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; I said, in great concern.</p>
<p>I had two or three shillings of my week's money in my pocket&mdash;from which I presume that it must have been on a Wednesday night when we held this conversation&mdash;and I hastily produced them, and with heartfelt emotion begged Mrs. Micawber to accept of them as a loan. But that lady, kissing me, and making me put them back in my pocket, replied that she couldn't think of it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my dear Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said she, &ldquo;far be it from my thoughts! But you have a discretion beyond your years, and can render me another kind of service, if you will; and a service I will thankfully accept of.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I begged Mrs. Micawber to name it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have parted with the plate myself,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;Six tea, two salt, and a pair of sugars, I have at different times borrowed money on, in secret, with my own hands. But the twins are a great tie; and to me, with my recollections of papa and mama, these transactions are very painful. There are still a few trifles that we could part with. Mr. Micawber's feelings would never allow <hi rend="italics">him</hi> to dispose of them; and Clickett&rdquo;&mdash;this was the girl from the workhouse&mdash;&ldquo;being of a vulgar mind, would take painful liberties if so much confidence was reposed in her. Master Copperfield, if I might ask you&rdquo;&mdash;</p>
<p>I understood Mrs. Micawber now, and begged her to make use of me to any extent. I began to dispose of the more portable articles of property that very evening; and went out on a similar expedition almost every morning, before I went to Murdstone and Grinby's.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber had a few books on a little chiffonier, which he called the library; and those went first. I carried them, one after another, to a bookstall in the City Road&mdash;one part of which, near our house, was almost all bookstalls and bird-shops then&mdash;and sold them for whatever they would bring, The keeper of this bookstall, who lived in a little house behind it, used to get tipsy every night, and to be violently scolded by his wife every morning. More than once, when I went there early, I had audience of him in a turn-up bedstead, with a cut in his forehead or a black eye, bearing witness to his excesses over night (I am afraid he was quarrelsome in his drink), and he, with a shaking hand, endeavouring to find the needful shillings in one or other of the pockets of his clothes, which lay upon the floor, while his wife, with a baby in her arms and her shoes down at heel, never left off rating him. Sometimes he had lost his money, and then he would ask me to call again; but his wife had always got some&mdash;had taken his, I dare say, while he was drunk&mdash;and secretly completed the bargain on the stairs, as we went down together.</p>
<p>At the pawnbroker's shop, too, I began to be very well known. The principal gentleman who officiated behind the counter, took a good deal of notice of me; and often got me, I recollect, to decline a Latin noun or adjective, or to conjugate a Latin verb, in his ear, while he transacted my business. After all these occasions Mrs. Micawber made a little treat, which was generally a supper; and there was a peculiar relish in these meals which I well remember.</p>
<pb n="119" id="p119"/>
<p>At last Mr. Micawber's difficulties came to a crisis, and he was arrested early one morning, and carried over to the King's Bench Prison in the Borough. He told me, as he went out of the house, that the God of day had now gone down upon him&mdash;and I really thought his heart was broken and mine too. But I heard, afterwards, that he was seen to play a lively game at skittles, before noon.</p>
<p>On the first Sunday after he was taken there, I was to go and see him, and have dinner with him. I was to ask my way to such a place, and just short of that place I should see such another place, and just short of that I should see a yard, which I was to cross, and keep straight on until I saw a turnkey. All this I did; and when at last I did see a turnkey (poor little fellow that I was!), and thought how, when Roderick Random was in a debtor's prison, there was a man there with nothing on him but an old rug, the turnkey swam before my dimmed eyes and my beating heart.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber was waiting for me within the gate, and we went up to his room (top story but one), and cried very much. He solemnly conjured me, I remember, to take warning by his fate; and to observe that if a man had twenty pounds a-year for his income, and spent nineteen pounds nineteen shillings and sixpence, he would be happy, but that if he spent twenty pounds one he would be miserable. After which he borrowed a shilling of me for porter, gave me a written order on Mrs. Micawber for the amount, and put away his pocket-handkerchief, and cheered up.</p>
<p>We sat before a little fire, with two bricks put within the rusted grate, one on each side, to prevent its burning too many coals; until another debtor, who shared the room with Mr. Micawber, came in from the bakehouse with the loin of mutton which was our joint-stock repast. Then I was sent up to &ldquo;Captain Hopkins&rdquo; in the room overhead, with Mr. Micawber's compliments, and I was his young friend, and would Captain Hopkins lend me a knife and fork.</p>
<p>Captain Hopkins lent me the knife and fork, with his compliments to Mr. Micawber. There was a very dirty lady in his little room, and two wan girls, his daughters, with shock heads of hair. I thought it was better to borrow Captain Hopkins's knife and fork, than Captain Hopkins's comb. The Captain himself was in the last extremity of shabbiness, with large whiskers, and an old, old brown great-coat with no other coat below it. I saw his bed rolled up in a corner; and what plates and dishes and pots he had, on a shelf; and I divined (God knows how) that though the two girls with the shock heads of hair were Captain Hopkins's children, the dirty lady was not married to Captain Hopkins. My timid station on his threshhold was not occupied more than a couple of minutes at most; but I came down again with all this in my knowledge, as surely as the knife and fork were in my hand.</p>
<p>There was something gipsy-like and agreeable in the dinner, after all. I took back Captain Hopkins's knife and fork early in the afternoon, and went home to comfort Mrs. Micawber with an account of my visit. She fainted when she saw me return, and made a little jug of egg-hot afterwards to console us while we talked it over.</p>
<p>I don't know how the household furniture came to be sold for the family benefit, or who sold it, except that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> did not. Sold it was, however, and carried away in a van; except the bed, a few chairs, and the
<pb n="120" id="p120"/>
kitchen-table. With these possessions we encamped, as it were, in the two parlors of the emptied house in Windsor Terrace; Mrs. Micawber, the children, the Orfling, and myself; and lived in those rooms night and day. I have no idea for how long, though it seems to me for a long time. At last Mrs. Micawber resolved to move into the prison, where Mr. Micawber had now secured a room to himself. So I took the key of the house to the landlord, who was very glad to get it; and the beds were sent over to the King's Bench, except mine, for which a little room was hired outside the walls in the neighbourhood of that Institution, very much to my satisfaction, since the Micawbers and I had become too used to one another, in our troubles, to part. The Orfling was likewise accommodated with an inexpensive lodging in the same neighbourhood. Mine was a quiet back-garret with a sloping roof, commanding a pleasant prospect of a timber-yard; and when I took possession of it, with the reflection that Mr. Micawber's troubles had come to a crisis at last, I thought it quite a paradise.</p>
<p>All this time I was working at Murdstone and Grinby's in the same common way, and with the same common companions, and with the same sense of unmerited degradation as at first. But I never, happily for me no doubt, made a single acquaintance, or spoke to any of the many boys whom I saw daily in going to the warehouse, in coming from it, and in prowling about the streets at meal-times. I led the same secretly unhappy life; but I led it in the same lonely, self-reliant manner. The only changes I am conscious of are, firstly, that I had grown more shabby, and secondly, that I was now relieved of much of the weight of Mr. and Mrs. Micawber's cares; for some relatives or friends had engaged to help them at their present pass, and they lived more comfortably in the prison than they had lived for a long while out of it. I used to breakfast with them now, in virtue of some arrangement, of which I have forgotten the details. I forget, too, at what hour the gates were opened in the morning, admitting of my going in; but I know that I was often up at six o'clock, and that my favorite lounging-place in the interval was old London Bridge, where I was wont to sit in one of the stone recesses, watching the people going by, or to look over the balustrades at the sun shining in the water, and lighting up the golden flame on the top of the Monument. The Orfling met me here sometimes, to be told some astonishing fictions respecting the wharves and the Tower; of which I can say no more than that I hope I believed them myself. In the evening I used to go back to the prison, and walk up and down the parade with Mr. Micawber; or play casino with Mrs. Micawber, and hear reminiscences of her papa and mama. Whether Mr. Murdstone knew where I was, I am unable to say. I never told them at Murdstone and Grinby's.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber's affairs, although past their crisis, were very much involved by reason of a certain &ldquo;Deed,&rdquo; of which I used to hear a great deal, and which I suppose, now, to have been some former composition with his creditors, though I was so far from being clear about it then, that I am conscious of having confounded it with those demoniacal parchments which are held to have, once upon a time, obtained to a great extent in Germany. At last this document appeared to be got out of the way, somehow; at all events it ceased to be the rock-ahead it had been; and Mrs. Micawber informed me that &ldquo;her family&rdquo; had decided that Mr.
<pb n="121" id="p121"/>
Micawber should apply for his release under the Insolvent Debtors Act, which would set him free, she expected, in about six weeks.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And then,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, who was present, &ldquo;I have no doubt I shall, please Heaven, begin to be beforehand with the world, and to live in a perfectly new manner, if&mdash;in short, if anything turns up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>By way of going in for anything that might be on the cards, I call to mind that Mr. Micawber, about this time, composed a petition to the House of Commons, praying for an alteration in the law of imprisonment for debt. I set down this remembrance here, because it is an instance to myself of the manner in which I fitted my old books to my altered life, and made stories for myself, out of the streets, and out of men and women; and how some main points in the character I shall unconsciously develope, I suppose, in writing my life, were gradually forming all this while.</p>
<p>There was a club in the prison, in which Mr. Micawber, as a gentleman, was a great authority. Mr. Micawber had stated his idea of this petition to the club, and the club had strongly approved of the same. Wherefore Mr. Micawber (who was a thoroughly good-natured man, and as active a creature about everything but his own affairs as ever existed, and never so happy as when he was busy about something that could never be of any profit to him) set to work at the petition, invented it, engrossed it on an immense sheet of paper, spread it out on a table, and appointed a time for all the club, and all within the walls if they chose, to come up to his room and sign it.</p>
<p>When I heard of this approaching ceremony, I was so anxious to see them all come in, one after another, though I knew the greater part of them already, and they me, that I got an hour's leave of absence from Murdstone and Grinby's, and established myself in a corner for that purpose. As many of the principal members of the club as could be got into the small room without filling it, supported Mr. Micawber in front of the petition, while my old friend Captain Hopkins (who had washed himself, to do honor to so solemn an occasion) stationed himself close to it, to read it to all who were unacquainted with its contents. The door was then thrown open, and the general population began to come in, in a long file: several waiting outside, while one entered, affixed his signature, and went out. To everybody in succession, Captain Hopkins said: &ldquo;Have you read it?&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;No.&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;Would you like to hear it read?&rdquo; If he weakly showed the least disposition to hear it, Captain Hopkins, in a loud sonorous voice, gave him every word of it. The Captain would have read it twenty thousand times, if twenty thousand people would have heard him, one by one. I remember a certain luscious roll he gave to such phrases as &ldquo;The people's representatives in Parliament assembled,&rdquo; &ldquo;Your petitioners therefore humbly approach your honorable house,&rdquo; &ldquo;His gracious Majesty's unfortunate subjects,&rdquo; as if the words were something real in his mouth, and delicious to taste; Mr. Micawber, meanwhile, listening with a little of an author's vanity, and contemplating (not severely) the spikes on the opposite wall.</p>
<p>As I walked to and fro daily between Southwark and Blackfriars, and lounged about at meal-times in obscure streets, the stones of which may, for anything I know, be worn at this moment by my childish feet, I wonder how many of these people were wanting in the crowd that used to come filing before me in review again, to the echo of Captain
<pb n="122" id="p122"/>
Hopkins's voice! When my thoughts go back, now, to that slow agony of my youth, I wonder how much of the histories I invented for such people hangs like a mist of fancy over well-remembered facts! When I tread the old ground, I do not wonder that I seem to see and pity, going on before me, an innocent romantic boy, making his imaginative world out of such strange experiences and sordid things!</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XII. <lb/> LIKING LIFE ON MY OWN ACCOUNT NO BETTER, I FORM A GREAT <lb/> RESOLUTION.</head>
<p>IN due time, Mr. Micawber's petition was ripe for hearing; and that gentleman was ordered to be discharged under the act, to my great joy. His creditors were not implacable; and Mrs. Micawber informed me that even the revengeful bootmaker had declared in open court that he bore him no malice, but that when money was owing to him he liked to be paid. He said he thought it was human nature.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber returned to the King's Bench when his case was over, as some fees were to be settled, and some formalities observed, before he could be actually released. The club received him with transport, and held an harmonic meeting that evening in his honor; while Mrs. Micawber and I had a lamb's fry in private, surrounded by the sleeping family.</p>
<p>&ldquo;On such an occasion I will give you, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;in a little more flip,&rdquo; for we had been having some already, &ldquo;the memory of my papa and mama.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are they dead, ma'am?&rdquo; I enquired, after drinking the toast in a wine-glass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My mama departed this life,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;before Mr. Micawber's difficulties commenced, or at least before they became pressing. My papa lived to bail Mr. Micawber several times, and then expired, regretted by a numerous circle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber shook her head, and dropped a pious tear upon the twin who happened to be in hand.</p>
<p>As I could hardly hope for a more favourable opportunity of putting a question in which I had a near interest, I said to Mrs. Micawber:</p>
<p>&ldquo;May I ask, ma'am, what you and Mr. Micawber intend to do, now that Mr. Micawber is out of his difficulties, and at liberty? Have you settled yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My family,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, who always said those two words with an air, though I never could discover who came under the denomination, &ldquo;my family are of opinion that Mr. Micawber should quit London, and exert his talents in the country. Mr. Micawber is a man of great talent, Master Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said I was sure of that.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of great talent,&rdquo; repeated Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;My family are of opinion, that, with a little interest, something might be done for a man of his ability in the Custom House. The influence of my family being local, it is their
<pb n="123" id="p123"/>
wish that Mr. Micawber should go down to Plymouth. They think it indispensable that he should be upon the spot.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That he may be ready?&rdquo; I suggested.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Exactly,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;That he may be ready&mdash;in case of anything turning up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And do you go too, ma'am?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The events of the day, in combination with the twins, if not with the flip, had made Mrs. Micawber hysterical, and she shed tears as she replied:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never will desert Mr. Micawber. Mr. Micawber may have concealed his difficulties from me in the first instance, but his sanguine temper may have led him to expect that he would overcome them. The pearl necklace and bracelets which I inherited from mama, have been disposed of for less than half their value; and the set of coral, which was the wedding gift of my papa, has been actually thrown away for nothing. But I never will desert Mr. Micawber. No!&rdquo; cried Mrs. Micawber, more affected than before, &ldquo;I never will do it! It's of no use asking me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt quite uncomfortable&mdash;as if Mrs. Micawber supposed I had asked her to do anything of the sort!&mdash;and sat looking at her in alarm.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Micawber has his faults. I do not deny that he is improvident. I do not deny that he has kept me in the dark as to his resources and his liabilities, both,&rdquo; she went on, looking at the wall; &ldquo;but I never will desert Mr. Micawber!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber having now raised her voice into a perfect scream, I was so frightened that I ran off to the club-room, and disturbed Mr. Micawber in the act of presiding at a long table, and leading the chorus of 
<q><lg type="poem">
<l>Gee up, Dobbin,</l>
<l>Gee ho, Dobbin,</l>
<l>Gee up, Dobbin,</l>
<l>Gee up, and gee ho&mdash;o&mdash;o!</l>
</lg></q>
&mdash;with the tidings that Mrs. Micawber was in an alarming state, upon which he immediately burst into tears, and came away with me with his waistcoat full of the heads and tails of shrimps, of which he had been partaking.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Emma, my angel!&rdquo; cried Mr. Micawber, running into the room; &ldquo;what is the matter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never will desert you, Micawber!&rdquo; she exclaimed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My life!&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, taking her in his arms. &ldquo;I am perfectly aware of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is the parent of my children! He is the father of my twins! He is the husband of my affections,&rdquo; cried Mrs. Micawber, struggling; &ldquo;and I ne&mdash;ver&mdash;will&mdash;desert Mr. Micawber!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber was so deeply affected by this proof of her devotion (as to me, I was dissolved in tears), that he hung over her in a passionate manner, imploring her to look up, and to be calm. But the more he asked Mrs. Micawber to look up, the more she fixed her eyes on nothing; and the more he asked her to compose herself, the more she wouldn't. Consequently Mr. Micawber was soon so overcome, that he mingled his tears with hers and mine; until he begged me to do him the favor of taking a chair on the staircase, while he got her into bed. I would have taken my
<pb n="124" id="p124"/>
leave for the night, but he would not hear of my doing that until the strangers' bell should ring. So I sat at the staircase window, until he came out with another chair and joined me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How is Mrs. Micawber now, sir?&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very low,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, shaking his head; &ldquo;re-action. Ah, this has been a dreadful day! We stand alone now&mdash;everything is gone from us!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber pressed my hand, and groaned, and afterwards shed tears. I was greatly touched, and disappointed too, for I had expected that we should be quite gay on this happy and long-looked for occasion. But Mr. and Mrs. Micawber were so used to their old difficulties, I think, that they felt quite shipwrecked when they came to consider that they were released from them. All their elasticity was departed, and I never saw them half so wretched as on this night; insomuch that when the bell rang, and Mr. Micawber walked with me to the lodge, and parted from me there with a blessing, I felt quite afraid to leave him by himself, he was so profoundly miserable.</p>
<p>But through all the confusion and lowness of spirits in which we had been, so unexpectedly to me, involved, I plainly discerned that Mr. and Mrs. Micawber and their family were going away from London, and that a parting between us was near at hand. It was in my walk home that night, and in the sleepless hours which followed when I lay in bed, that the thought first occurred to me&mdash;though I don't know how it came into my head&mdash;which afterwards shaped itself into a settled resolution.</p>
<p>I had grown to be so accustomed to the Micawbers, and had been so intimate with them in their distresses, and was so utterly friendless without them, that the prospect of being thrown upon some new shift for a lodging, and going once more among unknown people, was like being that moment turned adrift into my present life, with such a knowledge of it ready made, as experience had given me. All the sensitive feelings it wounded so cruelly, all the shame and misery it kept alive within my breast, became more poignant as I thought of this; and I determined that the life was unendurable.</p>
<p>That there was no hope of escape from it, unless the escape was my own act, I knew quite well. I rarely heard from Miss Murdstone, and never from Mr. Murdstone: but two or three parcels of made or mended clothes had come up for me, consigned to Mr. Quinion, and in each there was a scrap of paper to the effect that J. M. trusted D. C. was applying himself to business, and devoting himself wholly to his duties&mdash;not the least hint of my ever being any thing else than the common drudge into which I was fast settling down.</p>
<p>The very next day showed me, while my mind was in the first agitation of what it had conceived, that Mrs. Micawber had not spoken of their going away without warrant. They took a lodging in the house where I lived, for a week; at the expiration of which time they were to start for Plymouth. Mr. Micawber himself came down to the counting-house, in the afternoon, to tell Mr. Quinion that he must relinquish me on the day of his departure, and to give me a high character, which I am sure I deserved. And Mr. Quinion, calling in Tipp the carman, who was a married man, and had a room to let, quartered me prospectively on him&mdash;
<pb n="125" id="p125"/>
by our mutual consent, as he had every reason to think; for I said nothing, though my resolution was now taken.</p>
<p>I passed my evenings with Mr. and Mrs. Micawber, during the remaining term of our residence under the same roof; and I think we became fonder of one another as the time went on. On the last Sunday, they invited me to dinner; and we had a loin of pork and apple sauce, and a pudding. I had bought a spotted wooden horse over-night as a parting gift to little Wilkins Micawber&mdash;that was the boy&mdash;and a doll for little Emma. I had also bestowed a shilling on the Orfling, who was about to be disbanded.</p>
<p>We had a very pleasant day, though we were all in a tender state about our approaching separation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall never, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;revert to the period when Mr. Micawber was in difficulties, without thinking of you. Your conduct has always been of the most delicate and obliging description. You have never been a lodger. You have been a friend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber; &ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; for so he had been accustomed to call me, of late, &ldquo;has a heart to feel for the distresses of his fellow creatures when they are behind a cloud, and a head to plan, and a hand to&mdash;in short, a general ability to dispose of such available property as could be made away with.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I expressed my sense of this commendation, and said I was very sorry we were going to lose one another.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear young friend,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;I am older than you; a man of some experience in life, and&mdash;and of some experience, in short, in difficulties, generally speaking. At present, and until something turns up (which I am, I may say, hourly expecting), I have nothing to bestow but advice. Still my advice is so far worth taking, that&mdash;in short, that I have never taken it myself, and am the&rdquo;&mdash;here Mr. Micawber, who had been beaming and smiling, all over his head and face, up to the present moment, checked himself and frowned&mdash;&ldquo;the miserable wretch you behold.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Micawber!&rdquo; urged his wife.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I say,&rdquo; returned Mr. Micawber, quite forgetting himself, and smiling again, &ldquo;the miserable wretch you behold. My advice is, never do to-morrow what you can do to-day. Procrastination is the thief of time. Collar him!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My poor papa's maxim,&rdquo; Mrs. Micawber observed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;your papa was very well in his way, and Heaven forbid that I should disparage him. Take him for all in all, we ne'er shall&mdash;in short, make the acquaintance, probably, of anybody else possessing, at his time of life, the same legs for gaiters, and able to read the same description of print, without spectacles. But he applied that maxim to our marriage, my dear; and that was so far prematurely entered into, in consequence, that I never recovered the expence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber looked aside at Mrs. Micawber, and added: &ldquo;Not that I am sorry for it. Quite the contrary, my love.&rdquo; After which, he was grave for a minute or so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My other piece of advice, Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;you know. Annual income twenty pounds, annual expenditure nineteen nineteen six, result happiness. Annual income twenty pounds, annual expenditure
<pb n="126" id="p126"/>
twenty pounds ought and six, result misery. The blossom is blighted, the leaf is withered, the god of day goes down upon the dreary scene, and&mdash;and in short you are for ever floored. As I am!&rdquo;</p>
<p>To make his example the more impressive, Mr. Micawber drank a glass of punch with an air of great enjoyment and satisfaction, and whistled the College Hornpipe.</p>
<p>I did not fail to assure him that I would store these precepts in my mind, though indeed I had no need to do so, for, at the time, they affected me visibly. Next morning I met the whole family at the coach-office, and saw them, with a desolate heart, take their places outside, at the back.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;God bless you! I never can forget all that, you know, and I never would if I could.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;farewell! Every happiness and prosperity! If, in the progress of revolving years, I could persuade myself that my blighted destiny had been a warning to you, I should feel that I had not occupied another man's place in existence altogether in vain. In case of anything turning up (of which I am rather confident), I shall be extremely happy if it should be in my power to improve your prospects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think, as Mrs. Micawber sat at the back of the coach, with the children, and I stood in the road looking wistfully at them, a mist cleared from her eyes, and she saw what a little creature I really was. I think so, because she beckoned to me to climb up, with quite a new and motherly expression in her face, and put her arm round my neck, and gave me just such a kiss as she might have given to her own boy. I had barely time to get down again before the coach started, and I could hardly see the family for the handkerchiefs they waved. It was gone in a minute. The Orfling and I stood looking vacantly at each other in the middle of the road, and then shook hands and said good bye; she going back, I suppose, to Saint Luke's workhouse, as I went to begin my weary day at Murdstone and Grinby's.</p>
<p>But with no intention of passing many more weary days there. No. I had resolved to run away.&mdash;To go, by some means or other, down into the country, to the only relation I had in the world, and tell my story to my aunt, Miss Betsey.</p>
<p>I have already observed that I don't know how this desperate idea came into my brain. But, once there, it remained there; and hardened into a purpose than which I have never entertained a more determined purpose in my life. I am far from sure that I believed there was anything hopeful in it, but my mind was thoroughly made up that it must be carried into execution.</p>
<p>Again, and again, and a hundred times again, since the night when the thought had first occurred to me and banished sleep, I had gone over that old story of my poor mother's about my birth, which it had been one of my great delights in the old time to hear her tell, and which I knew by heart. My aunt walked into that story, and walked out of it, a dread and awful personage; but there was one little trait in her behaviour which I liked to dwell on, and which gave me some faint shadow of encouragement. I could not forget how my mother had thought that she felt her touch her pretty hair with no ungentle hand; and though it might have been altogether my mother's fancy, and might have had no foundation whatever in fact, I made a little picture, out of it, of my terrible aunt relenting towards the girlish beauty that I recollected so well and loved
<pb n="127" id="p127"/>
so much, which softened the whole narrative. It is very possible that it had been in my mind a long time, and had gradually engendered my determination.</p>
<p>As I did not even know where Miss Betsey lived, I wrote a long letter to Peggotty, and asked her, incidentally, if she remembered; pretending that I had heard of such a lady living at a certain place I named at random, and had a curiosity to know if it were the same. In the course of that letter, I told Peggotty that I had a particular occasion for half a guinea; and that if she could lend me that sum until I could repay it, I should be very much obliged to her, and would tell her afterwards what I had wanted it for.</p>
<p>Peggotty's answer soon arrived, and was, as usual, full of affectionate devotion. She enclosed the half guinea (I was afraid she must have had a world of trouble to get it out of Mr. Barkis's box), and told me that Miss Betsey lived near Dover, but whether at Dover itself, at Hythe, Sandgate, or Folkstone, she could not say. One of our men, however, informing me on my asking him about these places, that they were all close together, I deemed this enough for my object, and resolved to set out at the end of that week.</p>
<p>Being a very honest little creature, and unwilling to disgrace the memory I was going to leave behind me at Murdstone and Grinby's, I considered myself found to remain until Saturday night; and, as I had been paid a week's wages in advance when I first came there, not to present myself in the counting-house at the usual hour, to receive my stipend. For this express reason, I had borrowed the half-guinea, that I might not be without a fund for my travelling-expenses. Accordingly, when the Saturday night came, and we were all waiting in the warehouse to be paid, and Tipp the carman, who always took precedence, went in first to draw his money, I shook Mick Walker by the hand; asked him when it came to his turn to be paid, to say to Mr. Quinion that I had gone to move my box to Tipp's; and, bidding a last good night to Mealy Potatoes, ran away.</p>
<p>My box was at my old lodging, over the water, and I had written a direction for it on the back of one of our address cards that we nailed on the casks: &ldquo;Master David, to be left till called for, at the Coach Office, Dover.&rdquo; This I had in my pocket ready to put on the box, after I should have got it out of the house; and as I went towards my lodging, I looked about me for some one who would help me to carry it to the booking-office.</p>
<p>There was a long-legged young man with a very little empty donkeycart, standing near the Obelisk, in the Blackfriars Road, whose eye I caught as I was going by, and who, addressing me as &ldquo;Sixpenn'orth of bad ha'pence,&rdquo; hoped &ldquo;I should know him agin to swear to&rdquo;&mdash;in allusion, I have no doubt, to my staring at him. I stopped to assure him that I had not done so in bad manners, but uncertain whether he might or might not like a job.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wot job?&rdquo; said the long-legged young man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To move a box,&rdquo; I answered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wot box?&rdquo; said the long-legged young man.</p>
<p>I told him mine, which was down that street there, and which I wanted him to take to the Dover coach-office for sixpence.</p>
<pb n="128" id="p128"/>
<p>&ldquo;Done with you for a tanner!&rdquo; said the long-legged young man, and directly got upon his cart, which was nothing but a large wooden-tray on wheels, and rattled away at such a rate, that it was as much as I could do to keep pace with the donkey.</p>
<p>There was a defiant manner about this young man, and particularly about the way in which he chewed straw as he spoke to me, that I did not much like; as the bargain was made, however, I took him up-stairs to the room I was leaving, and we brought the box down, and put it on his cart. Now, I was unwilling to put the direction-card on there, lest any of my landlord's family should fathom what I was doing, and detain me; so I said to the young man that I would be glad if he would stop for a minute, when he came to the dead-wall of the King's Bench prison. The words were no sooner out of my mouth, than he rattled away as if he, my box, the cart, and the donkey, were all equally mad; and I was quite out of breath with running and calling after him, when I caught him at the place appointed.</p>
<p>Being much flushed and excited, I tumbled my half-guinea out of my pocket in pulling the card out. I put it in my mouth for safety, and though my hands trembled a good deal, had just tied the card on very much to my satisfaction, when I felt myself violently chucked under the chin by the long-legged young man, and saw my half-guinea fly out of my mouth into his hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wot!&rdquo; said the young man, seizing me by my jacket collar, with a frightful grin. &ldquo;This is a pollis case, is it? You're a going to bolt, are you? Come to the pollis, you young warmin, come to the pollis!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You give me my money back, if you please,&rdquo; said I, very much frightened; &ldquo;and leave me alone.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come to the pollis!&rdquo; said the young man. &ldquo;You shall prove it yourn to the pollis.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Give me my box and money, will you,&rdquo; I cried, bursting into tears.</p>
<p>The young man still replied: &ldquo;Come to the pollis!&rdquo; and was dragging me against the donkey in a violent manner, as if there were any affinity between that animal and a magistrate, when he changed his mind, jumped into the cart, sat upon my box, and, exclaiming that he would drive to the pollis straight, rattled away harder than ever.</p>
<p>I ran after him as fast as I could, but I had no breath to call out with, and should not have dared to call out, now, if I had. I narrowly escaped being run over, twenty times at least, in half a mile. Now I lost him, now I saw him, now I lost him, now I was cut at with a whip, now shouted at, now down in the mud, now up again, now running into somebody's arms, now running headlong at a post. At length, confused by fright and heat, and doubting whether half London might not by this time be turning out for my apprehension, I left the young man to go where he would with my box and money; and, panting and crying, but never stopping, faced about for Greenwich, which I had understood was on the Dover Road: taking very little more out of the world, towards the retreat of my aunt, Miss Betsey, than I had brought into it, on the night when my arrival gave her so much umbrage.</p>
</div2>
</div1>


</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<head>THE VAUNTING MARTS OF RIVALRY</head>
<lg type="poem">
<head>AIR&mdash; &ldquo;The Flaunting Flag of Liberty.&rdquo;</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>The vaunting marts of rivalry,</l>
<l>Which none can well admire,</l>
<l>Shall never once be sought by me,</l>
<l>In purchasing attire.</l>
<l>The only warehouse which appears</l>
<l>To claim my zealous aid,</l>
<l>Is a mart that's brav'd, for many years</l>
<l>The battle of the trade.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem">
<l>MOSES &amp; SON can furnish Dress</l>
<l>Upon the choicest plan,</l>
<l>And yet the clothing costs us less&mdash;</l>
<l>Dispute it if you can.</l>
<l>The gentleman, where'er he steers,</l>
<l>Sees tasty styles display'd,</l>
<l>From the mart that's braved, for many years,</l>
<l>The battle of the trade.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Let all unite, as long they've done,</l>
<l>Their favours to bestow;</l>
<l>And sure I am that M. &amp; SON,</l>
<l>Will greater merits show.</l>
<l>While such vast benefit appears,</l>
<l>'Tis right that we should aid</l>
<l>The mart that's braved, for many years,</l>
<l>The battle of the trade.</l>
</lg>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Spring and Summer Wrappers, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, Pacha, Paletot, and every description of Light Overcoat from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture, and handsomely trimmed from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture, and handsomely trimmed lined with Silk from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture, and handsomely trimmed superior quality &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Jean and Holland Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fancy Victoria Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tweed Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock Coats &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spring and Summer Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin and Buckskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spring and Summer Vests, in every variety&mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black and Figured Satin Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black superior quality &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White Marcella Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Cloth Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boye' Hussar and Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boye' Spring and Summer Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Fishing Coats, in every variety &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="22" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paletots, made from a variety of materials, fitted for Summer wear from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paletots, in every style, elegantly trimmed, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Cloth in every style, of a light texture </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Cloth in every style lined with Silk </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Cloth Dress Coat &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dress Coat for </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Frock Dress Coat from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dress Coat for </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fancy Doeskin Trousers from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Doeskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Doeskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Cloth Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cloth Vests for </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Splendid Satin Cloth Vests from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Splendid Satin Cloth Vests for </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's White Marcella Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fishing Coats, in endless variety, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes, in great variety, from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>LIVERIES, NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Clothes complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Great Fact,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Parasol Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON,</head><p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p2a" n="[2]"/>
<head>THE NICOLL, REGENT STREET, <lb/> AND 22, CORNHILL, LONDON.</head>
<p>BESIDES the above Patented Article of Dress (called the NICOLL), there is another Novelty introduced for this Season, which is, however, Registered under the name of NICOLL'S MORNING COAT, it being especially intended for morning wear, in riding or walking exercise, when it necessarily avoids the stiff formality to be observed in the cut and form of the dress-coat. The price is TWO GUINEAS.</p>
<p>The premises (extending from 114 to 120, Regent Street), as illuminated in honour of <lb/> Her Majesty's and the Prince's Birthdays.</p>
<p>THE REGISTERED PALETOT is now ready for the Summer and Autumnal Months, with all the new and patented improvements, included in the moderate price of TWO GUINEAS. Thus it deservedly bears the name of being not only the most fashionable, but also the cheapest and most durable garment ever offered to the public; the immense value of the material known as NICOLLIAN, or LLAMA CLOTH, being, within the last few months, much enhanced; the same durability being retained, with an increased fineness and beauty in appearance. It can be seen, ready for immediate wear, in every size, at the Patentees' Warerooms.</p>
<p>114, 116, &amp; 120, REGENT STREET, <lb/> 22, CORNHILL, FACING ROYAL EXCHANGE.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
