<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VIII:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Brooke Phillips</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.   200K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VIII:</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>  54 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1849</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>
</p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings </title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2002-11-13, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-10-01, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>




<titlePage>


<docTitle><titlePart> No.  VIII. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> DECEMBER.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of Bedding, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest stock and greatest variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES, <lb/> Of which they were the Original Introducers: these Mattresses are made of the finest material, quite equal to the best made in Paris. Also, <lb/> GERMAN SPRING MATTRESSES.</p>
<p>These HEAL and SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are selling at a much lower price than any other house, and can recommend one of them, with a FRENCH MATTRESS on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>THE EIDER DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen <hi rend="italics">only</hi> at their House. It is the warmest, the lightest, and the most elegant covering ever introduced, suitable to the <hi rend="italics">Bed,</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Couch,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">Carriage.</hi> All who have travelled on the Continent are aware that no covering produces such extreme warmth with the same weight; so that for Invalids they are a perfect luxury. Their <lb/> BED FEATHERS <lb/> are also PURIFIED BY STEAM, WITH PATENT MACHINERY, by which the offensive properties of the quill are evaporated and carried off, without subjecting the Feathers to the unpleasant smell of the stove, to which all Feathers dressed in the ordinary way are liable.</p>
<p>HEAL and SON are now enabled to sell Grey Goose Feathers at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per lb., Poultry, 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foreign Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White Goose </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dantzie Goose </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>OLD FEATHER-BEDS re-dressed by this process are perfectly freed from all impurities; and, by expanding the Feathers, the bulk is greatly increased, and the Bed consequently rendered much fuller and softer, at 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb.</p>
<p>OLD AND MOTHY MATTRESSES effectually cured and re-made.</p>
<p>Every description of BLANKETS, QUILTS, and SHEETINGS.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S LIST OF BEDDING.</head>
<p>It contains full particulars of WEIGHTS, SIZES, and PRICES, of every description of Bedding, and is so arranged that purchasers are enabled to judge of the articles best suitable to make a comfortable Bed. Sent free by post on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196, (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL,) <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb id="p1" n="[1]"/>
<head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<head><hi rend="italics">ROYAL BANK BUILDINGS,</hi></head><p>LIVERPOOL, <hi rend="italics">September,</hi> 1850.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In September,</hi> 1840&mdash;<hi rend="italics">We Opened a department for the supplying of Families with Tea and Coffee&mdash;upon a principle calculated to afford the greatest advantage in Price&mdash;with every security as to Quality.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">WHEN QUALITY</hi> is thus made the primary consideration&mdash;and <hi rend="italics">Price</hi> is fixed upon strictly economical principles&mdash;we were confident that our interest&mdash;as involved in the question of Profit&mdash;would be fully secured by an increasing demand, which has been, and must be, the result of such a system&mdash;so obviously based.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">THE CONSTANT</hi> care and exact judgement exercised in our method of selection and classification of qualities&mdash;have been appreciated, and proved by the continually increasing extent of the FAMILY TRADE&mdash;in connection with our Establishment.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">WE CANNOT</hi> refrain from directing the attention of Family Purchasers, to the present anomalous state of the&mdash;TEA MARKET&mdash;viz.</p>
<p>THE FIRST COST of good and choice kinds is,&mdash;at present,&mdash;unusually reasonable, at the same time, there is an increasing demand for the commonest BLACK TEA. This indicates that&mdash;CHEAPNESS&mdash;being more regarded by many Dealers than QUALITY&mdash;Disappointment is the necessary consequence, to <hi rend="italics">FAMILIES</hi> whose supplies are derived from parties not possessing the requisite advantages in SELECTION and PURCHASE.</p>
<p>ROB<hi rend="superscript">T</hi> ROBERTS &amp; COMP<hi rend="superscript">Y.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Entrance up the Steps&mdash;leading to the BANK.</hi></p>
<p>NOTE.&mdash;Liverpool <hi rend="italics">with its</hi> Docks, <hi rend="italics">stands eminently advantageous for the Importing of Tea. Its superior Shipping Trade, having Docks covering upwards of</hi> 250 <hi rend="italics">Statute Acres&mdash;with more than</hi> 20 <hi rend="italics">miles of Quay space, an amount of accommodation to be found in no other Port in the World.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Low Rates of Shipping Charges and the great facility for Dispatch,&mdash;have already secured to the Port of Liverpool nearly the whole of the Export Trade to China.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<head>ILLUSTRATED WEEKLY PERIODICAL FOR LADIES.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s., bound in an elegant cover, designed expressly for the Work,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">by</hi> H. N. HUMPHREYS, Esq., <lb/> THE FIRST VOLUME OF <lb/> THE LADIES' COMPANION <lb/> At Home and Abroad.</p>
<p>EMBELLISHED WITH A GREAT NUMBER OF LARGE AND SMALL ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">And containing a variety of Contributions from some of the most distinguished Writers of the day.</hi></p>
<p>Published Weekly, price 3d., Stamped, 4d., and in Monthly Parts.</p>
<p>Part IX. is now ready, price 1s. 2d., and may be had of all Booksellers.</p>
<closer>OFFICE, 11, BOUVERIE STREET, FLEET STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW WORKS ON GARDENING.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In a few days will be Published, neatly bound in Cloth,</hi>
<lb/> &ldquo;HOW TO LAY OUT A SMALL GARDEN.&rdquo;</p>
<p>INTENDED AS A GUIDE TO AMATEURS <lb/> In Choosing, Forming, or Improving a Place, (from a Quarter of an Acre to Thirty Acres in extent,) <lb/> with reference to both Design and Execution.</p>
<p>BY EDWARD KEMP, <lb/> Landscape Gardener, Birkenhead Park.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s., bound in Cloth, for the Pocket,</hi>
<lb/> THE HAND-BOOK OF GARDENING; <lb/> Expressly intended for persons possessing, and fond of cultivating, a Garden of moderate size. A New Edition, revised, and greatly enlarged.</p>
<p>BY EDWARD KEMP.</p>
<p>New Monthly Work by Joseph Paxton and Dr. Lindley.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., No. IX. of</hi>
<lb/> PAXTON'S FLOWER GARDEN <lb/> EDITED BY JOSEPH PAXTON AND DR. LINDLEY.</p>
<p>AND ILLUSTRATED BY HIGHLY FINISHED PLATES AND WOODCUTS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Numbers I. to VIII. may be procured of any Bookseller.</hi></p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE NEW SERIES OF ROYAL FEMALE BIOGRAPHIES.</head>
<p>LIVES OF THE QUEENS OF SCOTLAND, <lb/> AND ENGLISH PRINCESSES <lb/> CONNECTED WITH THE REGAL SUCCESSION OF GREAT BRITAIN.</p>
<p>BY AGNES STRICKLAND, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Lives of the Queens of England.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This Series will be comprised in Six Volumes post 8vo, uniform in size with the &ldquo;LIVES OF THE QUEENS OF ENGLAND,&rdquo; embellished with Portraits and Engraved Title-pages.</p>
<p>Vol. I. will be published in October, containing the Lives of MARGARET TUDOR, Queen of James IV.; MAGDALENE OF FRANCE, first Queen of James V.; MARY OF LORRAINE, second Queen of James V., and Mother of Queen Mary.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., handsomely bound in cloth.</hi></p>
<p>Volume II. will be published early in 1851.</p>
<closer>WILLIAM BLACKWOOD AND SONS, EDINBURGH AND LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<head>Warren's Sketches of Character.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HANDWRITING.</p>
<p>Specimens of Writing, with an enclosure of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's age, to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head>
<p>The Patentees of this Umbrella, in thanking the Nobility and Public in general for the great patronage they have received, beg to state that the demand for it continues to increase as its advantages become demonstrated by daily experience, upwards of 60,000 having been sold during the last two years.</p>
<p>The economy effected in the cost of an article so indispensable in this climate, joined with its extreme durability, must always secure for it an extensive sale. They may be obtained of most Umbrella Dealers in the Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>A large assortment of Silk Umbrellas, at prices varying according to quality, from 7<hi rend="italics">s,</hi> each, and Gingham, from 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<closer>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, <lb/> 140, Regent-street; 94 Fleet-street; 10, Royal Exchange; <lb/> Warhouse 75, Cheapside.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free, for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA</head><p>and all other Medicines of a nauseous character may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES. These Capsule will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p>
<p>The recent discovery that the low priced Gelatine Capsules contain a compound of train and other oils, and in many cases no Copaiba whatever, renders it important that the public should be made aware that the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES are guaranteed to contain <hi rend="italics">genuine Copaiba only.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<opener>MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT</opener><head>HAIR AN ORNAMENT.</head>
<p>IT is universally admitted that one of the most admired ornaments of the person is the hair. So necessary is it considered to the perfection of female beauty, that any loss or deterioration of this covering of the head impairs good looks to such a degree that artificial locks are obliged to be resorted to to give the proper effect to beautiful features, which, without such aid, would be deprived of half their charm. Who will not say that the appearance of a man, also, is greatly improved by a fine head of hair?</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>GREEK AND ROMAN.</head>
<p>The ancients highly esteemed a fine head of hair. And we learn from Juvenal and Horace, that, among the Romans, nothing was deemed more essential to the beauty of a young person, than fine long hair covering the head&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Loose to the wind her golden tresses streamed.&rdquo;&mdash;PETRARCH.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<p>MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT <lb/> Will be found admirably to supply the deficiencies of Nature: its wonderful effects will be speedily observed to produce a change in hair, however, thin and harsh, to a state of silky luxuriance and beauty, easily dressed in any fashion.</p>
<p>Its perfume is essentially novel and most delicious. In elegant pots, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p>
<p>Sold by all Perfumers and Medicine Vendors in Town and Country. Wholesale London Agents:&mdash;Messrs. Barclay and Sons, Farringdon-street; Edwards, St. Paul's Churchyard; Sutton and Co., Bow Churchyard; Sanger, 151, Oxford-street; and Hannay and Co., Oxford, street.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">N.B. The above Engraving is a fac-simile of the Elegant Pot.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<opener>ON <lb/> THE <lb/> LAND,<lb/>OR <lb/> ON THE <lb/> SEA.<lb/> COMFORT IN A STORM!</opener>
<head>EDMISTON'S <lb/> POCKET SIPHONIA DREADNOUGHT,</head><p>WEIGHT ABOUT EIGHT OUNCES.</p>
<p>A NEWLY INVENTED WATERPROOF FABRIC, made as a Coat, expressly to carry in the Pocket, in lieu of an Umbrella, adapted for Fishing, Driving, or Shooting, will be found by Sportsmen, Sailors, and Travellers, superior to any other kind of Waterproof material made up for their use; they will resist the heaviest, rain, and the fiercest tropical heat; their lightness is such that one exclaims, &ldquo;Have I a coat on, or not?&rdquo; obviating the extreme heat engendered by all other waterproof material.</p>
<p>Price according to size; in India Cloth, 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 36<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and 42<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; and in Silk throughout, 50<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 65<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>LEGGINGS, YACHT JACKETS, LADIES' CAPES AND HOODS, ETC.</p>
<p>Country Gentlemen supplied by sending Height and Size round the Chest over the Coat.</p>
<closer>London: EDMISTON AND SON, 69, Strand, opposite the Adelphi Theatre.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>THE POSTMASTER-GENERAL having officially notified to the public the necessity of using Hard Sealing Wax for correspondence to hot climates, HYDE &amp; CO., of 61, Fleet st., Sealing-Wax-Makers to the Queen and the Government, intimate that they manufacture the INDIA WAX to the order of the Comptroller of her Majesty's Stationery Office. This Wax, from its peculiar properties, affords the only security to foreign letters. Each stick is stamped &ldquo;India Wax for Hot Climates. Hyde, London.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Supplied wholesale and retail, at 61, Fleet-street, London, the Manufactory for Sealing Wax of every description; also by MARION, Regent-street, and Paris; and by all country stationers.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>COUGH JUJUBE LOZENGES.&mdash;</head><p>These Jujubes are composed of the most approved expectorants, with pure gum, which, by relieving the irritation in the air passages, present a safe, agreeable, and efficacious Medicine in all cases of Asthma, Bronchitis, difficult Respirations, Consumptive complaints, and all other affections of the Chest and Lungs.</p>
<p>Prepared and sold, wholesale only, by WARRICK BROTHERS, 3, Garlick-hill, Upper Thames-street; land retail, by all Chemists and Druggists throughout the country. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per box, with directions.</p>
<p>Also Proprietors of the ACIDULATED CAYENNE JUJUBE LOZENGES.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Lauguor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p>furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy and preserving the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.&mdash;&ldquo;ROBERT SHAW, London,&rdquo; is in white letters on the Government Stamp of the genuine. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; quarts, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<opener>PERFECT HEALTH IS INVARIABLY RESTORED <lb/> without medicine, inconvenience, or expense, to the most nervous, delicate, dyspeptic, constipated, bilious, debilitated, or shattered constitution, by</opener><head>DU BARRY'S DELICIOUS HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD.</head>
<p>THE REVALENTA ARABICA which saves fifty times its cost in other means of cure, and effectually removes indigestion (dyspepsia), constipation and diarrhoea, nervousness, biliousness, liver complaint, flatulency, distension, palpitation of the heart, nervous headache, deafness, noises in the head and ears, pains in almost every part of the body, chronic inflammation and ulceration of the stomach, erysipelas, eruptions on the skin, incipient consumption, dropsy, rheumatism, gout, heartburn, nausea and sickness during pregnancy, after eating, or at sea, low spirits, spasms, cramps, spleen, general debility, paralysis, asthma, cough, inquietude, sleeplessness, involuntary blushing, tremors, dislike to society, unfitness for study, loss of memory, delusions, blood to the head, exhaustion, melancholy, groundless fear, indecision, wretchedness, thoughts of self-destruction, and many other complaints. It is the best food for infants and invalids generally, as it never turns acid on the weakest stomach, nor interferes with a good liberal diet, but imparts a healthy relish for lunch and dinner, and restores the faculty of digestion and muscular and nervous energy to the most enfeebled.</p>
<p>Discovered, exclusively grown, and imported by DU BARRY &amp; Co., 127, New Bond-street, London, sole owners of the Revalenta Arabica Estates, and of the Patent Machinery by which alone the curative principles of the Plant can be developed,&mdash;hence none other can be genuine.</p>
<p>DU BARRY &amp; CO., 127, NEW BOND STREET, LONDON.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>A FEW OF 50,000 TESTIMONIALS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">From the Right Honourable the Lord Stuart de Decies.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;I have derived much benefit from Du Barry's Health-Restoring Food.</p>
<p>STUART DE DECIES.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dromana, Cappoquin, county of Waterford.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twenty-five years' nervousness, constipation, indigestion, and debility, from which I had suffered great misery, and which no medicine could remove or relieve, have been effectually cured by DU BAHRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD, in a very short time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pool Anthony, Tiverton.&rdquo;</p>
<p>W. R. REEVES.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sixty years' partial paralysis, affecting one-half of my frame, and which had resisted all other remedies, has yielded to DU BARRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD; and I now consider myself a stranger to all complaints, excepting a hearty old age.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WILLIAM HUNT, Barrister-at-Law.</p>
<p>&ldquo;King's College, Cambridge.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not expected to live six days longer. I was cured by DU BARRY'S admirable HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Moffat, Scotland.&rdquo;</p>
<p>MAGDALENA PURVIS.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Eight years' dyspepsia, nervousness, debility with cramps, spasms, and nausea, for which my servant had consulted the advice of many, have been effectually removed by DU BARRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD, in a very short time. I shall be happy to answer any inquiries.</p>
<p>REV. JOHN W. FLAVELL.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ridlington Rectory, Norfolk.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Three years' excessive nervousness, with pains in my neck and left arm, and general debility, which rendered my life very miserable, has been radically removed by DU BARRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD.</p>
<p>ALEX. STUART,</p>
<p>&ldquo;Archdeacon of Ross, Skibbereen.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I consider you a blessing to society at large. It is not to be told, all the benefit DU BARRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD has been to me; and my little boy cries for a saucer of it every morning.</p>
<p>WALTER KEATING.</p>
<p>&ldquo;2, Manning-place, Five Oaks, Jersey.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thirteen years' cough, indigestion, and general debility have been removed by DU BARRY'S excellent HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD.</p>
<p>JAMES PORTER.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Athol-street, Perth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twenty years' dyspepsia, with the most distressing symptoms of flatulency, constipation, sickness at the stomach, acidity, and irritability, which had resisted all medicines, has been entirely removed by DU BARRY'S HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD.</p>
<p>&ldquo;SAMUEL BARLOW, Chemist, Darlington.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Devon Cottage, Bromley, Middlesex, March 31, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;GENTLEMEN.&mdash;The lady for whom I ordered your food is six months advanced in pregnancy, and was suffering severely from indigestion and constipation, throwing up her meals shortly after eating them, having a great deal of heartburn, and being constantly obliged to resort to physic or the enema, and sometimes to both. I am happy to inform you that your food produced immediate relief: she has never been sick since, has but little heartburn, and the functions are more regular, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;THOMAS WOODHOUSE.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Louisa-terrace, Exmouth, Aug. 17, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;DEAR SIR,&mdash;I will thank you to send me, on receipt of this, two ten-pound canisters of your HEALTH-RESTORING FOOD. I beg to assure you that its beneficial effects have been duly appreciated by, dear Sir, yours most respectfully,</p>
<p>&ldquo;THOMAS KING, Major-General.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;3, Sydney-terrace, Reading, Berks, Dec. 3, 1847.</p>
<p>&ldquo;GENTLEMEN,&mdash;I am happy to be able to inform you that the person for whom the former quantity was procured, has derived very great benefit from its use; distressing symptoms of long standing have been removed, and a feeling of restored health induced. Having witnessed the beneficial effects in the above-mentioned case, I can with confidence recommend it, and shall have much pleasure in so doing whenever an opportunity offers, &amp;c. &amp;c.&mdash;I am, gentlemen, very truly yours,</p>
<p>&ldquo;JAMES SHORLAND, late Surgeon 96th Regt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;22, High-street, Ayr, Scotland, Sept. 2nd, 1850.</p>
<p>&ldquo;GENTLEMEN,&mdash;I certainly must pay you the compliment of stating. that you have not said more in favour of your excellent FOOD than it deserves.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A. WILSON.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A full report of important cures of the above complaints, and a copious extract from 50,000 testimonials from parties of the highest respectability, is sent gratis by DO BARRY &amp; Co., on application. Important Caution.&mdash;Numerous complaints have been received from invalids of their health having been fearfully impaired by spurious compounds of pease, beans, Indian and oat-meal, palmed off upon them under closely similar names, such as Ervalenta, Arabian Revalenta, Lentil Powder, &amp;c., MESSRS. DU BARRY have taken the trouble of analysing all these compounds, and find them to be harmless as food to the healthy, but utterly devoid of all curative principles, and being of a flatulent and irritating tendency, they are no better adapted to cure disease, than oil to quenching a conflagration. Nor can these imitative impostors show a single cure, whilst DU BARRY'S REVALENTA ARABICA has received the most flattering testimonials from 50,000 persons of high respectability; nor is it an exaggeration to ascribe to this extraordinary curative FOOD a share in the great decrease of disease and mortality in the metropolis&mdash;a decrease of 200 deaths per week. Sold in canisters, with full instructions, and bearing the seal and signature of DU BARRY &amp; Co., (without which none can be genuine,) weighing 1 lb. at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; 2 lbs. at 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; 5 lbs at 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; 12 lbs. at 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; super-refined quality, 10 lbs. at 33<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>; 5 lbs. at 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>&mdash;DU BARRY &amp; Co., 127, New Bond Street, London; also of Fortnum, Mason, and Co., Purveyors to Her Majesty the Queen; Hedges and Butler; Barclay; Sterry, Sterry, and Co.; Evans, Lescher, and Co.; Edwards; Rumsey; Sutton; Newberry; Sanger; Hannay; and through all respectable grocers, chemists, medicine vendors, and booksellers, in the kingdom.</p>
<p>DU BARRY'S PULMONIC BONBONS, <lb/> A nice, safe, and effectual remedy for coughs, colds, asthma, and all affections of the lungs, throat, and voice, are <lb/> of unrivalled excellency. In boxes, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; or, Post Free, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<closer>DU BARRY &amp; Co., 127, NEW BOND STREET, LONDON.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambrie Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambrie Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Under Royal Patronage.</opener>
<head>Dr.  
LOCOCK'S <lb/> PULMONIC WAFERS</head>
<p>GIVE INSTANT RELIEF, AND A RAPID CURE OF <lb/> Asthma, Consumption, Coughs, Colds, and all Disorders of the Breath and Lungs.</p>
<p>IN COUGHS.&mdash;The effect of Dr. Locock's Waters is truly surprising, as within ten minutes after taking a dose the most violent cough is subdued.</p>
<p>They have a pleasant taste, and may be taken by infants as wells as adults.</p>
<p>TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS, these Wafers are invaluable, as by their action on the throat and lungs they remove all hoarseness in a few hours, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p>
<p>NOTE.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Full Directions are given with every Box in the English, German, and French languages.</hi></p>
<p>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per Box. The 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Boxes contain nearly three of the 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and the 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Boxes contain five of those at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> ALSO </p>
<p>
Dr.  
LOCOCK'S <lb/> ANTIBILIOUS WAFERS
<lb/> THEY HAVE A MOST PLEASANT TASTE.</p>
<p>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per Box.</p>
<p>THIS is an aromatic and aperient Medicine of great efficacy for regulating the secretions, and correcting the action of the Stomach and Liver, and is the only safe remedy for all BILIOUS AFFECTIONS,&mdash;Heartburn, Sick Head-ache, Giddiness, Pains in the Stomach, Flatulency, or Wind, and all those complaints which arise from Indigestion or Biliousness. It is mild in its action, and suitable for all seasons and constitutions, while its AGREEABLE TASTE renders it the <hi rend="italics">best Medicine for Children.</hi></p>
<p>Testimonial.&mdash;&ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;We have much pleasure in bearing testimony to the very great efficacy of Dr. Locock's Wafers; we have no hesitation in saying this from our own experience, and they continue to give the same satisfaction wherever they are introduced, &amp;c.&mdash;Signed, J. R. ALLAN and CO., 42, Kirkgate, Leith, August 17, 1850.&rdquo;</p>
<p>
Dr.  
LOCOCK'S <lb/>FEMALE WAFERS
<lb/>
HAVE A PLEASANT TASTE.</p>
<p>THEY fortify the constitution at all periods of life, and in all Nervous Affections act like a charm. They remove all Obstructions, Heaviness, Fatigue on Slight Exertion, Palpitation of the Heart, Lowness of Spirits, Weakness, and Allay Pain.</p>
<p>They create Appetite, and remove Indigestion, Heartburn, Wind, Head-aches, Giddiness, &amp;c.</p>
<p>In Hysterical Diseases, a proper perseverance in the use of this Medicine will be found to effect a Cure after all other means have failed.</p>
<p>Full directions are given with every Box.</p>
<p>NOTE.&mdash;These Wafers do not contain any Mineral, and may be taken either dissolved in water or whole.</p>
<p>BEWARE OF IMITATIONS IN THE FORM OF PILLS!</p>
<p>IMPORTANT CAUTION.&mdash;Counterfeits may be guarded against by simply observing that no Medicine is genuine but &ldquo;WAFERS,&rdquo; and that the words, &ldquo;DR. LOCOCK'S WAFERS,&rdquo; are in the Government Stamp outside' each Box.</p>
<closer>ALL PILLS UNDER SIMILAR NAMES ARE COUNTERFEITS.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<opener>Purity of Flavour <lb/> characterises <lb/> the Teas <lb/> sold by</opener><head>DAKIN &amp; COMPY.</head>
<p>Moderation in Price <lb/> recommends to <lb/> all classes of consumers <lb/> the Teas <lb/> sold at <lb/> NUMBER ONE, <lb/> SAINT PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</p>
<p>Excellence of Quality distinguishes the Teas sold by <lb/> DAKIN &amp; COMPY., TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> NUMBER ONE, SAINT PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</p>
<p>Excellence of Quality, Purity of Flavour, and Moderation in Price, all unite in <lb/> rendering pre-eminent the Teas supplied at</p><closer>NUMBER ONE, SAINT PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">I make the acquaintance of Miss Mowcher.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Martha.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<pb n="225" id="p225"/>

<head>[THE 

<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]

</head>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER XXII. <lb/> SOME OLD SCENES, AND SOME NEW PEOPLE.</head>
<p>STEERFORTH and I stayed for more than a fortnight in that part of the country. We were very much together, I need not say; but occasionally we were asunder for some hours at a time. He was a good sailor, and I was but an indifferent one; and when he went out boating with Mr. Peggotty, which was a favorite amusement of his, I generally remained ashore. My occupation of Peggotty's spare-room put a constraint upon me, from which he was free: for, knowing how assiduously she attended on Mr. Barkis all day, I did not like to remain out late at night; whereas Steerforth, lying at the Inn, had nothing to consult but his own humour. Thus it came about, that I heard of his making little treats for the fishermen at Mr. Peggotty's house of call, &ldquo;The Willing Mind,&rdquo; after I was in bed, and of his being afloat, wrapped in fisherman's clothes, whole moonlight nights, and coming back when the morning tide was at flood. By this time, however, I knew that his restless nature and bold spirits delighted to find a vent in rough toil and hard weather, as in any other means of excitement that presented itself freshly to him; so none of his proceedings surprised me.</p>
<p>Another cause of our being sometimes apart, was, that I had naturally an interest in going over to Blunderstone, and revisiting the old familiar scenes of my childhood; while Steerforth, after being there once, had naturally no great interest in going there again. Hence, on three or four days that I can at once recal, we went our several ways after an early breakfast, and met again at a late dinner. I had no idea how he employed his time in the interval, beyond a general knowledge that he was very popular in the place, and had twenty means of actively diverting himself where another man might not have found one.</p>
<p>For my own part, my occupation in my solitary pilgrimages was to recal every yard of the old road as I went along it, and to haunt the old spots, of which I never tired. I haunted them, as my memory had often done, and lingered among them as my younger thoughts had lingered when I was far away. The grave beneath the tree, where both my parents lay&mdash;on which I had looked out, when it was my father's only, with such curious feelings of compassion, and by which I had stood, so desolate, when it was opened to receive my pretty mother and her baby&mdash;the grave which Peggotty's own faithful care had ever since kept neat, and made a garden of, I walked near, by the hour. It lay a little off the church-yard path, in a quiet corner, not so far removed but I could read the names upon the stone as I walked to and fro, startled by the sound of the church-bell when it struck the hour, for it was like a departed voice to me. My reflections at these times were always associated with the figure I was to make in life, and the distinguished things I was to do. My echoing footsteps went to no other tune, but were as constant to that as if I had come home to build my castles in the air at a living mother's side.</p>
<pb n="226" id="p226"/>
<p>There were great changes in my old home. The ragged nests, so long deserted by the rooks, were gone; and the trees were lopped and topped out of their remembered shapes. The garden had run wild, and half the windows of the house were shut up. It was occupied, but only by a poor lunatic gentleman, and the people who took care of him. He was always sitting at my little window, looking out into the church-yard; and I wondered whether his rambling thoughts ever went upon any of the fancies that used to occupy mine, on the rosy mornings when I peeped out of that same little window in my night-clothes, and saw the sheep quietly feeding in the light of the rising sun.</p>
<p>Our old neighbours, Mr. and Mrs. Grayper, were gone to South America, and the rain had made its way through the roof of their empty house, and stained the outer walls. Mr. Chillip was married again to a tall, rawboned, high-nosed wife; and they had a weazen little baby, with a heavy head that it couldn't hold up, and two weak staring eyes, with which it seemed to be always wondering why it had ever been born.</p>
<p>It was with a singular jumble of sadness and pleasure that I used to linger about my native place, until the reddening winter sun admonished me that it was time to start on my returning walk. But, when the place was left behind, and especially when Steerforth and I were happily seated over our dinner by a blazing fire, it was delicious to think of having been there. So it was, though in a softened degree, when I went to my neat room at night; and, turning over the leaves of the crocodile-book (which was always there, upon a little table), remembered with a grateful heart how blest I was in having such a friend as Steerforth, such a friend as Peggotty, and such a substitute for what I had lost as my excellent and generous aunt.</p>
<p>My nearest way to Yarmouth, in coming back from these long walks, was by a ferry. It landed me on the flat between the town and the sea, which I could make straight across, and so save myself a considerable circuit by the high road. Mr. Peggotty's house being on that waste-place, and not a hundred yards out of my track, I always looked in as I went by. Steerforth was pretty sure to be there expecting me, and we went on together through the frosty air and gathering fog towards the twinkling lights of the town.</p>
<p>One dark evening, when I was later than usual&mdash;for I had, that day, been making my parting visit to Blunderstone, as we were now about to return home&mdash;I found him alone in Mr. Peggotty's house, sitting thoughtfully before the fire. He was so intent upon his own reflections that he was quite unconscious of my approach. This, indeed, he might easily have been if he had been less absorbed, for footsteps fell noiselessly on the sandy ground outside; but even my entrance failed to rouse him. I was standing close to him, looking at him; and still, with a heavy brow, he was lost in his meditations.</p>
<p>He gave such a start when I put my hand upon his shoulder, that he made me start too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You come upon me,&rdquo; he said, almost angrily, &ldquo;like a reproachful ghost!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was obliged to announce myself somehow,&rdquo; I replied. &ldquo;Have I called you down from the stars?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; he answered. &ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="227" id="p227"/>
<p>&ldquo;Up from anywhere, then?&rdquo; said I, taking my seat near him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was looking at the pictures in the fire,&rdquo; he returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But you are spoiling them for me,&rdquo; said I, as he stirred it quickly with a piece of burning wood, striking out of it a train of red-hot sparks that went careering up the little chimney, and roaring out into the air.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You would not have seen them,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;I detest this mongrel time, neither day nor night. How late you are! Where have you been?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been taking leave of my usual walk,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I have been sitting here,&rdquo; said Steerforth, glancing round the room, &ldquo;thinking that all the people we found so glad on the night of our coming down, might&mdash;to judge from the present wasted air of the place&mdash;be dispersed, or dead, or come to I don't know what harm. David, I wish to God I had had a judicious father these last twenty years!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Steerforth, what is the matter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wish with all my soul I had been better guided!&rdquo; he exclaimed. &ldquo;I wish with all my soul I could guide myself better!&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a passionate dejection in his manner that quite amazed me. He was more unlike himself than I could have supposed possible.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It would be better to be this poor Peggotty, or his lout of a nephew,&rdquo; he said, getting up and leaning moodily against the chimney-piece, with his face towards the fire, &ldquo;than to be myself, twenty times richer and twenty times wiser, and be the torment to myself that I have been, in this Devil's bark of a boat, within the last half-hour!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was so confounded by the alteration in him, that at first I could only observe him in silence, as he stood leaning his head upon his hand, and looking gloomily down at the fire. At length I begged him, with all the earnestness I felt, to tell me what had occurred to cross him so unusually, and to let me sympathise with him, if I could not hope to advise him. Before I had well concluded, he began to laugh&mdash;fretfully at first, but soon with returning gaiety.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tut, it's nothing, Daisy! nothing!&rdquo; he replied. &ldquo;I told you, at the inn in London, I am heavy company for myself, sometimes. I have been a nightmare to myself, just now&mdash;must have had one, I think. At odd dull times, nursery tales come up into the memory, unrecognised for what they are. I believe I have been confounding myself with the bad boy who &lsquo;didn't care,&rsquo; and became food for lions&mdash;a grander kind of going to the dogs, I suppose. What old women call the horrors, have been creeping over me from head to foot. I have been afraid of myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are afraid of nothing else, I think,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps not, and yet may have enough to be afraid of too,&rdquo; he answered. &ldquo;Well! So it goes by! I am not about to be hipped again, David; but I tell you, my good fellow, once more, that it would have been well for me (and for more than me) if I had had a steadfast and judicious father!&rdquo;</p>
<p>His face was always full of expression, but I never saw it express such a dark kind of earnestness as when he said these words, with his glance bent on the fire.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So much for that!&rdquo; he said, making as if he tossed something light into the air, with his hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Why, being gone, I am a man again,&rsquo;
<pb n="228" id="p228"/>
like Macbeth. And now for dinner! If I have not (Macbeth-like) broken up the feast with most admired disorder, Daisy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But where are they all, I wonder!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;God knows,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;After strolling to the ferry looking for you, I strolled in here and found the place deserted. That set me thinking, and you found me thinking.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The advent of Mrs. Gummidge with a basket, explained how the house had happened to be empty. She had hurried out to buy something that was needed, against Mr. Peggotty's return with the tide; and had left the door open in the meanwhile, lest Ham and little Em'ly, with whom it was an early night, should come home while she was gone. Steerforth, after very much improving Mrs. Gummidge's spirits by a cheerful salutation, and a jocose embrace, took my arm, and hurried me away.</p>
<p>He had improved his own spirits, no less than Mrs. Gummidge's, for they were again at their usual flow, and he was full of vivacious conversation as we went along.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And so,&rdquo; he said, gaily, &ldquo;we abandon this buccaneer life to-morrow, do we?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So we agreed,&rdquo; I returned. &ldquo;And our places by the coach are taken, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay! there's no help for it, I suppose,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;I have almost forgotten that there is anything to do in the world but to go out tossing on the sea here. I wish there was not.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;As long as the novelty should last,&rdquo; said I, laughing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Like enough,&rdquo; he returned; &ldquo;though there's a sarcastic meaning in that observation for an amiable piece of innocence like my young friend. Well! I dare say I am a capricious fellow, David. I know I am; but while the iron <hi rend="italics">is</hi> hot, I can strike it vigorously too. I could pass a reasonably good examination already, as a pilot in these waters, I think.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Peggotty says you are a wonder,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A nautical phenomenon, eh?&rdquo; laughed Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed he does, and you know how truly; knowing how ardent you are in any pursuit you follow, and how easily you can master it. And that amazes me most in you, Steerforth&mdash;that you should be contented with such fitful uses of your powers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Contented?&rdquo; he answered, merrily. &ldquo;I am never contented, except with your freshness, my gentle Daisy. As to fitfulness, I have never learnt the art of binding myself to any of the wheels on which the Ixions of these days are turning round and round. I missed it somehow in a bad apprenticeship, and now don't care about it.&mdash;You know I have bought a boat down here?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What an extraordinary fellow you are, Steerforth!&rdquo; I exclaimed, stopping&mdash;for this was the first I had heard of it. &ldquo;When you may never care to come near the place again!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know that,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;I have taken a fancy to the place. At all events,&rdquo; walking me briskly on, &ldquo;I have bought a boat that was for sale&mdash;a clipper, Mr. Peggotty says; and so she is&mdash;and Mr. Peggotty will be master of her in my absence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now I understand you, Steerforth!&rdquo; said I, exultingly. &ldquo;You pretend to have bought it for yourself, but you have really done so to confer a benefit on him. I might have know as much at first, knowing you.
<pb n="229" id="p229"/>
My dear kind Steerforth, how can I tell you what I think of your generosity?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tush!&rdquo; he answered, turning red. &ldquo;The less said, the better.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Didn't I know?&rdquo; cried I, &ldquo;didn't I say that there was not a joy, or sorrow, or any emotion of such honest hearts that was indifferent to you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye, aye,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;you told me all that. There let it rest. We have said enough!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Afraid of offending him by pursuing the subject when he made so light of it, I only pursued it in my thoughts as we went on at even a quicker pace than before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She must be newly rigged,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;and I shall leave Littimer behind to see it done, that I may know she is quite complete. Did I tell you Littimer had come down?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, yes! came down this morning, with a letter from my mother.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As our looks met, I observed that he was pale even to his lips, though he looked very steadily at me. I feared that some difference between him and his mother might have led to his being in the frame of mind in which I had found him at the solitary fireside. I hinted so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh no!&rdquo; he said, shaking his head, and giving a slight laugh. &ldquo;Nothing of the sort! Yes. He is come down, that man of mine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The same as ever?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The same as ever,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Distant and quiet as the North Pole. He shall see to the boat being fresh named. She's the Stormy Petrel now. What does Mr. Peggotty care for Stormy Petrels! I'll have her christened again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By what name?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Little Em'ly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As he had continued to look steadily at me, I took it as a reminder that he objected to being extolled for his consideration. I could not help showing in my face how much it pleased me, but I said little, and he resumed his usual smile, and seemed relieved.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But see here,&rdquo; he said, looking before us, &ldquo;where the original little Em'ly comes! And that fellow with her, eh? Upon my soul, he's a true knight. He never leaves her!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham was a boat-builder in these days, having improved a natural ingenuity in that handicraft, until he had become a skilled workman. He was in his working-dress, and looked rugged enough, but manly withal, and a very fit protector for the blooming little creature at his side. Indeed, there was a frankness in his face, an honesty, and an undisguised show of his pride in her, and his love for her, which were, to me, the best of good looks. I thought, as they came towards us, that they were well matched even in that particular.</p>
<p>She withdrew her hand timidly from his arm as we stopped to speak to them, and blushed as she gave it to Steerforth and to me. When they passed on, after we had exchanged a few words, she did not like to replace that hand, but, still appearing timid and constrained, walked by herself. I thought all this very pretty and engaging, and Steerforth seemed to think so too, as we looked after them fading away in the light of a young moon.</p>
<p>Suddenly there passed us&mdash;evidently following them&mdash;a young woman
<pb n="230" id="p230"/>
whose approach we had not observed, but whose face I saw as she went by, and thought I had a faint remembrance of. She was lightly dressed; looked bold, and haggard, and flaunting, and poor; but seemed, for the time, to have given all that to the wind which was blowing, and to have nothing in her mind but going after them. As the dark distant level, absorbing their figures into itself, left but itself visible between us and the sea and clouds, her figure disappeared in like manner, still no nearer to them than before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That is a black shadow to be following the girl,&rdquo; said Steerforth, standing still; &ldquo;what does it mean?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He spoke in a low voice that sounded almost strange to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She must have it in her mind to beg of them, I think,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A beggar would be no novelty,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;but it is a strange thing that the beggar should take that shape to-night.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why?&rdquo; I asked him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For no better reason, truly, than because I was thinking,&rdquo; he said, after a pause, &ldquo;of something like it, when it came by. Where the Devil did it come from, I wonder!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;From the shadow of this wall, I think,&rdquo; said I, as we emerged upon a road on which a wall abutted.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's gone!&rdquo; he returned, looking over his shoulder. &ldquo;And all ill go with it. Now for our dinner!&rdquo;</p>
<p>But, he looked again over his shoulder towards the sea-line glimmering afar off; and yet again. And he wondered about it, in some broken expressions, several times, in the short remainder of our walk; and only seemed to forget it when the light of fire and candle shone upon us, seated warm and merry, at table.</p>
<p>Littimer was there, and had his usual effect upon me. When I said to him that I hoped Mrs. Steerforth and Miss Dartle were well, he answered respectfully (and of course respectably), that they were tolerably well, he thanked me, and had sent their compliments. This was all, and yet he seemed to me to say as plainly as a man could say: &ldquo;You are very young, sir; you are exceedingly young.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We had almost finished dinner, when taking a step or two towards the table, from the corner where he kept watch upon us, or rather upon me, as I felt, he said to his master:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, sir. Miss Mowcher is down here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who?&rdquo; cried Steerforth, much astonished.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Mowcher, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, what on earth does <hi rend="italics">she</hi> do here?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It appears to be her native part of the country, sir. She informs me that she makes one of her professional visits here, every year, sir. I met her in the street this afternoon, and she wished to know if she might have the honor of waiting on you after dinner, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know the Giantess in question, Daisy?&rdquo; inquired Steerforth.</p>
<p>I was obliged to confess&mdash;I felt ashamed, even of being at this disadvantage before Littimer&mdash;that Miss Mowcher and I were wholly unacquainted.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then you shall know her,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;for she is one of the seven wonders of the world. When Miss Mowcher comes, show her in.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="231" id="p231"/>
<p>I felt some curiosity and excitement about this lady, especially as Steerforth burst into a fit of laughing when I referred to her, and positively refused to answer any question of which I made her the subject. I remained, therefore, in a state of considerable expectation until the cloth had been removed some half an hour, and we were sitting over our decanter of wine before the fire, when the door opened, and Littimer, with his habitual serenity quite undisturbed, announced:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Mowcher!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I looked at the doorway and saw nothing. I was still looking at the doorway, thinking that Miss Mowcher was a long while making her appearance, when, to my infinite astonishment, there came waddling round a sofa which stood between me and it, a pursy dwarf, of about forty or forty-five, with a very large head and face, a pair of roguish grey eyes, and such extremely little arms, that, to enable herself to lay a finger archly against her snub nose, as she ogled Steerforth, she was obliged to meet the finger half-way, and lay her nose against it. Her chin, which was what is called a double-chin, was so fat that it entirely swallowed up the strings of her bonnet, bow and all. Throat she had none; waist she had none; legs she had none, worth mentioning; for though she was more than full-sized down to where her waist would have been, if she had had any, and though she terminated, as human beings generally do, in a pair of feet, she was so short that she stood at a common-sized chair as at a table, resting a bag she carried on the seat. This lady; dressed in an off-hand, easy style; bringing her nose and her forefinger together, with the difficulty I have described; standing with her head necessarily on one side, and, with one of her sharp eyes shut up, making an uncommonly knowing face; after ogling Steerforth for a few moments, broke into a torrent of words.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What! My flower!&rdquo; she pleasantly began, shaking her large head at him. &ldquo;You're there, are you! Oh, you naughty boy, fie for shame, what do you do so far away from home? Up to mischief, I'll be bound. Oh, you're a downy fellow, Steerforth, so you are, and I'm another, ain't I? Ha, ha, ha! You'd have betted a hundred pound to five, now, that you wouldn't have seen me here, wouldn't you? Bless you, man alive, I'm everywhere. I'm here and there, and where not, like the conjuror's half-crown in the lady's handkercher. Talking of hankerchers&mdash;<hi rend="italics">and</hi> talking of ladies&mdash;what a comfort you are to your blessed mother, ain't you, my dear boy, over one of my shoulders, and I don't say which!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Mowcher untied her bonnet, at this passage of her discourse, threw back the strings, and sat down, panting, on a footstool in front of the fire&mdash;making a kind of arbor of the dining-table, which spread its mahogany shelter above her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh my stars and what's-their-names!&rdquo; she went on, clapping a hand on each of her little knees, and glancing shrewdly at me, &ldquo;I'm of too full a habit, that's the fact, Steerforth. After a flight of stairs, it gives me as much trouble to draw every breath I want, as if it was a bucket of water. If you saw me looking out of an upper window, you'd think I was a fine woman, wouldn't you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should think that, wherever I saw you,&rdquo; replied Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Go along, you dog, do!&rdquo; cried the little creature, making a whisk at him with the handkerchief with which she was wiping her face, &ldquo;and don't
<pb n="232" id="p232"/>
be impudent! But I give you my word and honor I was at Lady Mithers's last week&mdash;<hi rend="italics">there's</hi> a woman! How <hi rend="italics">she</hi> wears!&mdash;and Mithers himself came into the room where I was waiting for her&mdash;<hi rend="italics">there's</hi> a man! How <hi rend="italics">he</hi> wears! and his wig too, for he's had it these ten years&mdash;and he went on at that rate in the complimentary line, that I began to think I should be obliged to ring the bell. Ha! ha! ha! He's a pleasant wretch, but he wants principle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What were you doing for Lady Mithers?&rdquo; asked Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's tellings, my blessed infant,&rdquo; she retorted, tapping her nose again, screwing up her face, and twinkling her eyes like an imp of supernatural intelligence. &ldquo;Never <hi rend="italics">you</hi> mind! You'd like to know whether I stop her hair from falling off, or dye it, or touch up her complexion, or improve her eyebrows, wouldn't you? And so you shall, my darling&mdash;when I tell you! Do you know what my great grandfather's name was?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was Walker, my sweet pet,&rdquo; replied Miss Mowcher, &ldquo;and he came of a long line of Walkers, that I inherit all the Hookey estates from.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I never beheld anything approaching to Miss Mowcher's wink, except Miss Mowcher's self-possession. She had a wonderful way too, when listening to what was said to her, or when waiting for an answer to what she had said herself, of pausing with her head cunningly on one side, and one eye turned up like a magpie's. Altougher I was lost in amazement, and sat staring at her, quite oblivious, I am afraid, of the laws of politeness.</p>
<p>She had by this time drawn the chair to her side, and was busily engaged in producing from the bag (plunging in her short arm to the shoulder, at every dive) a number of small bottles, sponges, combs, brushes, bits of flannel, little pairs of curling irons, and other instruments, which she tumbled in a heap upon the chair. From this employment she suddenly desisted, and said to Steerforth, much to my confusion:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who's your friend?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Steerforth; &ldquo;he wants to know you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, then, he shall! I thought he looked as if he did!&rdquo; returned Miss Mowcher, waddling up to me, bag in hand, and laughing on me as she came. &ldquo;Face like a peach!&rdquo; standing on tiptoe to pinch my cheek as I sat. &ldquo;Quite tempting! I'm very fond of peaches. Happy to make your acquaintance, Mr. Copperfield, I'm sure.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said that I congratulated myself on having the honor to make hers, and that the happiness was mutual.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh my goodness, how polite we are!&rdquo; exclaimed Miss Mowcher, making a preposterous attempt to cover her large face with her morsel of a hand. &ldquo;What a world of gammon and spinnage it is, though, ain't it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was addressed confidentially to both of us, as the morsel of a hand came away from the face, and buried itself, arm and all, in the bag again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you mean, Miss Mowcher?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ha! ha! ha! What a refreshing set of humbugs we are, to be sure, ain't we, my sweet child?&rdquo; replied that morsel of a woman, feeling in the bag with her head on one side, and her eye in the air. &ldquo;Look here!&rdquo; taking something out. &ldquo;Scraps of the Russian Prince's nails! Prince Alphabet turned topsy-turvy, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> call him, for his name's got all the letters in it, higgledy-piggledy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Russian Prince is a client of yours, is he?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<pb n="233" id="p233"/>
<p>&ldquo;I believe you, my pet,&rdquo; replied Miss Mowcher. &ldquo;I keep his nails in order for him. Twice a week! Fingers <hi rend="italics">and</hi> toes!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He pays well, I hope?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pays as he speaks, my dear child&mdash;through the nose,&rdquo; replied Miss Mowcher. &ldquo;None of your close shavers the Prince ain't. You'd say so, if you saw his moustachios. Red by nature, black by art.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By your art, of course,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>Miss Mowcher winked assent. &ldquo;Forced to send for me. Couldn't help it. The climate affected <hi rend="italics">his</hi> dye; it did very well in Russia, but it was no go here. You never saw such a rusty Prince in all your born days as he was. Like old iron!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is that why you called him a humbug, just now?&rdquo; inquired Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, you're a broth of a boy, ain't you?&rdquo; returned Miss Mowcher, shaking her head violently. &ldquo;I said, what a set of humbugs we were in general, and I showed you the scraps of the Prince's nails to prove it. The Prince's nails do more for me, in private families of the genteel sort, than all my talents put together. I always carry 'em about. They're the best introduction. If Miss Mowcher cuts the Prince's nails, she <hi rend="italics">must</hi> be all right. I give 'em away to the young ladies. They put 'em in albums, I believe. Ha! ha! ha! Upon my life, &lsquo;the whole social system&rsquo; (as the men call it when they make speeches in Parliament) is a system of Prince's nails!&rdquo; said this least of women, trying to fold her short arms, and nodding her large head.</p>
<p>Steerforth laughed heartily, and I laughed too. Miss Mowcher continuing all the time to shake her head (which was very much on one side), and to look into the air with one eye, and to wink with the other.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, well!&rdquo; she said, smiting her small knees, and rising, &ldquo;this is not business. Come, Steerforth, let's explore the polar regions, and have it over.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She then selected two or three of the little instruments, and a little bottle, and asked (to my surprise) if the table would bear. On Steerforth's replying in the affirmative, she pushed a chair against it, and begging the assistance of my hand, mounted up, pretty nimbly, to the top, as if it were a stage.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If either of you saw my ankles,&rdquo; she said, when she was safely elevated, &ldquo;say so, and I'll go home and destroy myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> did not,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> did not,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well then,&rdquo; cried Miss Mowcher, &ldquo;I'll consent to live. Now, ducky, ducky, ducky, come to Mrs. Bond and be killed!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was an invocation to Steerforth to place himself under her hands; who, accordingly, sat himself down, with his back to the table, and his laughing face towards me, and submitted his head to her inspection, evidently for no other purpose than our entertainment. To see Miss Mowcher standing over him, looking at his rich profusion of brown hair through a large round magnifying glass, which she took out of her pocket, was a most amazing spectacle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">You're</hi> a pretty fellow!&rdquo; said Miss Mowcher, after a brief inspection. &ldquo;You'd be as bald as a friar on the top of your head in twelve months, but for me. Just half-a-minute, my young friend, and we'll give you a polishing that shall keep your curls on for the next ten years!&rdquo;</p>
<p>With this, she tilted some of the contents of the little bottle on to one
<pb n="234" id="p234"/>
of the little bits of flannel, and, again imparting some of the virtues of that preparation to one of the little brushes, began rubbing and scraping away with both on the crown of Steerforth's head in the busiest manner I ever witnessed, talking all the time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's Charley Pyegrave, the duke's son,&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;You know Charley?&rdquo; peeping round into his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A little,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a man <hi rend="italics">he</hi> is! <hi rend="italics">There's</hi> a whisker! As to Charley's legs, if they were only a pair (which they ain't), they'd defy competition. Would you believe he tried to do without me&mdash;in the Life-Guards, too?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mad!&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It looks like it. However, mad or sane, he tried,&rdquo; returned Miss Mowcher. &ldquo;What does he do, but, lo and behold you, he goes into a perfumer's shop, and wants to buy a bottle of the Madagascar Liquid.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Charley does?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Charley does. But they haven't got any of the Madagascar Liquid.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is it? Something to drink?&rdquo; asked Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To drink?&rdquo; returned Miss Mowcher, stopping to slap his cheek. &ldquo;To doctor his own moustachios with, you <hi rend="italics">know.</hi> There was a woman in the shop&mdash;elderly female&mdash;quite a Griffin&mdash;who had never even heard of it by name. &lsquo;Begging pardon, sir,&rsquo; said the Griffin to Charley, &lsquo;it's not&mdash;not&mdash;not ROUGE, is it?&rsquo; &lsquo;Rouge,&rsquo; said Charley to the Griffin. &lsquo;What the unmentionable to ears polite, do you think I want with rouge?&rsquo; &lsquo;No offence, sir,&rsquo; said the Griffin; &lsquo;we have it asked for by so many names, I thought it might be.&rsquo; Now that, my child,&rdquo; continued Miss Mowcher, rubbing all the time as busily as ever, &ldquo;is another instance of the refreshing humbug I was speaking of. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> do something in that way myself&mdash;perhaps a good deal&mdash;perhaps a little&mdash;sharp's the word, my dear boy&mdash;never mind!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In what way do you mean? In the rouge way?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Put this and that together, my tender pupil,&rdquo; returned the wary Mowcher, touching her nose, &ldquo;work it by the rule of Secrets in all trades, and the product will give you the desired result. I say <hi rend="italics">I</hi> do a little in that way myself. One Dowager, <hi rend="italics">she</hi> calls it lip-salve. Another, <hi rend="italics">she</hi> calls it gloves. Another, <hi rend="italics">she</hi> calls it tucker-edging. Another, <hi rend="italics">she</hi> calls it a fan. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> call it whatever <hi rend="italics">they</hi> call it. I supply it for 'em, but we keep up the trick so, to one another, and make believe with such a face, that they'd as soon think of laying it on, before a whole drawing-room, as before me. And when I wait upon 'em, they'll say to me sometimes&mdash;<hi rend="italics">with it on</hi>&mdash;thick, and no mistake&mdash;&lsquo;How am I looking, Mowcher? Am I pale?&rsquo; Ha! ha! ha! ha! Isn't <hi rend="italics">that</hi> refreshing, my young friend!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I never did in my days behold anything like Mowcher as she stood upon the dining-table, intensely enjoying this refreshment, rubbing busily at Steerforth's head, and winking at me over it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;Such things are not much in demand hereabouts. That sets me off again! I havn't seen a pretty women since I've been here, Jemmy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not the ghost of one,&rdquo; replied Miss Mowcher.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We could show her the substance of one, I think?&rdquo; said Steerforth, addressing his eyes to mine. &ldquo;Eh, Daisy?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="235" id="p235"/>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, indeed,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aha?&rdquo; cried the little creature, glancing sharply at my face, and then peeping round at Steerforth's. &ldquo;Umph?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The first exclamation sounded like a question put to both of us, and the second like a question put to Steerforth only. She seemed to have found no answer to either, but continued to rub, with her head on one side and her eye turned up, as if she were looking for an answer in the air, and were confident of its appearing presently.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A sister of yours, Mr. Copperfield?&rdquo; she cried, after a pause, and still keeping the same look out. &ldquo;Aye, aye?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said Steerforth, before I could reply. &ldquo;Nothing of the sort. On the contrary, Mr. Copperfield used&mdash;or I am much mistaken&mdash;to have a great admiration for her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, hasn't he now?&rdquo; returned Miss Mowcher. &ldquo;Is he fickle? oh, for shame! Did he sip every flower, and change every hour, until Polly his passion requited?&mdash;Is her name Polly?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Elfin suddenness with which she pounced upon me with this question, and a searching look, quite disconcerted me for a moment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, Miss Mowcher,&rdquo; I replied. &ldquo;Her name is Emily.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aha?&rdquo; she cried exactly as before. &ldquo;Umph? What a rattle I am! Mr. Copperfield, ain't I volatile?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Her tone and look implied something that was not agreeable to me in connexion with the subject. So I said, in a graver manner than any of us had yet assumed:</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is as virtuous as she is pretty. She is engaged to be married to a most worthy and deserving man in her own station of life. I esteem her for her good sense, as much as I admire her for her good looks.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well said!&rdquo; cried Steerforth. &ldquo;Hear, hear, hear! Now, I'll quench the curiosity of this little Fatima, my dear Daisy, by leaving her nothing to guess at. She is at present apprenticed, Miss Mowcher, or articled, or whatever it may be, to Omer and Joram, Haberdashers, Milliners, and so forth, in this town. Do you observe? Omer and Joram. The promise of which my friend has spoken, is made and entered into with her cousin; Christian name, Ham; surname, Peggotty; occupation, boat-builder; also of this town. She lives with a relative; Christian name, unknown; surname, Peggotty; occupation, seafaring; also of this town. She is the prettiest and most engaging little fairy in the world. I admire her&mdash;as my friend does&mdash;exceedingly. If it were not that I might appear to disparage her Intended, which I know my friend would not like, I would add, that to <hi rend="italics">me</hi> she seems to be throwing herself away; that I am sure she might do better; and that I swear she was born to be a lady.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Mowcher listened to these words, which were very slowly and distinctly spoken, with her head on one side, and her eye in the air as if she were still looking for that answer. When he ceased, she became brisk again in an instant, and rattled away with surprising volubility.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! And that's all about it, is it?&rdquo; she exclaimed, trimming his whiskers with a little restless pair of scissors, that went glancing round his head in all directions. &ldquo;Very well: <hi rend="italics">very</hi> well! Quite a long story. Ought to end, &lsquo;and they lived happy ever afterwards;&rsquo; oughtn't it? Ah! What's that game at forfeits? I love my love with an E, because she's enticing; I hate her with an E, because she's engaged. I took her to the
<pb n="236" id="p236"/>
sign of the exquisite, and treated her with an elopement, her name's Emily, and she lives in the east? Ha! ha! ha! Mr. Copperfield, ain't I volatile?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Merely looking at me with extravagant slyness, and not waiting for any reply, she continued, without drawing breath:</p>
<p>&ldquo;There! If ever any scapegrace was trimmed and touched up to perfection, you are, Steerforth. If I understand any noddle in the world, I understand yours. Do you hear me when I tell you that, my darling? I understand yours,&rdquo; peeping down into his face. &ldquo;Now you may mizzle, Jemmy (as we say at Court), and if Mr. Copperfield will take the chair I'll operate on him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you say, Daisy?&rdquo; inquired Steerforth, laughing, and resigning his seat. &ldquo;Will you be improved?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Miss Mowcher, not this evening.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't say no,&rdquo; returned the little woman, looking at me with the aspect of a connoisseur; &ldquo;a little bit more eyebrow?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;some other time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have it carried half a quarter of an inch towards the temple,&rdquo; said Miss Mowcher. &ldquo;We can do it in a fortnight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, I thank you. Not at present.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Go in for a tip,&rdquo; she urged. &ldquo;No? Let's get the seaffolding up, then, for a pair of whiskers. Come!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I could not help blushing as I declined, for I felt we were on my weak point, now. But Miss Mowcher, finding that I was not at present disposed for any decoration within the range of her art, and that I was, for the time being, proof against the blandishments of the small bottle which she held up before one eye to enforce her persuasions, said we would make a beginning on an early day, and requested the aid of my hand to descend from her elevated station. Thus assisted, she skipped down with much agility, and began to tie her double chin into her bonnet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The fee,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;is&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Five bob,&rdquo; replied Miss Mowcher, &ldquo;and dirt-cheap, my chicken. Ain't I volatile, Mr. Copperfield?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I replied politely: &ldquo;Not at all.&rdquo; But I thought she was rather so, when she tossed up his two half-crowns like a goblin pieman, caught them, dropped them in her pocket, and gave it a loud slap.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the Till!&rdquo; observed Miss Mowcher, standing at the chair again, and replacing in the bag the miscellaneous collection of little objects she had emptied out of it. &ldquo;Have I got all my traps? It seems so. It won't do to be like long Ned Beadwood, when they took him to church &lsquo;to marry him to somebody,&rsquo; as he says, and left the bride behind. Ha! ha! ha! A wicked rascal, Ned, but droll! Now, I know I'm going to break your hearts, but I am forced to leave you. You must call up all your fortitude, and try to bear it. Good bye, Mr. Copperfield! Take care of yourself, Jockey of Norfolk! How I <hi rend="italics">have</hi> been rattling on! It's all the fault of you two wretches. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> forgive you! &lsquo;Bob swore!&rsquo;&mdash;as the Englishman said for &lsquo;Good night,&rsquo; when he first learnt French, and thought it so like English. &lsquo;Bob swore,&rsquo; my ducks!&rdquo;</p>
<p>With the bag slung over her arm, and rattling as she waddled away, she waddled to the door; where she stopped to inquire if she should leave us a lock of her hair. &ldquo;Ain't I volatile?&rdquo; she added, as a commentary on this offer, and, with her finger on her nose, departed.</p>
<pb n="237" id="p237"/>
<p>Steerforth laughed to that degree, that it was impossible for me to help laughing too; though I am not sure I should have done so, but for this inducement. When we had had our laugh quite out, which was after some time, he told me that Miss Mowcher had quite an extensive connexion, and made herself useful to a variety of people in a variety of ways. Some people trifled with her as a mere oddity, he said; but she was as shrewdly and sharply observant as any one he knew, and as long-headed as she was short-armed. He told me that what she had said of being here, and there, and everywhere, was true enough; for she made little darts into the provinces, and seemed to pick up customers everywhere, and to know everybody. I asked him what her disposition was: whether it was at all mischievous, and if her sympathies were generally on the right side of things: but, not succeeding in attracting his attention to these questions after two or three attempts, I forbore or forgot to repeat them. He told me instead, with much rapidity, a good deal about her skill, and her profits; and about her being a scientific cupper, if I should ever have occasion for her services in that capacity.</p>
<p>She was the principal theme of our conversation during the evening: and when we parted for the night Steerforth called after me over the bannisters, &ldquo;Bob swore!&rdquo; as I went down stairs.</p>
<p>I was surprised, when I came to Mr. Barkis's house to find Ham walking up and down in front of it, and still more surprised to learn from him that little Em'ly was inside. I naturally inquired why he was not there too, instead of pacing the street by himself?</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you see, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; he rejoined, in a hesitating manner, &ldquo;Em'ly, she's talking to some 'un in here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should have thought,&rdquo; said I, smiling, &ldquo;that that was a reason for your being in here too, Ham.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Mas'r Davy, in a general way, so 't would be,&rdquo; he returned; &ldquo;but look'ee here, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; lowering his voice, and speaking very gravely. &ldquo;It's a young woman, sir&mdash;a young woman, that Em'ly knowed once, and doen't ought to know no more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When I heard these words, a light began to fall upon the figure I had seen following them, some hours ago.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's a poor wurem, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; said Ham, &ldquo;as is trod under foot by all the town. Up street and down street. The mowld o' the churchyard don't hold any that the folk shrink away from, more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did I see her to-night, Ham, on the sands, after we met you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Keeping us in sight?&rdquo; said Ham. &ldquo;It's like you did, Mas'r Davy. &ldquo;Not that I know'd, then, she was theer, sir, but along of her creeping soon arterwards under Em'ly's little winder, when she see the light come, and whisp'ring &lsquo;Em'ly, Em'ly, for Christ's sake have a woman's heart towards me. I was once like you!&rsquo; Those was solemn words, Mas'r Davy, fur to hear!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They were indeed, Ham. What did Em'ly do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Says Em'ly, &lsquo;Martha, is it you? Oh, Martha, can it be you!&rsquo;&mdash;for they had sat at work together, many a day, at Mr. Omer's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I recollect her now!&rdquo; cried I, recalling one of the two girls I had seen when I first went there. &ldquo;I recollect her quite well!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Martha Endell,&rdquo; said Ham. &ldquo;Two or three year older than Em'ly, but was at the school with her.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="238" id="p238"/>
<p>&ldquo;I never heard her name,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I didn't mean to interrupt you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For the matter o' that, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; replied Ham, &ldquo;all's told a'most in them words, &lsquo;Em'ly, Em'ly, for Christ's sake have a woman's heart towards me. I was once like you!&rsquo; She wanted to speak to Em'ly. Em'ly couldn't speak to her theer, for her loving uncle was come home, and he wouldn't&mdash;no, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; said Ham, with great earnestness, &ldquo;he couldn't, kind-naturd, tender-hearted as he is, see them two together, side by side, for all the treasures that's wrecked in the sea.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt how true this was. I knew it, on the instant, quite as well as Ham.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So Em'ly writes in pencil on a bit of paper,&rdquo; he pursued, &ldquo;and gives it to her out o'winder to bring here. &lsquo;Show that,&rsquo; she says, &lsquo;to my aunt, Mrs. Barkis, and she'll set you down by her fire, for the love of me, till uncle is gone out, and I can come.&rsquo; By-and-by she tells me what I tell you, Mas'r Davy, and asks me to bring her. What can I do? She doen't ought to know any such, but I can't deny her, when the tears is on her face.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He put his hand into the breast of his shaggy jacket, and took out with great care a pretty little purse.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And if I could deny her when the tears was on her face, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; said Ham, tenderly adjusting it on the rough palm of his hand, &ldquo;how could I deny her when she give me this to carry for her&mdash;knowing what she brought it for? Such a toy as it is!&rdquo; said Ham, thoughtfully looking on it. &ldquo;With such a little money in it, Em'ly my dear!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I shook him warmly by the hand when he had put it away again&mdash;for that was more satisfactory to me than saying anything&mdash;and we walked up and down, for a minute or two, in silence. The door opened then, and Peggotty appeared, beckoning to Ham to come in. I would have kept away, but she came after me, entreating me to come in too. Even then, I would have avoided the room where they all were, but for its being the neat-tiled kitchen I have mentioned more than once. The door opening immediately into it, I found myself among them, before I considered whither I was going.</p>
<p>The girl&mdash;the same I had seen upon the sands&mdash;was near the fire. She was sitting on the ground, with her head and one arm lying on a chair. I fancied, from the disposition of her figure, that Em'ly had but newly risen from the chair, and that the forlorn head might perhaps have been lying on her lap. I saw but little of the girl's face, over which her hair fell loose and scattered, as if she had been disordering it with her own hands; but I saw that she was young, and of a fair complexion. Peggotty had been crying. So had little Em'ly. Not a word was spoken when we first went in; and the Dutch clock by the dresser seemed, in the silence, to tick twice as loud as usual.</p>
<p>Em'ly spoke first.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Martha wants,&rdquo; she said to Ham, &ldquo;to go to London.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why to London?&rdquo; returned Ham.</p>
<p>He stood between them, looking on the prostrate girl with a mixture of compassion for her, and of jealousy of her holding any companionship with her whom he loved so well, which I have always remembered distinctly. They both spoke as if she were ill; in a soft, suppressed tone that was plainly heard, although it hardly rose above a whisper.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Better there than here,&rdquo; said a third voice aloud&mdash;Martha's, though
<pb n="239" id="p239"/>
she did not move. &ldquo;No one knows me there. Everybody knows me here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What will she do there?&rdquo; inquired Ham.</p>
<p>She lifted up her head, and looked darkly round at him for a moment; then laid it down again, and curved her right arm about her neck, as a woman in a fever, or in an agony of pain from a shot, might twist herself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She will try to do well,&rdquo; said little Em'ly. &ldquo;You don't know what she has said to us. Does he&mdash;do they&mdash;aunt?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Peggotty shook her head compassionately.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll try,&rdquo; said Martha, &ldquo;if you'll help me away. I never can do worse than I have done here. I may do better. Oh!&rdquo; with a dreadful shiver, &ldquo;take me out of these streets, where the whole town knows me from a child!&rdquo;</p>
<p>As Em'ly held out her hand to Ham, I saw him put in it a little canvas bag. She took it, as if she thought it were her purse, and made a step or two forward; but finding her mistake, came back to where he had retired near me, and showed it to him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's all yourn, Em'ly,&rdquo; I could hear him say. &ldquo;I haven't nowt in all the wureld that ain't yourn, my dear. It ain't of no delight to me, except for you!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The tears rose freshly in her eyes, but she turned away, and went to Martha. What she gave her, I don't know. I saw her stooping over her, and putting money in her bosom. She whispered something, and asked was that enough? &ldquo;More than enough,&rdquo; the other said, and took her hand and kissed it.</p>
<p>Then Martha arose, and gathering her shawl about her, covering her face with it, and weeping aloud, went slowly to the door. She stopped a moment before going out, as if she would have uttered something or turned back; but no word passed her lips. Making the same low, dreary, wretched moaning in her shawl, she went away.</p>
<p>As the door closed, little Em'ly looked at us three in a hurried manner, and then hid her face in her hands, and fell to sobbing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doen't, Em'ly!&rdquo; said Ham, tapping her gently on the shoulder. &ldquo;Doen't, my dear! You doen't ought to cry so, pretty!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, Ham!&rdquo; she exclaimed, still weeping pitifully, &ldquo;I am not as good a girl as I ought to be! I know I have not the thankful heart, sometimes, I ought to have!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes, you have, I'm sure,&rdquo; said Ham.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No! no! no!&rdquo; cried little Em'ly, sobbing, and shaking her head. &ldquo;I am not as good a girl as I ought to be. Not near! not near!&rdquo;</p>
<p>And still she cried, as if her heart would break.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I try your love too much. I know I do!&rdquo; she sobbed. &ldquo;I'm often cross to you, and changeable with you, when I ought to be far different. You are never so to me. Why am I ever so to you, when I should think of nothing but how to be grateful, and to make you happy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You always make me so,&rdquo; said Ham, &ldquo;my dear! I am happy in the sight of you. I am happy, all day long, in the thoughts of you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! that's not enough!&rdquo; she cried. &ldquo;That is because you are good; not because I am! Oh, my dear, it might have been a better fortune for you, if you had been fond of some one else&mdash;of some one steadier and
<pb n="240" id="p240"/>
much worthier than me, who was all bound up in you, and never vain and changeable like me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Poor little tender-heart,&rdquo; said Ham, in a low voice. &ldquo;Martha has overset her, altogether.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Please, aunt,&rdquo; sobbed Em'ly, &ldquo;come here, and let me lay my head upon you. Oh, I am very miserable to-night, aunt! Oh, I am not as good a girl as I ought to be. I am not, I know!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Peggotty had hastened to the chair before the fire. Em'ly, with her arms around her neck, kneeled by her, looking up most earnestly into her face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, pray, aunt, try to help me! Ham, dear, try to help me! Mr. David, for the sake of old times, do, please, try to help me! I want to be a better girl than I am. I want to feel a hundred times more thankful than I do. I want to feel more, what a blessed thing it is to be the wife of a good man, and to lead a peaceful life. Oh me, oh me! Oh, my heart, my heart!&rdquo;</p>
<p>She dropped her face on my old nurse's breast, and, ceasing this supplication, which in its agony and grief was half a woman's, half a child's, as all her manner was (being, in that, more natural, and better suited to her beauty, as I thought, than any other manner could have been), wept silently, while my old nurse hushed her like an infant.</p>
<p>She got calmer by degrees, and then we soothed her; now talking encouragingly, and now jesting a little with her, until she began to raise her head and speak to us. So we got on, until she was able to smile, and then to laugh, and then to sit up, half ashamed; while Peggotty recalled her stray ringlets, dried her eyes, and made her neat again, lest her uncle should wonder, when she got home, why his darling had been crying.</p>
<p>I saw her do, that night, what I had never seen her do before. I saw her innocently kiss her chosen husband on the cheek, and creep close to his bluff form as if it were her best support. When they went away together, in the waning moonlight, and I looked after them, comparing their departure in my mind with Martha's, I saw that she held his arm with both her hands, and still kept close to him.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXIII. <lb/> I CORROBORATE MR. DICK, AND CHOOSE A PROFESSION.</head>
<p>WHEN I awoke in the morning I thought very much of little Em'ly, and her emotion last night, after Martha had left. I felt as if I had come into the knowledge of those domestic weaknesses and tendernesses in a sacred confidence, and that to disclose them, even to Steerforth, would be wrong. I had no gentler feeling towards any one than towards the pretty creature who had been my playmate, and whom I have always been persuaded, and shall always be persuaded, to my dying day, I then devotedly loved. The repetition to any ears&mdash;even to Steerforth's
<pb n="241" id="p241"/>
&mdash;of what she had been unable to repress when her heart lay open to me by an accident, I felt would be a rough deed, unworthy of myself, unworthy of the light of our pure childhood, which I always saw encircling her head. I made a resolution, therefore, to keep it in my own breast; and there it gave her image a new grace.</p>
<p>While we were at breakfast, a letter was delivered to me from my aunt. As it contained matter on which I thought Steerforth could advise me as well as any one, and on which I knew I should be delighted to consult him, I resolved to make it a subject of discussion on our journey home. For the present we had enough to do, in taking leave of all our friends. Mr. Barkis was far from being the last among them, in his regret at our departure; and I believe would even have opened the box again, and sacrificed another guinea, if it would have kept us eight-and-forty hours in Yarmouth. Peggotty, and all her family, were full of grief at our going. The whole house of Omer and Joram turned out to bid us good bye; and there were so many seafaring volunteers in attendance on Steerforth, when our portmanteaus went to the coach, that if we had had the baggage of a regiment with us, we should hardly have wanted porters to carry it. In a word, we departed to the regret and admiration of all concerned, and left a great many people very sorry behind us.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you stay long here, Littimer?&rdquo; said I, as he stood waiting to see the coach start.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, sir,&rdquo; he replied; &ldquo;probably not very long, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He can hardly say just now,&rdquo; observed Steerforth, carelessly. &ldquo;He knows what he has to do, and he'll do it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That I am sure he will,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>Littimer touched his hat in acknowledgment of my good opinion, and I felt about eight years old. He touched it once more, wishing us a good journey; and we left him standing on the pavement, as respectable a mystery as any pyramid in Egypt.</p>
<p>For some little time we held no conversation, Steerforth being unusually silent, and I being sufficiently engaged in wondering, within myself, when I should see the old places again, and what new changes might happen to me or them in the meanwhile. At length Steerforth, becoming gay and talkative in a moment, as he could become anything he liked at any moment, pulled me by the arm:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Find a voice, David. What about the letter you were speaking of at breakfast?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said I, taking it out of my pocket. &ldquo;It's from my aunt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what does she say, requiring consideration!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, she reminds me, Steerforth,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;that I came out on this expedition to look about me, and to think a little.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Which, of course, you have done?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed I can't say I have, particularly. To tell you the truth, I am afraid I had forgotten it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well! look about you now, and make up for your negligence,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Look to the right, and you'll see a flat country, with a good deal of marsh in it; look to the left, and you'll see the same. Look to the front, and you'll find no difference; look to the rear, and there it is still.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="242" id="p242"/>
<p>I laughed, and replied that I saw no suitable profession in the whole prospect; which was perhaps to be attributed to its flatness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What says our aunt on the subject?&rdquo; inquired Steerforth, glancing at the letter in my hand. &ldquo;Does she suggest anything?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, yes,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;She asks me, here, if I think I should like to be a proctor? What do you think of it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, I don't know,&rdquo; replied Steerforth, coolly. &ldquo;You may as well do that as anything else, I suppose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I could not help laughing again, at his balancing all callings and professions so equally; and I told him so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a proctor, Steerforth?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, he is a sort of monkish attorney,&rdquo; replied Steerforth. &ldquo;He is, to some faded courts held in Doctors' Commons&mdash;a lazy old nook near St. Paul's Churchyard&mdash;what solicitors are to the courts of law and equity. He is a functionary whose existence, in the natural course of things, would have terminated about two hundred years ago. I can tell you best what he is, by telling you what Doctors' Commons is. It's a little out-of-the-way place, where they administer what is called ecclesiastical law, and play all kinds of tricks with obsolete old monsters of acts of Parliament, which three-fourths of the world know nothing about, and the other fourth supposes to have been dug up, in a fossil state, in the days of the Edwards. It's a place that has an ancient monopoly in suits about people's wills and people's marriages, and disputes among ships and boats.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nonsense, Steerforth!&rdquo; I exclaimed. &ldquo;You don't mean to say that there is any affinity between nautical matters and ecclesiastical matters?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't, indeed, my dear boy,&rdquo; he returned; &ldquo;but I mean to say that they are managed and decided by the same set of people, down in that same Doctors' Commons. You shall go there one day, and find them blundering through half the nautical terms in Young's Dictionary, apropos of the &lsquo;Nancy&rsquo; having run down the &lsquo;Sarah Jane,&rsquo; or Mr. Peggotty and the Yarmouth boatmen having put off in a gale of wind with an anchor and cable to the &lsquo;Nelson&rsquo; Indiaman in distress; and you shall go there another day, and find them deep in the evidence, pro and con, respecting a clergyman who has misbehaved himself; and you shall find the judge in the nautical case, the advocate in the clergyman case, or contrariwise. They are like actors: now a man's a judge, and now he is not a judge; now he's one thing, now he's another; now he's something else, change and change about; but it's always a very pleasant profitable little affair of private theatricals, presented to an uncommonly select audience.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But advocates and proctors are not one and the same?&rdquo; said I, a little puzzled. &ldquo;Are they?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; returned Steerforth, &ldquo;the advocates are civilians&mdash;men who have taken a doctor's degree at college&mdash;which is the first reason of my knowing anything about it. The proctors employ the advocates. Both get very comfortable fees, and altogether they make a mighty snug little party. On the whole, I would recommend you to take to Doctors' Commons kindly, David. They plume themselves on their gentility there, I can tell you, if that's any satisfaction.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I made allowance for Steerforth's light way of treating the subject, and, considering it with reference to the staid air of gravity and antiquity which I associated with that &ldquo;lazy old nook near St. Paul's Churchyard,&rdquo;
<pb n="243" id="p243"/>
did not feel indisposed towards my aunt's suggestion; which she left to my free decision, making no scruple of telling me that it had occurred to her, on her lately visiting her own proctor in Doctors' Commons for the purpose of settling her will in my favor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a laudable proceeding on the part of our aunt, at all events,&rdquo; said Steerforth, when I mentioned it; &ldquo;and one deserving of all encouragement. Daisy, my advice is that you take kindly to Doctors' Commons.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I quite made up my mind to do so. I then told Steerforth that my aunt was in town awaiting me (as I found from her letter), and that she had taken lodgings for a week at a kind of private hotel in Lincoln's Inn Fields, where there was a stone staircase, and a convenient door in the roof; my aunt being firmly persuaded that every house in London was going to be burnt down every night.</p>
<p>We achieved the rest of our journey pleasantly, sometimes recurring to Doctors' Commons, and anticipating the distant days when I should be a proctor there, which Steerforth pictured in a variety of humorous and whimsical lights, that made us both merry. When we came to our journey's end, he went home, engaging to call upon me next day but one; and I drove to Lincoln's Inn Fields, where I found my aunt up, and waiting supper.</p>
<p>If I had been round the world since we parted, we could hardly have been better pleased to meet again. My aunt cried outright as she embraced me; and said, pretending to laugh, that if my poor mother had been alive, that silly little creature would have shed tears, she had no doubt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So you have left Mr. Dick behind, aunt?&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I am sorry for that. Ah, Janet, how do you do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>As Janet curtsied, hoping I was well, I observed my aunt's visage lengthen very much.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry for it, too,&rdquo; said my aunt, rubbing her nose. &ldquo;I have had no peace of mind, Trot, since I have been here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Before I could ask why, she told me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am convinced,&rdquo; said my aunt; laying her hand with melancholy firmness on the table, &ldquo;that Dick's character is not a character to keep the donkies off. I am confident he wants strength of purpose. I ought to have left Janet at home, instead, and then my mind might perhaps have been at ease. If ever there was a donkey trespassing on my green,&rdquo; said my aunt, with emphasis, &ldquo;there was one this afternoon at four o'clock. A cold feeling came over me from head to foot, and I <hi rend="italics">knew</hi> it was a donkey!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I tried to comfort her on this point, but she rejected consolation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was a donkey,&rdquo; said my aunt; &ldquo;and it was the one with the stumpy tail which that Murdering sister of a woman rode, when she came to my house.&rdquo; This had been, ever since, the only name my aunt knew for Miss Murdstone. &ldquo;If there is any donkey in Dover, whose audacity it is harder to me to bear than another's, that,&rdquo; said my aunt, striking the table, &ldquo;is the animal!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Janet ventured to suggest that my aunt might be disturbing herself unnecessarily, and that she believed the donkey in question was then engaged in the sand and gravel line of business, and was not available for purposes of trespass. But my aunt wouldn't hear of it.</p>
<pb n="244" id="p244"/>
<p>Supper was comfortably served and hot, though my aunt's rooms were very high up&mdash;whether that she might have more stone stairs for her money, or might be nearer to the door in the roof, I don't know&mdash;and consisted of a roast fowl, a steak, and some vegetables, to all of which I did ample justice, and which were all excellent. But my aunt had her own ideas concerning London provision, and ate but little.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose this unfortunate fowl was born and brought up in a cellar,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;and never took the air except on a hackney coach-stand. I <hi rend="italics">hope</hi> the steak may be beef, but I don't believe it. Nothing's genuine in the place, in my opinion, but the dirt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you think the fowl may have come out of the country, aunt?&rdquo; I hinted.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly not,&rdquo; returned my aunt. &ldquo;It would be no pleasure to a London tradesman to sell anything which was what he pretended it was.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I did not venture to controvert this opinion, but I made a good supper, which it greatly satisfied her to see me do. When the table was cleared, Janet assisted her to arrange her hair, to put on her nightcap, which was of a smarter construction than usual (&ldquo;in case of fire,&rdquo; my aunt said), and to fold her gown back over her knees, these being her usual preparations for warming herself before going to bed. I then made her, according to certain established regulations from which no deviation, however slight, could ever be permitted, a glass of hot white wine and water, and a slice of toast cut into long thin strips. With these accompaniments we were left alone to finish the evening, my aunt sitting opposite to me drinking her wine and water; soaking her strips of toast, in it, one by one, before eating them; and looking benignantly on me, from among the borders of her nightcap.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Trot,&rdquo; she began, &ldquo;what do you think of the proctor plan? Or have you not begun to think about it yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have thought a good deal about it, my dear aunt, and I have talked a good deal about it with Steerforth. I like it very much indeed. I like it exceedingly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come!&rdquo; said my aunt. &ldquo;That's cheering!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have only one difficulty, aunt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Say what it is, Trot,&rdquo; she returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I want to ask, aunt, as this seems, from what I understand, to be a limited profession, whether my entrance into it would not be very expensive?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It will cost,&rdquo; returned my aunt, &ldquo;to article you, just a thousand pounds.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, my dear aunt,&rdquo; said I, drawing my chair nearer, &ldquo;I am uneasy in my mind about that. It's a large sum of money. You have expended a great deal on my education, and have always been as liberal to me in all things, as it was possible to be. You have been the soul of generosity. Surely there are some ways in which I might begin life with hardly any outlay, and yet begin with a good hope of getting on by resolution and exertion. Are you sure that it would not be better to try that course? Are you certain that you can afford to part with so much money, and that it is right it should be so expended? I only ask you, my second mother, to consider. Are you certain?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="245" id="p245"/>
<p>My aunt finished eating the piece of toast on which she was then engaged, looking me full in the face all the while; and then setting her glass on the chimney-piece, and folding her hands upon her folded skirts, replied as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trot, my child, if I have any object in life, it is to provide for your being a good, a sensible, and a happy man. I am bent upon it&mdash;so is Dick. I should like some people that I know to hear Dick's conversation on the subject. Its sagacity is wonderful. But no one knows the resources of that man's intellect, except myself!&rdquo;</p>
<p>She stopped for a moment to take my hand between hers, and went on:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's in vain, Trot, to recall the past, unless it works some influence upon the present. Perhaps I might have been better friends with your poor father. Perhaps I might have been better friends with that poor child your mother, even after your sister Betsey Trotwood disappointed me. When you came to me, a little runaway boy, all dusty and wayworn, perhaps I thought so. From that time until now, Trot, you have ever been a credit to me and a pride and pleasure. I have no other claim upon my means; at least&rdquo; &mdash; here to my surprise she hesitated, and was confused&mdash;&ldquo;no, I have <hi rend="italics">no</hi> other claim upon my means&mdash;and you are my adopted child. Only be a loving child to me in my age, and bear with my whims and fancies; and you will do more for an old woman whose prime of life was not so happy or conciliating as it might have been, than ever that old woman did for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was the first time I had heard my aunt refer to her past history. There was a magnanimity in her quiet way of doing so, and of dismissing it, which would have exalted her in my respect and affection, if any thing could.</p>
<p>&ldquo;All is agreed and understood between us now, Trot,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;and we need talk of this no more. Give me a kiss, and we'll go to the Commons after breakfast to-morrow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We had a long chat by the fire before we went to bed. I slept in a room on the same floor with my aunt's, and was a little disturbed in the course of the night by her knocking at my door, as often as she was agitated by a distant sound of hackney-coaches or market-carts, and inquiring &ldquo;if I heard the engines?&rdquo; But towards morning she slept better, and suffered me to do so too.</p>
<p>At about mid-day, we set out for the offices of Messrs. Spenlow and Jorkins in Doctors' Commons. My aunt, who had this other general opinion in reference to London, that every man she saw was a pickpocket, gave me her purse to carry for her, which had ten guineas in it and some silver.</p>
<p>We made a pause at the toy-shop in Fleet-street, to see the giants of Saint Dunstan's strike upon the bells&mdash;we had timed our going, so as to catch them at it, at twelve o'clock&mdash;and then went on towards Ludgate Hill, and St. Paul's Churchyard. We were crossing to the former place, when I found that my aunt greatly accelerated her speed, and looked frightened. I observed, at the same time, that a lowering ill-dressed man who had stopped and stared at us in passing, a little before, was coming so close after us, as to brush against her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trot! My dear Trot!&rdquo; cried my aunt, in a terrified whisper, and pressing my arm. &ldquo;I don't know what I am to do.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="246" id="p246"/>
<p>&ldquo;Don't be alarmed,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;There's nothing to be afraid of. Step into a shop, and I'll soon get rid of this fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, child!&rdquo; she returned. &ldquo;Don't speak to him for the world. I entreat, I order you!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good Heaven, aunt!&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;He is nothing but a sturdy beggar.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You don't know what he is!&rdquo; replied my aunt. &ldquo;You don't know who he is! You don't know what you say!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We had stopped in an empty doorway, while this was passing, and he had stopped too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't look at him!&rdquo; said my aunt, as I turned my head indignantly, &ldquo;but get me a coach, my dear, and wait for me in St. Paul's Churchyard.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wait for you?&rdquo; I repeated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; rejoined my aunt, &ldquo;I must go alone. I must go with him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With him, aunt? This man?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am in my senses,&rdquo; she replied, &ldquo;and I tell you I <hi rend="italics">must.</hi> Get me a coach!&rdquo;</p>
<p>However much astonished I might be, I was sensible that I had no right to refuse compliance with such a peremptory command. I hurried away a few paces, and called a hackney chariot which was passing empty. Almost before I could let down the steps, my aunt sprang in, I don't know how, and the man followed. She waved her hand to me to go away, so earnestly, that, all confounded as I was, I turned from them at once. In doing so I heard her say to the coachman, &ldquo;Drive anywhere! Drive straight on!&rdquo; and presently the chariot passed me, going up the hill.</p>
<p>What Mr. Dick had told me, and what I had supposed to be a delusion of his, now came into my mind. I could not doubt that this person was the person of whom he had made such mysterious mention, though what the nature of his hold upon my aunt could possibly be, I was quite unable to imagine. After half an hour's cooling in the churchyard, I saw the chariot coming back. The driver stopped beside me, and my aunt was sitting in it alone.</p>
<p>She had not yet sufficiently recovered from her agitation to be quite prepared for the visit we had to make. She desired me to get into the chariot, and to tell the coachman to drive slowly up and down a little while. She said no more, except, &ldquo;My dear child, never ask me what it was, and don't refer to it,&rdquo; until she had perfectly regained her composure, when she told me she was quite herself now, and we might get out. On her giving me her purse, to pay the driver, I found that all the guineas were gone, and only the loose silver remained.</p>
<p>Doctors' Commons was approached by a little low archway. Before we had taken many paces down the street beyond it, the noise of the city seemed to melt, as if by magic, into a softened distance. A few dull courts, and narrow ways, brought us to the sky-lighted offices of Spenlow and Jorkins; in the vestibule of which temple, accessible to pilgrims without the ceremony of knocking, three or four clerks were at work as copyists. One of these, a little dry man, sitting by himself, who wore a stiff brown wig that looked as if it were made of gingerbread, rose to receive my aunt, and show us into Mr. Spenlow's room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Spenlow's in Court, ma'am,&rdquo; said the dry man; &ldquo;it's an Arches day; but it's close by, and I'll send for him directly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As we were left to look about us while Mr. Spenlow was fetched, I
<pb n="247" id="p247"/>
availed myself of the opportunity. The furniture of the room was old-fashioned and dusty; and the green baize on the top of the writing-table had lost all its color, and was as withered and pale as an old pauper. There were a great many bundles of papers on it, some indorsed as Allegations, and some (to my surprise) as Libels, and some as being in the Consistory Court, and some in the Arches Court, and some in the Prerogative Court, and some in the Admiralty Court, and some in the Delegates' Court; giving me occasion to wonder much, how many Courts there might be in the gross, and how long it would take to understand them all. Besides these, there were sundry immense manuscript Books of Evidence taken on affidavit, strongly bound, and tied together in massive sets, a set to each cause, as if every cause were a history in ten or twenty volumes. All this looked tolerably expensive, I thought, and gave me an agreeable notion of a proctor's business. I was casting my eyes with increasing complacency over these and many similar objects, when hasty footsteps were heard in the room outside, and Mr. Spenlow, in a black gown trimmed with white fur, came hurrying in, taking off his hat as he came.</p>
<p>He was a little light-haired gentleman, with undeniable boots, and the stiffest of white cravats and shirt-collars. He was buttoned up, mighty trim and tight, and must have taken a great deal of pains with his whiskers, which were accurately curled. His gold watch-chain was so massive, that a fancy came across me, that he ought to have a sinewy golden arm, to draw it out with, like those which are put up over the goldbeaters' shops. He was got up with such care, and was so stiff, that he could hardly bend himself; being obliged, when he glanced at some papers on his desk, after sitting down in his chair, to move his whole body, from the bottom of his spine, like Punch.</p>
<p>I had previously been presented by my aunt, and had been courteously received. He now said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;And so, Mr. Copperfield, you think of entering into our profession? I casually mentioned to Miss Trotwood, when I had the pleasure of an interview with her the other day,&rdquo;&mdash;with another inclination of his body&mdash;Punch again&mdash;&ldquo;that there was a vacancy here. Miss Trotwood was good enough to mention that she had a nephew who was her peculiar care, and for whom she was seeking to provide genteelly in life. That nephew, I believe, I have now the pleasure of&rdquo;&mdash;Punch again.</p>
<p>I bowed my acknowledgments, and said, my aunt had mentioned to me that there was that opening, and that I believed I should like it very much. That I was strongly inclined to like it, and had taken immediately to the proposal. That I could not absolutely pledge myself to like it, until I knew something more about it. That although it was little else than a matter of form, I presumed I should have an opportunity of trying how I liked it, before I bound myself to it irrevocably.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh surely! surely!&rdquo; said Mr. Spenlow. &ldquo;We always, in this house, propose a month&mdash;an initiatory month. I should be happy, myself, to propose two months&mdash;three&mdash;an indefinite period, in fact&mdash;but I have a partner. Mr. Jorkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And the premium, sir,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;is a thousand pounds?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And the premium, Stamp included, is a thousand pounds,&rdquo; said Mr. Spenlow. &ldquo;As I have mentioned to Miss Trotwood, I am actuated by no mercenary considerations; few men are less so, I believe; but
<pb n="248" id="p248"/>
Mr. Jorkins has his opinions on these subjects, and I am bound to respect Mr. Jorkins's opinions. Mr. Jorkins thinks a thousand pounds too little, in short.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose, sir,&rdquo; said I, still desiring to spare my aunt, &ldquo;that it is not the custom here, if an articled clerk were particularly useful, and made himself a perfect master of his profession&mdash;&rdquo; I could not help blushing, this looked so like praising myself&mdash;&ldquo;I suppose it is not the custom, in the later years of his time, to allow him any&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Spenlow, by a great effort, just lifted his head far enough out of his cravat to shake it, and answered, anticipating the word &ldquo;salary:&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. I will not say what consideration I might give to that point myself, Mr. Copperfield, if I were unfettered. Mr. Jorkins is immovable.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was quite dismayed by the idea of this terrible Jorkins. But I found out afterwards that he was a mild man, of a heavy temperament, whose place in the business was to keep himself in the back-ground, and be constantly exhibited by name as the most obdurate and ruthless of men. If a clerk wanted his salary raised, Mr. Jorkins wouldn't listen to such a proposition. If a client were slow to settle his bill of costs, Mr. Jorkins was resolved to have it paid; and however painful these things might be (and always were) to the feelings of Mr. Spenlow, Mr. Jorkins would have his bond. The heart and hand of the good angel Spenlow would have been always open, but for the restraining demon Jorkins. As I have grown older, I think I have had experience of some other houses doing business on the principle of Spenlow and Jorkins!</p>
<p>It was settled that I should begin my month's probation as soon as I pleased, and that my aunt need neither remain in town nor return at its expiration, as the articles of agreement, of which I was to be the subject, could easily be sent to her at home for her signature. When we had got so far, Mr. Spenlow offered to take me into Court then and there, and show me what sort of place it was. As I was willing enough to know, we went out with this object, leaving my aunt behind; who would trust herself, she said, in no such place, and who, I think, regarded all Courts of Law as a sort of powder-mills that might blow up at any time.</p>
<p>Mr. Spenlow conducted me through a paved courtyard formed of grave brick houses, which I inferred, from the Doctors' names upon the doors, to be the official abiding-places of the learned advocates of whom Steerforth had told me; and into a large dull room, not unlike a chapel to my thinking, on the left hand. The upper part of this room was fenced off from the rest; and there, on the two sides of a raised platform of the horse-shoe form, sitting on easy old-fashioned dining-room chairs, were sundry gentlemen in red gowns and grey wigs, whom I found to be the Doctors aforesaid. Blinking over a little desk like a pulpit-desk, in the curve of the horse-shoe, was an old gentleman, whom, if I had seen him in an aviary, I should certainly have taken for an owl, but who I learned was the presiding judge. In the space within the horse-shoe, lower than these, that is to say, on about the level of the floor, were sundry other gentlemen, of Mr. Spenlow's rank, and dressed like him in black gowns with white fur upon them, sitting at a long green table. Their cravats were in general stiff, I thought, and their looks haughty; but in this last respect I presently conceived I had done them an injustice, for when two or three of them had to rise and answer a question of the
<pb n="249" id="p249"/>
presiding dignitary, I never saw anything more sheepish. The public, represented by a boy with a comforter, and a shabby-genteel man secretly eating crumbs out of his coat pockets, was warming itself at a stove in the centre of the Court. The languid stillness of the place was only broken by the chirping of this fire and by the voice of one of the Doctors, who was wandering slowly through a perfect library of evidence, and stopping to put up, from time to time, at little roadside inns of argument on the journey. Altogether, I have never, on any occasion, made one at such a cosey, dosey, old-fashioned, time-forgotten, sleepy-headed little family-party in all my life; and I felt it would be quite a soothing opiate to belong to it in any character&mdash;except perhaps as a suitor.</p>
<p>Very well satisfied with the dreamy nature of this retreat, I informed Mr. Spenlow that I had seen enough for that time, and we rejoined my aunt; in company with whom I presently departed from the Commons, feeling very young when I went out of Spenlow and Jorkins's, on account of the clerks poking one another with their pens to point me out.</p>
<p>We arrived at Lincoln's Inn Fields without any new adventures, except encountering an unlucky donkey in a costermonger's cart, who suggested painful associations to my aunt. We had another long talk about my plans, when we were safely housed; and as I knew she was anxious to get home, and, between fire, food, and pickpockets, could never be considered at her ease for half-an-hour in London, I urged her not to be uncomfortable on my account, but to leave me to take care of myself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have not been here a week to-morrow, without considering that too, my dear,&rdquo; she returned. &ldquo;There is a furnished little set of chambers to be let in the Adelphi, Trot, which ought to suit you to a marvel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With this brief introduction, she produced from her pocket an advertisement, carefully cut out of a newspaper, setting forth that in Buckingham Street in the Adelphi there was to be let, furnished, with a view of the river, a singularly desirable, and compact set of chambers, forming a genteel residence for a young gentleman, a member of one of the Inns of Court, or otherwise, with immediate possession. Terms moderate, and could be taken for a month only if required.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, this is the very thing, aunt!&rdquo; said I, flushed with the possible dignity of living in chambers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then come,&rdquo; replied my aunt, immediately resuming the bonnet she had a minute before laid aside. &ldquo;We'll go and look at 'em.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Away we went. The advertisement directed us to apply to Mrs. Crupp on the premises, and we rung the area bell, which we supposed to communicate with Mrs. Crupp. It was not until we had rung three or four times that we could prevail on Mrs. Crupp to communicate with us, but at last she appeared, being a stout lady with a flounce of flannel petticoat below a nankeen gown.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let us see these chambers of yours, if you please, ma'am,&rdquo; said my aunt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For this gentleman?&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, feeling in her pocket for her keys.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, for my nephew,&rdquo; said my aunt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And a sweet set they is for sich!&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp.</p>
<p>So we went up-stairs.</p>
<p>They were on the top of the house&mdash;a great point with my aunt, being
<pb n="250" id="p250"/>
near the fire-escape&mdash;and consisted of a little half-blind entry where you could see hardly anything, a little stone-blind pantry where you could see nothing at all, a sitting-room, and a bed-room. The furniture was rather faded, but quite good enough for me; and, sure enough, the river was outside the windows.</p>
<p>As I was delighted with the place, my aunt and Mrs. Crupp withdrew into the pantry to discuss the terms, while I remained on the sitting-room sofa, hardly daring to think it possible that I could be destined to live in such a noble residence. After a single combat of some duration they returned, and I saw, to my joy, both in Mrs. Crupp's countenance and in my aunt's, that the deed was done.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is it the last occupant's furniture?&rdquo; inquired my aunt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes it is, ma'am,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's become of him?&rdquo; asked my aunt.</p>
<p>Mrs. Crupp was taken with a troublesome cough, in the midst of which she articulated with much difficulty. &ldquo;He was took ill here, ma'am, and&mdash;ugh! ugh! ugh! dear me!&mdash;and he died.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hey! What did he die of?&rdquo; asked my aunt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, ma'am, he died of drink,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp in confidence. &ldquo;And smoke.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Smoke? You don't mean chimneys?&rdquo; said my aunt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, ma'am,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Crupp. &ldquo;Cigars and pipes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">That's</hi> not catching, Trot, at any rate,&rdquo; remarked my aunt, turning to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, indeed,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>In short, my aunt, seeing how enraptured I was with the premises, took them for a month, with leave to remain for twelve months when that time was out. Mrs. Crupp was to find linen, and to cook; every other necessary was already provided; and Mrs. Crupp expressly intimated that she should always yearn towards me as a son. I was to take possession the day after to-morrow, and Mrs. Crupp said thank Heaven she had now found summun she could care for!</p>
<p>On our way back, my aunt informed me how she confidently trusted that the life I was now to lead would make me firm and self-reliant, which was all I wanted. She repeated this several times next day, in the intervals of our arranging for the transmission of my clothes and books from Mr. Wickfield's; relative to which, and to all my late holiday, I wrote a long letter to Agnes, of which my aunt took charge, as she was to leave on the succeeding day. Not to lengthen these particulars, I need only add, that she made a handsome provision for all my possible wants during my month of trial; that Steerforth, to my great disappointment and hers too, did not make his appearance before she went away; that I saw her safely seated in the Dover coach, exulting in the coming discomfiture of the vagrant donkeys, with Janet at her side; and that when the coach was gone, I turned my face to the Adelphi, pondering on the old days when I used to roam about its subterranean arches, and on the happy changes which had brought me to the surface.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="251" id="p251"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXIV. <lb/> MY FIRST DISSIPATION.</head>
<p>IT was a wonderfully fine thing to have that lofty castle to myself, and to feel, when I shut my outer door, like Robinson Crusoe, when he had got into his fortification, and pulled his ladder up after him. It was a wonderfully fine thing to walk about town with the key of my house in my pocket, and to know that I could ask any fellow to come home, and make quite sure of its being inconvenient to nobody, if it were not so to me. It was a wonderfully fine thing to let myself in and out, and to come and go without a word to any one, and to ring Mrs. Crupp up, gasping, from the depths of the earth, when I wanted her&mdash;and when she was disposed to come. All this, I say, was wonderfully fine; but I must say, too, that there were times when it was very dreary.</p>
<p>It was fine in the morning, particularly in the fine mornings. It looked a very fresh, free life, by daylight: still fresher, and more free, by sunlight. But as the day declined, the life seemed to go down too. I don't know how it was; it seldom looked well by candle-light. I wanted somebody to talk to, then. I missed Agnes. I found a tremendous blank, in the place of that smiling repository of my confidence. Mrs. Crupp appeared to be a long way off. I thought about my predecessor, who had died of drink and smoke; and I could have wished he had been so good as to live, and not bother me with his decease.</p>
<p>After two days and nights, I felt as if I had lived there for a year, and yet I was not an hour older, but was quite as much tormented by my own youthfulness as ever.</p>
<p>Steerforth not yet appearing, which induced me to apprehend that he must be ill, I left the Commons early on the third day, and walked out to Highgate. Mrs. Steerforth was very glad to see me, and said that he had gone away with one of his Oxford friends to see another who lived near St. Albans, but that she expected him to return to-morrow. I was so fond of him, that I felt quite jealous of his Oxford friends.</p>
<p>As she pressed me to stay to dinner, I remained, and I believe we talked about nothing but him all day. I told her how much the people liked him at Yarmouth, and what a delightful companion he had been. Miss Dartle was full of hints and mysterious questions, but took a great interest in all our proceedings there, and said, &ldquo;Was it really, though?&rdquo; and so forth, so often, that she got everything out of me she wanted to know. Her appearance was exactly what I have described it, when I first saw her; but the society of the two ladies was so agreeable, and came so natural to me, that I felt myself falling a little in love with her. I could not help thinking, several times in the course of the evening, and particularly when I walked home at night, what delightful company she would be in Buckingham Street.</p>
<p>I was taking my coffee and roll in the morning, before going to the Commons&mdash;and I may observe in this place that it is surprising how much coffee Mrs. Crupp used, and how weak it was, considering&mdash;when Steerforth himself walked in, to my unbounded joy.</p>
<pb n="252" id="p252"/>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Steerforth,&rdquo; cried I, &ldquo;I began to think I should never see you again!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was carried off, by force of arms,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;the very next morning after I got home. Why, Daisy, what a rare old bachelor you are here!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I showed him over the establishment, not omitting the pantry, with no little pride, and he commended it highly. &ldquo;I tell you what, old boy,&rdquo; he added, &ldquo;I shall make quite a town-house of this place, unless you give me notice to quit.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was a delightful hearing. I told him if he waited for that, he would have to wait till doomsday.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But you shall have some breakfast!&rdquo; said I, with my hand on the bell-rope, &ldquo;and Mrs. Crupp shall make you some fresh coffee, and I'll toast you some bacon in a bachelor's Dutch-oven that I have got here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no!&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Don't ring! I can't! I am going to breakfast with one of these fellows who is at the Piazza Hotel, in Covent Garden.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But you'll come back to dinner?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can't, upon my life. There's nothing I should like better, but I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> remain with these two fellows. We are all three off together to-morrow morning.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then bring them here to dinner,&rdquo; I returned. &ldquo;Do you think they would come?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! they would come fast enough,&rdquo; said Steerforth; &ldquo;but we should inconvenience you. You had better come and dine with us somewhere.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I would not by any means consent to this, for it occurred to me that I really ought to have a little housewarming, and that there never could be a better opportunity. I had a new pride in my rooms after his approval of them, and burned with a desire to develop their utmost resources. I therefore made him promise positively in the names of his two friends, and we appointed six o'clock as the dinner-hour.</p>
<p>When he was gone, I rang for Mrs. Crupp, and acquainted her with my desperate design. Mrs. Crupp said, in the first place, of course it was well known she couldn't be expected to wait, but she knew a handy young man, who she thought could be prevailed upon to do it, and whose terms would be five shillings, and what I pleased. I said, certainly we would have him. Next, Mrs. Crupp said it was clear she couldn't be in two places at once (which I felt to be reasonable), and that &ldquo;a young gal&rdquo; stationed in the pantry with a bed-room candle, there never to desist from washing plates, would be indispensable. I said, what would be the expense of this young female, and Mrs. Crupp said she supposed eighteen-pence would neither make me nor break me. I said I supposed not; and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> was settled. Then Mrs. Crupp said, Now about the dinner.</p>
<p>It was a remarkable instance of want of forethought on the part of the ironmonger who had made Mrs. Crupp's kitchen fire-place, that it was capable of cooking nothing but chops and mashed potatoes. As to a fishkittle, Mrs. Crupp said, well! would I only come and look at the range. She couldn't say fairer than that. Would I come and look at it? As I should not have been much the wiser if I <hi rend="italics">had</hi> looked at it, I declined, and said, &ldquo;Never mind fish.&rdquo; But Mrs. Crupp said, Don't say that; oysters was in, and why not them? So <hi rend="italics">that</hi> was settled. Mrs. Crupp then
<pb n="253" id="p253"/>
said what she would recommend would be this. A pair of hot roast fowls&mdash;from the pastry-cook's; a dish of stewed beef, with vegetables&mdash;from the pastry-cook's; two little corner things, as a raised pie and a dish of kidneys&mdash;from the pastry-cook's; a tart, and (if I liked) a shape of jelly&mdash;from the pastry-cook's. This, Mrs. Crupp said, would leave her at full liberty to concentrate her mind on the potatoes, and to serve up the cheese and celery as she could wish to see it done.</p>
<p>I acted on Mrs. Crupp's opinion, and gave the order at the pastry-cook's myself. Walking along the Strand, afterwards, and observing a hard mottled substance in the window of a ham and beef shop, which resembled marble, but was labelled &ldquo;Mock Turtle,&rdquo; I went in and bought a slab of it, which I have since seen reason to believe would have sufficed for fifteen people. This preparation, Mrs. Crupp, after some difficulty, consented to warm up; and it shrunk so much in a liquid state, that we found it what Steerforth called &ldquo;rather a tight fit&rdquo; for four.</p>
<p>These preparations happily completed, I bought a little dessert in Covent Garden Market, and gave a rather extensive order at a retail wine-merchant's in that vicinity. When I came home in the afternoon, and saw the bottles drawn up in a square on the pantry-floor, they looked so numerous (though there were two missing, which made Mrs. Crupp very uncomfortable), that I was absolutely frightened at them.</p>
<p>One of Steerforth's friends was named Grainger, and the other Markham. They were both very gay and lively fellows; Grainger, something older than Steerforth; Markham, youthful-looking, and I should say not more than twenty. I observed that the latter always spoke of himself indefinitely, as &ldquo;a man,&rdquo; and seldom or never in the first person singular.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A man might get on very well here, Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Markham&mdash;meaning himself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's not a bad situation,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;and the rooms are really commodious.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope you have both brought appetites with you?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Upon my honour,&rdquo; returned Markham, &ldquo;town seems to sharpen a man's appetite. A man is hungry all day long. A man is perpetually eating.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Being a little embarrassed at first, and feeling much too young to preside, I made Steerforth take the head of the table when dinner was announced, and seated myself opposite to him. Everything was very good; we did not spare the wine; and he exerted himself so brilliantly to make the thing pass off well, that there was no pause in our festivity. I was not quite such good company during dinner, as I could have wished to be, for my chair was opposite the door, and my attention was distracted by observing that the handy young man went out of the room very often, and that his shadow always presented itself, immediately afterwards, on the wall of the entry, with a bottle at its mouth. The &ldquo;young gal&rdquo; likewise occasioned me some uneasiness: not so much by neglecting to wash the plates, as by breaking them. For being of an inquisitive disposition, and unable to confine herself (as her positive instructions were) to the pantry, she was constantly peering in at us, and constantly imagining herself detected; in which belief, she several times retired upon the plates (with which she had carefully paved the floor), and did a great deal of destruction.</p>
<p>These, however, were small drawbacks, and easily forgotten when the
<pb n="254" id="p254"/>
cloth was cleared, and the dessert put on the table; at which period of the entertainment the handy young man was discovered to be speechless. Giving him private directions to seek the society of Mrs. Crupp, and to remove the &ldquo;young gal&rdquo; to the basement also, I abandoned myself to enjoyment.</p>
<p>I began, by being singularly cheerful and light-hearted; all sorts of half-forgotten things to talk about, came rushing into my mind, and made me hold forth in a most unwonted manner. I laughed heartily at my own jokes, and everybody else's; called Steerforth to order for not passing the wine; made several engagements to go to Oxford; announced that I meant to have a dinner party exactly like that, once a week until further notice; and madly took so much snuff out of Grainger's box, that I was obliged to go into the pantry, and have a private fit of sneezing ten minutes long.</p>
<p>I went on, by passing the wine faster and faster yet, and continually starting up with a corkscrew to open more wine, long before any was needed. I proposed Steerforth's health. I said he was my dearest friend, the protector of my boyhood, and the companion of my prime. I said I was delighted to propose his health. I said I owed him more obligations than I could ever repay, and held him in a higher admiration than I could ever express. I finished by saying, &ldquo;I'll give you Steerforth! God bless him! Hurrah!&rdquo; We gave him three times three, and another, and a good one to finish with. I broke my glass in going round the table to shake hands with him, and I said (in two words) &ldquo;Steerforth-you're the guidingstar of my exist ence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I went on, by finding suddenly that somebody was in the middle of a song. Markham was the singer, and he sang &ldquo;When the heart of a man is depressed with care.&rdquo; He said, when he had sung it, he would give us &ldquo;Woman!&rdquo; I took objection to that, and I couldn't allow it. I said it was not a respectful way of proposing the toast, and I would never permit that toast to be drunk in my house otherwise than as &ldquo;The Ladies!&rdquo; I was very high with him, mainly I think because I saw Steerforth and Grainger laughing at me&mdash;or at him&mdash;or at both of us. He said a man was not to be dictated to. I said a man <hi rend="italics">was.</hi> He said a man was not to be insulted, then. I said he was right there&mdash;never under my roof, where the Lares were sacred, and the laws of hospitality paramount. He said it was no derogation from a man's dignity to confess that I was a devilish good fellow. I instantly proposed his health.</p>
<p>Somebody was smoking. We were all smoking. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was smoking, and trying to suppress a rising tendency to shudder. Steerforth had made a speech about me, in the course of which I had been affected almost to tears. I returned thanks, and hoped the present company would dine with me to-morrow, and the day after&mdash;each day at five o'clock, that we might enjoy the pleasures of conversation and society through a long evening. I felt called upon to propose an individual. I would give them my aunt. Miss Betsey Trotwood, the best of her sex!</p>
<p>Somebody was leaning out of my bed-room window, refreshing his forehead against the cool stone of the parapet, and feeling the air upon his face. It was myself. I was addressing myself as &ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; and
<pb n="255" id="p255"/>
saying, &ldquo;Why did you try to smoke? You might have known you couldn't do it.&rdquo; Now, somebody was unsteadily contemplating his features in the looking-glass. That was I too. I was very pale in the looking-glass; my eyes had a vacant appearance; and my hair&mdash;only my hair, nothing else&mdash;looked drunk.</p>
<p>Somebody said to me, &ldquo;Let us go to the theatre, Copperfield!&rdquo; There was no bed-room before me, but again the jingling table covered with glasses; the lamp; Grainger on my right hand, Markham on my left, and Steerforth opposite&mdash;all sitting in a mist, and a long way off. The theatre? To be sure. The very thing. Come along! But they must excuse me if I saw everybody out first, and turned the lamp off&mdash;in case of fire.</p>
<p>Owing to some confusion in the dark, the door was gone. I was feeling for it in the window-curtains, when Steerforth, laughing, took me by the arm and led me out. We went down-stairs, one behind another. Near the bottom, somebody fell, and rolled down. Somebody else said it was Copperfield. I was angry at that false report, until, finding myself on my back in the passage, I began to think there might be some foundation for it.</p>
<p>A very foggy night, with great rings round the lamps in the streets! There was an indistinct talk of its being wet. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> considered it frosty. Steerforth dusted me under a lamp-post, and put my hat into shape, which somebody produced from somewhere in a most extraordinary manner, for I hadn't had it on before. Steerforth then said, &ldquo;You are all right, Copperfield, are you not?&rdquo; and I told him, &ldquo;Neverberrer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A man, sitting in a pigeon-hole-place, looked out of the fog, and took money from somebody, inquiring if I was one of the gentlemen paid for, and appearing rather doubtful (as I remember in the glimpse I had of him) whether to take the money for me or not. Shortly afterwards, we were very high up in a very hot theatre, looking down into a large pit, that seemed to me to smoke; the people with whom it was crammed were so indistinct. There was a great stage, too, looking very clean and smooth after the streets; and there were people upon it, talking about something or other, but not at all intelligibly. There was an abundance of bright lights, and there was music, and there were ladies down in the boxes, and I don't know what more. The whole building looked to me, as if it were learning to swim; it conducted itself in such an unaccountable manner, when I tried to steady it.</p>
<p>On somebody's motion, we resolved to go down-stairs to the dressboxes, where the ladies were. A gentleman lounging, full dressed, on a sofa, with an opera-glass in his hand, passed before my view, and also my own figure at full length in a glass. Then I was being ushered into one of these boxes, and found myself saying something as I sat down, and people about me crying &ldquo;Silence!&rdquo; to somebody, and ladies casting indignant glances at me, and&mdash;what! yes!&mdash;Agnes, sitting on the seat before me, in the same box, with a lady and gentleman beside her, whom I didn't know. I see her face now, better than I did then I dare say, with its indelible look of regret and wonder turned upon me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Agnes!&rdquo; I said, thickly, &ldquo;Lorblessmer! Agnes!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hush! Pray!&rdquo; she answered, I could not conceive why. &ldquo;You disturb the company. Look at the stage!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="256" id="p256"/>
<p>I tried, on her injunction, to fix it, and to hear something of what was going on there, but quite in vain. I looked at her again by-and-by, and saw her shrink into her corner, and put her gloved hand to her forehead.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Agnes!&rdquo; I said. &ldquo;I'mafraidyou'renorwell.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes. Do not mind me, Trotwood,&rdquo; she returned. &ldquo;Listen! Are you going away soon?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Amigoarawaysoo?&rdquo; I repeated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I had a stupid intention of replying that I was going to wait, to hand her down-stairs. I suppose I expressed it, somehow; for after she had looked at me attentively for a little while, she appeared to understand, and replied in a low tone:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know you will do as I ask you, if I tell you I am very earnest in it. Go away now, Trotwood, for my sake, and ask your friends to take you home.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She had so far improved me, for the time, that though I was angry with her, I felt ashamed, and with a short &ldquo;Goori!&rdquo; (which I intended for &ldquo;Good night!&rdquo;) got up and went away. They followed, and I stepped at once out of the box-door into my bedroom, where only Steerforth was with me, helping me to undress, and where I was by turns telling him that Agnes was my sister, and adjuring him to bring the corkscrew, that I might open another bottle of wine.</p>
<p>How somebody, lying in my bed, lay saying and doing all this over again, at cross purposes, in a feverish dream all night&mdash;the bed a rocking sea that was never still! How, as that somebody slowly settled down into myself, did I begin to parch, and feel as if my outer covering of skin were a hard board; my tongue the bottom of an empty kettle, furred with long service, and burning up over a slow fire; the palms of my hands, hot plates of metal which no ice could cool!</p>
<p>But the agony of mind, the remorse, and shame I felt, when I became conscious next day! My horror of having committed a thousand offences I had forgotten, and which nothing could ever expiate&mdash;my recollection of that indelible look which Agnes had given me&mdash;the torturing impossibility of communicating with her, not knowing, Beast that I was, how she came to be in London, or where she stayed&mdash;my disgust of the very sight of the room where the revel had been held&mdash;my racking head&mdash;the smell of smoke, the sight of glasses, the impossibility of going out, or even getting up! Oh, what a day it was!</p>
<p>Oh, what an evening, when I sat down by my fire to a basin of mutton broth, dimpled all over with fat, and thought I was going the way of my predecessor, and should succeed to his dismal story as well as to his chambers, and had half a mind to rush express to Dover and reveal all! What an evening, when Mrs. Crupp, coming in to take away the broth-basin, produced one kidney on a cheese-plate as the entire remains of yesterday's feast, and I was really inclined to fall upon her nankeen breast, and say, in heartfelt penitence, &ldquo;Oh, Mrs. Crupp, Mrs. Crupp, never mind the broken meats! I am very miserable!&rdquo;&mdash;only that I doubted, even at that pass, if Mrs. Crupp were quite the sort of woman to confide in!</p>
</div2>

</div1>


</body>
<back>
<div1>
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<epigraph><p>Quotation, sir, is a good thing; there is a community of mind in it; classical quotation is the parole of literary men all over the world.&mdash;JOHNSON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Knowledge is like the atmosphere; in order to dispel the vapour and dislodge the frost, our ancestors felled the forest, drained the marsh, and cultivated the waste, and we now breathe, in the purified air and the chastened climate, the result of the labour of generations and the progress of art.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Some of the most stirrin men in the world, persons in the thick of business of all kinds, and, indeed, with the business of the world itself on their hands, have combined with their other energies the greatest love of books, and found no recreation at once so wholesome and so useful.&mdash;LEIGH HUNT.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Knowledge in general expands the mind, exalts the faculties, refines the taste of pleasure, and opens numerous sources of intellectual enjoyment.&mdash;ROBERT HALL.</p></epigraph><opener>186, STRAND, NOVEMBER 1st, 1849.</opener>
<head>CHAPMAN AND HALL'S <lb/> ANNOUNCEMENT OF <lb/> NEW BOOKS AND NEW EDITIONS</head><p>NOW READY AND IN PREPARATION.</p>
<div2>
<head>MR. THACKERAY'S NEW CHRISTMAS BOOK.</head>
<p>A NEW WORK BY MR. M. A. TITMARSH, <lb/> Uniform with &ldquo;DR. BIRCH,&rdquo; &ldquo;OUR STREET,&rdquo; &amp;c. [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In three volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi>
<lb/> THE OGILVIES.</p>
<p>A Novel. [<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi>
<lb/> THE AUSTRIAN EMPIRE AND HUNGARY, <lb/> INCLUDING <lb/> A PRELIMINARY VIEW OF THE SEVERAL STATES OF EUROPE, IN THE YEAR 1848.</p>
<p>BY JOHN MACGREGOR, Esq., M.P, <lb/> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p>MR. CHARLES LEVER'S NEW WORK.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In one thick octavo volume, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s., cloth,</hi>
<lb/> ROLAND CASHEL.</p>
<p>BY CHARLES LEVER, <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;HARRY LORREQUER,&rdquo; &ldquo;KNIGHT OF GWYNNE,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>WITH FORTY ILLUSTRATIONS BY &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Work will also be issued in half-morocco, marbled edges, price 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In November.</hi></p>
</div2><div2>
<head>SOUTHERN AUSTRIA.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 32<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE HIGHLANDS &amp; ISLANDS OF THE ADRIATIC.</p>
<p>INCLUDING <lb/> Dalmatia, Croatia, and the Southern Provinces of the Austrian Empire.</p>
<p>BY ARCHIBALD A. PATON, ESQ., <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;SERVIA; THE YOUNGEST MEMBER OF THE EUROPEAN FAMILY,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>WITH MAPS AND ILLUSTRATIONS IN TINTED LITHOGRAPHY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Replete with information. * * * * Independently of the special interest which attaches to these countries at this moment, these volumes form a valuable contribution to our stores of geographical and ethnographical knowledge.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
<epigraph><p>It is manifest that all government of action is to be gotten by knowledge, and knowledge but by gathering many knowledges, which is reading.&mdash;SIR P. SIDNEY.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Criticism stands like au interpreter between the inspired and the uninspired, between the prophet and those who hear the melody of his words, and catch some glimpse of their material meaning, but understand not their deeper import.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The precepts of knowledge it is difficult to extricate from error; but once discovered, thay gradually pass into maxims: and thus what the Sage's lite was spent in acquiring, becomes the acquisition of a moment to posterity.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Learning teacheth more in one year than experience in twenty; and learning teacheth safely when experience maketh more miserable than wise.&mdash;ROGER ASCHAM.</p></epigraph>
<head>THE IRISH ANNUAL.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In a handsome folio volume, full gilt, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE DAUGHTERS OF ERIN.</p>
<p>A Series of Portraits, <lb/> ILLUSTRATIVE OF MOORE'S IRISH MELODIES, <lb/> From Paintings by W. P. FRITH, A.R.A., A. ELMORE, A.R.A., W. FISHER, <lb/> J. WRIGHT, A. DERBY, E. HAWKES, W. ROOM, J. G. MIDDLETON, R. T. BOTT, <lb/> and J. WOOD.</p>
<p>ENGRAVED BY OR UNDER THE IMMEDIATE SUPERINTENDENCE OF MR. EDWARD FINDEN.</p>
<p>WITH DESCRIPTIVE LETTER-PRESS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This Volume is a selection of Plates from</hi> &ldquo;FINDEN'S BEAUTIES OF MOORE.&rdquo;</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., the Third Volume of</hi>
<lb/> THE ROMANCE OF THE PEERAGE; <lb/> OR, CURIOSITIES OF FAMILY HISTORY.</p>
<p>BY GEORGE LILLIE CRAIK.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Contents of Volume</hi> III, <lb/> WITH A PORTRAIT OF SIR ROBERT DUDLEY.</p>
<p>The Hereditary Principle; Aristocracy and Democracy.&mdash;Charles Brandon's Widow and her Second Marriage.&mdash;The Lady Mary Grey.&mdash;Sir Robert Dudley.&mdash;Bess of Hardwick and the Talbots.&mdash;The Cavendishes and the Stanhopes.&mdash;Lord Pembroke and Sir Richard Wharton.&mdash;The Wharton and Stuart Duel.&mdash;The Bruce and Sackville Duel.&mdash;The Lord Crichton of Sanquhar.&mdash;The Earldom of Menteith, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. [<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In four volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 42<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Third Edition, with numerous Additions and Corrections, <lb/> OLIVER CROMWELL'S LETTERS AND SPEECHES.</p>
<p>WITH ELUCIDATIONS AND CONNECTING NARRATIVE.</p>
<p>BY THOMAS CARLYLE.</p>
<p>WITH A PORTRAIT OF CROMWELL, FROM AN ORIGINAL MINIATURE BY COOPER.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Supplement to the First and Second Editions, comprising the new matter introduced into</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">the Third Edition, is published in demy</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo.</hi></p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BOOKS FOR PRESENTS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In an elegant volume, small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, fancy boards, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>FAIRY TALES FROM ALL <lb/> NATIONS.</p>
<p>BY ANTHONY R. MONTALBA.</p>
<p>EMBELLISHED WITH TWENTY-FOUR ILLUSTRATIONS <lb/> BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes, small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>A BOOK FOR A CORNER; <lb/> Or Selections in Prose and Verse from Authors best suited to that mode of enjoyment. With <lb/> comments and a general Introduction.</p>
<p>BY LEIGH HUNT.</p>
<p>WITH EIGHTY ILLUSTRATIONS BY F. W.</p>
<p>HULME AND J. FRANKLIN.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
<epigraph><p>There are few kinds of composition from which an author, however learned or ingenious, can hope a long continuance of fame. He who has carefully studied human nature, and can well describe it, may with most reason flatter his ambition.&mdash;JOHNSON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Style in painting is the same as in writing; a power over materials, whether words or colours, by which conceptions or sentiments are conveyed.&mdash;SIR JOSHUA REYNOLDS.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>There is a sort of wit peculiar to knowledge of the world, and we usually find that writers, who are supposed to have the most exhibited that knowledge in their books, are also commonly esteemed the wittiest authors of their country.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Libraries are as the shrines where all the relies of the ancient saints, full of true virtue, and that without delusion or imposture, are preserved and reposed.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph><head>CHEAP EDITION OF MR. AINSWORTH'S WORKS, <lb/> IN SHILLING VOLUMES.</head>
<p>PREPARING FOR IMMEDIATE PUBLICATION, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, ornamental boards,</hi>
<lb/> A CHEAP EDITION <lb/> OF <lb/> THE WORKS OF <lb/> W. HARRISON AINSWORTH, ESQ.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="2">
<head>THIS EDITION WILL COMPRISE</head>
<row>
<cell> WINDSOR CASTLE </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> ROOKWOOD </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> GUY FAWKES </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> CRICHTON </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> JACK SHEPPARD </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> OLD ST. PAUL'S </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> THE MISER'S DAUGHTER </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> ST. JAMES'S </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>PUBLISHED FOR THE AUTHOR BY</p><closer>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Monthly Numbers, Price</hi> ONE SHILLING <hi rend="italics">each,</hi>
<lb/> WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS,</opener><head>THE <lb/> JOURNAL OF DESIGN AND MANUFACTURES,</head><p>ADDRESSED TO <lb/> MERCHANTS, MANUFACTURERS, RETAIL DEALERS, DESIGNERS, <lb/> ART-WORKMEN, AND THE GENERAL PUBLIC.</p>
<p>THE JOURNAL OF DESIGN has, as it ought to have, politics of its own. In this matter of Ornamental Design we hope to prove ourselves thoroughly conservative of the best interests of manufacturers, designers, and all parties concerned. We are the advocates for better laws and a better tribunal to protect copyright in designs, and for a largely increased extension of copyright. We think the restless demands of the public for constant novelty, are alike mischievous to the progress of good ornamental art as they are to all commercial interests. We think that the Schools of Design should be reformed and made business-like realities. We shall wage war against all pirates; and we hope to see the day when it will be thought as disgraceful for one manufacturer to pillage another's patterns, as it is held to be if he should walk into the counting-house and rob his till. These are some of the points of our political creed, with which we start on our undertaking. We profess that our aim is to foster ornamental art in all its ways, and to do those things for its advance, in all its branches, which it would be the appropriate business of a Board of Design to do, if such a useful department of Government actually existed.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Vol. I. is now ready with</hi> 50 <hi rend="italics">Patterns of actual Fabrics, and nearly</hi> 200 <hi rend="italics">Engravings</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">on Wood. Cloth,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
<epigraph><p>They who speak truth, however discovered, have a right to be heard;&mdash;they who assist others in discovering it have the yet higher claim to be applauded.&mdash;PARR.</p></epigraph><epigraph><p>God Almighty first planted a garden.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Authorship is, according to the spirit in which it is pursued, an infancy, a pastime, a day-labour, a handicraft, an art, a science, a virtue.&mdash;SCHLEGEL.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Truth will be uppermost, some time or other.&mdash;SIR W. TEMPLE.</p></epigraph>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Monthly Numbers, price One Shilling each,</hi></opener><head>THE FLORIST AND GARDEN MISCELLANY.</head>
<p>SUPERINTENDED BY EDWARD BECK, OF ISLEWORTH.</p>
<p>THIS work contains communications from many of the most successful cultivators of Flowers; and will be found not only interesting to the lovers of gardens, but the year's numbers, when bound up, form an elegant book for the drawing-room table.</p>
<p>Each Monthly Part includes a Monthly Calendar of operations supplied by practical Florists, with a Coloured Plate and a Woodcut executed in the best manner.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Vol. II. will be published early in December.</hi></p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW AND CHEAPER EDITIONS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Elegantly Printed in a Pocket Volume, in</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">limp cloth, gilt edges, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> SHAKESPEARE PROVERBS; <lb/> Or, the <hi rend="italics">Wise Saws</hi> of our Wisest Poet, collected <lb/> into a <hi rend="italics">Modern Instance.</hi></p>
<p>By MARY COWDEN CLARKE, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;The Concordance to Shakespeare.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>LIFE IN DALECARLIA: <lb/> THE PARSONAGE OF MORA.</p>
<p>By FREDERIKA BREMER.</p>
<p>Translated by WILLIAM HOWITT.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>ST. PATRICK'S EVE; <lb/> Or, Three Eras in the Life of an Irish <lb/> Peasant.</p>
<p>By CHARLES LEVER, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Harry Lorrequer,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>With numerous Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ,&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>IRISH DIAMONDS; <lb/> Or, a Theory of Irish Wit and Blunders; <lb/> combined with other kindred Subjects.</p>
<p>By JOHN SMITH.</p>
<p>With Six Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> The SECOND EDITION of <lb/> THE YOUNG SPORTSMAN'S MANUAL; <lb/> OR, RECREATIONS IN SHOOTING.</p>
<p>With some Account of <sic corr="the">tho</sic> Game of the British Islands, and practical Directions for the <lb/> Management of the Dog and Gun.</p>
<p>By &ldquo;CRAVEN.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With Sixty-two Illustrations of Game and Sporting Dogs, by WILLIAM HARVEY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">New <sic corr="and">aud</sic> Cheaper Edition, in post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth gilt, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> <lb/> FRANCE IN 1848 AND 1849.</p>
<p>A Narrative of the French Revolution, from the commencement of the Reform <lb/> Movement to the close of the First Session of the Republican Parliament.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">New Edition, with Additions and Corrections.</hi></p>
<p>WITH PORTRAITS AND OTHER ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>JUVENILE BOOKS, NEW EDITIONS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE NOVEL ADVENTURES OF <lb/> TOM THUMB THE GREAT.</p>
<p>Showing how he visited the Insect World <lb/> and learned much Wisdom.</p>
<p>By MRS. BARWELL.</p>
<p>WITH EIGHT ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">to, cloth, gilt back and edges,</hi>
<lb/> THE OLD STORY BOOKS OF <lb/> ENGLAND, <lb/> Newly Revised and Amended, for the Amusement and Delight of all good little Masters <lb/> and Misses.</p>
<p>By AMBROSE MERTON, Gent, F.S.A.</p>
<p>ILLUSTRATED WITH TWELVE PICTURES BY <lb/> EMINENT ARTISTS.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5a"/>
<epigraph><p>It is impossible to make people understand their ignorance; for it requires knowledge to perceive it; and therefore be that can perceive it hath it not.&mdash;BISHOP TAYLOR.</p></epigraph><epigraph><p>To be proud of learning is the greatest ignorance in the world.&mdash;BISHOP TAYLOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Real knowledge never promoted either turbulence or unbelief; but its progress is the forerunner of liberality and enlightened toleration.&mdash;LORD BROUGHAM.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The highest learning is to be wise, and the greatest wisdom is to be good.&mdash;M. AURELIUS.</p></epigraph>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in super-royal folio, half-bound, gilt bands and edges, price</hi> &pound;1 16<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">or with the Maps coloured,</hi> &pound;2 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>SHARPE'S CORRESPONDING ATLAS,</head><p>COMPRISING <lb/> FIFTY-FOUR MAPS, <lb/> CONSTRUCTED UPON A SYSTEM OF SCALE AND PROPORTION, FROM THE MOST RECENT <lb/> AUTHORITIES, AND ENGRAVED ON STEEL BY J. WILSON LOWRY.</p>
<p>WITH A COPIOUS CONSULTING INDEX, <lb/> PREPARED EXPRESSLY FOR THE WORK AND BASED UPON THE MAPS THEMSELVES.</p>
<p>THIS Atlas combines at once new and important means of facilitating geographical study with just accuracy and skilful execution, at an unexampled lowness of price. Nothing superfluous is admitted into it, to the needless increase of its cost, nor is anything omitted, the absence of which would impair its general utility. It is a Work at once available for all purposes of general reference, is complete in character, comprehensive in scope, and compact in form, and accomplishes, by its peculiar plan of construction, effects of great practical value, never before attempted; and is, at the same time, so cheap as to be within the means of every who desires to possess an Atlas.</p>
<p>The term &ldquo;Corresponding&rdquo; is applied to indicate that Uniformity of Scale by which these Maps are distinguished from those of every other collection. If we open any Atlas extant, we shall find in it almost as great a diversity of scales as of maps; the latter, therefore are so contradictory as to admit of no direct comparison with each other, either as to the linear or superficial dimensions they respectively represent. There must, of course, be considerable disparity of scale between maps of Continents and maps of States; but if the subject is examined it will be seen that a change of scale in the case of each individual map, as always has been the practice, is neither necessary nor useful. The leading purpose of this Work is to place the maps more efficiently in correspondence with each other, by limiting the number of scales. They are here reduced from about fifty to the inconsiderable number of four, with a single exception, that of Switzerland, the sheets of each series, just like the several parts of a single map, speaking one and the same language to the eye, and being capable of direct admeasurement one with the other.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>THE FOUR SCALES.</head>
<p>There are Twenty-seven DIVISIONAL Maps, which correspond in scale respectively with each other&mdash;Great Britain, France, Italy, &amp;c., as marked D in the list.</p>
<p>The CONTINENTAL Maps are ten in number; Asia being divided into three, North America and Africa each forming two maps; Europe, South America, and Australia, remaining single as before. These ten maps also correspond with each other, and are marked C in the list.</p>
<p>The above thirty-seven maps, with the two Index Maps to the subdivisions of India and Russia, and Mercator's Projection of the World, virtually complete the Atlas, as comprising the circuit of the Globe&mdash;Forty Maps.</p>
<p>But, as assistant to the above, there are twelve others. Five of the North and South American States, which correspond with the two Index Maps above, the seven maps forming an INTERMEDIATE class (marked I), and seven ENLARGED Maps (marked E)&mdash;England two sheets, Scotland, Ireland, Netherlands and Belgium, Greece, and Switzerland. Of these seven maps, six correspond with each other; Switzerland, as the lesser territory, being still farther extended, and forming the exception to the rule.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>ANALYSIS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> C refers to 10 CONTINENTAL Maps </cell>
<cell> 45 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 60 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> I refers to 7 INTERMEDIATE </cell>
<cell> 22&frac12; </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 30 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> D refers to 27 DIVISIONAL </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 12 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> E refers to 6 ENLARGED </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 4 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1 SWITZERLAND </cell>
<cell> 2&frac14; </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 3 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 TWO HEMISPHERES AND MERCATOR.&mdash;TOTAL, 54 MAPS. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Scale of Miles is adjusted to each Series and inserted on every Map in the usual</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">manner.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6a"/>
<epigraph><p>The more widely knowledge is spread, the more will they be prized whose happy lot it is to extend its bounds by discovering new truths, to multiply its uses by inventing new modes of applying it in practice.&mdash;LORD BROUGHAM.</p></epigraph><epigraph><p>He that would make a real progress in knowledge must dedicate his age as well as youth, the latter growth as well as the first fruits, at the altar of truth.&mdash;BERKELEY.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>A country which has no national literature, or a literature too insignificant to force its way abroad must always be to its neighbours, at least in every important spiritual respect, an unknown and misestimated country.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Learning is like a river, whose head, being far in the bank, is, at first rising, little, and easily viewed; but still as you go, it gapeth with a wider bank.&mdash;FELTHAM.</p></epigraph><head>LIST OF SHARPE'S CORRESPONDING MAPS.</head>
<list>
<item>1. The World&mdash;Western Hemisphere.</item>
<item>2. The World&mdash;Eastern Hemisphere.</item>
<item>3. The World on Mercator's Projection.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>EUROPE.</head>
<item>4. C Europe with the Mediterranean.</item>
<item>5. D Great Britain and Ireland.</item>
<item>6. E England and Wales&mdash;North <hi rend="italics">Double Map with Railways</hi></item>
<item>7. E England and Wales&mdash;South <hi rend="italics">Double Map with Railways</hi></item>
<item>8. E Scotland&mdash;with Railways.</item>
<item>9. E Ireland&mdash;with Railways.</item>
<item>10. D France&mdash;Belgium&mdash;Switzerland.</item>
<item>11. E Holland and Belgium&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>12. D Prussia, Holland, and the German States.</item>
<item>13. E Switzerland&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>14. D Austrian Empire.</item>
<item>15. D Turkey and Greece.</item>
<item>16. E Greece and the Ionian Islands&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>17. D Italy.</item>
<item>18. D Spain and Portugal.</item>
<item>19. D Northern Sweden and Frontier of Russia <hi rend="italics">Double Map of the Baltic.</hi></item>
<item>20. D Denmark, Sweden, and Russia on the Baltic. <hi rend="italics">Double Map of the Baltic.</hi></item>
<item>21. D Western Russia from the Baltic to the Euxine.</item>
<item>22. D Russia on the Euxine.</item>
<item>23. D Russia on the Caucasus.</item>
</list>
<p>The topographical interest of the interior of this vast empire is hardly equal to its extent. The above series of frontier maps connect it with the neighbouring states, and, independent of their political bearing, have each a marked geographical character in itself. They also accord as to scale with Austria, Prussia, &amp;c.</p>
<list>
<item>24. I Russia in Europe&mdash;General Map.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>ASIA.</head>
<item>25. C Northern Asia&mdash;Asiatic Russia.</item>
<item>26. C South-Western Asia&mdash;Overland to India.</item>
<item>27. C South Eastern Asia&mdash;Birmah, China and Japan.</item>
<item>28. C Australia and New Zealand</item>
<item>29. D Egypt, the Red Sea, and Arabia Petr&aelig;.</item>
<item>30. D Nubia, the Red Sea, and Abyssinia, to the Strait of Bab-el-Mandeb.</item>
</list>
<p>Egypt and Nubia, although properly in Africa, are more conveniently placed with the Asiatic Maps, from their political bearing between Europe and India. Geographers must follow the track of the Steam Engine.</p>
<list>
<item>31. D Asia Minor.</item>
<item>32. D Syria and Provinces to the Persian Gulf.</item>
<item>33. D Western Persia.</item>
<item>34. D Eastern Persia.</item>
<item>35. D Affghanistan and the Punjab.</item>
<item>36. D Beloochistan and Sinde.</item>
<item>37. D Central India.</item>
<item>38. D The Carnatic, &amp;c.</item>
<item>39. D Bengal, &amp;c.</item>
<item>40. I India&mdash;General Map.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>AFRICA&mdash;AMERICA.</head>
<item>41. C North Africa.</item>
<item>42. C South Africa.</item>
<item>43. C British North America.</item>
<item>44. C Central America.</item>
<item>45. I United States&mdash;General Map.</item>
<item>46. D United States, North-East.</item>
<item>47. D United States, South-East.</item>
<item>48. D United States, South-West.</item>
<item>49. D Jamaica &mdash; Leeward and Windward Islands&mdash;with Jamaica on Enlarged Scale.</item>
<item>50. I Mexico and Guatemala</item>
<item>51. C South America.</item>
<item>52. I Columbian and Peruvian Republics, and Western Brazil.</item>
<item>53. I La Plata, Chili, and Southern Brazil.</item>
<item>54. I Eastern Brazil.</item>
</list>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>BINDING SUBSCRIBERS' COPIES.</head>
<p>The Publishers have made arrangements for BINDING &ldquo;SHARPE'S ATLAS&rdquo; in the best and strongest manner, with India-Rubber Backs, in <hi rend="italics">Half Morocco, Cloth Sides, Gilt Back and Edges, price</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Subscribers may have their Copies bound, by sending them through their respective Booksellers, or direct to CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, Strand, London.</p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>SINGLE MAPS.</head>
<p>For Commercial Purposes, and for General Diffusion in Schools, these Maps are sold in Separate Sheets at Fourpence each, Plain, or Sixpence Coloured. Parties choosing Maps marked the same letter in the list, will have them upon the same scale.</p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>MAPS FOR TRAVELLERS.</head>
<p>These Maps are also mounted on cloth, in cloth cases, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, single maps. <hi rend="italics">England and Wales,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">the Baltic,</hi> double maps, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This work deserves high praise. Though considerably cheaper than even the admirable maps of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge, the size is larger, the fulness and accuracy not less, and the engraving is remarkable for its care, clearness, and beauty.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The main feature of this series is, that the plates are engraved upon a uniform scale, so as to admit a direct comparison with each other in their respective linear and superficial dimensions; an arrangement which must be of immense advantage to the student and others.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Art-Union.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7a"/>
<epigraph><p>Plays and romances sell as well as books of devotion; but with this difference&mdash;more people read the former than buy them; and more buy the latter than read them.&mdash;TOM BROWN.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Of no given book, not even of a fashionable novel can you predicate with certainty that its vacuity is absolute.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Although our learning raiseth up against us many enemies among the low, and more among the powerful, yet doth it invest us with grand and glorious privileges; and grant to us a largess of beatitude.&mdash;LANDOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>To seize a character, even that of one man, in its life and secret mechanism, requires a philosopher; to delineate it with truth and impressiveness is work for a poet.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph><head>THE RECENT VOLUMES OF <lb/> Chapman and Hall's Series of Original Works.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Two Volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>FANNY HERVEY; <lb/> OR, THE MOTHER'S CHOICE.</p>
<p>A Novel.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Out of elements exceedingly simple in themselves, the Author has constructed a story of the deepest tragic power. * * The Novel is entitled to take rank among the best works of fiction.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>RAMBLES AND OBSERVATIONS IN <lb/> NEW SOUTH WALES.</p>
<p>WITH SKETCHES OF MEN AND MANNERS, NOTICES OF THE ABORIGINES, GLIMPSES <lb/> OF SCENERY, AND SOME HINTS TO EMIGRANTS.</p>
<p>BY JOSEPH PHIPPS TOWNSEND.</p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the best books on New South Wales that has appeared.&rdquo;&mdash;SPECTATOR.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Two Volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s., the</hi> THIRD EDITION <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
<lb/> MARY BARTON, <lb/> A TALE OF MANCHESTER LIFE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Its interest is intense&mdash;often painfully so. * * We can conscientiously pronounce it to be a production of great excellence, and of still greater promise.&rdquo;&mdash;EDINBURGH REVIEW.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE LIFE OF MAXIMILIEN ROBESPIERRE, <lb/> With Extracts from his Unpublished Correspondence.</p>
<p>BY G. H. LEWES, <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;RANTHORPE,&rdquo; &ldquo;BIOGRAPHICAL HISTORY OF PHILOSOPHY,&rdquo; &amp;C.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Lewes has rendered good service. not only to history, but to the cause of order in France, by the publication of the present volume.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s., the</hi> SECOND EDITIONS <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
<lb/> WAYFARING SKETCHES <lb/> Among the Greeks and Turks, and on the <lb/> Shores of the Danube.</p>
<p>BY <lb/> A SEVEN YEARS' RESIDENT IN GREECE.</p>
<p>THE <lb/> BACHELOR OF THE ALBANY.</p>
<p>A Novel.</p>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;THE FALCON FAMILY,&rdquo; <lb/> and &ldquo;MY UNCLE THE CURATE,&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8a"/>
<epigraph><p>The way to acquire lasting esteem is not by the fewness of a writer's faults, but the greatness of his beauties, and our noblest works are generally most replete with both.&mdash;GOLDSMITH.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The value of a book is only realised in proportion as it is read. A book which is never read, is of absolutely no value.&mdash;HENRY TAYLOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Eloquence, that leads mankind by the ears, gives a nobler superiority than power that every dunce may use, or fraud that every knave may employ, to lead them by the nose.&mdash;BOLINGBROKE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Read not to contradict and confute, nor to believe and take for granted, nor to find talk and discourse, but to weigh and consider.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph>
<head>Cheap Edition of the Works of Mr. Charles Dickens,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces.</hi></p>
<p>MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY FRANK STONE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p>BARNABY RUDGE.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY GEORGE CATTERMOLE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>NICHOLAS NICKLEBY.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY T. WEBSTER, R. A. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE PICKWICK PAPERS.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY C. R. LESLIE, R.A. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s., half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Cheap Edition of the Novels and Tales of Sir Edward <lb/> Bulwer Lytton, Bart.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces.</hi></p>
<p>RIENZI; <lb/> THE LAST OF THE TRIBUNES.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>PAUL CLIFFORD.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>PELHAM; <lb/> OR, THE ADVENTURES OF A GENTLEMAN.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>EUGENE ARAM.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE LAST OF THE BARONS.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p>A Catalogue of Works published by CHAPMAN and HALL, with Critical Notices, may be had gratis from all Booksellers.</p>
<closer>LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
<trailer>WHITING, LONDON.</trailer>
</div2>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>THE PROPER FIELD FOR &ldquo;Copperfield&rdquo;</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>WHERE shall we find a proper field</l>
<l>For circulating &ldquo;Copperfield?&rdquo;</l>
<l>A clever work like this should find</l>
<l>A place in ev'ry body's mind.</l>
<l>Nor should it fail to have a part</l>
<l>In ev'ry warm admiring heart,</l>
<l>The rising youth should read its page,</l>
<l>Nor should its leaves be hid from age.</l>
<l>It should bedeck the poor man's board,</l>
<l>And swell the volumes of my lord.</l>
<l>This novel merits to be read</l>
<l>Wherever MOSES' fame has spread;</l>
<l>Which, like a banner, is unfurl'd</l>
<l>Throughout the habitable world.</l>
<l>If all who favour MOSES' mart</l>
<l>Would join and take a monthly part,</l>
<l>The theme of our consideration</l>
<l>Would have a wond'rous circulation.</l>
<l>There's scarce a table in the land</l>
<l>On which its leaves would not expand.</l>
<l>'Tis clear that <hi rend="italics">that's</hi> the proper field</l>
<l>For circulating <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Copperfield.&rdquo;</hi></l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome style of Overcoats </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Shooting Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lounging and Morning Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Youth and Boys Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suit </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cassimere Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Dress Coats, from </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Frock </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> H. and T Suit, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from &pound;3 to &pound;20.</p>
<p>NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Minion of the Million,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON</head><p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minorities; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p10a" n="10"/>
<head>THE <lb/> NICOLL PALETOT</head><p>(Registered 6 &amp; 7 Vic. c. 65) <lb/> WAREROOMS, 114, 116, 120, REGENT <lb/> STREET, and 22, CORNHILL.</p>
<p>Also for NICOLL'S Morning Coat, now in almost universal request for the country, riding, walking, &amp;c. Shooting Jackets adapted for the Season, Many have assumed the use of the word PALETOT, but Messrs. NICOLL are the sole Patentees of the design and material. As also of the PATENT TREBLE GARMENT; Or. Palet&ocirc;t (called The Nicoll) which retains all the characteristics of the famed Palet&ocirc;t in its exterior, and has the additional advantages of being convertible from a warm to a light Overcoat, or vice vers&acirc;, at the pleasure of the wearer, or, as the mild or cold nature of the weather may require. This garment must be seen and worn to be properly appreciated; it will be found, perhaps, the best preservative of health in this variable climate.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
