<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VII:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Patricia Schefcick</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.   180K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VII:</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>  56 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1849</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>


<change>
<date>2002-11-12, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-10-01, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>




<titlePage>

<docTitle><titlePart> No.  VII. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> NOVEMBER.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID <lb/> COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to he Published on any Account.)
</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>

<docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.</docAuthor><docImprint>

<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<publisher>AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</publisher>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of Bedding, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest stock and greatest variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES, <lb/> Of which they were the Original Introducers: these Mattresses are made of the finest material, quite equal to the best made in Paris. Also, <lb/> GERMAN SPRING MATTRESSES.</p>
<p>These HEAL and SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are selling at a much lower price than any other house, and can recommend one of them, with a FRENCH MATTRESS on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>THE EIDER DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen <hi rend="italics">only</hi> at their House. It is the warmest, the lightest, and the most elegant covering ever introduced, suitable to the <hi rend="italics">Bed,</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Couch,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">Carriage.</hi> All who have travelled on the Continent are aware that no covering produces such extreme warmth with the same weight; so that for Invalids they are a perfect luxury. Their <lb/> BED FEATHERS <lb/> are also PURIFIED BY STEAM, WITH PATENT MACHINERY, by which the offensive properties of the quill are evaporated and carried off, without subjecting the Feathers to the unpleasant smell of the stove, to which all Feathers dressed in the ordinary way are liable.</p>
<p>HEAL and SON are now enabled to sell Grey Goose Feathers at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per lb., Poultry, 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foreign Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White Goose </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dantzie Goose </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>OLD FEATHER-BEDS re-dressed by this process are perfectly freed from all impurities; and, by expanding the Feathers, the bulk is greatly increased, and the Bed consequently rendered much fuller and softer, at 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb.</p>
<p>OLD AND MOTHY MATTRESSES effectually cured and re-made.</p>
<p>Every description of BLANKETS, QUILTS, and SHEETINGS.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S LIST OF BEDDING.</head>
<p>It contains full particulars of WEIGHTS, SIZES, and PRICES, of every description of Bedding, and is so arranged that purchasers are enabled to judge of the articles best suitable to make a comfortable Bed. Sent free by post on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196, (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL,) <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="1" id="p1"/>
<opener>No. VII&mdash;NOVEMBER, 1849.</opener>
<head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> A SHORT INQUIRY <lb/> INTO <lb/> THE HISTORY OF AGRICULTURE, <lb/> In Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern Times. BY <lb/> CHANDOS WREN HOSKYNS, ESQ.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Work now published is executed with great ability, and displays an intimate knowledge of the subject.&rdquo; <hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We feel assured there is not a landowner or practical farmer extant, who will not confess himself both pleased and edified after reading Mr. Hoskyns' very acceptable contribution to Agricultural literature.&rdquo; <hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth,</hi> <lb/> THE <lb/> POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</p>
<p>REVISED AND ARRANGED EXPRESSLY FOR YOUNG PERSONS AND SCHOOLS.</p>
<p>By W. C. MACREADY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This neat little volume has peculiar claims to public attention, and the Work of expurgation is very carefully done. Mr. Macready has left no blanks, considering them as so many temptations to pry into unclean places, and while providing the family library with a new and useful volume, he has at the same time produced a monument of his own taste and discernment.&rdquo; <hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In One Vol.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 14<hi rend="italics">s., cloth,</hi> <lb/> MEDICAL AND OECONOMICAL BOTANY, <lb/> Illustrated with upwards of Three Hundred Diagrams and Woodcuts. Being the THIRD PART of The <lb/> ELEMENTS OF BOTANY, Structural, Physiological and Medical.</p>
<p>BY JOHN LINDLEY, PH.D., F.R.S., &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Also, by the same Author,</hi> <lb/> PARTS I. &amp; II. Forming the ELEMENTS OF BOTANY, Structural and Physiological.</p>
<p>One Vol. 8vo, price 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth.</p>
<closer>LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2><div2 type="section">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In One Large Volume, with Forty Original Designs, engraved on Wood, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF <lb/> OLIVER GOLDSMITH.</head>
<p>A BIOGRAPHY: IN FOUR BOOKS.</p>
<list>
<item>BOOK 1. THE SIZAR, STUDENT, TRAVELLER, APOTHECARY'S JOURNEYMAN, USHER, AND POOR PHYSICIAN.</item>
<item>2. AUTHORSHIP BY COMPULSION.</item>
<item>3. AUTHORSHIP BY CHOICE.</item>
<item>4. THE FRIEND OF JOHNSON, BURKE, AND REYNOLDS: DRAMATIST, NOVELIST, AND POET.</item>
</list>
<p>BY JOHN FORSTER, <lb/> Of the Inner Temple, Barrister, Author of &ldquo;Lives of Statesmen of the Commonwealth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A fitting, and we think, a permanent companion to the works of the author whose career it commemorates:&mdash;a gentle but a manly apology for the life, which it tracks through each pathetic transition of light and shadow: written in that spirit of which Goldsmith himself would have approved&mdash;pleasing while it instructs us, mild without tameness, earnest without acerbity.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, Bouverie Street; and CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, Strand.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<head>NOTICE.</head>
<p>WITH AN ILLUSTRATION <lb/> THE <lb/> LADDER GOLD <lb/> BY ROBERT BELL, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Wayside Pictures in France, Belgium, and Holland,&rdquo; <lb/> Will be commenced in the next Number of <lb/> BENTLEY'S MISCELLANY.</p>
<closer>NEW BURLINGTON STREET, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">November</hi> 1, 1849.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW WORK BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;JANE EYRE.&rdquo;</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now ready, and may be had at all the Libraries, in</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics">Vols. post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo.</hi></p>
<p>Shirley, by Currer Bell.</p>
<p>Author of &ldquo;Jane Eyre.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, &amp; CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>New and cheaper issue, and Second Edition of SOANE'S New Curiosities <lb/> of Literature.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">This day is published, Part II., containing</hi> 186 <hi rend="italics">pages, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, and a Steel Plate, after N. Poussin,</hi> <lb/> <hi rend="italics">price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d,</hi> <lb/> NEW CURIOSITIES OF LITERATURE AND BOOK <lb/> OF THE MONTHS.</p>
<p>By GEORGE SOANE, ESQ., B.A.</p>
<p>Author of &ldquo;A Life of the Duke of Wellington;&rdquo; &ldquo;The Frolics of Puck;&rdquo; &ldquo;January Eve,&rdquo; &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>The Work will be completed in Four Parts, each Illustrated by a Steel Engraving, forming two handsome post 8vo. vols.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Two pleasant volumes of light, agreeable reading . . . We shall be surprised if these &lsquo;New Curiosities&rsquo; do not become permanently popular.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Just ready, beautifully bound, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., post free</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>CHRISTIAN DOCTRINES; <lb/> FROM THE WORDS OF OUR LORD, OF THE APOSTLES, AND THE PROPHETS.</p>
<p>Beautifully printed, and illuminated in the Missal style, with eight subjects after the Old Masters.</p>
<closer>LONDON: E. CHURTON, 26, Holles Street. DUBLIN: M'GLASHAN, EDINBURGH MENZIES AND Co.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<opener>Early in November, <lb/> LUKE LIMNER'S NEW WORK.</opener>
<head>CHRISTMAS <lb/> COMES <lb/> BUT <lb/> ONCE A YEAR.</head>
<p>SHOWING <lb/> WHAT MR. BROWN DID, THOUGHT, AND INTENDED TO DO, DURING THAT FESTIVE SEASON.</p>
<p>Now first Edited from the Original M.S.S. (or M.E.S.S.), <lb/> WITH NOTES AND ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> BY LUKE LIMNER, ESQ.</p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co., PANCRAS LANE, CHEAPSIDE.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>SECOND EDITION, REVISED AND ENLARGED.<lb/>This day is Published, Second Edition, considerably Enlarged, with Portrait of the Author; Cloth, <lb/> Gilt lettered. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>RUINS OF MANY LANDS.</head>
<p>A PILGRIMAGE. BY NICHOLAS MICHELL.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;Babylon&mdash;Nineveh&mdash;Petra&mdash;Nubia&mdash;Egypt&mdash; Ruined Cities of America&mdash;Rock-Temples of India&mdash;Athens&mdash;Corinth&mdash;Sparta&mdash;Greek Isles&mdash;Troy&mdash;Rome&mdash;Pompeil&mdash;P&aelig;stum&mdash;Roman Amphitheatres&mdash;Roman Ruins in the South of France&mdash;Carthage&mdash;Ephesus&mdash;Tyre&mdash;Baalbec&mdash;Palmyra&mdash;Persepolis&mdash;Susa-Geraza&mdash;Jerusalem, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the most interesting and exquisite volumes of modern days.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Era.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;It conveys in a delightful manner a rich store of information.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG, and Co., Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Cheap Edition of the Novels and Tales <lb/> OF <lb/> G. P. R. JAMES, ESQ.</head>
<p>MESSRS. SIMMS &amp; M'INTYRE beg to announce, that having purchased the Copy right of all Mr. JAMES'S WORKS OF FICTION, it is their intention to publish them in the &ldquo;PARLOUR LIBRARY,&rdquo; varied at intervals by works of other celebrated authors.</p>
<p>To meet the views of those who may desire to have these admirable works bound in a more lasting manner than that hitherto adopted in the &ldquo;PARLOUR LIBRARY,&rdquo; it is intended to issue them also in volumes bound in Fancy Cloth, with Gilt Back, at EIGHTEEN-FENCE each. The consecutive numbering will be dropped, so that a selection may be made from the Series without having the appearance of being imperfect.</p>
<p>ON DECEMBER 1ST, 1849, WILL BE PUBLISHED, <lb/> THE GIPSY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Price One Shilling in Boards; or, One Shilling and Sixpence in Fancy Cloth, Gill Back.</hi></p>
<closer>SIMMS &amp; M'INTYRE, PATERNOSTER ROW, LONDON; AND DONEGAL STREET, BELFAST.</closer>
<trailer>GEORGE PHILIP AND SON, LIVERPOOL. J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH, R. GRIFFIN AND CO., GLASGOW. JAMES M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.</trailer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head>THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</head>
<p>A Fairy Tale for Little People.</p>
<p>By MARK LEMON.</p>
<p>WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Just Published</hi>
<lb/> Second Edition, in One Vol. with a Memoir of the Author and Frontispiece, price 6s. 6d.,</opener><head>HOME INFLUENCE, <lb/> A Tale for Mothers and Daughters.</head>
<p>BY GRACE AGUILAR.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a clever and interesting tale; it corresponds well to its name. Illustrating the silent constant influence of a wise and affectionate parent over characters the most diverse.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Christian Lady's Magazine.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: GROOMBRIDGE &amp; SONS, PUBLISHERS.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. in cloth, gilt edges,</hi></opener><head>SKETCHES OF CANTABS.</head>
<p>By JOHN SMITH (of Smith-hall), Gent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We have laughed heartily at Mr. Smith's sketches, and recommend them to the reader who has a taste for real mirth, sly humour, and gentlemanly good-natured satire. They have nothing of commonplace imitation about them, and beneath their surface of banter and persiflage, there is a good spirit and useful intention.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A more entertaining little book we scarcely ever remember to have read. Many a well-known character and well-remembered scene is here depicted with great spirit, and will be recalled with interest to the minds of those who have been familiar with such scenes.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Observer.</hi></p>
<closer>London: GEORGE EARLE, 67, Castle-street East, <lb/> Berners street, Oxford-street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;FOR INDIGESTION, STOMACH AND LIVER COMPLAINTS, TAKE HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>Persons suffering from any derangement of the liver, stomach, or the organs of digestion, should have recourse to Holloway's Pills, as there is no other medicine that acts on these particular complaints with such certain success. Its peculiar properties strengthen the tone of the stomach, increase the appetite, and purify the liver. For bowel complaints it is admirable, as it removes every primary cause of them, thereby restoring the patient to the soundest health and strength. Nervous or sick headaches and lowness of spirits may be easily cured by taking a course of Holloway's Pills.&mdash;Sold by all druggists, and at Professor Holloway's establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well-known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Cahncerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p>and all other Medicines of a nauseous character, may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT ORGANIC CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom. Ask for the Patent Flexible Capsules.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>TO secure Household Linen and Wearing Apparel against Loss or Mistake, use</opener><head>BOND'S PERMANENT MARKING INK.</head>
<p>The Original, and by far the best, requiring no preparation.</p>
<p>Prepared by the Inventor, JOHN BOND, 28, Long Lane, West Smithfield, City, and sold by most Chemists, Stationers, and Medicine Vendors.</p>
<p>Price One Shilling a bottle.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FORD'S. <lb/> EUREKA <lb/> SHIRT</head><p>185 STRAND.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The shirt before us (Mr. Ford's Eureka) appears in every way calculated to fit, and fully bears out the inventor's statement, as &lsquo;the most unique, and the only perfect fitting shirt made.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Observer, October</hi> 7, 1849.</p>
<p>Six very superior shirts for 30s. Patterns of the new coloured shirtings, with list of prices, and directions for self-measurement, sent post free.</p>
<closer>RICHARD FORD, 185, Strand, London.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<head>Warren's Sketches of Character.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER.</p>
<p>Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HAND-WRITING.</p>
<p>Specimens of Writing, with the fee of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's sex to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>LITHOGRAPHIC PRESSES AND MATERIALS</head><p>For Home Trade or Export, <lb/> AT S. STRAKER'S LITHOGRAPHIC ESTABLISHMENT, <lb/> 80, BISHOPSGATE STREET WITHIN, LONDON.</p>
<p>The most extensive Stock of his IMPROVED SIDE LEVER LITHOGRAPHIC PRESSES, together with STONES, INKS, and every requisite for the various branches of the Art are always ready for use. Detailed Price Lists forwarded, and Instruction in the Art afforded.</p>
<p>STRAKER'S LITHOGRAPHIC ESTABLISHMENT for the execution of every description of Drawings, Maps, Plans, Writings, &amp;c., &amp;c., by the first Artists, and on the most moderate terms, with promptitude and dispatch.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 31<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambrie Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>USE <lb/> KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Co.'s. NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES. <lb/> Sold by every Draper. &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> Ad dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eights. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>ENGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND's newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Balance Ivory Table Knives, 10s. per DOZEN.</head>
<p>DESSERT ditto, 9<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Carvers, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair. White Bone Table Knives, 6<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Dessert ditto, 4<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Carvers, 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> per pair. Superior Kitchen Table Knives and Forks, from 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per dozen. Table Knives with pure Nickel Silver&mdash;Tables, 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen; Dessert ditto, 18<hi rend="italics">s.:</hi> Carvers, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair, all marked Richard and John Slack, and warranted.</p>
<p>FENDERS AND FIRE IRONS, <lb/> The greatest variety in London, at Prices that defy competition.</p>
<p>Bronzed Scroll Fenders, with Steel Bar, from 10s.</p>
<p>SILVER SUPERSEDED BY RICHARD AND JOHN SLACK'S <lb/> CHEMICALLY PURIFIED NICKEL SILVER, <lb/> Acknowledged to be the purest metal in existence, made into every article for the table, as spoons, forks, candlesticks, cruet frames, tea-pots, &amp;c., at one-twelfth the price of silver. Send 10 postage stamps, and by return of post you will receive a sample spoon of their metal free; try it, and then send your orders. Their illustrated catalogue may be had gratis, and sent post free to any part.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell>
<cell> Strongest Fiddle. </cell>
<cell> Thread Pattern. </cell>
<cell> King's Pattern. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Table Spoons and Forks </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Table Spoons </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>RICHARD AND JOHN SLACK, <lb/> 336, Strand, opposite Somerset House.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Their Book, containing upwards of</hi> 200 <hi rend="italics">Engravings, may be had gratis, or sent to any part post free.</hi></p><closer> ESTABLISHED 1818.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<opener>NO MORE PILLS NOR ANY OTHER DRUGS.&mdash;DYSPEPSIA (INDIGESTION), CONSTIPATION, DIARRHOEA, NAUSEA, and SICKNESS DURING PREGNANCY OR AT SEA, ACIDITY, HEARTBURN, FLATULENCY, DISTENSION, HEMORRHOIDAL AFFECTIONS, NERVOUS, BILIOUS, and LIVER COMPLAINTS, PALPITATION OF THE HEART. DERANGEMENT OF THE KIDNEYS AND BLADDER, ASTHMA, DROPSY, SCROFULA, CONSUMPTION, DEBILITY, PARALYSIS, DEPRESSION OF SPIRITS, &amp;c., are effectually and permanently removed by</opener><head>DU BARRY'S REVALENTA ARABICA FOOD,</head><p>without inconvenience, medicine, or expense, as it saves other more costly remedies.&mdash;Du Barry and Co., 127, New Bond-street, London.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>CASES.</head>
<p>From the Right Hon. the Lord Stuart de Decies. &ldquo;Dromana, Capoquin, County Waterford, Feb. 15, 1849. &ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;I have derived much benefit from the use of the &lsquo;Revalenta Food.&rsquo; &ldquo;STUART DE DECIES.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;4, Park Walk, Little Chelsea, London, Oct. 2, 1848.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twenty-seven years' dyspepsia has been effectually removed by your excellent &lsquo;Revalenta Arabica Food,&rsquo; in six weeks' time, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;PARKER D. BINGHAM. Captain, Royal Navy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Louisa Terrace, Exmouth, Aug. 17, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear Sir,&mdash;I will thank you to send me, on receipt of this, two 101b. canisters of your &lsquo;Revaleota Arabica Food.&rsquo; I beg to assure you that its beneficial effects have been duly appreciated by, dear sir, yours respectfully,</p>
<p>&ldquo;THOMAS KING, Major-General.&rdquo;</p>
<p>From the Venerab'e the Archdeacon of Ross. &ldquo;Aghadown Glebe, Skibbereen, County Cork, Aug. 22, 1849. &ldquo;Dear Sir,&mdash;I cannot speak too favourably of the &lsquo;Revalenta Arabica.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;ALEX, STUART, Archdeacon of Ross.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bromley, Middlesex, March 31, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;The lady for whom I ordered your food is six months advanced in pregnancy; she was suffering severely from indigestion and constipation, throwing up her meals shorting after eating them, having a great deal of heartburn, and being constantly obliged to resort to physic or the enema, and sometimes to both. I am happy to inform you that your food produced immediate relief. She has never been sick since, had but little heartburn, and the functions are more regular. I authorise the publication of this note if you think it will assist you in benefiting other sufferers.&mdash;I am, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;THOMAS WOODHOUSE.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Athol-street, Perth, May 2, 1848.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some time has now elapsed since the lady, who had been an invalid for thirteen years from want of digestion, accompanied with cough and general prostration of strength, for whom I procured your &lsquo;Arabica Food,&rsquo; has been using it daily as directed, and I am happy to say that it has produced a most salutary change in her system, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;JAMES PORTER.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Haddington, East Lothian, March 8, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear Sir,&mdash;Your excellent &lsquo;Arabica Food&rsquo; has completely restored my stomach, nerves, and liver, which had been disordered for nearly twenty years past, and my health is now everything I could wish, and has been so these three months past, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;ANDREW FRASER.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;2, Princess-street, Manchester, 3rd Month, 19th, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Respected Friend,&mdash;I think no one, who had received or seen so much good and comfort result from it as in my mother's case would be without it in sickness. Thou art at liberty to use this letter as thou thinkest best, and I will cheerfully answer any inquiries. I am, thy friend,</p>
<p>&ldquo;EDWARD CORBETT, Sanitary Engineer,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pool Anthony, Tiverton, November 8, 1848.</p>
<p>&ldquo;All that I had suffered from for twenty-five years, and which no medicine could remove or relieve, seems to vanish under the influence of Revalenta. I enjoy sound and refreshing sleep, which, until now, I could not procure. Nervousness is passing away rapidly, and I am much more calm and collected in everything I do, and it has quite sweetened my poor temper. It now affords me pleasure to do for others what before I did not dare to do for nervous irritation, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WM. R. REEVES.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;King's College, Cambridge, Oct. 15, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I now consider myself a stranger to all complaints, except a hearty old age. I am as well as ever I was, and even quite free from the vexatious and troublesome annoyance of an eruption of the skin, of which I had suffered for years, and which my medical attendant had declared incurable at my time of life. About sixty years ago, I had a fall from my horse, hemiplegia was the consequence; my left arm and leg were paralysed, also my left eyelid and the eye was displaced. From 1789, these dilapidations have resisted all remedies until now, at the age of 85, by two years' use of your delicious breakfast food, my left arm and leg have been rendered as useful to me as the right, and the left eyelid restored to health; the eye so much so, that it requires no spectacles, &amp;c. I deem this extraordinary cure of much importance to sufferers at large, and consider it my duty to place the above details at your disposal, in any way you think will promote the welfare of others. Faithfully.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WILLIAM HUNT, Barrister-at-Law.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;3, Sidney Terrace, Reading. Berks, Dec. 3, 1847.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen,&mdash;I am happy to be able to inform you, that the person for whom the former quantity was procured, has derived very great benefit from its use: distressing symptoms of long standing have been removed, and a feeling of restored health induced. Having witnessed the beneficial effects in the above mentioned case, I can with confidence recommend it, and shall have much pleasure in so doing whenever an opportunity offers, &amp;c., &amp;c. I am, gentlemen, very truly yours.</p>
<p>&ldquo;JAMES SHORLAND, late Surgeon, 96 Regiment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With regard to the above case, of which the particulars have been communicated to us, the distressing symptoms alluded to were derangement of the digestive organs, with a peculiar distension of the skin over the whole body; the impression conveyed being that of general Anasarca, except that it did not pit on pressure, but was a firm elastic swelling. After a few days use of the &ldquo;Revalenta Arabica,&rdquo; this unnatural tumefaction subsided, and by continuing its use, the integuments have become soft and pliable, and all the unpleasant feelings have been removed.</p>
<p>Similar expressions of gratitude from 5000 other correspondents.</p>
<p>In canisters at 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d;</hi> of 4lb. at 11<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> 10lb. at 22<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> super-refined quality, 8lb, 33<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and 4lb., 22<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> suitably packed for all climates. 6lb. and 10lb. canisters forwarded by DU BARRY and Co., on receipt of Post-office or bankers' orders (carriage free) to any town or railway station connected by rail with London, or to any port in Scotland or Ireland connected with London by steam or railing vessels. Shipments abroad attended to. Their amount may be sent in a bill or banker's order on London, or placed to the credit of Messrs. Du Barry and Co's account, at Messrs. Coutts and Co., bankers, London.</p>
<p>A popular Treatise on &ldquo;The Restoration of the Human Frame, however seriously impaired, without Medicine,&rdquo; by Du Barry and Co., forwarded by them, post tree, on receipt of letter stamps for 8<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> also at Whittaker and Co's; Simpkin, Marshall and Co., and all Booksellers.</p>
<p>Agents and the Trade will please apply to Messrs. DU BARRY and Co., 127, New Bond Street, London.</p>
<p> The word &ldquo;Revalenta,&rdquo; pronounced by the Arabs and Bedouins &ldquo;Reval Yenta,&rdquo; may be translated the &ldquo;Restorer,&rdquo; or &ldquo;Renovator,&rdquo; Its origin may be traced in the Sanscrit, where it corresponds to the Latin verb Revalescere, sco. &ldquo;Ex capitali morbo revalescere.&rdquo;&mdash;Ovid. &ldquo;To recover from a deadly complaint.&rdquo;</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head>
<p>THE economy both in the cost and wear of this Umbrella has been fully borne out by the experience of these last 18 months, and which can be testified by some thousands of purchasers to whom they have given universal satisfaction. They may be obtained of most Umbrella Dealers in the United Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Patentees, 140, Regent-street, <lb/> 94, Fleet-street, <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</p>
<p>Warehouse, 75, Cheapside.</p>
<p>CHEAP SILK UMBRELLAS, from 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p>
<p>The houses licensed for the manufacture of the Alpaca Umbrella, wholesale, are <lb/> Messrs. J. &amp; W. RUTTER, 122, Cheapside.</p>
<p>Messrs. J. MORLAND &amp; SON, 50, Eastcheap.</p>
<p>Messrs. WADDINGTON &amp; SONS, 1, Coleman St.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS</head>
<p>The QUEEN, <lb/> H. R. H. Prince Albert, <lb/> Queen Adelaide, <lb/> King Louis Philippe, <lb/> and the <lb/> Duchess of Kent.</p>
<p>DOUDNEYS.</p>
<p>The efforts of the Doudneys to overcome old fashioned prejudices having resulted in their obtaining the continued patronage and unqualified approbation of the principal Sovereigns, Royalty and Nobility of Europe; they henceforth proudly point to this fact, and say, BEHOLD THE TRIUMPH OF CASH PAYMENTS OVER THE OLD CREDIT SYSTEM! And forget not, that,&mdash;To be Cheap things must be Good.</p>
<p>The Queens Victoria and Adelaide, and the Royal and Noble Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge Sutherland and Buccleuch, constantly wear Doudney's elegant Registered Cloak, in a variety of Waterproof materials for Winter Wraps and the Promenade.&mdash;&ldquo;Every Lady should see these graceful Garments.&rdquo; <hi rend="italics">(Vide Morning Post, Sep.</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">th.)</hi> They surpass all others as School Cloaks for the Sons and Daughters.</p>
<p>For Gentlemen.&mdash;The Royal Registered Cloak, as made for H.R H. Prince Albert, the Nobility, the Army, and Navy, and all who study comfort, coupled with a truly Gentlemanly exterior. These cloaks are pronounced by those who understand the matter, &ldquo;The most sensible Garment ever introduced,&rdquo; at prices to suit all customers from the Superb down to the useful Guinea Cloak.</p>
<p>Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria, and the Ladies of the Court. A Superfine Cloth Habit for 4 Guineas.</p>
<p>The New Patent Belt for Riding or general exercise, the only really effectual protection against rupture, the support commencing at the <hi rend="italics">bottom edge</hi> of the belt, and producing an uniform upward pressure. They may be enlarged or tightened to the extent of six inches at pleasure, and never produce indigestion either in Ladies or Gentlemen. They are attached to Drawers with excellent effect. The most eminent of the Faculty are recommending these in preference to all others.</p>
<p>LIVERIES. Three Guineas the Plain Suit of Best Quality. <hi rend="italics">Ready Money does it!!!</hi> and a very extensive practice among families of first distinction insures satisfactory results.</p>
<p>Waterproof Irish Poplin.&mdash;The DOUDNEYS are the sole manufacturers of this beautiful article to HER MAJESTY AND THE PRINCE CONSORT. Gentlemen's Coats, Ladies' Cloaks, and lengths for Dresses can be obtained only at their Establishments,</p><p>CELEBRATED <lb/> FOR <lb/> BOY'S CLOTHING</p>
<p>CEREBRATED FOR SHOOTING JACKETS</p>
<closer>17, OLD BOND STREET, <lb/> Extending into BURLINGTON ARCADE, (No. 25.) and at <lb/> 49, LOMBARD STREET, Established 1784.</closer>
<trailer><hi rend="italics">Ladies and Gentlemen in the Country should send for a book of details.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>


<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">My first fall in life.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">We arrive unexpectedly at Mr. Peggotty's fireside.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>

<div1 type="section">
<pb id="pv" n="[iii]"/>
<opener>This day is published, price 2s. 6d., roan, gilt edges,</opener><head>PUNCH'S <lb/> POCKET-BOOK <lb/> FOR 1850.</head>
<p>WITH A COLOURED FRONTISPIECE ON STEEL, <lb/> (COMMUNISM;) <lb/> AND OTHER ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> BY JOHN LEECH, RICHARD DOYLE, &amp; H. K. BROWNE.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>CONTENTS:&mdash;FIRST PART.</head>
<div3 type="section">
<head>THE STATE.&mdash;</head>
<p>The Royal Family&mdash;Sovereigns of Europe&mdash;The Queen's Ministers&mdash;Officers of State in Scotland&mdash;Officers of State in Ireland&mdash;The Queen's Household&mdash;Ambassadors and Ministers abroad&mdash;Ambassadors and Ministers in England&mdash;Lords Lieutenant of England, &amp;c.&mdash;Government Offices and Officers.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>THE LEGISLATURE.&mdash;</head>
<p>The House of Peers&mdash;Peeresses&mdash;Officers of the House of Peers&mdash;The House of Commons&mdash;Alphabetical List of the Commons&mdash;Officers of the House of Commons.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>COMMERCE.&mdash;</head>
<p>The City Corporation&mdash;East India Company&mdash;Bank of England&mdash;Bankers in London&mdash;Army and Navy Agents&mdash;The Public Funds.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>LAW.&mdash;</head>
<p>English Courts of Law&mdash;Scottish Courts of Law&mdash;Irish Courts of Law&mdash;Law Terms and Returns&mdash;Allowance to Witnesses&mdash;Ditto at County Courts&mdash;Quarter Sessions&mdash;University Terms.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>TAXES AND MISCELLANEOUS.&mdash;</head>
<p>Assessed Taxes&mdash;Commercial and other Stamps&mdash;Post and Transit&mdash;Coach and Cab Fares&mdash;Tide Table&mdash;Table to find High Water&mdash;Eclipses&mdash;General Notes for the Year&mdash;Table to calculate the Income-Tax&mdash;Public Amusements&mdash;Abstract of the Health of Towns Act&mdash;Residences of the Foreign Ambassadors&mdash;Calendar&mdash;Cash Account&mdash;Diary and Memoranda&mdash;Solar Ingresses&mdash;Table to calculate Payments&mdash;Marketing Table&mdash;Public Offices.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>SECOND PART.</head>
<p>The Heir of Mortlake; or, the Fatal Name&mdash;Who do You think will look at You?&mdash;Fancies in an Omnibus&mdash;The Bill&mdash;The Inconveniences of a Ground Floor&mdash;The Music of Mind&mdash;The Brazen Knocker; or, the Lost Clerk&mdash;Enlgma&mdash;Society for the Discouragement of Punning&mdash;The Sentiment of Trade&mdash;A String of Pearls from a Barrel of Oysters&mdash;The Bachelor's Housekeeper&mdash;A Yarn&mdash;An Emigrant's Letter&mdash;Hopes and Fears on Paying Taxes&mdash;A Hard Case of Eggs and Bacon&mdash;Lessons for Old and Young&mdash;Paragraphs for a few Millions of our Readers&mdash;A Family of Lord Chancellors&mdash;How the Hospitable Briggs secured the best Cuts&mdash;The Swoop of the Night Hawk&mdash;Wholesome Superstitions.</p>
<closer>LONDON: PUNCH OFFICE, 85, FLEET STREET.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="section">
<pb id="pvi" n="[iv]"/>
<p>PUNCH'S ALMANACK for 1850 will be published <lb/> in December. The Illustrations by John Leech <lb/> and Richard Doyle,</p><closer><hi rend="italics">Office,</hi> 85, <hi rend="italics">Fleet Street.</hi></closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="narrative">
<pb n="193" id="p193"/>

<head>[THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]

</head>
<div2 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER XIX. <lb/> I LOOK ABOUT ME, AND MAKE A DISCOVERY.</head>
<p>I AM doubtful whether I was at heart glad or sorry, when my school-days drew to an end, and the time came for my leaving Doctor Strong's. I had been very happy there, I had a great attachment for the Doctor, and I was eminent and distinguished in that little world. For these reasons I was sorry to go; but for other reasons, unsubstantial enough, I was glad. Misty ideas of being a young man at my own disposal, of the importance attaching to a young man at his own disposal, of the wonderful things to be seen and done by that magnificent animal, and the wonderful effects he could not fail to make upon society, lured me away. So powerful were these visionary considerations in my boyish mind, that I seem, according to my present way of thinking, to have left school without natural regret. The separation has not made the impression on me, that other separations have. I try in vain to recal how I felt about it, and what its circumstances were; but it is not momentous in my recollection. I suppose the opening prospect confused me. I know that my juvenile experiences went for little or nothing then; and that life was more like a great fairy story, which I was just about to begin to read, than anything else.</p>
<p>My aunt and I had held many grave deliberations on the calling to which I should be devoted. For a year or more I had endeavoured to find a satisfactory answer to her often-repeated question, &ldquo;What I would like to be?&rdquo; But I had no particular liking, that I could discover, for anything. If I could have been inspired with a knowledge of the science of navigation, taken the command of a fast-sailing expedition, and gone round the world on a triumphant voyage of discovery, I think I might have considered myself completely suited. But, in the absence of any such miraculous provision, my desire was to apply myself to some pursuit that would not lie too heavily upon her purse; and to do my duty in it, whatever it might be.</p>
<p>Mr. Dick had regularly assisted at our councils, with a meditative and sage demeanour. He never made a suggestion but once; and on that occasion (I don't know what put it in his head), he suddenly proposed that I should be &ldquo;a Brazier.&rdquo; My aunt received this proposal so very ungraciously, that he never ventured on a second; but ever afterwards confined himself to looking watchfully at her for her suggestions, and rattling his money.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trot, I tell you what, my dear,&rdquo; said my aunt, one morning in the Christmas season when I left school; &ldquo;as this knotty point is still unsettled, and as we must not make a mistake in our decision if we can help it, I think we had better take a little breathing-time. In the meanwhile, you must try to look at it from a new point of view, and not as a schoolboy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I will, aunt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It has occurred to me,&rdquo; pursued my aunt, &ldquo;that a little change, and a glimpse of life out of doors, may be useful, in helping you to know your
<pb n="194" id="p194"/>
own mind, and form a cooler judgment. Suppose you were to take a journey now. Suppose you were to go down into the old part of country again, for instance, and see that&mdash;that out-of-the-way woman with the savagest of names,&rdquo; said my aunt, rubbing her nose, for could never thoroughly forgive Peggotty for being so called.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of all things in the world, aunt, I should like it best!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;that's lucky, for I should like it too. it's natural and rational that you should like it. And I am very well persuaded that whatever you do, Trot, will always be natural and rational.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope so, aunt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your sister, Betsey Trotwood,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;would have been as natural and rational a girl as ever breathed. You'll be worthy of won't you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope I shall be worthy of <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> aunt. That will be enough for me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's a mercy that poor dear baby of a mother of yours didn't live,&rdquo; said my aunt, looking at me approvingly, &ldquo;or she'd have been so vain of her boy by this time, that her soft little head would have been completely turned, if there was anything of it left to turn.&rdquo; (My aunt always excused any weakness of her own in my behalf, by transferring it in this way to my poor mother.) &ldquo;Bless me, Trotwood, how you do remind me of her!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pleasantly, I hope, aunt?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He's as like her, Dick,&rdquo; said my aunt, emphatically, &ldquo;he's as like her, as she was that afternoon, before she began to fret&mdash;bless my heart, he's as like her, as he can look at me out of his two eyes!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is he indeed?&rdquo; said Mr. Dick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And he's like David, too,&rdquo; said my aunt, decisively.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is very like David!&rdquo; said Mr. Dick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But what I want you to be, Trot,&rdquo; resumed my aunt &ldquo;&mdash;I don't mean physically, but morally; you are very well physically&mdash;is, a firm fellow. A fine firm fellow, with a will of your own. With resolution,&rdquo; said my aunt, shaking her cap at me, and clenching her hand. &ldquo;With determination. With character, Trot&mdash;with strength of character that is not to be influenced, except on good reason, by anybody, or by anything. That's what I want you to be. That's what your father and mother might both have been, Heaven knows, and been the better for it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I intimated that I hoped I should be what she described.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That you may begin, in a small way, to have a reliance upon yourself, and to act for yourself,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;I shall send you upon your trip, alone. I did think, once, of Mr. Dick's going with you; but, on second thoughts, I shall keep him to take care of me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Dick, for a moment, looked a little disappointed; until the honor and dignity of having to take care of the most wonderful woman in the world, restored the sunshine to his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Besides,&rdquo; said my aunt, &ldquo;there's the Memorial&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, certainly,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, in a hurry, &ldquo;I intend, Trotwood, to get that done immediately&mdash;it really must be done immediately! And then it will go in, you know&mdash;and then&mdash;,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, after checking himself, and pausing a long time, &ldquo;there'll be a pretty kettle of fish!&rdquo;</p>
<p>In pursuance of my aunt's kind scheme, I was shortly afterwards fitted out with a handsome purse of money, and a portmanteau, and tenderly dismissed
<pb n="195" id="p195"/>
upon my expedition. At parting, my aunt gave me some good advice, and a good many kisses; and said that as her object was that I should look about me, and should think a little, she would recommend me to stay a few days in London, if I liked it, either on my way down into Suffolk, or in coming back. In a word, I was at liberty to do what I would, for three weeks or a month; and no other conditions were imposed upon my freedom than the before-mentioned thinking and looking about me, and a pledge to write three times a week and faithfully report myself.</p>
<p>I went to Canterbury first, that I might take leave of Agnes and Mr. Wickfield (my old room in whose house I had not yet relinquished), and also of the good Doctor. Agnes was very glad to see me, and told me that the house had not been like itself since I had left it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure I am not like myself when I am away,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I seem to want my right hand, when I miss you. Though that's not saying much; for there's no head in my right hand, and no heart. Every one who knows you, consults with you, and is guided by you, Agnes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Every one who knows me, spoils me, I believe,&rdquo; she answered, smiling.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. It's because you are like no one else. You are so good, and so sweet-tempered. You have such a gentle nature, and you are always right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You talk,&rdquo; said Agnes, breaking into a pleasant laugh, as she sat at work, &ldquo;as if I were the late Miss Larkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come! It's not fair to abuse my confidence,&rdquo; I answered, reddening at the recollection of my blue enslaver. &ldquo;But I shall confide in you, just the same, Agnes. I can never grow out of that. Whenever I fall into trouble, or fall in love, I shall always tell you, if you'll let me&mdash;even when I come to fall in love in earnest.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you have always been in earnest!&rdquo; said Agnes, laughing again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! that was as a child, or a school-boy,&rdquo; said I, laughing in my turn, not without being a little shame-faced. &ldquo;Times are altering now, and I suppose I shall be in a terrible state of earnestness one day or other. My wonder is, that you are not in earnest yourself, by this time, Agnes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Agnes laughed again, and shook her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, I know you are not!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;because if you had been, you would have told me. Or at least&rdquo;&mdash;for I saw a faint blush in her face, &ldquo;you would have let me find it out for myself. But there is no one that I know of, who deserves to love <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> Agnes. Some one of nobler character, and more worthy altogether than any one I have ever seen here, must rise up, before I give <hi rend="italics">my</hi> consent. In the time to come, I shall have a wary eye on all admirers; and shall exact a great deal from the successful one, I assure you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We had gone on, so far, in a mixture of confidential jest and earnest, that had long grown naturally out of our familiar relations, begun as mere children. But Agnes, now suddenly lifting up her eyes to mine, and speaking in a different manner, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trotwood, there is something that I want to ask you, and that I may not have another opportunity of asking for a long time, perhaps&mdash;something I would ask, I think, of no one else. Have you observed any gradual alteration in Papa?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="196" id="p196"/>
<p>I had observed it, and had often wondered whether she had too. I must have shown as much, now, in my face; for her eyes were in a moment cast down, and I saw tears in them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tell me what it is,&rdquo; she said, in a low voice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think&mdash;shall I be quite plain, Agnes, liking him so much?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; she said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think he does himself no good by the habit that has increased upon him since I first came here. He is often very nervous&mdash;or I fancy so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is not fancy,&rdquo; said Agnes, shaking her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;His hand trembles, his speech is not plain, and his eyes look wild. I have remarked that at those times, and when he is least like himself, he is most certain to be wanted on some business.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By Uriah,&rdquo; said Agnes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes; and the sense of being unfit for it, or of not having understood it, or of having shown his condition in spite of himself, seems to make him so uneasy, that next day he is worse, and next day worse, and so he becomes jaded and haggard. Do not be alarmed by what I say, Agnes, but in this state I saw him, only the other evening, lay down his head upon his desk, and shed tears like a child.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Her hand passed softly before my lips while I was yet speaking, and in a moment she had met her father at the door of the room, and was hanging on his shoulder. The expression of her face, as they both looked towards me, I felt to be very touching. There was such deep fondness for him, and gratitude to him for all his love and care, in her beautiful look; and there was such a fervent appeal to me to deal tenderly by him, even in my inmost thoughts, and to let no harsh construction find any place against him; she was, at once, so proud of him and devoted to him, yet so compassionate and sorry, and so reliant upon me to be so, too; that nothing she could have said would have expressed more to me, or moved me more.</p>
<p>We were to drink tea at the Doctor's. We went there at the usual hour; and round the study-fireside found the Doctor, and his young wife, and her mother. The Doctor, who made as much of my going away as if I were going to China, received me as an honored guest; and called for a log of wood to be thrown on the fire, that he might see the face of his old pupil reddening in the blaze.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall not see many more new faces in Trotwood's stead, Wickfield,&rdquo; said the Doctor, warming his hands; &ldquo;I am getting lazy, and want ease. I shall relinquish all my young people in another six months, and lead a quieter life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have said so, any time these ten years, Doctor,&rdquo; Mr. Wickfield answered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But now I mean to do it,&rdquo; returned the Doctor. &ldquo;My first master will succeed me&mdash;I am in earnest at last&mdash;so you'll soon have to arrange our contracts, and to bind us firmly to them, like a couple of knaves.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And to take care,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, &ldquo;that you're not imposed on, eh?&mdash;as you certainly would be, in any contract you should make for yourself. Well! I am ready. There are worse tasks than that, in my calling.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall have nothing to think of then,&rdquo; said the Doctor, with a smile, &ldquo;but my Dictionary; and this other contract-bargain&mdash;Annie.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="197" id="p197"/>
<p>As Mr. Wickfield glanced towards her, sitting at the tea-table by Agnes, she seemed to me to avoid his look with such unwonted hesitation and timidity, that his attention became fixed upon her, as if something were suggested to his thoughts.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is a post come in from India, I observe,&rdquo; he said, after a short silence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By-the-by! and letters from Mr. Jack Maldon!&rdquo; said the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Poor dear Jack!&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham, shaking her head. &ldquo;That trying climate!&mdash;like living, they tell me, on a sand-heap, underneath a burning-glass! He looked strong, but he wasn't. My dear Doctor, it was his spirit, not his constitution, that he ventured on so boldly. Annie, my dear, I am sure you must perfectly recollect that your cousin never was strong&mdash;not what can be called <hi rend="italics">robust,</hi> you know,&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham, with emphasis, and looking round upon us generally &ldquo;&mdash;from the time when my daughter and himself were children together, and walking about, arm in arm, the livelong day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Annie, thus addressed, made no reply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do I gather from what you say, ma'am, that Mr. Maldon is ill?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ill!&rdquo; replied the Old Soldier. &ldquo;My dear sir, he is all sorts of things.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Except well?&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Except well, indeed!&rdquo; said the Old Soldier. &ldquo;He has had dreadful strokes of the sun, no doubt, and jungle fevers and agues, and every kind of thing you can mention. As to his liver,&rdquo; said the Old Soldier resignedly, &ldquo;that, of course, he gave up altogether, when he first went out!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does he say all this?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Say? My dear sir,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Markleham, shaking her head and her fan, &ldquo;you little know my poor Jack Maldon when you ask that question. Say? Not he. You might drag him at the heels of four wild horses first.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mama!&rdquo; said Mrs. Strong.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Annie, my dear,&rdquo; returned her mother, &ldquo;once for all, I must really beg that you will not interfere with me, unless it is to confirm what I say. You know as well as I do, that your cousin Maldon would be dragged at the heels of any number of wild horses&mdash;why should I confine myself to four! I <hi rend="italics">won't</hi> confine myself to four&mdash;eight, sixteen, two-and-thirty, rather than say anything calculated to overturn the Doctor's plans.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wickfield's plans,&rdquo; said the Doctor, stroking his face, and looking penitently at his adviser. &ldquo;That is to say, our joint plans for him. I said myself, abroad or at home.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I said,&rdquo; added Mr. Wickfield gravely, &ldquo;abroad. I was the means of sending him abroad. It's my responsibility.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! Responsibility!&rdquo; said the Old Soldier. &ldquo;Every thing was done for the best, my dear Mr. Wickfield; every thing was done for the kindest and best, we know. But if the dear fellow can't live there, he can't live there. And if he can't live there, he'll die there, sooner than he'll over-turn the Doctor's plans. I know him,&rdquo; said the Old Soldier, fanning herself, in a sort of calm prophetic agony, &ldquo;and I know he'll die there, sooner than he'll overturn the Doctor's plans.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="198" id="p198"/>
<p>&ldquo;Well, well, ma'am,&rdquo; said the Doctor, cheerfully, &ldquo;I am not bigoted to my plans, and I can overturn them myself. I can substitute some other plans. If Mr. Jack Maldon comes home on account of ill health, he must not be allowed to go back, and we must endeavour to make some more suitable and fortunate provision for him in this country.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Markleham was so overcome by this generous speech&mdash;which, I need not say, she had not at all expected or led up to&mdash;that she could only tell the Doctor it was like himself, and go several times through that operation of kissing the sticks of her fan, and then tapping his hand with it. After which she gently child her daughter Annie, for not being more demonstrative when such kindnesses were showered, for her sake, on her old playfellow; and entertained us with some particulars concerning other deserving members of her family, whom it was desirable to set on their deserving legs.</p>
<p>All this time, her daughter Annie never once spoke, or lifted up her eyes. All this time, Mr. Wickfield had his glance upon her as she sat by his own daughter's side. It appeared to me that he never thought of being observed by any one; but was so intent upon her, and upon his own thoughts in connexion with her, as to be quite absorbed. He now asked what Mr. Jack Maldon had actually written in reference to himself, and to whom he had written it?</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, here,&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham, taking a letter from the chimney-piece above the Doctor's head, &ldquo;the dear fellow says to the Doctor himself&mdash;where is it? Oh!&mdash;&lsquo;I am sorry to inform you that my health is suffering severely, and that I fear I may be reduced to the necessity of returning home for a time, as the only hope of restoration.&rsquo; That's pretty plain, poor fellow! His only hope of restoration! But Annie's letter is plainer still. Annie, show me that letter again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not now, mama,&rdquo; she pleaded in a low tone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear, you absolutely are, on some subjects, one of the most ridiculous persons in the world,&rdquo; returned her mother, &ldquo;and perhaps the most unnatural to the claims of your own family. We never should have heard of the letter at all, I believe, unless I had asked for it myself. Do you call that confidence, my love, towards Doctor Strong? I am surprised. You ought to know better.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The letter was reluctantly produced; and as I handed it to the old lady, I saw how the unwilling hand from which I took it, trembled.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now let us see,&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham, putting her glass to her eye, &ldquo;where the passage is. &lsquo;The remembrance of old times, my dearest Annie&rsquo;&mdash;and so forth&mdash;it's not there. &lsquo;The amiable old Proctor&rsquo;&mdash;who's he? Dear me, Annie, how illegibly your cousin Maldon writes, and how stupid I am! &lsquo;Doctor,&rsquo; of course. Ah! amiable indeed!&rdquo; Here she left off, to kiss her fan again, and shake it at the Doctor, who was looking at us in a state of placid satisfaction. &ldquo;Now I have found it. &lsquo;<hi rend="italics">You</hi> may not be surprised to hear, Annie&rsquo; &rdquo;&mdash;no, to be sure, knowing that he never was really strong; what did I say just now?&mdash;&lsquo;that I have undergone so much in this distant place, as to have decided to leave it at all hazards; on sick leave, if I can; on total resignation, if that is not to be obtained. What I have endured, and do endure here, is insupportable.&rsquo; And but for the promptitude of that best of creatures,&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham,
<pb n="199" id="p199"/>
telegraphing the Doctor as before, and refolding the letter, &ldquo;it would be insupportable to me to think of.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Wickfield said not one word, though the old lady looked to him as if for his commentary on this intelligence; but sat severely silent, with his eyes fixed on the ground. Long after the subject was dismissed, and other topics occupied us, he remained so; seldom raising his eyes, unless to rest them for a moment, with a thoughtful frown, upon the Doctor, or his wife, or both.</p>
<p>The Doctor was very fond of music. Agnes sang with great sweetness and expression, and so did Mrs. Strong. They sang together, and played duets together, and we had quite a little concert. But I remarked two things: first, that though Annie soon recovered her composure, and was quite herself, there was a blank between her and Mr. Wickfield which separated them wholly from each other; secondly, that Mr. Wickfield seemed to dislike the intimacy between her and Agnes, and to watch it with uneasiness. And now, I must confess, the recollection of what I had seen on that night when Mr. Maldon went away, first began to return upon me with a meaning it had never had, and to trouble me. The innocent beauty of her face was not as innocent to me as it had been; I mistrusted the natural grace and charm of her manner; and when I looked at Agnes by her side, and thought how good and true Agnes was, suspicions arose within me that it was an ill-assorted friendship.</p>
<p>She was so happy in it herself, however, and the other was so happy too, that they made the evening fly away as if it were but an hour. It closed in an incident which I well remember. They were taking leave of each other, and Agnes was going to embrace her and kiss her, when Mr. Wickfield stepped between them, as if by accident, and drew Agnes quickly away. Then I saw, as though all the intervening time had been cancelled, and I were still standing in the doorway on the night of the departure, the expression of that night in the face of Mrs. Strong, as it confronted his.</p>
<p>I cannot say what an impression this made upon me, or how impossible I found it, when I thought of her afterwards, to separate her from this look, and remember her face in its innocent loveliness again. It haunted me when I got home. I seemed to have left the Doctor's roof with a dark cloud lowering on it. The reverence that I had for his grey head, was mingled with commiseration for his faith in those who were treacherous to him, and with resentment against those who injured him. The impending shadow of a great affliction, and a great disgrace that had no distinct form in it yet, fell like a stain upon the quiet place where I had worked and played as a boy, and did it a cruel wrong. I had no pleasure in thinking, any more, of the grave old broad-leaved aloe-trees which remained shut up in themselves a hundred years together, and of the trim smooth grass-plot, and the stone urns, and the Doctor's walk, and the congenial sound of the Cathedral bell hovering above them all. It was as if the tranquil sanctuary of my boyhood had been sacked before my face, and its peace and honor given to the winds.</p>
<p>But morning brought with it my parting from the old house, which Agnes had filled with her influence; and that occupied my mind sufficiently. I should be there again soon, no doubt; I might sleep again&mdash;
<pb n="200" id="p200"/>
perhaps often&mdash;in my old room; but the days of my inhabiting there were gone, and the old time was past. I was heavier at heart when I packed up such of my books and clothes as still remained there to be sent to Dover, than I cared to show to Uriah Heep: who was so officious to help me, that I uncharitably thought him mighty glad that I was going.</p>
<p>I got away from Agnes and her father, somehow, with an indifferent show of being very manly, and took my seat upon the box of the London coach. I was so softened and forgiving, going through the town, that I had half a mind to nod to my old enemy the butcher, and throw him five shillings to drink. But he looked such a very obdurate butcher as he stood scraping the great block in the shop, and moreover, his appearance was so little improved by the loss of a front tooth which I had knocked out, that I thought it best to make no advances.</p>
<p>The main object on my mind, I remember, when we got fairly on the road, was to appear as old as possible to the coachman, and to speak extremely gruff. The latter point I achieved at great personal inconvenience; but I stuck to it, because I felt it was a grown-up sort of thing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are going through, sir?&rdquo; said the coachman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, William,&rdquo; I said, condescendingly (I knew him); &ldquo;I am going to London. I shall go down into Suffolk afterwards.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Shooting, sir?&rdquo; said the coachman.</p>
<p>He knew as well as I did that it was just as likely, at that time of year, I was going down there whaling; but I felt complimented, too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know,&rdquo; I said, pretending to be undecided, &ldquo;whether I shall take a shot or not.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Birds is got wery shy, I'm told,&rdquo; said William.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So I understand,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Suffolk your county, sir?&rdquo; asked William.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; I said, with some importance, &ldquo;Suffolk's my county.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'm told the dumplings is uncommon fine down there,&rdquo; said William.</p>
<p>I was not aware of it myself, but I felt it necessary to uphold the institutions of my county, and to evince a familiarity with them; so I shook my head, as much as to say &ldquo;I believe you!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And the Punches,&rdquo; said William. &ldquo;There's cattle! A Suffolk Punch, when he's a good un, is worth his weight in gold. Did you ever breed any Suffolk Punches yourself, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;N&mdash;no,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;not exactly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here's a gen'lm'n behind me, I'll pound it,&rdquo; said William, &ldquo;as has bred 'em by wholesale.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The gentleman spoken of was a gentleman with a very unpromising squint, and a prominent chin, who had a tall white hat on with a narrow flat brim, and whose close-fitting drab trousers seemed to button all the way up outside his legs from his boots to his hips. His chin was cocked over the coachman's shoulder, so near to me, that his breath quite tickled the back of my head; and as I looked round at him, he leered at the leaders with the eye with which he didn't squint, in a very knowing manner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ain't you?&rdquo; said William.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ain't I what?&rdquo; asked the gentleman behind.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bred them Suffolk Punches by wholesale?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="201" id="p201"/>
<p>&ldquo;I should think so,&rdquo; said the gentleman. &ldquo;There ain't no sort of orse that I ain't bred, and no sort of dorg. Orses and dorgs is some men's fancy. They're wittles and drink to me&mdash;lodging, wife, and children&mdash;reading, writing, and 'rithmetic&mdash;snuff, tobacker, and sleep.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That ain't a sort of man to see sitting behind a coach-box, is it though?&rdquo; said William in my ear, as he handled the reins.</p>
<p>I construed this remark into an indication of a wish that he should have my place, so I blushingly offered to resign it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, if you don't mind, sir,&rdquo; said William, &ldquo;I think it <hi rend="italics">would</hi> be more correct.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have always considered this as the first fall I had in life. When I booked my place at the coach-office, I had had &ldquo;Box Seat&rdquo; written against the entry, and had given the book-keeper half-a-crown. I was got up in a special great coat and shawl, expressly to do honor to that distinguished eminence; had glorified myself upon it a good deal; and had felt that I was a credit to the coach. And here, in the very first stage, I was supplanted by a shabby man with a squint, who had no other merit than smelling like a livery-stables, and being able to walk across me, more like a fly than a human being, while the horses were at a canter!</p>
<p>A distrust of myself, which has often beset me in life on small occasions, when it would have been better away, was assuredly not stopped in its growth by this little incident outside the Canterbury coach. It was in vain to take refuge in gruffness of speech. I spoke from the pit of my stomach for the rest of the journey, but I felt completely extinguished, and dreadfully young.</p>
<p>It was curious and interesting, nevertheless, to be sitting up there, behind four horses: well educated, well dressed, and with plenty of money in my pocket: and to look out for the places where I had slept on my weary journey. I had abundant occupation for my thoughts, in every conspicuous landmark on the road. When I looked down at the trampers whom we passed, and saw that well-remembered style of face turned up, I felt as if the tinker's blackened hand were in the bosom of my shirt again. When we clattered through the narrow street of Chatham, and I caught a glimpse, in passing, of the lane where the old monster lived who had bought my jacket, I stretched my neck eagerly to look for the place where I had sat, in the sun and in the shade, waiting for my money. When we came, at last, within a stage of London, and passed the veritable Salem House where Mr. Creakle had laid about him with a heavy hand, I would have given all I had, for lawful permission to get down and thrash him, and let all the boys out like so many caged sparrows.</p>
<p>We went to the Golden Cross at Charing Cross, then a mouldy sort of establishment in a close neighbourhood. A waiter showed me into the coffee-room; and a chambermaid introduced me to my small bedchamber, which smelt like a hackney-coach, and was shut up like a family vault. I was still painfully conscious of my youth, for nobody stood in any awe of me at all: the chambermaid being utterly indifferent to my opinions on any subject, and the waiter being familiar with me, and offering advice to my inexperience.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well now,&rdquo; said the waiter, in a tone of confidence, &ldquo;what would you like for dinner? Young gentlemen likes poultry in general, have a fowl!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="202" id="p202"/>
<p>I told him, as majestically as I could, that I wasn't in the humour for a fowl.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ain't you!&rdquo; said the waiter. &ldquo;Young gentlemen is generally tired of beef and mutton, have a weal cutlet!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I assented to this proposal, in default of being able to suggest anything else.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you care for taters?&rdquo; said the waiter, with an insinuating smile, and his head on one side. &ldquo;Young gentlemen generally has been overdosed with taters.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I commanded him, in my deepest voice, to order a veal cutlet and potatoes, and all things fitting; and to inquire at the bar if there were any letters for Trotwood Copperfield, Esquire&mdash;which I knew there were not, and couldn't be, but thought it manly to appear to expect.</p>
<p>He soon came back to say that there were none (at which I was much surprised), and began to lay the cloth for my dinner in a box by the fire. While he was so engaged, he asked me what I would take with it; and on my replying &ldquo;Half a pint of sherry,&rdquo; thought it a favourable opportunity, I am afraid, to extract that measure of wine from the stale leavings at the bottoms of several small decanters. I am of this opinion, because, while I was reading the newspaper, I observed him behind a low wooden partition, which was his private apartment, very busy pouring out of a number of those vessels into one, like a chemist and druggist making up a prescription. When the wine came, too, I thought it flat; and it certainly had more English crumbs in it, than were to be expected in a foreign wine in anything like a pure state; but I was bashful enough to drink it, and say nothing.</p>
<p>Being, then, in a pleasant frame of mind (from which I infer that poisoning is not always disagreeable in some stages of the process), I resolved to go to the play. It was Covent Garden Theatre that I chose; and there, from the back of a centre box, I saw Julius C&aelig;sar and the new Pantomime. To have all those noble Romans alive before me, and walking in and out for my entertainment, instead of being the stern task-masters they had been at school, was a most novel and delightful effect. But the mingled reality and mystery of the whole show, the influence upon me of the poetry, the lights, the music, the company, the smooth stupendous changes of glittering and brilliant scenery, were so dazzling, and opened up such illimitable regions of delight, that when I came out into the rainy street, at twelve o'clock at night, I felt as if I had come from the clouds, where I had been leading a romantic life for ages, to a bawling, splashing, link-lighted, umbrella-struggling, hackney-coachjostling, patten-clinking, muddy, miserable world.</p>
<p>I had emerged by another door, and stood in the street for a little while, as if I really were a stranger upon earth: but the unceremonious pushing and hustling that I received, soon recalled me to myself, and put me in the road back to the hotel; whither I went, revolving the glorious vision all the way; and where, after some porter and oysters, I sat revolving it still, at past one o'clock, with my eyes on the coffee-room fire.</p>
<p>I was so filled with the play, and with the past&mdash;for it was, in a manner, like a shining transparency, through which I saw my earlier life moving along&mdash;that I don't know when the figure of a handsome well-formed young
<pb n="203" id="p203"/>
man, dressed with a tasteful easy negligence which I have reason to remember very well, became a real presence to me. But I recollect being conscious of his company without having noticed his coming in&mdash;and my still sitting, musing, over the coffee-room fire.</p>
<p>At last I rose to go to bed, much to the relief of the sleepy waiter, who had got the fidgets in his legs, and was twisting them, and hitting them, and putting them through all kinds of contortions in his small pantry. In going towards the door, I passed the person who had come in, and saw him plainly. I turned directly, came back, and looked again. He did not know me, but I knew him in a moment.</p>
<p>At another time I might have wanted the confidence or the decision to speak to him, and might have put it off until next day, and might have lost him. But, in the then condition of my mind, where the play was still running high, his former protection of me appeared so deserving of my gratitude, and my old love for him overflowed my breast so freshly and spontaneously, that I went up to him at once, with a fast-beating heart, and said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Steerforth! won't you speak to me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He looked at me&mdash;just as he used to look, sometimes&mdash;but I saw no recognition in his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You don't remember me, I am afraid,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My God!&rdquo; he suddenly exclaimed. &ldquo;It's little Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I grasped him by both hands, and could not let them go. But for very shame, and the fear that it might displease him, I could have held him round the neck and cried.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never, never, never was so glad! My dear Steerforth, I am so overjoyed to see you!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I am rejoiced to see you, too!&rdquo; he said, shaking my hands heartily. &ldquo;Why, Copperfield, old boy, don't be overpowered!&rdquo; And yet he was glad, too, I thought, to see how the delight I had in meeting him affected me.</p>
<p>I brushed away the tears that my utmost resolution had not been able to keep back, and I made a clumsy laugh of it, and we sat down together, side by side.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, how do you come to be here?&rdquo; said Steerforth, clapping me on the shoulder.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I came here by the Canterbury coach, to-day. I have been adopted by an aunt down in that part of the country, and have just finished my education there. How do <hi rend="italics">you</hi> come to be here, Steerforth?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, I am what they call an Oxford man,&rdquo; he returned; &ldquo;that is to say, I get bored to death down there, periodically&mdash;and I am on my way now to my mother's. You're a devilish amiable-looking fellow, Copperfield. Just what you used to be, now I look at you! Not altered in the least!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I knew <hi rend="italics">you</hi> immediately,&rdquo; I said; &ldquo;but you are more easily remembered.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He laughed as he ran his hand through the clustering curls of his hair, and said gaily:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I am on an expedition of duty. My mother lives a little way out of town; and the roads being in a beastly condition, and our house
<pb n="204" id="p204"/>
tedious enough, I remained here to-night instead of going on. I have not been in town half-a-dozen hours, and those I have been dozing and grumbling away at the play.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been at the play, too,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;At Covent Garden. What a delightful and magnificent entertainment, Steerforth!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Steerforth laughed heartily.</p>
<p>&mdash;&ldquo;My dear young Davy,&rdquo; he said, clapping me on the shoulder again, &ldquo;you are a very Daisy. The daisy of the field, at sunrise, is not fresher than you are! I have been at Covent Garden, too, and there never was a more miserable business.&mdash;Holloa, you sir!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was addressed to the waiter, who had been very attentive to our recognition, at a distance, and now came forward deferentially.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where have you put my friend, Mr. Copperfield?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Beg your pardon, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where does he sleep? What's his number? You know what I mean,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir,&rdquo; said the waiter, with an apologetic air. &ldquo;Mr. Copperfield is at present in forty-four, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what the devil do you mean,&rdquo; retorted Steerforth, &ldquo;by putting Mr. Copperfield into a little loft over a stable?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you see we wasn't aware, sir,&rdquo; returned the waiter, still apologetically, &ldquo;as Mr. Copperfield was anyways particular. We can give Mr. Copperfield seventy-two, sir, if it would be preferred. Next you, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course it would be preferred,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;And do it at once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The waiter immediately withdrew to make the exchange. Steerforth, very much amused at my having been put into forty-four, laughed again, and clapped me on the shoulder again, and invited me to breakfast with him next morning at ten o'clock&mdash;an invitation I was only too proud and happy to accept. It being now pretty late, we took our candles and went up-stairs, where we parted with friendly heartiness at his door, and where I found my new room a great improvement on my old one, it not being at all musty, and having an immense four-post bedstead in it, which was quite a little landed estate. Here, among pillows enough for six, I soon fell asleep in a blissful condition, and dreamed of ancient Rome, Steerforth, and friendship, until the early morning coaches, rumbling out of the archway underneath, made me dream of thunder and the gods.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="205" id="p205"/>
<head>CHAPTER XX. <lb/> STEERFORTH'S HOME.</head>
<p>WHEN the chambermaid tapped at my door at eight o'clock, and informed me that my shaving-water was outside, I felt severely the having no occasion for it, and blushed in my bed. The suspicion that she laughed too, when she said it, preyed upon my mind all the time I was dressing; and gave me, I was conscious, a sneaking and guilty air when I passed her on the staircase, as I was going down to breakfast. I was so sensitively aware, indeed, of being younger than I could have wished, that for some time I could not make up my mind to pass her at all, under the ignoble circumstances of the case; but, hearing her there with a broom, stood peeping out of window at King Charles on horseback, surrounded by a maze of hackney-coaches and looking anything but regal in a drizzling rain and a dark-brown fog, until I was admonished by the waiter that the gentleman was waiting for me.</p>
<p>It was not in the coffee-room that I found Steerforth expecting me, but in a snug private apartment, red-curtained and Turkey-carpeted, where the fire burnt bright, and a fine hot breakfast was set forth on a table covered with a clean cloth; and a cheerful miniature of the room, the fire, the breakfast, Steerforth, and all, was shining in the little round mirror over the sideboard. I was rather bashful at first, Steerforth being so self-possessed, and elegant, and superior to me in all respects (age included); but his easy patronage soon put that to rights, and made me quite at home. I could not enough admire the change he had wrought in the Golden Cross; or compare the dull forlorn state I had held yesterday, with this morning's comfort and this morning's entertainment. As to the waiter's familiarity, it was quenched as if it had never been. He attended on us, as I may say, in sackcloth and ashes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, Copperfield,&rdquo; said Steerforth, when we were alone, &ldquo;I should like to hear what you are doing, and where you are going, and all about you. I feel as if you were my property.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Glowing with pleasure to find that he had still this interest in me, I told him how my aunt had proposed the little expedition that I had before me, and whither it tended.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As you are in no hurry, then,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;come home with me to Highgate, and stay a day or two. You will be pleased with my mother&mdash;she is a little vain and prosy about me, but that you can forgive her&mdash;and she will be pleased with you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should like to be as sure of that, as you are kind enough to say you are,&rdquo; I answered, smiling.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;every one who likes me, has a claim on her that is sure to be acknowledged.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then I think I shall be a favorite,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good!&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Come and prove it. We will go and see
<pb n="206" id="p206"/>
the lions for an hour or two&mdash;it's something to have a fresh fellow like you to show them to, Copperfield&mdash;and then we'll journey out to High-gate by the coach.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I could hardly believe but that I was in a dream, and that I should wake presently in number forty-four, to the solitary box in the coffeeroom and the familiar waiter again. After I had written to my aunt and told her of my fortunate meeting with my admired old school-fellow, and my acceptance of his invitation, we went out in a hackney-chariot, and saw a Panorama and some other sights, and took a walk through the Museum, where I could not help observing how much Steerforth knew, on an infinite variety of subjects, and of how little account he seemed to make his knowledge.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You'll take a high degree at college, Steerforth,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;if you have not done so already; and they will have good reason to be proud of you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> take a degree!&rdquo; cried Steerforth. &ldquo;Not I! my dear Daisy&mdash;will you mind my calling you Daisy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a good fellow! My dear Daisy,&rdquo; said Steerforth, laughing, &ldquo;I have not the least desire or intention to distinguish myself in that way. I have done quite sufficient for my purpose. I find that I am heavy company enough for myself, as I am.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But the fame&mdash;&rdquo; I was beginning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You romantic Daisy!&rdquo; said Steerforth, laughing still more heartily; &ldquo;why should I trouble myself, that a parcel of heavy-headed fellows may gape and hold up their hands? Let them do it at some other man. There's fame for him, and he's welcome to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was abashed at having made so great a mistake, and was glad to change the subject. Fortunately it was not difficult to do, for Steerforth could always pass from one subject to another with a carelessness and lightness that were his own.</p>
<p>Lunch succeeded to our sight-seeing, and the short winter day wore away so fast, that it was dusk when the stage-coach stopped with us at an old brick house at Highgate on the summit of the hill. An elderly lady, though not very far advanced in years, with a proud carriage and a handsome face, was in the doorway as we alighted; and greeting Steerforth as &ldquo;My dearest James,&rdquo; folded him in her arms. To this lady he presented me as his mother, and she gave me a stately welcome.</p>
<p>It was a genteel old-fashioned house, very quiet and orderly. From the windows of my room I saw all London lying in the distance like a great vapour, with here and there some lights twinkling through it. I had only time, in dressing, to glance at the solid furniture, the framed pieces of work (done, I supposed, by Steerforth's mother when she was a girl), and some pictures in crayons of ladies with powdered hair and boddices, coming and going on the walls, as the newly-kindled fire crackled and sputtered, when I was called to dinner.</p>
<p>There was a second lady in the dining-room, of a slight short figure, dark, and not agreeable to look at, but with some appearance of good looks too, who attracted my attention: perhaps because I had not expected to see her; perhaps because I found myself sitting opposite to her; perhaps
<pb n="207" id="p207"/>
because of something really remarkable in her. She had black hair and eager black eyes, and was thin, and had a scar upon her lip. It was an old scar&mdash;I should rather call it, seam, for it was not discolored, and had healed years ago&mdash;which had once cut through her mouth, downward towards the chin, but was now barely visible across the table, except above and on her upper lip, the shape of which it had altered. I concluded in my own mind that she was about thirty years of age, and that she wished to be married. She was a little dilapidated&mdash;like a house&mdash;with having been so long to let; yet had, as I have said, an appearance of good looks. Her thinness seemed to be the effect of some wasting fire within her, which found a vent in her gaunt eyes.</p>
<p>She was introduced as Miss Dartle, and both Steerforth and his mother called her Rosa. I found that she lived there, and had been for a long time Mrs. Steerforth's companion. It appeared to me that she never said anything she wanted to say, outright; but hinted it, and made a great deal more of it by this practice. For example, when Mrs. Steerforth observed, more in jest than earnest, that she feared her son led but a wild life at college, Miss Dartle put in thus:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, really? You know how ignorant I am, and that I only ask for information, but isn't it always so? I thought that kind of life was on all hands understood to be&mdash;eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is education for a very grave profession, if you mean that, Rosa,&rdquo; Mrs. Steerforth answered with some coldness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! Yes! That's very true,&rdquo; returned Miss Dartle. &ldquo;But isn't it, though?&mdash;I want to be put right if I am wrong&mdash;isn't it really?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really what?&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! You mean it's <hi rend="italics">not!</hi>&rdquo; returned Miss Dartle. &ldquo;Well, I'm very glad to hear it! Now, I know what to do. That's the advantage of asking. I shall never allow people to talk before me about wastefulness and profligacy, and so forth, in connection with that life, any more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And you will be right,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth. &ldquo;My son's tutor is a conscientious gentleman; and if I had not implicit reliance on my son, I should have reliance on him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Should you?&rdquo; said Miss Dartle. &ldquo;Dear me! Conscientious, is he? Really conscientious, now?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I am convinced of it,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How very nice!&rdquo; exclaimed Miss Dartle. &ldquo;What a comfort! Really conscientious? Then he's not&mdash;but of course he can't be, if he's really conscientious. Well, I shall be quite happy in my opinion of him, from this time. You can't think how it elevates him in my opinion, to know for certain that he's really conscientious!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Her own views of every question, and her correction of everything that was said to which she was opposed, Miss Dartle insinuated in the same way: sometimes, I could not conceal from myself, with great power, though in contradiction even of Steerforth. An instance happened before dinner was done. Mrs. Steerforth speaking to me about my intention of going down into Suffolk, I said at hazard how glad I should be, if Steerforth would only go there with me; and explaining to him that I was going to see my old nurse, and Mr. Peggotty's family, I reminded him of the boatman whom he had seen at school.</p>
<pb n="208" id="p208"/>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! That bluff fellow!&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;He had a son with him, hadn't he?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. That was his nephew,&rdquo; I replied; &ldquo;whom he adopted, though, as a son. He has a very pretty little niece too, whom he adopted as a daughter. In short, his house (or rather his boat, for he lives in one, on dry land) is full of people who are objects of his generosity and kindness. You would be delighted to see that household.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Should I?&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Well, I think I should. I must see what can be done. It would be worth a journey&mdash;not to mention the pleasure of a journey with you, Daisy,&mdash;to see that sort of people together, and to make one of 'em.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My heart leaped with a new hope of pleasure. But it was in reference to the tone in which he had spoken of &ldquo;that sort of people,&rdquo; that Miss Dartle, whose sparkling eyes had been watchful of us, now broke in again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, but, really? Do tell me. Are they, though?&rdquo; she said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are they what? And are who what?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That sort of people.&mdash;Are they really animals and clods, and beings of another order? I want to know <hi rend="italics">so</hi> much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, there's a pretty wide separation between them and us,&rdquo; said Steerforth, with indifference. &ldquo;They are not to be expected to be as sensitive as we are. Their delicacy is not to be shocked, or hurt very easily. They are wonderfully virtuous, I dare say&mdash;some people contend for that, at least; and I am sure I don't want to contradict them&mdash;but they have not very fine natures, and they may be thankful that, like their coarse rough skins, they are not easily wounded.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really!&rdquo; said Miss Dartle. &ldquo;Well, I don't know, now, when I have been better pleased than to hear that. It's so consoling! It's such a delight to know that, when they suffer, they don't feel! Sometimes I have been quite uneasy for that sort of people; but now I shall just dismiss the idea of them, altogether. Live and learn. I had my doubts, I confess, but now they're cleared up. I didn't know, and now I do know; and that shows the advantage of asking&mdash;don't it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I believed that Steerforth had said what he had, in jest, or to draw Miss Dartle out; and I expected him to say as much when she was gone, and we two were sitting before the fire. But he merely asked me what I thought of her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is very clever, is she not?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Clever! She brings everything to a grindstone,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;and sharpens it, as she has sharpened her own face and figure these years past. She has worn herself away by constant sharpening. She is all edge.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a remarkable scar that is upon her lip!&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>Steerforth's face fell, and he paused a moment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, the fact is,&rdquo; he returned, &ldquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> did that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By an unfortunate accident!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. I was a young boy, and she exasperated me, and I threw a hammer at her. A promising young angel I must have been!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was deeply sorry to have touched on such a painful theme, but that was useless now.</p>
<pb n="209" id="p209"/>
<p>&ldquo;She has borne the mark ever since, as you see,&rdquo; said Steerforth; &ldquo;and she'll bear it to her grave, if she ever rests in one&mdash;though I can hardly believe she will ever rest anywhere. She was the motherless child of a sort of cousin of my father's. He died one day. My mother, who was then a widow, brought her here to be company to her. She has a couple of thousand pounds of her own, and saves the interest of it every year, to add to the principal. There's the history of Miss Rosa Dartle for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I have no doubt she loves you like a brother?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Humph!&rdquo; retorted Steerforth, looking at the fire. &ldquo;Some brothers are not loved over much; and some love&mdash;but help yourself, Copperfield! We'll drink the daisies of the field, in compliment to you; and the lilies of the valley that toil not, neither do they spin, in compliment to me&mdash;the more shame for me!&rdquo; A moody smile that had overspread his features cleared off as he said this merrily, and he was his own frank, winning self again.</p>
<p>I could not help glancing at the scar with a painful interest when we went in to tea. It was not long before I observed that it was the most susceptible part of her face, and that, when she turned pale, that mark altered first, and became a dull, lead-colored streak, lengthening out to its full extent, like a mark in invisible ink brought to the fire. There was a little altercation between her and Steerforth about a cast of the dice at backgammon&mdash;when I thought her, for one moment, in a storm of rage; and then I saw it start forth like the old writing on the wall.</p>
<p>It was no matter of wonder to me to find Mrs. Steerforth devoted to her son. She seemed to be able to speak or think about nothing else. She showed me his picture as an infant, in a locket, with some of his baby-hair in it; she showed me his picture as he had been when I first knew him; and she wore at her breast his picture as he was now. All the letters he had ever written to her, she kept in a cabinet near her own chair by the fire; and she would have read me some of them, and I should have been very glad to hear them too, if he had not interposed, and coaxed her out of the design.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was at Mr. Creakle's, my son tells me, that you first became acquainted,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, as she and I were talking at one table, while they played backgammon at another. &ldquo;Indeed, I recollect his speaking, at that time, of a pupil younger than himself who had taken his fancy there; but your name, as you may suppose, has not lived in my memory.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was very generous and noble to me in those days, I assure you, ma'am,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;and I stood in need of such a friend. I should have been quite crushed without him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is always generous and noble,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, proudly.</p>
<p>I subscribed to this with all my heart, God knows. She knew I did; for the stateliness of her manner already abated towards me, except when she spoke in praise of him, and then her air was always lofty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was not a fit school generally for my son,&rdquo; said she; &ldquo;far from it; but there were particular circumstances to be considered at the time, of more importance even than that selection. My son's high spirit made it desirable that he should be placed with some man who felt its superiority, and would be content to bow himself before it; and we found such a man there.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="210" id="p210"/>
<p>I knew that, knowing the fellow. And yet I did not despise him the more for it, but thought it a redeeming quality in him&mdash;if he could be allowed any grace for not resisting one so irresistible as Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My son's great capacity was tempted on, there, by a feeling of voluntary emulation and conscious pride,&rdquo; the fond lady went on to say. &ldquo;He would have risen against all constraint; but he found himself the monarch of the place, and he haughtily determined to be worthy of his station. It was like himself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I echoed, with all my heart and soul, that it was like himself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So my son took, of his own will, and on no compulsion, to the course in which he can always, when it is his pleasure, outstrip every competitor,&rdquo; she pursued. &ldquo;My son informs me, Mr. Copperfield, that you were quite devoted to him, and that when you met yesterday you made yourself known to him with tears of joy. I should be an affected woman if I made any pretence of being surprised by my son's inspiring such emotions; but I cannot be indifferent to any one who is so sensible of his merit, and I am very glad to see you here, and can assure you that he feels an unusual friendship for you, and that you may rely on his protection.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Dartle plyed backgammon as eagerly as she did everything else. If I had seen her, first, at the board, I should have fancied that her figure had got thin, and her eyes had got large, over that pursuit, and no other in the world. But I am very much mistaken if she missed a word of this, or lost a look of mine as I received it with the utmost pleasure, and, honored by Mrs. Steerforth's confidence, felt older than I had done since I left Canterbury.</p>
<p>When the evening was pretty far spent, and a tray of glasses and decanters came in, Steerforth promised, over the fire, that he would seriously think of going down into the country with me. There was no hurry, he said; a week hence would do; and his mother hospitably said the same. While we were talking, he more than once called me Daisy; which brought Miss Dartle out again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But really, Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; she asked, &ldquo;is it a nick-name? And why does he give it you? Is it&mdash;eh?&mdash;because he thinks you young and innocent? I am so stupid in these things.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I colored in replying that I believed it was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said Miss Dartle. &ldquo;Now I am glad to know that! I ask for information, and I am glad to know it. He thinks you young and innocent; and so you are his friend. Well, that's quite delightful!&rdquo;</p>
<p>She went to bed soon after this, and Mrs. Steerforth retired too. Steerforth and I, after lingering for half an hour over the fire, talking about Traddles and all the rest of them at old Salem House, went up-stairs together. Steerforth's room was next to mine, and I went in to look at it. It was a picture of comfort, full of easy chairs, cushions and footstools, worked by his mother's hand, and with no sort of thing omitted that could help to render it complete. Finally, her handsome features looked down on her darling from a portrait on the wall, as if it were even something to her that her likeness should watch him while he slept.</p>
<p>I found the fire burning clear enough in my room by this time, and the curtains drawn before the windows and round the bed, giving it a very snug appearance. I sat down in a great chair upon the hearth to meditate on my happiness; and had enjoyed the contemplation of it for
<pb n="211" id="p211"/>
some time, when I found a likeness of Miss Dartle looking eagerly at me from above the chimney-piece.</p>
<p>It was a startling likeness, and necessarily had a startling look. The painter hadn't made the scar, but <hi rend="italics">I</hi> made it; and there it was, coming and going: now confined to the upper lip as I had seen it at dinner, and now showing the whole extent of the wound inflicted by the hammer, as I had seen it when she was passionate.</p>
<p>I wondered peevishly why they couldn't put her anywhere else instead of quartering her on me. To get rid of her, I undressed quickly, extinguished my light, and went to bed. But, as I fell asleep, I could not forget that she was still there looking, &ldquo;Is it really, though? I want to know;&rdquo; and when I awoke in the night, I found that I was uneasily asking all sorts of people in my dreams whether it really was or not&mdash;without knowing what I meant.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXI. <lb/> LITTLE EM'LY.</head>
<p>THERE was a servant in that house, a man who, I understood, was usually with Steerforth, and had come into his service at the University, who was in appearance a pattern of respectability. I believe there never existed in his station a more respectable-looking man. He was taciturn, soft-footed, very quiet in his manner, deferential, observant, always at hand when wanted, and never near when not wanted; but his great claim to consideration was his respectability. He had not a pliant face, he had rather a stiff neck, rather a tight smooth head with short hair clinging to it at the sides, a soft way of speaking, with a peculiar habit of whispering the letter S so distinctly, that he seemed to use it oftener than any other man; but every peculiarity that he had he made respectable. If his nose had been upside-down, he would have made that respectable. He surrounded himself with an atmosphere of respectability, and walked secure in it. It would have been next to impossible to suspect him of anything wrong, he was so thoroughly respectable. Nobody could have thought of putting him in a livery, he was so highly respectable. To have imposed any derogatory work upon him, would have been to inflict a wanton insult on the feelings of a most respectable man. And of this, I noticed the women-servants in the household were so intuitively conscious, that they always did such work themselves, and generally while he read the paper by the pantry fire.</p>
<p>Such a self-contained man I never saw. But in that quality, as in every other he possessed, he only seemed to be the more respectable. Even the fact that no one knew his Christian name, seemed to form a part of his respectability. Nothing could be objected against his surname Littimer, by which he was known. Peter might have been hanged, or Tom transported; but Littimer was perfectly respectable.</p>
<pb n="212" id="p212"/>
<p>It was occasioned, I suppose, by the reverend nature of respectability in the abstract, but I felt particularly young in this man's presence. How old he was himself I could not guess&mdash;and that again went to his credit on the same score; for in the calmness of respectability he might have numbered fifty years as well as thirty.</p>
<p>Littimer was in my room in the morning before I was up, to bring me that reproachful shaving-water, and to put out my clothes. When I undrew the curtains and looked out of bed, I saw him, in an equable temperature of respectability, unaffected by the east wind of January, and not even breathing frostily, standing my boots right and left in the first dancing position, and blowing specks of dust off my coat as he laid it down like a baby.</p>
<p>I gave him good morning, and asked him what o'clock it was. He took out of his pocket the most respectable hunting-watch I ever saw, and preventing the spring with his thumb from opening far, looked in at the face as if he were consulting an oracular oyster, shut it up again, and said, if I pleased, it was halfpast eight.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Steerforth will be glad to hear how you have rested, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;very well indeed. Is Mr. Steerforth quite well?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, sir, Mr. Steerforth is tolerably well.&rdquo; Another of his characteristics,&mdash;no use of superlatives. A cool calm medium always.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is there anything more I can have the honor of doing for you, sir? The warning-bell will ring at nine; the family take breakfast at halfpast nine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing, I thank you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thank <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> sir, if you please;&rdquo; and with that, and with a little inclination of his head when he passed the bedside, as an apology for correcting me, he went out, shutting the door as delicately as if I had just fallen into a sweet sleep on which my life depended.</p>
<p>Every morning we held exactly this conversation: never any more, and never any less: and yet, invariably, however far I might have been lifted out of myself over-night, and advanced towards maturer years, by Steerforth's companionship, or Mrs. Steerforth's confidence, or Miss Dartle's conversation, in the presence of this most respectable man I became, as our smaller poets sing, &ldquo;a boy again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He got horses for us; and Steerforth, who knew every thing, gave me lessons in riding. He provided foils for us, and Steerforth gave me lessons in fencing&mdash;gloves, and I began, of the same master, to improve in boxing. It gave me no manner of concern that Steerforth should find me a novice in these sciences, but I never could bear to show my want of skill before the respectable Littimer. I had no reason to believe that Littimer understood such arts himself; he never led me to suppose anything of the kind, by so much as the vibration of one of his respectable eyelashes; yet whenever he was by, while we were practising, I felt myself the greenest and most inexperienced of mortals.</p>
<p>I am particular about this man, because he made a particular effect on me at that time, and because of what took place thereafter.</p>
<p>The week passed away in a most delightful manner. It passed rapidly, as may be supposed, to one entranced as I was; and yet it gave me so many occasions for knowing Steerforth better, and admiring him more in a thousand respects, that at its close I seemed to have been with him for
<pb n="213" id="p213"/>
a much longer time. A dashing way he had of treating me like a plaything, was more agreeable to me than any behaviour he could have adopted. It reminded me of our old acquaintance; it seemed the natural sequel of it; it showed me that he was unchanged; it relieved me of any uneasiness I might have felt, in comparing my merits with his, and measuring my claims upon his friendship by any equal standard; above all, it was a familiar, unrestrained, affectionate demeanor that he used towards no one else. As he had treated me at school differently from all the rest, I joyfully believed that he treated me in life unlike any other friend he had. I believed that I was nearer to his heart than any other friend, and my own heart warmed with attachment to him.</p>
<p>He made up his mind to go with me into the country, and the day arrived for our departure. He had been doubtful at first whether to take Littimer or not, but decided to leave him at home. The respectable creature, satisfied with his lot whatever it was, arranged our portmanteaus on the little carriage that was to take us into London, as if they were intended to defy the shocks of ages; and received my modestly proffered donation with perfect tranquillity.</p>
<p>We bade adieu to Mrs. Steerforth and Miss Dartle, with many thanks on my part, and much kindness on the devoted mother's. The last thing I saw was Littimer's unruffled eye; fraught, as I fancied, with the silent conviction that I was very young indeed.</p>
<p>What I felt, in returning so auspiciously to the old familiar places, I shall not endeavour to describe. We went down by the Mail. I was so concerned, I recollect, even for the honor of Yarmouth, that when Steerforth said, as we drove through its dark streets to the inn, that, as well as he could make out, it was a good, queer, out-of-the-way kind of hole, I was highly pleased. We went to bed on our arrival (I observed a pair of dirty shoes and gaiters in connexion with my old friend the Dolphin as we passed that door), and breakfasted late in the morning. Steerforth, who was in great spirits, had been strolling about the beach before I was up, and had made acquaintance, he said, with half the boatmen in the place. Moreover he had seen, in the distance, what he was sure must be the identical house of Mr. Peggotty, with smoke coming out of the chimney; and had had a great mind, he told me, to walk in and swear he was myself grown out of knowledge.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When do you propose to introduce me there, Daisy?&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;I am at your disposal. Make your own arrangements.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I was thinking that this evening would be a good time, Steerforth, when they are all sitting round the fire. I should like you to see it when it's snug, it's such a curious place.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So be it!&rdquo; returned Steerforth. &ldquo;This evening.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall not give them any notice that we are here, you know,&rdquo; said I, delighted. &ldquo;We must take them by surprise.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, of course! It's no fun,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;unless we take them by surprise. Let us see the natives in their aboriginal condition.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Though they <hi rend="italics">are</hi> that sort of people that you mentioned,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aha! What! you recollect my skirmishes with Rosa, do you?&rdquo; he exclaimed with a quick look. &ldquo;Confound the girl, I am half afraid of her. She's like a goblin to me. But never mind her. Now what are you going to do? You are going to see your nurse, I suppose?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="214" id="p214"/>
<p>&ldquo;Why, yes,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;I must see Peggotty first of all.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; replied Steerforth, looking at his watch. &ldquo;Suppose I deliver you up to be cried over for a couple of hours. Is that long enough?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I answered, laughing, that I thought we might get through it in that time, but that he must come also; for he would find that his renown had preceded him, and that he was almost as great a personage as I was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll come anywhere you like,&rdquo; said Steerforth, &ldquo;or do anything you like. Tell me where to come to; and in two hours I'll produce myself in any state you please, sentimental or comical.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I gave him minute directions for finding the residence of Mr. Barkis, carrier to Blunderstone and elsewhere, and, on this understanding, went out alone. There was a sharp bracing air; the ground was dry; the sea was crisp and clear; the sun was diffusing abundance of light, if not much warmth; and everything was fresh and lively. I was so fresh and lively myself, in the pleasure of being there, that I could have stopped the people in the streets and shaken hands with them.</p>
<p>The streets looked small, of course. The streets that we have only seen as children, always do, I believe, when we go back to them. But I had forgotten nothing in them, and found nothing changed, until I came to Mr. Omer's shop. OMER AND JORAM was now written up, where OMER used to be; but the inscription, DRAPER, TAILOR, HABERDASHER, FUNERAL FURNISHER, &amp;c., remained as it was.</p>
<p>My footsteps seemed to tend so naturally to the shop-door, after I had read these words from over the way, that I went across the road and looked in. There was a pretty woman at the back of the shop, dancing a little child in her arms, while another little fellow clung to her apron. I had no difficulty in recognising either Minnie or Minnie's children. The glass-door of the parlor was not open; but in the workshop across the yard I could faintly hear the old tune playing, as if it had never left off.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Mr. Omer at home?&rdquo; said I, entering. &ldquo;I should like to see him, for a moment, if he is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes, sir, he is at home,&rdquo; said Minnie; &ldquo;this weather don't suit his asthma out of doors. Joe, call your grandfather!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The little fellow, who was holding her apron, gave such a lusty shout, that the sound of it made him bashful, and he buried his face in her skirts, to her great admiration. I heard a heavy puffing and blowing coming towards us, and soon Mr. Omer, shorter-winded than of yore, but not much older-looking, stood before me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Servant, sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;What can I do for you, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You can shake hands with me, Mr. Omer, if you please,&rdquo; said I, putting out my own. &ldquo;You were very good-natured to me once, when I am afraid I didn't show that I thought so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Was I though?&rdquo; returned the old man. &ldquo;I'm glad to hear it, but I don't remember when. Are you sure it was me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think my memory has got as short as my breath,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, looking at me and shaking his head; &ldquo;for I don't remember you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you remember your coming to the coach to meet me, and my having breakfast here, and our riding out to Blunderstone together: you, and I, and Mrs. Joram, and Mr. Joram too&mdash;who wasn't her husband then?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="215" id="p215"/>
<p>&ldquo;Why, Lord bless my soul!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Omer, after being thrown by his surprise into a fit of coughing, &ldquo;you don't say so! Minnie, my dear, you recollect? Dear me, yes&mdash;the party was a lady, I think?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My mother,&rdquo; I rejoined.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To&mdash;be&mdash;sure,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, touching my waistcoat with his forefinger, &ldquo;and there was a little child too! There was two parties. The little party was laid along with the other party. Over at Blunderstone it was, of course. Dear me! And how have you been since?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Very well, I thanked him, as I hoped he had been too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! nothing to grumble at, you know,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;I find my breath gets short, but it seldom gets longer as a man gets older. I take it as it comes, and make the most of it. That's the best way, ain't it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer coughed again, in consequence of laughing, and was assisted out of his fit by his daughter, who now stood close beside us, dancing her smallest child on the counter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Yes, to be sure. Two parties! Why, in that very ride, if you'll believe me, the day was named for my Minnie to marry Joram. &lsquo;Do name it, sir,&rsquo; says Joram. &lsquo;Yes, do, father,&rsquo; says Minnie. And now he's come into the business. And look here! The youngest!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Minnie laughed, and stroked her banded hair upon her temples, as her father put one of his fat fingers into the hand of the child she was dancing on the counter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Two parties, of course!&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, nodding his head retrospectively. &ldquo;Ex-actly so! And Joram's at work, at this minute, on a grey one with silver nails, not this measurement&rdquo;&mdash;the measurement of the dancing child upon the counter&mdash;&ldquo;by a good two inches.&mdash;Will you take something?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thanked him, but declined.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let me see,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Barkis's the carrier's wife&mdash;Peggotty's the boatman's sister&mdash;she had something to do with your family? She was in service there, sure?&rdquo;</p>
<p>My answering in the affirmative gave him great satisfaction.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I believe my breath will get long next, my memory's getting so much so,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Well, sir, we've got a young relation of hers here, under articles to us, that has as elegant a taste in the dressmaking business&mdash;I assure you I don't believe there's a Duchess in England can touch her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not little Em'ly?&rdquo; said I, involuntarily.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Em'ly's her name,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo;and she's little too. But if you'll believe me, she has such a face of her own that half the women in this town are mad against her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nonsense, father!&rdquo; cried Minnie.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo;I don't say it's the case with you,&rdquo; winking at me, &ldquo;but I say that half the women in Yarmouth&mdash;ah! and in five mile round&mdash;are mad against that girl.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then she should have kept to her own station in life, father,&rdquo; said Minnie, &ldquo;and not have given them any hold to talk about her, and then they couldn't have done it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Couldn't have done it, my dear!&rdquo; retorted Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Couldn't
<pb n="216" id="p216"/>
have done it! Is that <hi rend="italics">your</hi> knowledge of life? What is there that any woman couldn't do, that she shouldn't do&mdash;especially on the subject of another woman's good looks?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I really thought it was all over with Mr. Omer, after he had uttered this libellous pleasantry. He coughed to that extent, and his breath eluded all his attempts to recover it with that obstinacy, that I fully expected to see his head go down behind the counter, and his little black breeches, with the rusty little bunches of ribbons at the knees, come quivering up in a last ineffectual struggle. At length, however, he got better, though he still panted hard, and was so exhausted that he was obliged to sit on the stool of the shop-desk.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You see,&rdquo; he said, wiping his head, and breathing with difficulty, &ldquo;she hasn't taken much to any companions here; she hasn't taken kindly to any particular acquaintances and friends, not to mention sweethearts. In consequence, an ill-natured story got about, that Em'ly wanted to be a lady. Now my opinion is, that it came into circulation principally on account of her sometimes saying, at the school, that if she was a lady she would like to do so and so for her uncle&mdash;don't you see?&mdash;and buy him such and such fine things.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I assure you, Mr. Omer, she has said so to me,&rdquo; I returned eagerly, &ldquo;when we were both children.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer nodded his head and rubbed his chin. &ldquo;Just so. Then out of a very little, she could dress herself, you see, better than most others could out of a deal, and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> made things unpleasant. Moreover, she was rather what might be called wayward&mdash;I'll go so far as to say what I should call wayward myself,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo; &mdash; didn't know her own mind quite&mdash;a little spoiled&mdash;and couldn't, at first, exactly bind herself down. No more than that was ever said against her, Minnie?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, father,&rdquo; said Mrs. Joram. &ldquo;That's the worst, I believe.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So when she got a situation,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo;to keep a fractious old lady company, they didn't very well agree, and she didn't stop. At last she came here, apprenticed for three years. Nearly two of 'em are over, and she has been as good a girl as ever was. Worth any six! Minnie, is she worth any six, now?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, father,&rdquo; replied Minnie. &ldquo;Never say <hi rend="italics">I</hi> detracted from her!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very good,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;That's right. And so, young gentleman,&rdquo; he added, after a few moments' further rubbing of his chin, &ldquo;that you may not consider me long-winded as well as short-breathed, I believe that's all about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As they had spoken in a subdued tone, while speaking of Em'ly, I had no doubt that she was near. On my asking now, if that were not so, Mr. Omer nodded yes, and nodded towards the door of the parlor. My hurried inquiry if I might peep in, was answered with a free permission; and, looking through the glass, I saw her sitting at her work. I saw her, a most beautiful little creature, with the cloudless blue eyes, that had looked into my childish heart, turned laughingly upon another child of Minnie's who was playing near her; with enough of wilfulness in her bright face to justify what I had heard; with much of the old capricious coyness lurking in it; but with nothing in her pretty looks, I am sure, but what was meant for goodness and for happiness, and what was on a good and happy course.</p>
<pb n="217" id="p217"/>
<p>The tune across the yard that seemed as if it never had left off&mdash;alas! it was the tune that never <hi rend="italics">does</hi> leave off&mdash;was beating, softly, all the while.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wouldn't you like to step in,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo;and speak to her? Walk in and speak to her, sir! Make yourself at home!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was too bashful to do so then&mdash;I was afraid of confusing her, and I was no less afraid of confusing myself: but I informed myself of the hour at which she left of an evening, in order that our visit might be timed accordingly; and taking leave of Mr. Omer, and his pretty daughter, and her little children, went away to my dear old Peggotty's.</p>
<p>Here she was, in the tiled kitchen, cooking dinner! The moment I knocked at the door she opened it, and asked me what I pleased to want. I looked at her with a smile, but she gave me no smile in return. I had never ceased to write to her, but it must have been seven years since we had met.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Mr. Barkis at home, ma'am?&rdquo; I said, feigning to speak roughly to her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He's at home, sir,&rdquo; returned Peggotty, &ldquo;but he's bad abed with the rheumatics.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't he go over to Blunderstone now?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When he's well, he do,&rdquo; she answered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do <hi rend="italics">you</hi> ever go there, Mrs. Barkis?&rdquo;</p>
<p>She looked at me more attentively, and I noticed a quick movement of her hands towards each other.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because I want to ask a question about a house there, that they call the&mdash;what is it?&mdash;the Rookery,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>She took a step backward, and put out her hands in an undecided frightened way, as if to keep me off.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Peggotty!&rdquo; I cried to her.</p>
<p>She cried, &ldquo;My darling boy!&rdquo; and we both burst into tears, and were locked in one another's arms.</p>
<p>What extravagancies she committed; what laughing and crying over me; what pride she showed, what joy, what sorrow that she whose pride and joy I might have been, could never hold me in a fond embrace; I have not the heart to tell. I was troubled with no misgiving that it was young in me to respond to her emotions. I had never laughed and cried in all my life, I dare say&mdash;not even to her&mdash;more freely than I did that morning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Barkis will be so glad,&rdquo; said Peggotty, wiping her eyes with her apron, &ldquo;that it'll do him more good than pints of liniment. May I go and tell him you are here? Will you come up and see him, my dear?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Of course I would. But Peggotty could not get out of the room as easily as she meant to, for as often as she got to the door and looked round at me, she came back again to have another laugh and another cry upon my shoulder. At last, to make the matter easier, I went up-stairs with her; and having waited outside for a minute, while she said a word of preparation to Mr. Barkis, presented myself before that invalid.</p>
<p>He received me with absolute enthusiasm. He was too rheumatic to be shaken hands with, but he begged me to shake the tassel on the top of his nightcap, which I did most cordially. When I sat down by the side of the bed, he said that it did him a world of good to feel as if he was driving me on the Blunderstone road again. As he lay in bed, face upward, and so covered, with that exception, that he seemed to be nothing but a face&mdash;like a conventional cherubim,&mdash;he looked the queerest object I ever beheld.</p>
<pb n="218" id="p218"/>
<p>&ldquo;What name was it, as I wrote up, in the cart, sir?&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, with a slow rheumatic smile.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! Mr. Barkis, we had some grave talks about that matter, hadn't we?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was willin' a long time, sir?&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A long time,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I don't regret it,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis. &ldquo;Do you remember what you told me once, about her making all the apple parsties and doing all the cooking?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, very well,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was as true,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, &ldquo;as turnips is. It was as true,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, nodding his nightcap, which was his only means of emphasis, &ldquo;as taxes is. And nothing's truer than them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Barkis turned his eyes upon me, as if for my assent to this result of his reflections in bed; and I gave it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing's truer than them,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Barkis; &ldquo;a man as poor as I am finds that out in his mind when he's laid up. I'm a very poor man, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry to hear it, Mr. Barkis.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A very poor man, indeed I am,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis.</p>
<p>Here his right hand came slowly and feebly from under the bedclothes, and with a purposeless uncertain grasp took hold of a stick which was loosely tied to the side of the bed. After some poking about with this instrument, in the course of which his face assumed a variety of distracted expressions, Mr. Barkis poked it against a box, an end of which had been visible to me all the time. Then his face became composed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Old clothes,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wish it was Money, sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wish it was, indeed,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But it AIN'T,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, opening both his eyes as wide as he possibly could.</p>
<p>I expressed myself quite sure of that, and Mr. Barkis, turning his eyes more gently to his wife, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;She's the usefullest and best of women, C. P. Barkis. All the praise that any one can give to C. P. Barkis, she deserves, and more! My dear, you'll get a dinner to-day, for company; something good to eat and drink, will you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I should have protested against this unnecessary demonstration in my honor, but that I saw Peggotty, on the opposite side of the bed, extremely anxious I should not. So I held my peace.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have got a trifle of money somewhere about me, my dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Barkis, &ldquo;but I'm a little tired. If you and Mr. David will leave me for a short nap, I'll try and find it when I wake.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We left the room, in compliance with this request. When we got outside the door, Peggotty informed me that Mr. Barkis, being now &ldquo;a little nearer&rdquo; than he used to be, always resorted to this same device before producing a single coin from his store; and that he endured unheard-of agonies in crawling out of bed alone, and taking it from that unlucky box. In effect, we presently heard him uttering suppressed groans of the most dismal nature, as this magpie proceeding racked him in every joint; but while Peggotty's eyes were full of compassion for him, she said his
<pb n="219" id="p219"/>
generous impulse would do him good, and it was better not to check it. So he groaned on, until he had got into bed again, suffering, I have no doubt, a martyrdom; and then called us in, pretending to have just woke up from a refreshing sleep, and to produce a guinea from under his pillow. His satisfaction in which happy imposition on us, and in having preserved the impenetrable secret of the box, appeared to be a sufficient compensation to him for all his tortures.</p>
<p>I prepared Peggotty for Steerforth's arrival, and it was not long before he came. I am persuaded she knew no difference between his having been a personal benefactor of hers, and a kind friend to me, and that she would have received him with the utmost gratitude and devotion in any case. But his easy, spirited, good humour; his genial manner, his handsome looks, his natural gift of adapting himself to whomsoever he pleased, and making direct, when he cared to do it, to the main point of interest in anybody's heart; bound her to him wholly in five minutes. His manner to me, alone, would have won her. But, through all these causes combined, I sincerely believe she had a kind of adoration for him before he left the house that night.</p>
<p>He stayed there with me to dinner&mdash;if I were to say willingly, I should not half express how readily and gaily. He went into Mr. Barkis's room like light and air, brightening and refreshing it as if he were healthy weather. There was no noise, no effort, no consciousness, in anything he did; but in everything an indescribable lightness, a seeming impossibility of doing anything else, or doing anything better, which was so graceful, so natural, and agreeable, that it overcomes me, even now, in the remembrance.</p>
<p>We made merry in the little parlor, where the Book of Martyrs, unthumbed since my time, was laid out upon the desk as of old, and where I now turned over its terrific pictures, remembering the old sensations they had awakened, but not feeling them. When Peggotty spoke of what she called my room, and of its being ready for me at night, and of her hoping I would occupy it, before I could so much as look at Steerforth, hesitating, he was possessed of the whole case.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;You'll sleep here, while we stay, and I shall sleep at the hotel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But to bring you so far,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;and to separate, seems bad companionship, Steerforth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, in the name of Heaven, where do you naturally belong!&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;What is &lsquo;seems,&rsquo; compared to that!&rdquo; It was settled at once.</p>
<p>He maintained all his delightful qualities to the last, until we started forth, at eight o'clock, for Mr. Peggotty's boat. Indeed, they were more and more brightly exhibited as the hours went on; for I thought even then, and I have no doubt now, that the consciousness of success in his determination to please, inspired him with a new delicacy of perception, and made it, subtle as it was, more easy to him. If any one had told me, then, that all this was a brilliant game, played for the excitement of the moment, for the employment of high spirits, in the thoughtless love of superiority, in a mere wasteful careless course of winning what was worthless to him, and next minute thrown away&mdash;I say, if any one had told me such a lie that night, I wonder in what manner of receiving it my indignation would have found a vent!</p>
<pb n="220" id="p220"/>
<p>Probably only in an increase, had that been possible, of the romantic feelings of fidelity and friendship with which I walked beside him, over the dark wintry sands, towards the old boat; the wind sighing around us even more mournfully, than it had sighed and moaned upon the night when I first darkened Mr. Peggotty's door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a wild kind of place, Steerforth, is it not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dismal enough in the dark,&rdquo; he said; &ldquo;and the sea roars as if it were hungry for us. Is that the boat, where I see a light yonder?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the boat,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And it's the same I saw this morning,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;I came straight to it, by instinct, I suppose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We said no more as we approached the light, but made softly for the door. I laid my hand upon the latch; and whispering Steerforth to keep close to me, went in.</p>
<p>A murmur of voices had been audible on the outside, and, at the moment of our entrance, a clapping of hands: which latter noise, I was surprised to see, proceeded from the generally disconsolate Mrs. Gummidge. But Mrs. Gummidge was not the only person there, who was unusually excited. Mr. Peggotty, his face lighted up with uncommon satisfaction, and laughing with all his might, held his rough arms wide open, as if for little Em'ly to run into them; Ham, with a mixed expression in his face of admiration, exultation, and a lumbering sort of bashfulness that sat upon him very well, held little Em'ly by the hand, as if he were presenting her to Mr. Peggotty; little Em'ly herself, blushing and shy, but delighted with Mr. Peggotty's delight, as her joyous eyes expressed, was stopped by our entrance (for she saw us first) in the very act of springing from Ham to nestle in Mr. Peggotty's embrace. In the first glimpse we had of them all, and at the moment of our passing from the dark cold night into the warm light room, this was the way in which they were all employed: Mrs. Gummidge in the back ground, clapping her hands like a madwoman.</p>
<p>The little picture was so instantaneously dissolved by our going in, that one might have doubted whether it had ever been. I was in the midst of the astonished family, face to face with Mr. Peggotty, and holding out my hand to him, when Ham shouted:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mas'r Davy! It's Mas'r Davy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>In a moment we were all shaking hands with one another, and asking one another how we did, and telling one another how glad we were to meet, and all talking at once. Mr. Peggotty was so proud and overjoyed to see us, that he did not know what to say or do, but kept over and over again shaking hands with me, and then with Steerforth, and then with me, and then ruffling his shaggy hair all over his head, and laughing with such glee and triumph, that it was a treat to see him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, that you two gent'lmen&mdash;gent'lmen growed&mdash;should come to this here roof to-night, of all nights in my life,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;is such a thing as never happened afore, I do rightly believe! Em'ly, my darling, come here! Come here, my little witch! There's Mas'r Davy's friend, my dear! There's the gent'lman as you've heerd on, Em'ly. He comes to see you, along with Mas'r Davy, on the brightest night of your uncle's life as ever was or will be, Gorm the t'other one, and horroar for it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>After delivering this speech all in a breath, and with extraordinary animation and pleasure, Mr. Peggotty put one of his large hands rapturously
<pb n="221" id="p221"/>
on each side of his niece's face, and kissing it a dozen times, laid it with a gentle pride and love upon his broad chest, and patted it as if his hand had been a lady's. Then he let her go; and as she ran into the little chamber where I used to sleep, looked round upon us, quite hot and out of breath with his uncommon satisfaction.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you two gent'lmen&mdash;gent'lmen growed now, and such gent'lmen&mdash;&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So th'are, so th'are!&rdquo; cried Ham. &ldquo;Well said! So th'are. Mas'r Davy bor&mdash;gent'lmen growed&mdash;so th'are!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you two gent'lmen, gent'lmen growed,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;don't ex-cuse me for being in a state of mind, when you understand matters, I'll arks your pardon. Em'ly, my dear!&mdash;She knows I'm a going to tell,&rdquo; here his delight broke out again, &ldquo;and has made off. Would you be so good as look arter her, Mawther, for a minute?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Gummidge nodded and disappeared.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If this ain't,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, sitting down among us by the fire, &ldquo;the brightest night o' my life, I'm a shellfish&mdash;biled too&mdash;and more I can't say. This here little Em'ly, sir,&rdquo; in a low voice to Steerforth, &ldquo;&mdash;her as you see a blushing here just now&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Steerforth only nodded; but with such a pleased expression of interest, and of participation in Mr. Peggotty's feelings, that the latter answered him as if he had spoken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To be sure,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;That's her, and so she is. Thankee, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham nodded to me several times, as if he would have said so too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This here little Em'ly of ours,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;has been, in our house, what I suppose (I'm a ignorant man, but that's my belief) no one but a little bright-eyed creetur <hi rend="italics">can</hi> be in a house. She ain't my child; I never had one; but I couldn't love her more. You understand! I couldn't do it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I quite understand,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know you do, sir,&rdquo; returned Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;and thankee again. Mas'r Davy, he can remember what she was; you may judge for your own self what she is; but neither of you can't fully know what she has been, is, and will be, to my loving art. I am rough, sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;I am as rough as a Sea Porkypine; but no one, unless, mayhap, it is a woman, can know, I think, what our little Em'ly is to me. And betwixt ourselves,&rdquo; sinking his voice lower yet, &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">that</hi> woman's name ain't Missis Gummidge neither, though she has a world of merits.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty ruffled his hair again with both hands, as a further preparation for what he was going to say, and went on with a hand upon each of his knees.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There was a certain person as had know'd our Em'ly, from the time when her father was drownded; as had seen her constant; when a babby, when a young gal, when a woman. Not much of a person to look at, he warn't,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;something o' my own build&mdash;rough&mdash;a good deal o' the sou'-wester in him&mdash;wery salt&mdash;but, on the whole, a honest sort of a chap, with his art in the right place.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thought I had never seen Ham grin to anything like the extent to which he sat grinning at us now.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What does this here blessed tarpaulin go and do,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty,
<pb n="222" id="p222"/>
with his face one high noon of enjoyment, &ldquo;but he loses that there art of his to our little Em'ly. He follers her about, he makes hisself a sort o' servant to her, he loses in a great measure his relish for his wittles, and in the long run he makes it clear to me wot's amiss. Now I could wish myself, you see, that our little Em'ly was in a fair way of being married. I could wish to see her, at all ewents, under articles to a honest man as had a right to defend her. I don't know how long I may live, or how soon I may die; but I know that if I was capsized, any night, in a gale of wind in Yarmouth Roads here, and was to see the town-lights shining for the last time over the rollers as I couldn't make no head against, I could go down quieter for thinking &lsquo;There's a man ashore there, iron-true to my little Em'ly, God bless her, and no wrong can touch my Em'ly while so be as that man lives!&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty, in simple earnestness, waved his right arm, as if he were waving it at the town-lights for the last time, and then, exchanging a nod with Ham, whose eye he caught, proceeded as before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well! I counsels him to speak to Em'ly. He's big enough, but he's bashfuller than a little un, and he don't like. So <hi rend="italics">I</hi> speak. &lsquo;What! <hi rend="italics">Him!</hi>&rsquo; says Em'ly. &lsquo;<hi rend="italics">Him</hi> that I've know'd so intimate so many years, and like so much! Oh, Uncle! I never can have <hi rend="italics">him.</hi> He's such a good fellow!&rsquo; I gives her a kiss, and I says no more to her than &lsquo;My dear, you're right to speak out, you're to choose for yourself, you're as free as a little bird.&rsquo; Then I aways to him, and I says, &lsquo;I wish it could have been so, but it can't. But you can both be as you was, and wot I say to you is, Be as you was with her, like a man.&rsquo; He says to me, a shaking of my hand, &lsquo;I will!&rsquo; he says. And he was&mdash;honorable and manful&mdash;for two year going on, and we was just the same at home here as afore.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty's face, which had varied in its expression with the various stages of his narrative, now resumed all its former triumphant delight, as he laid a hand upon my knee and a hand upon Steerforth's (previously wetting them both, for the greater emphasis of the action), and divided the following speech between us:</p>
<p>&ldquo;All of a sudden, one evening&mdash;as it might be to-night&mdash;comes little Em'ly from her work, and him with her! There ain't so much in <hi rend="italics">that,</hi> you'll say. No, because he takes care on her, like a brother, arter dark, and indeed afore dark, and at all times. But this tarpaulin chap, he takes hold of her hand, and he cries out to me, joyful, &lsquo;Look here! This is to be my little wife!&rsquo; And she says, half bold and half shy, and half a laughing and half a crying, &lsquo;Yes, uncle! If you please.&rsquo;&mdash;If I please!&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty, rolling his head in an ecstacy at the idea; &ldquo;Lord, as if I should do anythink else!&mdash;&lsquo;If you please, I am steadier now, and I have thought better of it, and I'll be as good a little wife as I can to him, for he's a dear, good fellow!&rsquo; Then Missis Gummidge, she claps her hands like a play, and you come in. There! the murder's out!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty&mdash;&ldquo;You come in! It took place this here present hour; and here's the man that'll marry her, the minute she's out of her time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham staggered, as well he might, under the blow Mr. Peggotty dealt him in his unbounded joy, as a mark of confidence and friendship; but feeling called upon to say something to us, he said, with much faltering and great difficulty:</p>
<pb n="223" id="p223"/>
<p>&ldquo;She warn't no higher than you was, Mas'r Davy&mdash;when you first come&mdash;when I thought what she'd grow up to be. I see her grow up&mdash;gent'lmen&mdash;like a flower. I'd lay down my life for her&mdash;Mas'r Davy&mdash;Oh! most content and cheerful! She's more to me&mdash;gent'lmen&mdash;than&mdash;she's all to me that ever I can want, and more than ever I&mdash;than ever I could say. I&mdash;I love her true. There ain't a gent'lman in all the land&mdash;nor yet sailing upon all the sea&mdash;that can love his lady more than I love her, though there's many a common man&mdash;would say better&mdash;what he meant.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thought it affecting to see such a sturdy fellow as Ham was now, trembling in the strength of what he felt for the pretty little creature who had won his heart. I thought the simple confidence reposed in us by Mr. Peggotty and by himself, was, in itself, affecting. I was affected by the story altogether. How far my emotions were influenced by the recollections of my childhood, I don't know. Whether I had come there with any lingering fancy that I was still to love little Em'ly, I don't know. I know that I was filled with pleasure by all this; but, at first, with an indescribably sensitive pleasure, that a very little would have changed to pain.</p>
<p>Therefore, if it had depended upon me to touch the prevailing chord among them with any skill, I should have made a poor hand of it. But it depended upon Steerforth; and he did it with such address, that in a few minutes we were all as easy and as happy as it was possible to be.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Peggotty,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;you are a thoroughly good fellow, and deserve to be as happy as you are to-night. My hand upon it! Ham, I give you joy, my boy. My hand upon that, too! Daisy, stir the fire, and make it a brisk one! and Mr. Peggotty, unless you can induce your gentle niece to come back (for whom I vacate this seat in the corner), I shall go. Any gap at your fireside on such a might&mdash;such a gap least of all&mdash;I wouldn't make, for the wealth of the Indies!&rdquo;</p>
<p>So Mr. Peggotty went into my old room to fetch little Em'ly. At first little Em'ly didn't like to come, and then Ham went. Presently they brought her to the fireside, very much confused, and very shy,&mdash;but she soon became more assured when she found how gently and respectfully Steerforth spoke to her; how skilfully he avoided anything that would embarrass her; how he talked to Mr. Peggotty of boats, and ships, and tides, and fish; how he referred to me about the time when he had seen Mr. Peggotty at Salem House; how delighted he was with the boat and all belonging to it; how lightly and easily he carried on, until he brought us, by degrees, into a charmed circle, and we were all talking away without any reserve.</p>
<p>Em'ly, indeed, said little all the evening; but she looked, and listened, and her face got animated, and she was charming. Steerforth told a story of a dismal shipwreck (which arose out of his talk with Mr. Peggotty), as if he saw it all before him&mdash;and little Em'ly's eyes were fastened on him all the time, as if she saw it too. He told us a merry adventure of his own as a relief to that, with as much gaiety as if the narrative were as fresh to him as it was to us&mdash;and little Em'ly laughed until the boat rang with the musical sounds, and we all laughed (Steerforth too), in irresistible sympathy with what was so pleasant and light-hearted. He got Mr. Peggotty to sing, or rather to roar, &ldquo;When the stormy winds do blow, do blow, do blow;&rdquo; and he sang a sailor's song himself, so pathetically and beautifully, that I could have almost fancied that the real wind
<pb n="224" id="p224"/>
creeping sorrowfully round the house, and murmuring low through our unbroken silence, was there to listen.</p>
<p>As to Mrs. Gummidge, he roused that victim of despondency with a success never attained by any one else (so Mr. Peggotty informed me) since the decease of the old one. He left her so little leisure for being miserable that she said next day she thought she must have been bewitched.</p>
<p>But he set up no monopoly of the general attention, or the conversation. When little Em'ly grew more courageous, and talked (but still bashfully) across the fire to me, of our old wanderings upon the beach, to pick up shells and pebbles; and when I asked her if she recollected how I used to be devoted to her; and when we both laughed and reddened, casting these looks back on the pleasant old times, so unreal to look at now; he was silent and attentive, and observed us thoughtfully. She sat, at this time, and all the evening, on the old locker in her old little corner by the fire&mdash;Ham beside her, where I used to sit. I could not satisfy myself whether it was in her own little tormenting way, or in a maidenly reserve before us, that she kept quite close to the wall, and away from him; but I observed that she did so, all the evening.</p>
<p>As I remember, it was almost midnight when we took our leave. We had had some biscuit and dried fish for supper, and Steerforth had produced from his pocket a full flask of Hollands, which we men (I may say we men, now, without a blush) had emptied. We parted merrily; and as they all stood crowded round the door to light us as far as they could upon our road, I saw the sweet blue eyes of little Em'ly peeping after us, from behind Ham, and heard her soft voice calling to us to be careful how we went.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A most engaging little Beauty!&rdquo; said Steerforth, taking my arm. &ldquo;Well! It's a quaint place, and they are quaint company, and it's quite a new sensation to mix with them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How fortunate we are, too,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;to have arrived to witness their happiness in that intended marriage! I never saw people so happy. How delightful to see it, and to be made the sharers in their honest joy, as we have been!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's rather a chuckle-headed fellow for the girl; isn't he?&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>He had been so hearty with him, and with them all, that I felt a shock in this unexpected and cold reply. But turning quickly upon him, and seeing a laugh in his eyes, I answered, much relieved:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, Steerforth! It's well for you to joke about the poor! You may skirmish with Miss Dartle, or try to hide your sympathies in jest from me, but I know better. When I see how perfectly you understand them, how exquisitely you can enter into happiness like this plain fisherman's, or humour a love like my old nurse's, I know that there is not a joy or sorrow, not an emotion, of such people, that can be indifferent to you. And I admire and love you for it, Steerforth, twenty times the more!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He stopped, and, looking in my face, said, &ldquo;Daisy, I believe you are in earnest, and are good. I wish we all were!&rdquo; Next moment he was gaily singing Mr. Peggotty's song, as we walked at a round pace back to Yarmouth.</p>
</div2></div1>




</body>
<back>
<div1>
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<epigraph><p>Knowledge is like the atmosphere; in order to dispel the vapour and dislodge the frost, our ancestors felled the forest, drained the marsh, and cultivated the waste, and we now breathe, in the purified air and the chastened climate, the result of the labour of generations and the progress of art.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Quotation, sir, is a good thing; there is a community of mind in it; classical quotation is the parole of literary men all over the world.&mdash;JOHNSON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Some of the most stirrin men in the world, persons in the thick of business of all kinds, and, indeed, with the business of the world itself on their hands, have combined with their other energies the greatest love of books, and found no recreation at once so wholesome and so useful.&mdash;LEIGH HUNT.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Knowledge in general expands the mind, exalts the faculties, refines the taste of pleasure, and opens numerous sources of intellectual enjoyment.&mdash;ROBERT HALL.</p></epigraph><opener>186, STRAND, NOVEMBER 1st, 1849.</opener>
<head>CHAPMAN AND HALL'S <lb/> ANNOUNCEMENT OF <lb/> NEW BOOKS AND NEW EDITIONS</head><p>NOW READY AND IN PREPARATION.</p>
<div2>
<head>MR. THACKERAY'S NEW CHRISTMAS BOOK.</head>
<p>A NEW WORK BY MR. M. A. TITMARSH, <lb/> Uniform with &ldquo;DR. BIRCH,&rdquo; &ldquo;OUR STREET,&rdquo; &amp;c. [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In three volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi>
<lb/> THE OGILVIES.</p>
<p>A Novel. [<hi rend="italics">Now Ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi>
<lb/> THE AUSTRIAN EMPIRE AND HUNGARY, <lb/> INCLUDING <lb/> A PRELIMINARY VIEW OF THE SEVERAL STATES OF EUROPE, IN THE YEAR 1848.</p>
<p>BY JOHN MACGREGOR, ESQ., M.P, <lb/> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
</div2><div2>
<head>MR. CHARLES LEVER'S NEW WORK.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In one thick octavo volume, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s., cloth,</hi>
<lb/> ROLAND CASHEL.</p>
<p>BY CHARLES LEVER, <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;HARRY LORREQUER,&rdquo; &ldquo;KNIGHT OF GWYNNE,&rdquo; &amp;C. &amp;c.</p>
<p>WITH FORTY ILLUSTRATIONS BY &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Work will also be issued in half-morocco, marbled edges, price 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In November.</hi></p>
</div2><div2>
<head>SOUTHERN AUSTRIA.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 32<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE HIGHLANDS &amp; ISLANDS OF THE ADRIATIC.</p>
<p>INCLUDING <lb/> Dalmatia, Croatia, and the Southern Provinces of the Austrian Empire.</p>
<p>BY ARCHIBALD A. PATON, ESQ., <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;SERVIA; THE YOUNGEST MEMBER OF THE EUROPEAN FAMILY,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>WITH MAPS AND ILLUSTRATIONS IN TINTED LITHOGRAPHY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Replets with information. * * * * Independently of the special interest which attaches to these countries at this moment, these volumes form a valuable contribution to our stores of geographical and ethnographical knowledge.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
<epigraph><p>Criticism stands like an interpreter between the inspired and the uninspired, between the prophet and those who hear the melody of his words, and catch some glimpse of their material meaning, but understand not their deeper import.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>It is manifest that all government of action is to be gotten by knowledge, and knowledge but by gathering many knowledges, which is reading.&mdash;SIR P. SIDNEY.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The precepts of knowledge it is difficult to extricate from error; but once discovered, <sic corr="they">thay</sic> gradually pass into maxims; and thus what the Sage's lite was spent in acquiring, becomes the acquisition of a moment to posterity.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Learning teacheth more in one year than experience in twenty; and learning teacheth safely when experience maketh more miserable than wise.&mdash;ROGER ASCHAM.</p></epigraph><head>THE IRISH ANNUAL.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In a handsome folio volume, full gilt, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE DAUGHTERS OF ERIN.</p>
<p>A Series of Portraits, <lb/> ILLUSTRATIVE OF MOORE'S IRISH MELODIES, <lb/> From Paintings by W. P. FRITH, A.R.A., A. ELMORE, A.R.A., W. FISHER, <lb/> J. WRIGHT, A. DERBY, E. HAWKES, W. ROOM, J. G. MIDDLETON, R. T. BOTT, <lb/> and J. WOOD.</p>
<p>ENGRAVED BY OR UNDER THE IMMEDIATE SUPERINTENDENCE OF MR. EDWARD FINDEN.</p>
<p>WITH DESCRIPTIVE LETTER-PRESS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This Volume is a selection of Plates from</hi> &ldquo;FINDEN'S BEAUTIES OF MOORE.&rdquo; [<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., the Third Volume of</hi>
<lb/> THE ROMANCE OF THE PEERAGE; <lb/> OR, CURIOSITIES OF FAMILY HISTORY.</p>
<p>BY GEORGE LILLIE CRAIK.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Contents of Volume</hi> III, <lb/> WITH A PORTRAIT OF SIR ROBERT DUDLEY.</p>
<p>The Hereditary Principle; Aristocracy and Democracy.&mdash;Charles Brandon's Widow and her Second Marriage.&mdash;The Lady Mary Grey.&mdash;Sir Robert Dudley.&mdash;Bess of Hardwick and the Talbots.&mdash;The Cavendishes and the Stanhopes.&mdash;Lord Pembroke and Sir Richard Wharton.&mdash;The Wharton and Stuart Duel.&mdash;The Bruce and Sackville Duel.&mdash;The Lord Crichton of Sanquhar.&mdash;The Earldom of Menteith, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. [<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In four volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 42<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Third Edition, with numerous Additions and Corrections, <lb/> OLIVER CROMWELL'S LETTERS AND SPEECHES.</p>
<p>WITH ELUCIDATIONS AND CONNECTING NARRATIVE.</p>
<p>BY THOMAS CARLYLE.</p>
<p>WITH A PORTRAIT OF CROMWELL, FROM AN ORIGINAL MINIATURE BY COOPER.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Supplement to the First and Second Editions, comprising the new matter introduced into</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">the Third Edition, is published in demy</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">Now ready.</hi></p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BOOKS FOR PRESENTS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In an elegant volume, small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, fancy</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">boards, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>FAIRY TALES FROM ALL <lb/> NATIONS.</p>
<p>BY ANTHONY R. MONTALBA.</p>
<p>EMBELLISHED WITH TWENTY-FOUR ILLUS- <lb/> TRATIONS BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In two volumes, small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>A BOOK FOR A CORNER; <lb/> Or Selections in Prose and Verse from Authors best suited to that mode of enjoyment. With comments and a general Introduction.</p>
<p>BY LEIGH HUNT.</p>
<p>WITH EIGHTY ILLUSTRATIONS BY F. W. HULME AND J. FRANKLIN.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
<epigraph><p>There are few kinds of composition from which an author, however learned or Ingenious, can hope a long continuance of fame. He who has carefully studied human nature, and can well describe it, may with most reason flatter his ambition.&mdash;JOHNSON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Style in painting is the same as in writing; a power over materials, whether words or colours, by which conceptions or sentiments are conveyed.&mdash;SIR JOSHUA REYNOLDS.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>There is a sort of wit peculiar to knowledge of the world, and we usually find that writers, who are supposed to have the most exhibited that knowledge in their books, are also commonly esteemed the wittiest authors of their country.&mdash;SIR E. BULWER LYTTON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Libraries are as the shrines where all the relics of the ancient saints, full of true virtue, and that without delusion or imposture, are preserved and reposed.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph>
<head>CHEAP EDITION OF MR. AINSWORTH'S WORKS, <lb/> IN SHILLING VOLUMES.</head>
<p>PREPARING FOR IMMEDIATE PUBLICATION, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, ornamental boards,</hi>
<lb/> A CHEAP EDITION <lb/> OF THE WORKS OF <lb/> W. HARRISON AINSWORTH, ESQ.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="2">
<head>THIS EDITION WILL COMPRISE</head>
<row>
<cell> WINDSOR CASTLE </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> ROOKWOOD </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> GUY FAWKES </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> CRICHTON </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> JACK SHEPPARD </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> OLD ST. PAUL'S </cell>
<cell> 2 VOLS. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> THE MISER'S DAUGHTER </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> ST. JAMES'S </cell>
<cell> 1 VOL. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>PUBLISHED FOR THE AUTHOR BY</p><closer>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Monthly Numbers, Price</hi> ONE SHILLING <hi rend="italics">each,</hi>
<lb/> WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS,</opener><head>THE <lb/> JOURNAL OF DESIGN AND MANUFACTURES,</head><p>ADDRESSED TO <lb/> MERCHANTS, MANUFACTURERS, RETAIL DEALERS, DESIGNERS, <lb/> ART-WORKMEN, AND THE GENERAL PUBLIC.</p>
<p>THE JOURNAL OF DESIGN has, as it ought to have, politics of its own. In this matter of Ornamental Design we hope to prove ourselves thoroughly conservative of the best interests of manufacturers, designers, and all parties concerned. We are the advocates for better laws and a better tribunal to protect copyright in designs, and for a largely increased extension of copyright. We think the restless demands of the public for constant novelty, are alike mischievous to the progress of good ornamental art as they are to all commercial interests. We think that the Schools of Design should be reformed and made business-like realities. We shall wage war against all pirates; and we hope to see the day when it will be thought as disgraceful for one manufacturer to pillage another's patterns, as it is held to be if he should walk into the counting-house and rob his till. These are some of the points of our political creed, with which we start on our undertaking. We profess that our aim is to foster ornamental art in all its ways, and to do those things for its advance, in all its branches, which it would be the appropriate business of a Board of Design to do, if such a useful department of Government actually existed.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Vol. I. is now ready with</hi> 50 <hi rend="italics">Patterns of actual Fabrics, and nearly</hi> 200 <hi rend="italics">Engravings</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">on Wood. Cloth,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
<epigraph><p>They who speak truth, however discovered, have a right to be heard;&mdash;they who assist others in discovering it have the yet higher claim to be applauded.&mdash;PARR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>God Almighty first planted a garden.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Authorship is, according to the spirit in which it is pursued, an infancy, a pastime, a day-labour, a handicraft, an art, a science, a virtue.&mdash;SCHLEGET.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Truth will be uppermost, some time or other.&mdash;SIR W. TEMPLE.</p></epigraph>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Monthly Numbers, price One Shilling each,</hi></opener><head>THE FLORIST AND GARDEN MISCELLANY.</head>
<p>SUPERINTENDED BY EDWARD BECK, OF ISLEWORTH.</p>
<p>THIS work contains communications from many of the most successful cultivators of Flowers; and will be found not only interesting to the lovers of gardens, but the year's numbers, when bound up, form an elegant book for the drawing-room table.</p>
<p>Each Monthly Part includes a Monthly Calendar of operations supplied by practical Florists, with a Coloured Plate and a Woodcut executed in the best manner.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Vol. II. will be published early in December.</hi></p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW AND CHEAPER EDITIONS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Elegantly Printed in a Pocket Volume, in</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">limp cloth, gilt edges, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> SHAKESPEARE PROVERBS; <lb/> Or, the <hi rend="italics">Wise Saws</hi> of our Wisest Poet, collected into a <hi rend="italics">Modern Instance.</hi></p>
<p>By MARY COWDEN CLARKE, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;The Concordance to Shakespeare.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>LIFE IN DALECARLIA: <lb/> THE PARSONAGE OF MORA.</p>
<p>By FREDERIKA BREMBER.</p>
<p>Translated by WILLIAM HOWITT.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>ST. PATRICK'S EVE; <lb/> Or, Three Eras in the Life of an Irish <lb/> Peasant.</p>
<p>By CHARLES LEVER, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Harry Lorrequer,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>With numerous Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ,&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>IRISH DIAMONDS; <lb/> Or, a Theory of Irish Wit and Blunders; <lb/> combined with other kindred Subjects.</p>
<p>By JOHN SMITH.</p>
<p>With Six Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ,&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> The SECOND EDITION of <lb/> THE YOUNG SPORTSMAN'S MANUAL; <lb/> OR, RECREATIONS IN SHOOTING.</p>
<p>With some Account of the Game of the British Islands, and practical Directions for the <lb/> Management of the Dog and Gun.</p>
<p>By &ldquo;CRAVEN.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With Sixty-two Illustrations of Game and Sporting Dogs, by WILLIAM HARVEY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">New <sic corr="and">aud</sic> Cheaper Edition, in post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth gilt, price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> FRANCE IN 1848 AND 1849.</p>
<p>A Narrative of the French Revolution, from the commencement of the Reform <lb/> Movement to the close of the First Session of the Republican Parliament.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">New Edition, with Additions and Corrections.</hi></p>
<p>WITH PORTRAITS AND OTHER ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>JUVENILE BOOKS, NEW EDITIONS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE NOVEL ADVENTURES OF <lb/> TOM THUMB THE GREAT.</p>
<p>Showing how he visited the Insect World <lb/> and learned much Wisdom.</p>
<p>By MRS. BARWELL.</p>
<p>WITH EIGHT ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">to, cloth, gilt back and edges,</hi>
<lb/> THE OLD STORY BOOKS OF <lb/> ENGLAND, <lb/> Newly Revised and Amended, for the Amusement and Delight of all good little Masters <lb/> and Misses.</p>
<p>By AMBROSE MERTON, Gent, F.S.A.</p>
<p>ILLUSTRATED WITH TWELVE PICTURES BY <lb/> EMINENT ARTISTS.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5a"/>
<epigraph><p>It is impossible to make people understand their ignorance; for it requires knowledge to perceive it; and therefore he that can perceive it hath it not.&mdash;BISHOP TAYLOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>To be proud of learning is the greatest ignorance in the world.&mdash;BISHOP TAYLOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Real knowledge never promoted either turbulence or unbelief; but its progress is the forerunner of liberality and enlightened toleration.&mdash;LORD BROUGHAM.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The highest learning is to be wise, and the greatest wisdom is to be good.&mdash;M. AURELIUS.</p></epigraph>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in super-royal folio, half-bound, gilt bands and edges, price</hi> &pound;1 16<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">or with the Maps coloured,</hi> &pound;2 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>SHARPE'S CORRESPONDING ATLAS,</head><p>COMPRISING <lb/> FIFTY-FOUR MAPS, <lb/> CONSTRUCTED UPON A SYSTEM OF SCALE AND PROPORTION, FROM THE MOST RECENT <lb/> AUTHORITIES, AND ENGRAVED ON STEEL BY J. WILSON LOWRY.</p>
<p>WITH A COPIOUS CONSULTING INDEX, <lb/> PREPARED EXPRESSLY FOR THE WORK AND BASED UPON THE MAPS THEMSELVES.</p>
<p>THIS Atlas combines at once new and important means of facilitating geographical study with just accuracy and skilful execution, at an unexampled lowness of price. Nothing superfluous is admitted into it, to the needless increase of its cost, nor is anything omitted, the absence of which would impair its general utility. It is a Work at once available for all purposes of general reference, is complete in character, comprehensive in scope, and compact in form, and accomplishes, by its peculiar plan of construction, effects of great practical value, never before attempted; and is, at the same time, so cheap as to be within the means of every who desires to possess an Atlas.</p>
<p>The term &ldquo;Corresponding&rdquo; is applied to indicate that Uniformity of Scale by which these Maps are distinguished from those of every other collection. If we open any Atlas extant, we shall find in it almost as great a diversity of scales as of maps; the latter, therefore are so contradictory as to admit of no direct comparison with each other, either as to the linear or superficial dimensions they respectively represent. There must, of course, be considerable disparity of scale between maps of Continents and maps of States; but if the subject is examined it will be seen that a change of scale in the case of each individual map, as always has been the practice, is neither necessary nor useful. The leading purpose of this Work is to place the maps more efficiently in correspondence with each other, by limiting the number of scales. They are here reduced from about fifty to the inconsiderable number of four, with a single exception, that of Switzerland, the sheets of each series, just like the several parts of a single map, speaking one and the same language to the eye, and being capable of direct admeasurement one with the other.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>THE FOUR SCALES.</head>
<p>There are Twenty-seven DIVISIONAL Maps, which correspond in scale respectively with each other&mdash;Great Britain, France, Italy, &amp;c., as marked D in the list.</p>
<p>The CONTINENTAL Maps are ten in number; Asia being divided into three, North America and Africa each forming two maps; Europe, South America, and Australia, remaining single as before. These ten maps also correspond with each other, and are marked C in the list.</p>
<p>The above thirty-seven maps, with the two Index Maps to the subdivisions of India and Russia, and Mercator's Projection of the World, virtually complete the Atlas, as comprising the circuit of the Globe&mdash;Forty Maps.</p>
<p>But, as assistant to the above, there are twelve others. Five of the North and South American States, which correspond with the two Index Maps above, the seven maps forming an INTERMEDIATE class (marked I), and seven ENLARGED Maps (marked E)&mdash;England two sheets, Scotland, Ireland, Netherlands and Belgium, Greece, and Switzerland. Of these seven maps, six correspond with each other; Switzerland, as the lesser territory, being still farther extended, and forming the exception to the rule.</p>
</div3><div3 type="section">
<head>ANALYSIS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> C refers to 10 CONTINENTAL Maps </cell>
<cell> 45 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 60 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> I refers to 7 INTERMEDIATE </cell>
<cell> 22&frac12; </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 30 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> D refers to 27 DIVISIONAL </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 12 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> E refers to 6 ENLARGED </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 4 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1 SWITZERLAND </cell>
<cell> 2&frac14; </cell>
<cell> DEGREES EQUATORIAL BY </cell>
<cell> 3 DEGREES. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3 TWO HEMISPHERES AND MERCATOR.&mdash; </cell>
<cell> TOTAL, 54 MAPS. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Scale of Miles is adjusted to each Series and inserted on every Map in the usual</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">manner.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6a"/>
<epigraph><p>The more widely knowledge is spread, the more will they be prized whose happy lot it is to extend its bounds by discovering new truths, to multiply its uses by inventing new modes of applying it in practice.&mdash;LORD BROUGHAM.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>He that would make a real progress in knowledge must dedicate his age as well as youth, the latter growth as well as the first fruits, at the altar of truth.&mdash;BERKELEY.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>A country which has no national literature, or a literature too insignificant to force its way abroad must always be to its neighbours, at least in every important spiritual respect, an unknown and misestimated country.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Learning is like a river, whose head, being far in the bank, is, at first rising, little, and easily viewed; but still as you go, it gapeth with a wider bank.&mdash;FELTHAM.</p></epigraph>
<head>LIST OF SHARPE'S CORRESPONDING MAPS.</head>
<list>
<item>1. The World&mdash;Western Hemisphere.</item>
<item>2. The World&mdash;Eastern Hemisphere.</item>
<item>3. The World on Mercator's Projection.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>EUROPE.</head>
<item>4. C Europe with the Mediterranean.</item>
<item>5. D Great Britain and Ireland.</item>
<item>6. E England and Wales&mdash;North <hi rend="italics">Double Map with Railways</hi></item>
<item>7. E England and Wales&mdash;South <hi rend="italics">Double Map with Railways</hi></item>
<item>8. E Scotland&mdash;with Railways.</item>
<item>9. E Ireland&mdash;with Railways.</item>
<item>10. D France&mdash;Belgium&mdash;Switzerland.</item>
<item>11. E Holland and Belgium&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>12. D Prussia, Holland, and the German States.</item>
<item>13. E Switzerland&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>14. D Austrian Empire.</item>
<item>15. D Turkey and Greece.</item>
<item>16. E Greece and the Ionian Islands&mdash;Enlarged.</item>
<item>17. D Italy.</item>
<item>18. D Spain and Portugal.</item>
<item>19. D Northern Sweden and Frontier of Russia <hi rend="italics">Double Map of the Baltic.</hi></item>
<item>20. D Denmark, Sweden, and Russia on the Baltic. <hi rend="italics">Double Map of the Baltic.</hi></item>
<item>21. D Western Russia from the Baltic to the Euxine.</item>
<item>22. D Russia on the Euxine.</item>
<item>23. D Russia on the Caucasus.</item>
</list>
<p>The topographical interest of the interior of this vast empire is hardly equal to its extent. The above series of frontier maps connect it with the neighbouring states, and, independent of their political bearing, have each a marked geographical character in itself. They also accord as to scale with Austria, Prussia, &amp;c.</p>
<list>
<item>24. I Russia in Europe&mdash;General Map.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>ASIA.</head>
<item>25. C Northern Asia&mdash;Asiatic Russia.</item>
<item>26. C South-Western Asia&mdash;Overland to India.</item>
<item>27. C South Eastern Asia&mdash;Birmah, China and Japan.</item>
<item>28. C Australia and New Zealand.</item>
<item>29. D Egypt, the Red Sea, and Arabia Petr&aelig;.</item>
<item>30. D Nubia, the Red Sea, and Abyssinia, to the Strait of Bab-el-Mandeb.</item>
</list>
<p>Egypt and Nubia, although properly in Africa, are more conveniently placed with the Asiatic Maps, from their political bearing between Europe and India. Geographers must follow the track of the Steam Engine.</p>
<list>
<item>31. D Asia Minor.</item>
<item>32. D Syria and Provinces to the Persian Gulf.</item>
<item>33. D Western Persia.</item>
<item>34. D Eastern Persia.</item>
<item>35. D Affghanistan and the Punjab.</item>
<item>36. D Beloochistan and Sinde.</item>
<item>37. D Central India.</item>
<item>38. D The Carnatic, &amp;c.</item>
<item>39. D Bengal, &amp;c.</item>
<item>40. I India&mdash;General Map.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>AFRICA&mdash;AMERICA.</head>
<item>41. C North Africa.</item>
<item>42. C South Africa.</item>
<item>43. C British North America.</item>
<item>44. C Central America.</item>
<item>45. I United States&mdash;General Map.</item>
<item>46. D United States, North-East.</item>
<item>47. D United States, South-East.</item>
<item>48. D United States, South-West.</item>
<item>49. D Jamaica &mdash; Leeward and Windward Islands&mdash;with Jamaica on Enlarged Scale.</item>
<item>50. I Mexico and Guatemala</item>
<item>51. C South America.</item>
<item>52. I Columbian and Peruvian Republics, and Western Brazil.</item>
<item>53. I La Plata, Chili, and Southern Brazil.</item>
<item>54. I Eastern Brazil.</item>
</list>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>BINDING SUBSCRIBERS' COPIES.</head>
<p>The Publishers have made arrangements for BINDING &ldquo;SHARPE'S ATLAS&rdquo; in the best and strongest manner, with India-Rubber Backs, in <hi rend="italics">Half Morocco, Cloth Sules, Gilt Back and Edges, price</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Subscribers may have their Copies bound, by sending them through their respective Booksellers, or direct to CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, Strand, London.</p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>SINGLE MAPS.</head>
<p>For Commercial Purposes, and for General Diffusion in Schools, these Maps are sold in Separate Sheets at Fourpence each, Plain, or Sixpence Coloured. Parties choosing Maps marked the same letter in the list, will have them upon the same scale.</p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>MAPS FOR TRAVELLERS.</head>
<p>These Maps are also mounted on cloth, in cloth cases, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, single maps. <hi rend="italics">England and Wales,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">the Baltic,</hi> double maps, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This work deserves high praise. Though considerably cheaper than even the admirable maps of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge, the size is larger, the fulness and accuracy not less, and the engraving is remarkable for its care, clearness, and beauty.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The main feature of this series is, that the plates are engraved upon a uniform scale, so as to admit a direct comparison with each other in their respective linear and superficial dimensions; an arrangement which must be of immense advantage to the student and others.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Art-Union.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7a"/>
<epigraph><p>Plays and romances sell as well as books of devotion; but with this difference&mdash;more people read the former than buy them; and more buy the latter than read them.&mdash;TOM BROWN.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Of no given book, not even of a fashionable novel can you predicate with certainty that its vacuity is absolute.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Although our learning raiseth up against us many enemies among the low, and more among the powerful, yet doth it invest us with grand and glorious privliges; and grant to us a largess of beatitude.&mdash;LANDOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>To seize a character, even that of one man, in its life and secret mechanism, requires a philosopher; to delineate it with truth and impressiveness is work for a poet.&mdash;CARLYLE.</p></epigraph>
<head>THE RECENT VOLUMES OF <lb/> Chapman and Hall's Series of Original Works.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Two Volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>FANNY HERVEY; <lb/> OR, THE MOTHER'S CHOICE.</p>
<p>A Novel.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Out of elements exceedingly simple in themselves, the Author has constructed a story of the deepest tragic power.</p>
<p>* * The Novel is entitled to take rank among the best works of fiction.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>RAMBLES AND OBSERVATIONS IN <lb/> NEW SOUTH WALES.</p>
<p>WITH SKETCHES OF MEN AND MANNERS, NOTICES OF THE ABORIGINES, GLIMPSES <lb/> OF SCENERY, AND SOME HINTS TO EMIGRANTS.</p>
<p>BY JOSEPH PHIPPS TOWNSEND.</p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the best books on New South Wales that has appeared.&rdquo;&mdash;SPECTATOR.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In Two Volumes, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s., the</hi> THIRD EDITION <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
<lb/> MARY BARTON, <lb/> A TALE OF MANCHESTER LIFE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Its interest is intense&mdash;often painfully so. * * We can conscientiously pronounce it to be a production of great excellence, and of still greater promise.&rdquo;&mdash;EDINBURGH REVIEW.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE LIFE OF MAXIMILIEN ROBESPIERRE, <lb/> With Extracts from his Unpublished Correspondence.</p>
<p>BY G. H. LEWES, <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;RANTHORPE,&rdquo; &ldquo;BIOGRAPHICAL HISTORY OF PHILOSOPHY,&rdquo; &amp;C.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Lewes has rendered good service, not only to history, but to the cause of order in France, by the publication of the present volume.&rdquo;&mdash;JOHN BULL.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s., the</hi> SECOND EDITIONS <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
<lb/> WAYFARING SKETCHES <lb/> Among the Greeks and Turks, and on the Shores of the Danube.</p>
<p>BY <lb/> A SEVEN YEARS' RESIDENT IN GREECE.</p>
<p>THE <lb/> BACHELOR OF THE ALBANY.</p>
<p>A Novel.</p>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;THE FALCON FAMILY,&rdquo; <lb/> and &ldquo;MY UNCLE THE CURATK,&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8a"/>
<epigraph><p>The way to acquire lasting esteem is not by the fewness of a writer's faults, but the greatness of his beauties, and our noblest works are generally most replete with both.&mdash;GOLDSMITH.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>The value of a book is only realised in proportion as it is read. A book which is never read, is of absolutely no value.&mdash;HENRY TAYLOR.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Eloquence, that leads mankind by the ears, gives a nobler superiority than power that every dance may use, or fraud that every knave may employ, to lead them by the nose.&mdash;BOLINGBROKE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>Read not to contradict and confute, nor to believe and take for granted, nor to find talk and discourse, but to weigh and consider.&mdash;BACON.</p></epigraph>
<head>Cheap Edition of the Works of Mr. Charles Dickens,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces.</hi></p>
<p>MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY FRANK STONE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p>BARNABY RUDGE.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY GEORGE CATTERMOLE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>NICHOLAS NICKLEBY.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY T. WEBSTER, R. A. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE PICKWICK PAPERS.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY C. R. LESLIE, R.A. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s., half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Cheap Edition of the Novels and Tales of Sir Edward <lb/> Bulwer Lytton, Bart.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Uniformly printed in crown</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new Prefaces.</hi></p>
<p>RIENZI; <lb/> THE LAST OF THE TRIBUNES.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>PAUL CLIFFORD.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>PELHAM; <lb/> OR, THE ADVENTURES OF A GENTLEMAN.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>EUGENE ARAM.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.; half-morocco,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE LAST OF THE BARONS.</p>
<p>WITH A FRONTISPIECE BY HABLOT K. BROWNE. <hi rend="italics">Cloth,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.; half-morocco,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">In December.</hi></p>
<p>A Catalogue of Works published by CHAPMAN and HALL, with <lb/> Critical Notices, may be had gratis from all Booksellers.</p>
<closer>LONDON: CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>THE WHALE IN THE THAMES.</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>THE mighty monster captur'd in the Thames,</l>
<l>May justly swell my advertising gems.</l>
<l>I call them <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;gems,&rdquo;</hi> not <hi rend="italics">vainly.</hi> Oh, dear, no!</l>
<l>But &ldquo;gems will rhyme with Thames, and so-and-so.</l>
<l>The mighty <hi rend="italics">whale</hi> no doubt be-&rdquo;<hi rend="italics">wail'd</hi> his lot,</l>
<l>When near the <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Basin&rdquo;</hi> of the Thames he got.</l>
<l>And doubtless, he was not without amaze</l>
<l>When thus he <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;grazed&rdquo;</hi> himself near <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Kentish Grays.&rdquo;</hi></l>
<l>But soon his captors told him woeful tales,</l>
<l>By landing on the beach a <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Prince of W(h)ales.&rdquo;</hi></l>
<l>Be that which way it may; I beg to state</l>
<l>I'm <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;fishing&rdquo;</hi> after trade in this huge <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;bait.&rdquo;</hi></l>
<l>When I, with thousands more, stood by to gaze</l>
<l>Upon the wand'ring Whale, safe moored at Grays,</l>
<l>I thought of that <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Leviathan&rdquo;</hi> Depot</l>
<l>Which raised a <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;swimming&rdquo;</hi> trade twelve years ago.</l>
<l>Till MOSES' came, the trade was in a thrall,</l>
<l>And <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;blubbering&rdquo;</hi> monopoly ruled all.</l>
<l>But MOSES' soon exposed his <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;oily&rdquo;</hi> terms,</l>
<l>Establishing themselves, the firm of firms.</l>
<l>They brought the monster to his proper <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;scale,&rdquo;</hi></l>
<l>And proved he <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;threw a sprat to cutch a whale.&rdquo;</hi></l>
<l>And now their purchasers appear to be</l>
<l>As plentiful as <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;fishes&rdquo;</hi> in the sea.</l>
<l>MOSES', by merit &ldquo;ONLY, <hi rend="italics">fish for praise,</hi>&rdquo;</l>
<l>And so I thought the other day at Grays.</l>
<l>Where thousands met to see the fated fish&mdash;</l>
<l>To dress as beautiful as you could wish.</l>
<l>The <hi rend="italics">guests,</hi> I mean, were clad. Don't be mistaken;</l>
<l>I wish to save my grammar and my bacon.</l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome style of Overcoats </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Shooting Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lounging and Morning Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Youth and Boys Overcoats in every style from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suit </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row><row>
<cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row><row>
<cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cassimere Trousers </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Dress Coats, from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Frock 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> H. and I. Suit, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from &pound;3 to &pound;20.</p>
<p>NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Minion of the Million,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON</head><p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb n="10" id="pxxx8"/>
<head>THE <lb/> NICOLL PALETOT</head><p>(Registered 6 &amp; 7 Vic. c. 65) <lb/> WAREROOMS, 114, 116, 120, REGENT <lb/> STREET, and 22, CORNHILL.</p>
<p>Also for NICOLL'S Morning Coat, now in almost universal request for the country, riding, walking, &amp;c. Shooting Jackets adapted for the Season. Many have assumed the use of the word PALETOT, but Messrs. NICOLL are the sole Patentees of the design and material. As also of the <lb/> PATENT TREBLE GARMENT; <lb/> Or, Paletot (called The Nicoll) which retains all the characteristics of the famed Paletot in its exterior, and has the additional advantages of being convertible from a warm to a light Overcoat, or vice versa, at the pleasure of the wearer, or, as the mild or cold nature of the weather may require. This garment must be seen and worn to be properly appreciated; it will be found, perhaps, the best preservative of health in this variable climate.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
