<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. X:</emph>
 Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870 </author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Harris Henderson</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.   240K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">  The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. X</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>  58 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1850</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.
 </p>
<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings </title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>

<change>
<date>2002-11-14, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-10-04, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>


<titlePage>
<docTitle><titlePart> No.  X. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> FEBRUARY.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID <lb/> COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of BEDDING, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest Stock and greatest Variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES: <lb/> ALSO <lb/> THE GERMAN SPRING MATTRESS.</p>
<p>This article HEAL AND SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are Selling at a much LOWER PRICE than any other House; and can recommend one of them, with a French Mattress on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>THE EIDER-DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen ONLY at their House; it is the warmest, lightest, and most elegant covering ever introduced; suitable to the Bed, the Couch, or the Carriage.</p>
<p>EVERY DESCRIPTION OF ENGLISH BEDDING, <lb/> AND OF <lb/> BLANKETS, QUILTS, AND SHEETING.</p>
<p>Their Bed Feathers are all Purified by Steam, <lb/> With Patent Machinery; which process is also employed in the Re-Dressing <lb/> of Old Beds.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S <lb/> LIST OF BEDDING,</head><p>Containing a full description of weights, sizes and prices of every description of Bedding, sent free by Post, on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196 (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL),<lb/>
 TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="1" id="p1"/>
<opener>No. X.&mdash;FEBRUARY, 1850.</opener>
<head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2 type="section">
<head>NEW WORKS AND NEW EDITIONS.</head>
<p>I. <lb/> SCENES FROM THE LIFE OF MOSES.</p>
<p>A series of TWENTY ENGRAVINGS, in Outline, Designed by SELOUS, and Engraved by ROLLS. Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> with Portfolio.</p>
<p>&ldquo;These beautiful Plates will be found a suitable companion to the much admired Series, by the same Artist, illustrative of Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress, which were issued by the Art Union of London.&rdquo;</p>
<p>II. <lb/> A POPULAR EDITION OF MR. TUPPER'S POEMS.</p>
<p>Uniform with &ldquo;Proverbial Philosophy,&rdquo; containing BALLADS FOR THE TIMES, now first collected; GERALDINE; HACTENUS; A THOUSAND LINES: and other Poems. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 1 vol., fcap. 8vo, cloth. With Steel Frontispiece, and Vignette View of the Author's residence at Albury.</p>
<p>III. <lb/> Also, MR. TUPPER's Three Tales, <lb/> THE CROCK OF GOLD, THE TWINS, AND HEART.</p>
<p>In one volume, price 8<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> with Illustrations by JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p>IV. <lb/> PLEASANT PASTIME; <lb/> Or, Drawing-Room Dramas.</p>
<p>Designed for private representation by the Young. By a Lady. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> bound and gilt.</p>
<p>V. <lb/> BAKEWELL'S PHILOSOPHICAL CONVERSATIONS.</p>
<p>Illustrated with Diagrams and Woodcuts. In 12mo. cloth, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Third Edition, revised and corrected.</p>
<p>VI. <lb/> CHEMISTRY NO MYSTERY: <lb/> Being the subject-matter of a Course of Lectures by DR. SCOFFERN, illustrated throughout with Diagrams and Woodcuts. Second Edition, in 12mo., cloth lettered, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>VII. <lb/> In one volume, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth lettered, with Frontispieces by LEECH and WEIR, <lb/> TOIL AND TRIAL, <lb/> A Story of London Life.</p>
<p>By Mrs. NEWTON CROSLAND. And <lb/> THE DOUBLE CLAIM, <lb/> A Tale of Real Life.</p>
<p>By MRS. T. K. HERVEY.</p>
<p>VIII. <lb/> Second Edition, in two vols., fcap. 8vo, price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth, <lb/> THE STORY OF LILLY DAWSON.</p>
<p>By CATHERINE CROWE, Author of &ldquo;Susan Hopley,&rdquo; &ldquo;Pippie's Warning,&rdquo; &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A novel of very rare merit.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Messenger.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crowe's style <sic corr="possesses">posseses</sic> a charm which renders her work irresistible.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Dispatch.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A narrative of stirring interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Jerrold's Paper.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A creation worthy of Scott.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<p>IX. <lb/> NEW Gift-Books for the Young.</p>
<p>THE JUVENILE CALENDAR, <lb/> And Zodiac of Flowers.</p>
<p>By MRS. T. K. HERVEY. With Emblematical Illustrations by RICHARD DOYLE. In super-royal 16mo, price, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth, gilt edges.</p>
<p>X. <lb/> THE ILLUSTRATED YEAR-BOOK <lb/> Of Wonders, Events, And Discoveries.</p>
<p>Edited by a Popular Writer. In fcap. 8vo, cloth gilt, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> with Numerous Engravings.</p>
<closer>London: ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE &amp; Co., 25, Paternoster Row.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<opener>13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</opener>
<head>MR. COLBURN'S NEW NOVELS.</head>
<p>TO BE HAD AT ALL THE LIBRARIES.</p>
<p>THE WILMINGTONS.</p>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;EMILIA WYNDHAM, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of all the novels of the last twelve months this beautiful story is in our estimation the best written, the most ingeniously continued, the healthiest in sentiment, and the most pathetic in interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p>
<p>THE PETREL.</p>
<p>A TALE OF THE SEA.</p>
<p>By a NAVAL OFFICER.</p>
<p>Second Edition of Passages in the Life of <lb/> MRS. MARGARET MAITLAND, <lb/> OF SUNNYSIDE.</p>
<p>Written by HERSELF.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The most gratifying work of its class since the great delineator of Scottish manners ceased to write.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Tait's Magazine.</hi></p>
<p>Adventures of a Gold Finder.</p>
<p>Written by HIMSELF.</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italics">Just ready.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Second Edition, Enlarged, with Portrait of the Author; Cloth, Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>RUINS OF MANY LANDS.</head>
<p>A PILGRIMAGE. BY NICHOLAS MICHELL.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;Babylon&mdash;Nineveh&mdash;Petra&mdash;Egypt&mdash;Ruined Cities of America&mdash;Rock-Temples of India&mdash;Athens&mdash;Rome&mdash;Pompeii &mdash; South of France &mdash; Ephesus&mdash;Tyre&mdash;Baalbec&mdash;Palmyra &mdash;Persepolis&mdash; Jerusalem, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This remarkable and interesting production must be deemed a standard composition wherever the English language is understood. It is an extraordinary volume.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser,</hi> Nov. 17, 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ideas more refined, poetic beauties more richly developed, and classic knowledge more extensive, we scarcely remember to have seen. The work is most valuable.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Independent Press,</hi> 24th Nov.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Ruins of Many Lands&rsquo; contains an astonishing amount of information.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bath and Cheltenham Gazette,</hi> 28th Nov.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is evidently the highest poetical effort published in this country in its style for some years.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Tait's Magazine,</hi> Dec. 1849.</p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG, and Co., 85, Queen Street, Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">This day is published, to be continued occasionally, price One Shilling,</hi></opener><head>LATTER-DAY PAMPHLETS,</head><p>EDITED BY THOMAS CARLYLE.</p>
<p>No. 1. THE PRESENT TIME.</p>
<p>No. 2. &ldquo;THE MODEL PRISONS,&rdquo; will be published on the 1st of March.</p>
<closer>London: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, Strand.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>THE FIRST MONTHLY PART OF</opener><head>THE WORKING MAN'S FRIEND <lb/> AND FAMILY INSTRUCTOR</head><p><hi rend="italics">Will be ready for delivery with the Magazines for February, price Fourpence-halfpenny, enclosed</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">in a neat Wrapper.</hi></p>
<p>[To prevent disappointment, persons wishing to be supplied with it ought to order it at once of the <lb/> nearest bookseller, that he may receive it through his monthly parcel.]</p>
<p>CONTENTS: The Working Man.&mdash;Cromwell and his Times&mdash;chapters 1, 2, 3, and 4.&mdash;A Picture of Brittany, by Michelet.&mdash;The Physical History of Man&mdash;chapters 1 and 2.&mdash;Christopher Chronicle's Lectures on the Social Arts and Dress in England.&mdash;Ebenezer Elliott, the Corn-law Rhymer.&mdash;The She-Eagle: an unpublished Sketch, by Fredrika Bremer, translated by Mary Howitt.&mdash;The Freehold Land Movement&mdash;chapters 1 and 2: a Dialogue between two Working Men, Samuel Styles and John Giles.&mdash;The Man with One Garment.&mdash;Family Pictures.&mdash;Household Economy: Letters by Martha Makepiece: Family Receipts.&mdash;Scientific Miscellany.&mdash;Weekly Calendar&mdash;Results of Reading and Thought, by a Literary Sexagenarian.&mdash;Diggings: &ldquo;Small, but Golden, Grains.&rdquo;&mdash;Notices to Correspondents, &amp;c.&mdash;The Wood-Nook Wells, or Neighbours' Quarrels, an original and interesting Story, by Mary Howitt.&mdash;The Good Words of Mr. Hagenmaier.&mdash;The Importance of a Knowledge of the Law.&mdash;English Reformers: Joseph Home.&mdash;Anomalous Taxes.&mdash;Out of your Inside.&mdash;Rates and Taxes.&mdash;Juvenile Cabinets.&mdash;Humourous Selections, &amp;c.&mdash;Charlemagne.&mdash;The Philosophical Cobbler.&mdash;Life is Onward.&mdash;An American's Opinion of English Reforms and Reformers.&mdash;Wit and Pleasantry.&mdash;The School-room, No. 1.&mdash;The Freedom of the Mind.&mdash;On Labour, translated from the French of M. Thiers.&mdash;Waghorn, the Overland Pioneer.&mdash;The Laws relating to Masters and Workmen.&mdash;The School-room, No. 2, &amp;c.</p>
<closer>Published at 335, Strand, London; J. MENZIES, Edinburgh; GALLIE, Glasgow; and all Booksellers throughout the United Kingdom.</closer>
<trailer>The WORKING MAN'S FRIEND and FAMILY INSTRUCTOR is published weekly, 32 pages, crown 8vo, price One Penny, or in monthly parts, four numbers, 4&frac12;d.; five numbers, 5&frac12;d.</trailer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<opener>11, BOUVERIE STREET.<lb/><hi rend="italics">MESSRS. BRADBURY &amp; EVANS beg to announce that in MARCH NEXT</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">will be published, PRICE TWOPENCE,</hi>
<lb/> THE FIRST NUMBER OF</opener><head>A NEW WEEKLY MISCELLANY <lb/> Of General Literature.</head>
<p>Conducted by Mr. CHARLES DICKENS; <lb/> Designed for the Entertainment and Instruction of all Classes of Readers, and to help in the <lb/> Discussion of the most Important Social Questions of the Time.</p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW WORK ON GARDENING AND BOTANY.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st of March will be published, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., No. I. of</hi> <lb/> PAXTON'S FLOWER GARDEN, <lb/> EDITED BY DR. LINDLEY AND JOSEPH PAXTON.</p>
<p>AND ILLUSTRATED BY HIGHLY FINISHED PLATES AND WOODCUTS.</p>
<p>This Work, for which Monsieur CONSTANS, a French Botanical Draughtsman of great taste and skill, and a pupil of Mons. Decaisne, has been expressly engaged, will be confined to the proper business of an illustrated book, namely the representation and description of all new plants which may appear in gardens. The species which are of most importance will be illustrated by coloured plates, one species or genus only to a plate, with a leaf or more of letter-press, explaining the principal scientific and horticultural facts which belong to each plant. The species of less importance will be treated of more briefly, and will be illustrated when necessary by copious woodcuts and vignettes. The object, in short, will be to combine Scientific Botany with Gardening, and exact delineations of plants with pictorial effect. It is believed that by such means this periodical will not only be indispensable to the BOTANIST and GARDENER, but be also a mine of invaluable hints by which the ARTIST and MANUFACTURER will be able to profit.</p>
<p>It is not intended to admit any other kind of matter than such as is now described. All special treatises on cultivation, and all disquisitions respecting subjects incidental to gardening will be transferred to the <hi rend="italics">Gardeners Chronicle</hi> and similar periodicals, in which there is ample space for such discussions, and to which they have now become better adapted than to a pictorial work.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>NEW PERIODICAL.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Just published, to be continued Monthly, price Half-a-Crown, Illustrated with Five beautifully</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Coloured Plates, Part I. of</hi>
<lb/> THE <lb/> GARDENERS' MAGAZINE OF BOTANY, <lb/> HORTICULTURE, FLORICULTURE, AND NATURAL SCIENCE.</p>
<list>
<head>CONDUCTED BY</head><item>THOMAS MOORE, F.B.S., Curator of the Botanic Garden of the Society of Apothecaries, Chelsea.</item>
<item>WILLIAM P. AYRES, C.M.H.S., Brooklands, Blackheath, Kent.</item>
</list><list>
<head>ASSISTED</head><item>In BOTANY, by ARTHUR HENFREY, Esq., F.L.S., Lecturer on. Botany at St. George's Hospital.</item>
<item>In ENTOMOLOGY, by J. O. WESTWOOD, Esq., F.L.S.</item>
<item>In NATURAL SCIENCE, by J. STEVENSON BUSHNAN, Esq., M.D.</item>
<item>And in FLORICULTURE, by Mr. BARNES, Stowmarket, assisted by the ablest Writers of the day.</item>
</list><p>This Work is intended to be a Guide to the Practical Gardener, and a Companion to Lady or Gentlemen Amateurs; it will furnish instructions in the art of designing, laying out, selecting, and planting gardens and pleasure grounds; in the erection and heating of horticultural buildings; in the application of scientific principles to the art of cultivation, and every other subject connected with the general management of the garden, combined with descriptions of all new Popular Flowers, Fruits, and Vegetables.</p>
<div3>
<head>MODE OF PUBLICATION.</head>
<p>This work will be published every Thursday morning (for Saturday), stitched in a neat wrapper. Each number will consist of eight pages of elegantly printed letterpress; illustrated, when necessary, with Engravings on Wood, in the best style of art, and a separate Plate, carefully drawn by a competent artist, and coloured after nature.</p>
<p>When there are only four Saturdays in the month, a Supplemental Number will be issued, which will comprise an entire treatise on some kindred subject connected with the objects of the Publication, and a coloured Plate, illustrative either of Florists' Flowers, Fruits, or Insects destructive to plants.</p>
<p>Thus, in each month, will be issued Five Sixpenny Numbers, which will be stitched together to form a Monthly Part, price Half-a-Crown.</p>
<closer>WM. S. ORR &amp; Co., Amen Corner, Paternoster Row.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>EXHIBITION OF THE WORKS OF INDUSTRY OF <lb/> ALL NATIONS, 1851.</head>
<p>The COMMISSIONERS appointed by HER MAJESTY for the promotion of the EXHIBITION of THE WORKS of INDUSTRY of ALL NATIONS, to be holden in the year 1851, hereby give notice:&mdash;</p>
<p>That the Exhibition is intended to take place in London in the early part of the year 1851.</p>
<p>That it will be divided generally into the following Sections:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>1. Raw materials and produce, illustrative of the natural productions on which human industry is employed.</item>
<item>2. Machinery for Agricultural, Manufacturing, Engineering, and other purposes, and Mechanical Inventions, illustrative of the agents which human ingenuity brings to bear upon the products of nature.</item>
<item>3. Manufactures, illustrative of the result produced by the operation of human industry upon natural produce.</item>
<item>4. Sculpture, Models, and the plastic Art generally, illustrative of the taste and skill displayed in such application of human industry.</item>
</list>
<p>That the productions of All Nations will be admitted to the Exhibition.</p>
<p>That due notice will be given as to any articles or classes of articles, which it may be found necessary to exclude from the Exhibition on account of their size, the impossibility of preserving them, or for other reasons.</p>
<p>That the conditions and regulations under which articles are to be admitted will be published hereafter.</p>
<p>That Subscriptions and Donations for the purpose of the Exhibition will be received by the Treasurers of the Commission, (A. K. Barclay, Esq.; W. Cotton, Esq.; Sir J. W. Lubbock. Bart.; S. M. Peto. Esq.; and Baron Lionel de Rothschild,) and may be paid to their account at the Bank of England, or through the hands of any London or Country Banker who may be willing to take charge of the same.</p>
<p>That the Commissioners will undertake the absolute control over the expenditure of all money that may come into the hands of their Treasurers, and will cause it to be expended in such manner as may seem to them best calculated to promote the objects of the Exhibition.</p>
<p>By Order of the Commissioners.</p>
<p>J. SCOTT RUSSELL <lb/> STAFFORD H. NORTHCOTE <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Secretaries.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">This day is published, price Fourteen Pence, Part I. of</hi></opener><head>THE LADIES' COMPANION <lb/> At Home and Abroad.</head>
<p>EDITED BY MRS. LOUDON.</p>
<p>ASSISTED BY THE MOST EMINENT WRITERS AND ARTISTS.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>CONTENTS OF PART I.</head>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. I.</head>
<item>Red Riding Hood's Doll.</item>
<item>The Little Girl's Lament. By DORA GREENWELL.</item>
<item>The Work-Basket. With Ten Illustrations.</item>
<item>Dropping in to Tea; or, Household Troubles. From Sad Experience.</item>
<item>New Year Festivals and Commemorations.</item>
<item>Illustration.&mdash;Sculptures from Nineveh.</item>
<item>A Few Words about Governesses. By TOM TAYLOR, Esq.</item>
<item>Christmas Day in the Bush. By MARK LEMON.</item>
<item>Letters on the Chemistry of Every Day Life. By EDWARD SOLLY, F.R.S.</item>
<item>Dress and Fashion. With an Illustration.</item>
<item>Play-Hours.&mdash;The &ldquo;What-Not.&rdquo;&mdash;My Letter-Bag.</item>
<item>Address by the EDITOR.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. II.</head>
<item>A Thimble-full of Romance. By RED RIDING HOOD.</item>
<item>'Tis Better Not to Know. Song. by SAMUEL LOVER.</item>
<item>Music as an Accomplishment. By G. HOGARTH.</item>
<item>Fancy Costume. With an Illustration.</item>
<item>On the Influence of Female Taste. By J. W. L. With Five Illustrations.</item>
<item>Crossing the Ferry, (From the German of Uhland). By DORA GREENWELL.</item>
<item>Illustration.&mdash;The Infant St. John.</item>
<item>A Few Words about Governesses. By T. TAYLOR.</item>
<item>Letters on Physical Geography. BY PROFESSOR ANSTED.</item>
<item>Scientific Mode of Cooking Meat, (taken from Liebig). By J. W. L.</item>
<item>New Year's Day in Scotland.</item>
<item>Shakspeare-Studies of Woman. BY MARY COWDEN CLARKE.</item>
<item>The Work-Basket&mdash;La Frivolit&eacute;. Illustrations.</item>
<item>Dress and Fashion. Illustrated.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. III.</head>
<item>A Ballad of King Ren&eacute;. With an Illustration.</item>
<item>&ldquo;Angelina's Fainted!&rdquo; BY RED RIDING HOOD.</item>
<item>Letters on Physical Geography. By PROFESSOR ANSTED.</item>
<item>The Life of Caroline Pichler. By MRS. PERCY SINNETT.</item>
<item>Illustration.&mdash;The Manuscript Room.</item>
<item>What will Mrs. Grundy Say? By HORACE MAYHEW.</item>
<item>Scientific Mode of Roasting Meat, and of Preparing Stews and Soups, (taken from Leibig). By J. W. L.</item>
<item>The Work-Basket. With Illustrations.</item>
<item>Dress and Fashion. With numerous Illustrations.</item>
<item>My Receipt Book. By MISS ACTON.</item>
<item>Play-Hours.&mdash;The &ldquo;What Not.&rdquo;&mdash;My Letter-Bag.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. IV.</head>
<item>A Moral for Doctors' Commons. By RED RIDING HOOD.</item>
<item>Letters on the Chemistry of Every Day Life.&mdash;Fires. By EDWARD SOLLY, F.R.S.</item>
<item>On the Cultivation of Female Taste. By J.W.L. With Illustrations.</item>
<item>Chimes. By FLORENCE WILSON.</item>
<item>Window and Balcony Gardens. By J. W. L. With Illustrations.</item>
<item>A Few Words about Governesses. By TOM TAYLOR, Esq.</item>
<item>Letters of the Ladies of England. By PETER CUNNINGHAM, Esq.</item>
<item>Illustration.&mdash;Views in New Zealand.</item>
<item>Dress and Fashion. With Illustrations.</item>
<item>The Work Basket. With Illustrations.</item>
<item>Play-Hours.&mdash;The &ldquo;What Not.&rdquo;&mdash;My Letter-Bag.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. V.</head>
<item>The Fire-side Fairy.&mdash;Hob's First Visit.</item>
<item>To a Friend on her Birthday. By DORA GREENWELL.</item>
<item>Shakspeare-Studies of Woman.&mdash;No. II. By MARY COWDEN CLARKE.</item>
<item>Lessons in the School of Life. By MRS. JAMES WHITTLE. With an Illustration.</item>
<item>Winter Gardens. By J. W. L. With an Illustration.</item>
<item>Household Philosophy &mdash; Letters on Diet. By Dr. LANKESTER.</item>
<item>Letters on Physical Geography. By PROFESSOR ANSTED.</item>
<item>Illustration.&mdash;The Babes in the Wood.</item>
<item>The School Room&mdash;Cultivation of the Voice. By F. ROMER.</item>
<item>The Dressing-Room&mdash;The Boudoir&mdash;The Work-Basket. With numerous Illustrations.</item>
<item>Play-Hours.&mdash;The &ldquo;What-Not.&rdquo;&mdash;My Letter-Bag.</item>
<item><hi rend="italics">Nos. III. and IV. of the Stamped Edition, being out of print, parties wishing to procure complete Sets, may obtain UNSTAMPED COPIES from any Bookseller.</hi></item>
</list>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
<div4 type="section">
<head>MORNING CHRONICLE.</head>
<p>&ldquo;The object of it is to afford amusement and instruction to those to whom it is dedicated. It contains a number of light agreeable tales and anecdotes written in a style calculated to make them popular. There are also a variety of well-executed pictorial illustrations.&rdquo;</p>
</div4>
<div4 type="section">
<head>EXAMINER.</head>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Loudon's <hi rend="italics">Ladies' Companion,</hi> a new weekly periodical addressed chiefly to ladies. The contents of the first number are not only lively and varied, but have a generally instructive and practical tone; and it is printed and illustrated with much elegance and taste. The undertaking appears to be of excellent promise.&rdquo;</p>
</div4>
<div4 type="section">
<head>SPECTATOR.</head>
<p>&ldquo;A handsome-looking quarto journal, containing about as much type as the literary weeklies that of yore were published at eightpence: while Mrs. Loudon offers a better-looking paper with woodcuts for threepence. Her papers in the present number are all original; but reviews of books, appropriate to the objects of the journal, are to appear hereafter. The objects seem to combine the <hi rend="italics">utile</hi> in matter with the <hi rend="italics">dulce</hi> in mode. &lsquo;Red Riding Hood's Doll&rsquo; is a pleasant little fairy tale, recommendatory of Mr. Sidney Herbert's emigration plan, and descriptive of the distresses of women in London; the ideas well embodied, the story well told, both in the reality and the fancy, and closing with an available moral for those who have fifteen pounds, or can only subscribe their mite towards it. The &lsquo;Work-Basket,&rsquo; illustrated by plates, gives a clear and lively account of a new style of ladies' work now fashionable in Paris. &lsquo;Mornings in the British Museum, No. I.&rsquo; illustrates both by words and wood-cuts the Assyrian sculptures of Dr. Layard. &lsquo;Tom Taylor, Esq.,&rsquo; begins a series of sensible papers on Governesses, in which, without losing sight of the <hi rend="italics">feeling</hi> of the subject, something is said about qualification and the fair claims of parents. There are also notices and cuts on the &lsquo;Fashions,&rsquo; several pieces of Poetry, the commencement of a series of papers on the Chemistry of every-day life, and a variety of Miscellanea, besides an explanatory leader from the Editor.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, Bouverie Street, and Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</closer>
</div4>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>Illustrated Works for Presents.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">This day is published, in a handsome quarto volume, price</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>MANNERS AND CVSTOMS OF YE ENGLYSHE <lb/> In 1849.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">BY RICHARD DOYLE.</hi></p>
<p>TOGETHER WITH SOME EXTRACTS FROM <lb/> MR. PIPS HIS DIARY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Contributed by PERCIVAL LEIGH.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This day is published, in a Series of Etchings on Steel, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. plain,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. coloured,</hi>
<lb/> &ldquo;YOUNG TROUBLESOME;&rdquo; OR, MASTER JACKY'S <lb/> HOLIDAYS.</p>
<p>From the Blessed Moment of his leaving School, to the identical Moment of his going back again.</p>
<p>SHOWING HOW THERE NEVER WAS SUCH A BOY AS THAT BOY,</p>
<p>DESIGNED AND ETCHED BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p>THE RISING GENERATION.</p>
<p>BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p>A Series of Coloured Drawings. Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each separately.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</p>
<p>A Fairy Tale for Little People.</p>
<p>By MARK LEMON.</p>
<p>WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This book is pretty in every sense of the word. It is a well-conducted legend, and one which children will like to hear many times.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
<p>Works by DR. LINDLEY.</p>
<p>SCHOOL BOTANY; or, THE RUDIMENTS OF BOTANICAL SCIENCE. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> half-bound.</p>
<p>ELEMENTS OF BOTANY (THE), STRUCTURAL AND PHYSIOLOGICAL, with a Copious Glossary of Terms. Fifth Edition. 8vo. Price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">N.B.&mdash;The Glossary may be had separately, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>VEGETABLE KINGDOM (THE); or, THE STRUCTURE, CLASSIFICATION, AND USES OF PLANTS. Illustrated upon the Natural System. Second Edition, with Additional Genera. Price 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>MEDICAL AND OECONOMICAL BOTANY; completing the Elements of Botany, Structural, Physiological, and Medical. 8vo. Price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>MACREADY'S EDITION OF POPE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Price</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., cloth,</hi>
<lb/> THE POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</p>
<p>REVISED AND ARRANGED EXPRESSLY FOR YOUNG PERSONS AND SCHOOLS.</p>
<p>BY W. C. MACREADY.</p>
<closer>LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, Bouverie-street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>Works by Mr. Charles Dickens.</head>
<p>I. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Complete in One thick Volume</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s. in cloth, or</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. half-bound.</hi></p>
<p>DOMBEY AND SON.</p>
<p>WITH FORTY ILLUSTRATIONS ON STEEL, BY H. K. BROWNE.</p>
<p>II. <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">In One Volume demy</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s., uniform with &ldquo;The Pickwick Papers.&rdquo;</hi></p>
<p>THE LIFE &amp; ADVENTURES OF OLIVER TWIST.</p>
<p>This Edition has been carefully corrected by the Author throughout, and contains the whole of the <lb/> Original Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p>
<p>III. <lb/> PICTURES FROM ITALY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Second Edition. Fcp.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>MR. DICKENS'S CHRISTMAS BOOKS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo. Price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound in cloth, with gilt edges.</hi></p>
<p>THE ILLUSTRATIONS BY D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEECH, <lb/> JOHN TENNIEL, AND RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<list>
<item>A Christmas Carol. In Prose.</item>
<item>The Chimes. A Goblin Story of some Bells that rang an Old Year Out, and a New Year in.</item>
<item>The Battle of Life. A Love Story.</item>
<item>The Cricket on the Hearth. A Fairy Tale of Home.</item>
<item>The Haunted Man and the Ghost's Bargain.</item>
</list><closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FORSTER'S LIFE OF GOLDSMITH.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In One Large Volume,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s., with Forty Illustrations on Wood, from designs by</hi>
<lb/> STANFIELD, MACLISE, LEECH, DOYLE, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> HAMERTON, <lb/> THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF <lb/> OLIVER GOLDSMITH.</p>
<p>BY JOHN FORSTER, <lb/> Of the Inner Temple, Barrister, Author of &ldquo;Lives of Statesmen of the Commonwealth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A biography executed with a spirit, a feeling, a grace, and an eloquence, that leave nothing to be desired. Indeed, it would have been presumption in me to undertake the subject after it had been thus felicitously treated, did I not stand committed by my previous sketch.&rdquo;</p>
<p>WASHINGTON IRVING'S <hi rend="italics">Preface to his Life of Goldsmith.</hi></p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET; AND CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In two handsome Volumes, beautifully printed in medium</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 32<hi rend="italics">s. cloth,</hi></opener><head>THE WORKS OF <lb/> WALTER SAVAGE LANDOR.</head>
<list>
<head>INCLUDING</head><item>The Imaginary Conversations, with a New and Original Series.</item>
<item>Pericles and Aspasia.</item>
<item>Examination of Shakspeare.</item>
<item>Pentameron of Boccaccio and Petrarca.</item>
<item>Hellenies (now for the first time published.) Tragedies, and poems.</item>
</list><p>With many large Additions throughout, and the Author's last corrections.</p>
<closer>LONDON: EDWARD MOXON, DOVER STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Published every Saturday, price Threepence, or Stamped for Post, Fourpence,</hi></opener><head>PUNCH;</head><p>Or, the London Charibari.</p>
<p>Illustrated with One Large Engraving, and from Twelve to Twenty <lb/> smaller ones.</p>
<p>A PART IS PUBLISHED EVERY MONTH, AND A VOLUME EVERY SIX MONTHS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Seventeen Volumes are already Published, and always kept on Sale, as well as all Back Numbers and Parts.</hi></p>
<p>For the convenience of persons wishing to possess complete sets of this popular work, AN EDITION IS PUBLISHED OF THE FIRST FOURTEEN VOLUMES, HANDSOMELY BOUND IN SEVEN, WITH GILT EDGES, PRICE 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and parties possessing copies of this Edition may purchase the Seventh Volume (comprising volumes 13 and 14) uniformly bound, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> These may be procured through any bookseller.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; Stamped,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> PUNCH'S ALMANACK FOR 1850.</p>
<p>Profusely Illustrated by JOHN LEECH and RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p>PUNCH'S ALMANACKS <lb/> For the Eight preceding Years have been collected, and are published in a handsome volume, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>Works Published by the Writers and Artists of Punch.</head>
<p>PUNCH'S POCKET-BOOK for 1850. With a Coloured Frontispiece on Steel, and many other Illustrations by JOHN LEECH, RICHARD DOVLE, and H. K. BROWNE. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> roan, gilt edges.</p>
<p>MANNERS AND CVSTOMS OF YE ENGLYSHE IN 1849. By RICHARD DOYLE. Together with some Extracts from Mr. PIPS HIS DIARY. Contributed by PERCIVAL LEIGH. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;YOUNG TROUBLESOME;&rdquo; OR, MASTER JACKY'S HOLIDAYS. In a Series of Etchings on Steel. Designed and Etched by JOHN LEECH. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> plain, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> coloured.</p>
<p>THE RISING GENERATION. By JOHN LEECH. A Series of Coloured Drawings. Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each, separately.</p>
<p>A MAN, MADE OF MONEY. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Post 8vo, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>MRS. CAUDLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>PUNCH'S COMPLETE LETTER WRITER. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>PUNCH'S LETTERS TO HIS SON. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE STORY OF A FEATHER. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>PENDENNIS (THE HISTORY OF). By W. M. THACKERAY. In course of publication in Shilling Numbers.</p>
<p>Volume I., price 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth, is now ready.</p>
<p>VANITY FAIR. By W. M. THACKERAY. 8vo, 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth; 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> half-bound morocco.</p>
<p>THE GREAT HOGGARTY DIAMOND. By W. M. THACKERAY. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE BOOK OF SNOBS. By W. M. THACKERAY. With Sixty Illustrations by the Author. In small 8vo, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE COMIC HISTORY OF ENGLAND. By G. A. A'BECKETT. Two vols. 8vo, price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth. With 20 Coloured Illustrations and numerous Woodcuts, by JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p>THE COMIC BLACKSTONE. By G. A. A'BECKETT. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<closer>PUNCH OFFICE, 85, FLEET STREET.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="9" id="p9"/>
<head>ADVENTURES OF A MEDICAL STUDENT.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Third Edition, post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>ADVENTURES OF A MEDICAL STUDENT.</p>
<p>BY ROBERT DOUGLAS, SURGEON, ROYAL NAVY.</p>
<p>WITH A MEMOIR OF THE LIFE OF THE AUTHOR.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There are few who read one of these stories that will not go on through the whole; and we can promise those who take up this volume, much pleasant reading, with passages of great power, and scenes of thrilling interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Daily News.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;These tales frequently exhibit force and power. The author is fond of the marvellous and terrible, and sometimes deals with his materials with novel effect.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We cannot imagine more delightful reading than this volume.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Weekly Chronicle.</hi></p>
<closer>London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co., 85, Queen Street, 7 Doors from Cheapside.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Cheap Re-issue of Mr. Ainsworth's <lb/> Works.</head>
<p>This day is published, <lb/> CRICHTON, <lb/> Complete in one vol., price 1s. boards, or 1s. 6d. cloth, <lb/> Now ready, <lb/> ROOKWOOD, <lb/> Complete, price 1s. boards, or 1s. 6d. cloth.</p>
<p>Also, <lb/> WINDSOR CASTLE, <lb/> Complete, price 1s. boards, or 1s. 6d. cloth, <lb/> London: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, Strand.</p>
<p>Sold by all Booksellers, Newsmen, and at all <lb/> Railway Stations.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Seventh edition, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or with 30 Maps on <lb/> steel, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head>A SCHOOL GEOGRAPHY.</head>
<p>BY JAMES CORNWELL, PH.D.</p>
<p>Also by the same, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> plain, or 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> coloured, <lb/> A SCHOOL ATLAS.</p>
<p>Consisting of 30 beautifully executed maps on steel, <lb/> in which is found every place mentioned in the <lb/> Author's &ldquo;School Geography.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL &amp; Co.; HAMILTON, <lb/> ADAMS &amp; Co.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Now ready.<lb/>New edition for 1850: thoroughly revised and corrected <lb/> from the first article to the last.</opener>
<head>PEERAGE, BARONETAGE, KNIGHTAGE, &amp;c., for 1850 (Tenth Year);</head><p>by CHARLES R. Don, Esq., Author of &ldquo;The Parliamentary Companion,&rdquo; &amp;c. Foolscap 8vo, handsomely bound in cloth, gilt, price 10s. 6d.</p>
<closer>WHITTAKER &amp; Co., Ave-Maria-lane.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Now ready, Second and cheaper Edition, cloth gilt, <lb/> 2s. 6d., or free by post, 3s.,</opener>
<head>THE ART OF CONVERSATION.</head>
<p>By Captain ORLANDO SABERTASH.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As far as conversation can be taught by a book, this is the book to teach it.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Argus.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The volume overflows with humour, good sense, and good advice.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette.</hi></p>
<closer>London: T. BOSWORTH, 215, Regent Street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just published, in 1 vol. 8vo, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head>HOMoeEOPATHY IN ACUTE DISEASES,</head><p>by STEPHEN YELDHAM. M.R.C.S.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A Book for the people.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Albion.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The best that has appeared on Homoeopathy for a long time past.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Brit. Jour. Homoeopathy.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Scientifically interesting and <hi rend="italics">practically useful.</hi>&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Weekly Times.</hi></p>
<closer>BAILLIERE, REGENT ST.; AYLOTT &amp; Co., 8, PATERNOSTER <lb/> ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES.&mdash;</head><p>A CERTAIN REMEDY for disorders of the Pulmonary Organs&mdash;in Difficulty of Breathing&mdash;in Redundancy of Phlegm&mdash;in Incipient Consumption (of which Cough is the most positive indication)&mdash;they are of unerring efficacy. In Asthma and in Winter Cough, they have never been known to fail.&mdash;Prepared and sold in boxes, 1s. 1&frac12;d., and tins, 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 10s. 6d. each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Churchyard, London. Sold retail by all druggists.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Important to Public Speakers and Singers.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;St. Paul's Cathedral, 20th Nov., 1849.</p>
<p>&ldquo;SIR,&mdash;I have much pleasure in recommending your Lozenges to those who may be distressed with Hoarseness. They have afforded me relief on several occasions when scarcely able to sing from the effects of Catarrh. I think they would be very useful to Clergymen, Barristers, and Public Orators.&mdash;I am, Sir, yours faithfully, THOMAS FRANCIS, Vicar-Choral.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To Mr. Keating.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="10" id="p10"/>
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head><p>IN a Climate so changeable as that of England, an Umbrella is indispensable, and it is consequently advisable, where Economy is consulted, that it should be made of a material that is the most durable.</p>
<p>The experience of the last two years justifies the Patentees of the ALPACA UMBRELLA in asserting, that whilst it can scarcely be distinguished from Silk, it will wear much longer, and cost only half the price.</p>
<p>Several of the largest houses in the trade being licensed, it may be procured of most respectable Umbrella Dealers in the Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A very extensive Assortment of Silk Umbrellas at all prices, from</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. to</hi> 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, 140, Regent-street, <lb/> 94, Fleet-street, <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</p>
<p>Warehouse, 75, Cheapside.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p>and all other Medicines of a nauseous character, may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p>
<p>The recent discovery that the low priced Gelatine Capsules contain a compound of train and other oils, and in many cases no Copaiba whatever, renders it important that the public should be made aware that the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES are <hi rend="italics">guaranteed</hi> to contain <hi rend="italics">genuine Copaiba only.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>AN EXCELLENT cure of a DISORDER in the STOMACH effected by HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>A Lady, an intimate friend of the family of General Rosas, Governor of the Republic of La Plata, declares that she was lately cured of a disorder in the stomach, and restored to perfect health, by the use of this admirable remedy. She had consulted the most eminent physicians in the country, but had not been able to obtain any relief from the complaint that was killing her by inches until she took Holloway's Pills. John Eastman, Esq., an eminent merchant of Buenos Ayres, communicated these particulars to Professor HOLLOWAY in a letter dated the 4th September, 1849.&mdash;Sold by all druggists, and at Professor HOLLOWAY's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SILVER SUPERSEDED <lb/> By RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK'S <lb/> PURIFIED NICKEL SILVER.</head>
<p>WARRANTED THE PUREST AND WHITEST METAL IN EXISTENCE, EXCEPT STERLING SILVER <lb/> AND AT ONE TWELFTH THE COST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell>
<cell> Strongest Fiddle. </cell>
<cell> Thread Pattern. </cell>
<cell> King's Pattern </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 19<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons and Forks </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Cruet Frames, with Rich Cut Glasses, from 22<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Table Candlesticks, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per Pair. Tea Sets, and every article for the Table, at proportionate prices. On receipt of 10 Postage Stamps a sample spoon will be sent free.</p>
<p>RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK also beg to call attention to their extensive Stock of NICKEL SILVER WARES, ELECTRO-PLATED by Messrs. ELKINGTON &amp; Co.'s PATENT PROCESS, WHICH CANNOT BE DISTINGUISHED FROM STERLING SILVER.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="4">
<head>BALANCE IVORY KNIVES.</head>
<row>
<cell> 3&frac12; inch Handles, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 4&frac58; inch Handles </cell>
<cell> 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3&frac34; inch Handles </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Steel Blades, Nickel Handles </cell>
<cell> 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Good Kitchen Knives and Forks, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per dozen; Fenders and Fire Irons, and every article in Furnishing Ironmongery, the greatest variety in London, at Prices that defy competition. Bronzed Scroll Fenders, with Steel Bar, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Their Illustrated Book of Prices may be had gratis, or sent post free. All Orders above 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> sent free per rail within 200 miles.</p>
<closer>RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK <lb/> 336, STRAND, <lb/> OPPOSITE SOMERSET HOUSE.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="11" id="p11"/>
<head>Warren's Sketches of Character.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HANDWRITING.</p>
<p>Specimens of Writing, with an enclosure of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's age to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND's newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Co.'s. <lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES, <lb/> &amp; NE PLUS ULTRA PINS, <lb/> WITH PERFECT SOLID HEADS.</p>
<p>Sold by every Draper, &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="12" id="p12"/>
<head>NUMBER ONE, SAINT PAUL'S CHURCH YARD.</head>
<p>THE present high PRICES OF COFFEE, and the late rise in the value of it, unprecedented for the last few years, require some explanation, in order to be understood by consumers.</p>
<p>The Coffee plant does not produce Coffee until the fourth year after it has been planted. It remains in bearing about four years, after which time it becomes useless. It is therefore necessary, in order to keep up a regular supply, that Coffee growers should have new plantations regularly coming into bearing, to make up for the deficiency of the old plantations that are regularly ceasing production. The low prices for Coffee that ruled from 1844 to 1849 in this country, but more particularly on the Continent, were not remunerative to the growers, in consequence of which they ceased planting Coffee, and employed their land for other purposes. The effect is now being felt. The produce of the coming year, as anticipated, will not equal, by 72,060 tons, the consumption of 1849. Supposing the average of the consumption of 1849 to be maintained for twelve months longer, not only the produce of the year, but all the present stocks in the world, by the end of that time, would be consumed. Prices have therefore risen very considerably, and it is impossible to say how much higher they will rise, in order to reduce consumption to the amount of the anticipated supply. It is satisfactory to know that our own colonies will continue to export as largely as ever. The estates that have ceased to grow Coffee are principally in Java, and in those countries that supply the foreign markets, where Coffee is consumed much more extensively than in this country. The large purchases for exportation to the continent made in our own market will account for the extent to which it is affected. It is gratifying, however, to notice that these shipments have been chiefly confined to common descriptions, and consequently, that fine kinds have not risen in proportion, whilst the quotations for the finest sorts have scarcely suffered alteration. The subjoined statement shows the anticipated consumption of Coffee in the world during the year 1849, and the anticipated supply for 1850:&mdash;</p>
<div3>
<head>COFFEE.</head>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>ESTIMATED EXPORTABLE PRODUCTION OF 1850.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Tons. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brazils (1,200,000 bags of 160 lbs. each) </cell>
<cell> 85,700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Java and Sumatra (580,000 piculs of 130 lbs. each) </cell>
<cell> 32,640 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Manilla </cell>
<cell> 1,300 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Mocha and Madras (exports to Europe, 12,000 bags and bales) </cell>
<cell> 1,100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dutch West Indies </cell>
<cell> 700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> La Guayra </cell>
<cell> 11,200 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Costa Rica (exports this year 2,200) </cell>
<cell> 3,600 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Porto Rico (official returns for 1847&mdash;6,000) </cell>
<cell> 6,700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cuba </cell>
<cell> 8,500 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Jamaica </cell>
<cell> 1,300 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ceylon (this year 16,500) </cell>
<cell> 18,700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> St. Domingo </cell>
<cell> 12,500 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Total production </cell>
<cell> Tons 184,940 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table>
<head>ESTIMATED CONSUMPTION OF 1849.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Tons. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Great Britain </cell>
<cell> 15,600 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Holland and Belgium </cell>
<cell> 39,300 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> France </cell>
<cell> 15,600 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> German Customs' Union </cell>
<cell> 41,500 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Other German Countries, not included in the Union, and Austria </cell>
<cell> 24,500 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Switzerland </cell>
<cell> 6,700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Mediterranean Countries </cell>
<cell> 17,900 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Russia </cell>
<cell> 3,600 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Sweden and Denmark </cell>
<cell> 3,900 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spain and Portugal </cell>
<cell> 6,700 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cape of Good Hope </cell>
<cell> 1,300 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> United States of America </cell>
<cell> 75,900 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Total consumption </cell>
<cell> Tons 257,500 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>DAKIN AND COMPY.'s PRESENT PRICE LIST.</head>
<p>In addition to the following, DAKIN &amp; COMPANY supply every other description of Coffee imported.</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> Good Ceylon Coffee </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Strong and full-flavoured Coffee </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Strong and fine Coffee </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Very fine and full-flavoured Coffee </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Particularly choice Coffee </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Finest Old Mocha, mellow in ripeness and richness of flavour </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> per Ib. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>In November, 1848, the price of Native Ceylon Coffee (the lowest description fit for consumers in this country) was 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per cwt., or with duty added, 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per Ib. roasted. The present price for the same Coffee is, as quoted in the &ldquo;Public Ledger&rdquo; of this day, 66<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per cwt., or with duty added, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per Ib. roasted. High quotations will be most probably maintained for some time to come. Certain it is that, prices being as they now are, Coffee growers will begin to plant afresh; but, as before stated, new plants produce very little Coffee till they have been planted about four or five years.</p>
<closer>DAKIN &amp; COMPY., Patentees <lb/> FOR ROASTING COFFEE IN SILVER CYLINDERS, <lb/> NUMBER ONE, ST. PAUL'S CHURCHYARD.</closer>
<trailer><hi rend="italics">January</hi> 9, 1850.</trailer>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>


<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">I find Mr. Barkis &ldquo;going out with the tide.&rdquo;</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">We are disturbed in our cookery.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>


<div1 type="chapter">
<pb n="289" id="p289"/>
<head>[THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head>
<div2 type="chapter"><head>CHAPTER XXVIII. <lb/> MR. MICAWBER'S GAUNTLET.</head>
<p>UNTIL the day arrived on which I was to entertain my newly-found old friends, I lived principally on Dora and coffee. In my love-lorn condition, my appetite languished; and I was glad of it, for I felt as though it would have been an act of perfidy towards Dora to have a natural relish for my dinner. The quantity of walking exercise I took, was not in this respect attended with its usual consequence, as the disappointment counteracted the fresh air. I have my doubts, too, founded on the acute experience acquired at this period of my life, whether a sound enjoyment of animal food can develop itself freely in any human subject who is always in torment from tight boots. I think the extremities require to be at peace before the stomach will conduct itself with vigour.</p>
<p>On the occasion of this domestic little party, I did not repeat my former extensive preparations. I merely provided a pair of soles, a small leg of mutton, and a pigeon-pie. Mrs. Crupp broke out into rebellion on my first bashful hint in reference to the cooking of the fish and joint, and said, with a dignified sense of injury, &ldquo;No! No, sir! You will not ask me <sic corr="such">sich</sic> a thing, for you are better acquainted with me than to suppose me capable of doing what I cannot do with ampial satisfaction to my own feelings!&rdquo; But, in the end, a compromise was effected; and Mrs. Crupp consented to achieve this feat, on condition that I dined from home for a fortnight afterwards.</p>
<p>And here I may remark, that what I underwent from Mrs. Crupp, in consequence of the tyranny she established over me, was dreadful. I never was so much afraid of any one. We made a compromise of everything. If I hesitated, she was taken with that wonderful disorder which was always lying in ambush in her system, ready, at the shortest notice, to prey upon her vitals. If I rang the bell impatiently, after half-a-dozen unavailing modest pulls, and she appeared at last&mdash;which was not by any means to be relied upon&mdash;she would appear with a reproachful aspect, sink breathless on a chair near the door, lay her hand upon her nankeen bosom, and become so ill, that I was glad, at any sacrifice of brandy or anything else, to get rid of her. If I objected to having my bed made at five o'clock in the afternoon&mdash;which I <hi rend="italics">do</hi> still think an uncomfortable arrangement&mdash;one motion of her hand towards the same nankeen region of wounded sensibility was enough to make me falter an apology. In short, I would have done anything in an honorable way rather than give Mrs. Crupp offence; and she was the terror of my life.</p>
<p>I bought a second-hand dumb-waiter for this dinner-party, in preference to re-engaging the handy young man; against whom I had conceived a prejudice, in consequence of meeting him in the Strand, one Sunday morning, in a waistcoat remarkably like one of mine, which had been missing
<pb n="290" id="p290"/>
since the former occasion. The &ldquo;young gal&rdquo; was re-engaged; but on the stipulation that she should only bring in the dishes, and then withdraw to the landing-place, beyond the outer door; where a habit of sniffing she had contracted would be lost upon the guests, and where her retiring on the plates would be a physical impossibility.</p>
<p>Having laid in the materials for a bowl of punch, to be compounded by Mr. Micawber; having provided a bottle of lavender-water, two wax candles, a paper of mixed pins, and a pincushion, to assist Mrs. Micawber in her toilette, at my dressing-table; having also caused the fire in my bed-room to be lighted for Mrs. Micawber's convenience; and having laid the cloth with my own hands, I awaited the result with composure.</p>
<p>At the appointed time, my three visitors arrived together. Mr. Micawber with more shirt-collar than usual, and a new ribbon to his eye-glass; Mrs. Micawber with her cap in a whitey-brown paper parcel; Traddles carrying the parcel, and supporting Mrs. Micawber on his arm. They were all delighted with my residence. When I conducted Mrs. Micawber to my dressing-table, and she saw the scale on which it was prepared for her, she was in such raptures, that she called Mr. Micawber to come in and look.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;this is luxurious. This is a way of life which reminds me of the period when I was myself in a state of celibacy, and Mrs. Micawber had not yet been solicited to plight her faith at the Hymeneal altar.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He means, solicited by him, Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber archly. &ldquo;He cannot answer for others.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; returned Mr. Micawber with sudden seriousness, &ldquo;I have no desire to answer for others. I am too well aware that when, in the inscrutable decrees of Fate, you were reserved for me, it is possible you may have been reserved for one, destined, after a protracted struggle, at length to fall a victim to pecuniary involvements of a complicated nature. I understand your allusion, my love. I regret it, but I can bear it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Micawber!&rdquo; exclaimed Mrs. Micawber, in tears. &ldquo;Have I deserved this! I, who never have deserted you; who never <hi rend="italics">will</hi> desert you, Micawber!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My love,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, much affected, &ldquo;you will forgive, and our old and tried friend Copperfield will, I am sure, forgive, the momentary laceration of a wounded spirit, made sensitive by a recent collision with the Minion of Power&mdash;in other words, with a ribald Turncock attached to the water-works&mdash;and will pity, not condemn, its excesses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber then embraced Mrs. Micawber, and pressed my hand; leaving me to infer from this broken allusion that his domestic supply of water had been cut off that afternoon, in consequence of default in the payment of the company's rates.</p>
<p>To divert his thoughts from this melancholy subject, I informed Mr. Micawber that I relied upon him for a bowl of punch, and led him to the lemons. His recent despondency, not to say despair, was gone in a moment. I never saw a man so thoroughly enjoy himself amid the fragrance of lemon-peel and sugar, the odor of burning rum, and the steam of boiling water, as Mr. Micawber did that afternoon. It was
<pb n="291" id="p291"/>
wonderful to see his face shining at us out of a thin cloud of these delicate fumes, as he stirred, and mixed, and tasted, and looked as if he were making, instead of punch, a fortune for his family down to the latest posterity. As to Mrs. Micawber, I don't know whether it was the effect of the cap, or the lavender-water, or the pins, or the fire, or the wax candles, but she came out of my room, comparatively speaking, lovely. And the lark was never gayer than that excellent woman.</p>
<p>I suppose&mdash;I never ventured to inquire, but I suppose&mdash;that Mrs. Crupp, after frying the soles, was taken ill. Because we broke down at that point. The leg of mutton came up very red within, and very pale without: besides having a foreign substance of a gritty nature sprinkled over it, as if it had had a fall into the ashes of that remarkable kitchen fire-place. But we were not in a condition to judge of this fact from the appearance of the gravy, forasmuch as the &ldquo;young gal&rdquo; had dropped it all upon the stairs&mdash;where it remained, by-the-by, in a long train, until it was worn out. The pigeon-pie was not bad, but it was a delusive pie: the crust being like a disappointing head, phrenologically speaking: full of lumps and bumps, with nothing particular underneath. In short, the banquet was such a failure that I should have been quite unhappy&mdash;about the failure, I mean, for I was always unhappy about Dora&mdash;if I had not been relieved by the great good-humour of my company, and by a bright suggestion from Mr. Micawber.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;accidents will occur in the best regulated families; and in families not regulated by that pervading influence which sanctifies while it enhances the&mdash;a&mdash;I would say, in short, by the influence of Woman, in the lofty character of Wife, they may be expected with confidence, and must be borne with philosophy. If you will allow me to take the liberty of remarking that there are few comestibles better, in their way, than a Devil, and that I believe, with a little division of labor, we could accomplish a good one if the young person in attendance could produce a gridiron, I would put it to you, that this little misfortune may be easily repaired.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a gridiron in the pantry, on which my morning rasher of bacon was cooked. We had it in, in a twinkling, and immediately applied ourselves to carrying Mr. Micawber's idea into effect. The division of labor to which he had referred was this:&mdash;Traddles cut the mutton into slices; Mr. Micawber (who could do anything of this sort to perfection) covered them with pepper, mustard, salt, and cayenne; I put them on the gridiron, turned them with a fork, and took them off, under Mr. Micawber's directions; and Mrs. Micawber heated, and continually stirred, some mushroom ketchup in a little saucepan. When we had slices enough done to begin upon, we fell-to, with our sleeves still tucked up at the wrists, more slices sputtering and blazing on the fire, and our attention divided between the mutton on our plates, and the mutton then preparing.</p>
<p>What with the novelty of this cookery, the excellence of it, the bustle of it, the frequent starting up to look after it, the frequent sitting down to dispose of it as the crisp slices came off the gridiron hot and hot, the being so busy, so flushed with the fire, so amused, and in the midst of such a tempting noise and savor, we reduced the leg of mutton to the bone. My own appetite came back miraculously. I am ashamed to
<pb n="292" id="p292"/>
record it, but I really believe I forgot Dora for a little while. I am satisfied that Mr. and Mrs. Micawber could not have enjoyed the feast more if they had sold a bed to provide it. Traddles laughed as heartily, almost the whole time, as he ate and worked. Indeed we all did, all at once; and I dare say there never was a greater success.</p>
<p>We were at the height of our enjoyment, and were all busily engaged, in our several departments, endeavouring to bring the last batch of slices to a state of perfection that should crown the feast, when I was aware of a strange presence in the room, and my eyes encountered those of the staid Littimer, standing hat in hand before me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What 's the matter!&rdquo; I involuntarily asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, sir, I was directed to come in. Is my master not here, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you not seen him, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No; don't you come from him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not immediately so, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did he tell you you would find him here?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not exactly so, sir. But I should think he might be here to-morrow, as he has not been here to-day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is he coming up from Oxford?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg, sir,&rdquo; he returned respectfully, &ldquo;that you will be seated, and allow me to do this.&rdquo; With which he took the fork from my unresisting hand, and bent over the gridiron, as if his whole attention were concentrated on it.</p>
<p>We should not have been much discomposed, I dare say, by the appearance of Steerforth himself, but we became in a moment the meekest of the meek before his respectable serving-man. Mr. Micawber, humming a tune, to show that he was quite at ease, subsided into his chair, with the handle of a hastily-concealed fork sticking out of the bosom of his coat, as if he had stabbed himself. Mrs. Micawber put on her brown gloves, and assumed a genteel languor. Traddles ran his greasy hands through his hair, and stood it bolt upright, and stared in confusion at the table-cloth. As for me, I was a mere infant at the head of my own table; and hardly ventured to glance at the respectable phenomenon, who had come from Heaven knows where, to put my establishment to rights.</p>
<p>Meanwhile he took the mutton off the gridiron, and gravely handed it round. We all took some, but our appreciation of it was gone, and we merely made a show of eating it. As we severally pushed away our plates, he noiselessly removed them, and set on the cheese. He took that off, too, when it was done with; cleared the table; piled everything on the dumb-waiter; gave us our wine-glasses; and, of his own accord, wheeled the dumb-waiter into the pantry. All this was done in a perfect manner, and he never raised his eyes from what he was about. Yet, his very elbows, when he had his back towards me, seemed to teem with the expression of his fixed opinion that I was extremely young.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can I do anything more, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thanked him and said, No; but would he take no dinner himself?</p>
<p>&ldquo;None, I am obliged to you, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Mr. Steerforth coming from Oxford?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="293" id="p293"/>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Mr. Steerforth coming from Oxford?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should imagine that he might be here to-morrow, sir. I rather thought he might have been here to-day, sir. The mistake is mine, no doubt, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you should see him first&mdash;&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you 'll excuse me, sir, I don't think I shall see him first.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In case you do,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;pray say that I am sorry he was not here to-day, as an old schoolfellow of his was here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed, sir!&rdquo; and he divided a bow between me and Traddles, with a glance at the latter.</p>
<p>He was moving softly to the door, when, in a forlorn hope of saying something naturally&mdash;which I never could, to this man&mdash;I said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! Littimer!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you remain long at Yarmouth, that time?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not particularly so, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You saw the boat completed?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir. I remained behind on purpose to see the boat completed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know!&rdquo; He raised his eyes to mine respectfully. &ldquo;Mr. Steerforth has not seen it yet, I suppose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I really can't say, sir. I think&mdash;but I really can't say, sir. I wish you good night, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He comprehended everybody present, in the respectful bow with which he followed these words, and disappeared. My visitors seemed to breathe more freely when he was gone; but my own relief was very great, for besides the constraint, arising from that extraordinary sense of being at a disadvantage which I always had in this man's presence, my conscience had embarrassed me with whispers that I had mistrusted his master, and I could not repress a vague uneasy dread that he might find it out. How was it, having so little in reality to conceal, that I always <hi rend="italics">did</hi> feel as if this man were finding me out?</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber roused me from this reflection, which was blended with a certain remorseful apprehension of seeing Steerforth himself, by bestowing many encomiums on the absent Littimer as a most respectable fellow, and a thoroughly admirable servant. Mr. Micawber, I may remark, had taken his full share of the general bow, and had received it with infinite condescension.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But punch, my dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, tasting it, &ldquo;like time and tide, waits for no man. Ah! it is at the present moment in high flavor. My love, will you give me your opinion?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber pronounced it excellent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then I will drink,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;if my friend Copperfield will permit me to take that social liberty, to the days when my friend Copperfield and myself were younger, and fought our way in the world side by side. I may say, of myself and Copperfield, in words we have sung together before now, that 

<q><lg type="poem"><l>We twa' hae run about the braes</l><l>And pu'd the gowans fine</l></lg></q>
<pb n="294" id="p294"/>

&mdash;in a figurative point of view&mdash;on several occasions. I am not exactly aware,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, with the old roll in his voice, and the old indescribable air of saying something genteel, &ldquo;what gowans may be, but I have no doubt that Copperfield and myself would frequently have taken a pull at them, if it had been feasible.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber, at the then present moment, took a pull at his punch. So we all did: Traddles evidently lost in wondering at what distant time Mr. Micawber and I could possibly have been comrades in the battle of the world.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ahem!&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, clearing his throat, and warming with the punch and with the fire. &ldquo;My dear, another glass?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber said it must be very little, but we couldn't allow that, so it was a glassful.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As we are quite confidential here, Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, sipping her punch, &ldquo;Mr. Traddles being a part of our domesticity, I should much like to have your opinion on Mr. Micawber's prospects. For corn,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber argumentatively, &ldquo;as I have repeatedly said to Mr. Micawber, may be gentlemanly, but it is not remunerative. Commission to the extent of two and ninepence in a fortnight cannot, however limited our ideas, be considered remunerative.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We were all agreed upon that.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, who prided herself on taking a clear view of things, and keeping Mr. Micawber straight by her woman's wisdom, when he might otherwise go a little crooked, &ldquo;then I ask myself this question. If corn is not to be relied upon, what is? Are coals to be relied upon? Not at all. We have turned our attention to that experiment, on the suggestion of my family, and we find it fallacious.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber, leaning back in his chair with his hands in his pockets, eyed us aside, and nodded his head, as much as to say that the case was very clearly put.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The articles of corn and coals,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, still more argumentatively, &ldquo;being equally out of the question, Mr. Copperfield, I naturally look round the world, and say, &lsquo;What is there in which a person of Mr. Micawber's talent is likely to succeed?&rsquo; And I exclude the doing anything on commission, because commission is not a certainty. What is best suited to a person of Mr. Micawber's peculiar temperament, is, I am convinced, a certainty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Traddles and I both expressed, by a feeling murmur, that this great discovery was no doubt true of Mr. Micawber, and that it did him much credit.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I will not conceal from you, my dear Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> have long felt the Brewing business to be particularly adapted to Mr. Micawber. Look at Barclay and Perkins! Look at Truman, Hanbury, and Buxton! It is on that extensive footing that Mr. Micawber, I know from my own knowledge of him, is calculated to shine; and the profits, I am told, are e-NOR&mdash;mous! But if Mr. Micawber cannot get into those firms&mdash;which decline to answer his letters, when he offers his services even in an inferior capacity&mdash;what is the use of dwelling upon that idea? None. I may have a conviction that Mr. Micawber's manners&rdquo;&mdash;</p>
<pb n="295" id="p295"/>
<p>&ldquo;Hem! Really, my dear,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Micawber.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My love, be silent,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, laying her brown glove on his hand. &ldquo;I may have a conviction, Mr. Copperfield, that Mr. Micawber's manners peculiarly qualify him for the Banking business. I may argue within myself, that if <hi rend="italics">I</hi> had a deposit at a banking-house, the manners of Mr. Micawber, as representing that banking-house, would inspire confidence, and must extend the connexion. But if the various banking-houses refuse to avail themselves of Mr. Micawber's abilities, or receive the offer of them with contumely, what is the use of dwelling upon <hi rend="italics">that</hi> idea? None. As to originating a banking-business, I may know that there are members of my family who, if they chose to place their money in Mr. Micawber's hands, might found an establishment of that description. But if they do <hi rend="italics">not</hi> choose to place their money in Mr. Micawber's hands&mdash;which they don't&mdash;what is the use of that? Again I contend that we are no farther advanced than we were before.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I shook my head, and said, &ldquo;Not a bit.&rdquo; Traddles also shook his head, and said, &ldquo;Not a bit.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do I deduce from this?&rdquo; Mrs. Micawber went on to say, still with the same air of putting a case lucidly. &ldquo;What is the conclusion, my dear Mr. Copperfield, to which I am irresistibly brought? Am I wrong in saying, it is clear that we must live?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I answered, &ldquo;Not at all!&rdquo; and Traddles answered, &ldquo;Not at all!&rdquo; and I found myself afterwards sagely adding, alone, that a person must either live or die.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just so,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;It is precisely that. And the fact is, my dear Mr. Copperfield, that we can <hi rend="italics">not</hi> live without something widely different from existing circumstances shortly turning up. Now I am convinced, myself, and this I have pointed out to Mr. Micawber several times of late, that things cannot be expected to turn up of themselves. We must, in a measure, assist to turn them up. I may be wrong, but I have formed that opinion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Both Traddles and I applauded it highly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very well,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;Then what do I recommend? Here is Mr. Micawber, with a variety of qualifications&mdash;with great talent&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really, my love,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray, my dear, allow me to conclude. Here is Mr. Micawber, with a variety of qualifications, with great talent&mdash;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> should say, with genius, but that may be the partiality of a wife&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Traddles and I both murmured &ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And here is Mr. Micawber without any suitable position or employment. Where does that responsibility rest? Clearly on society. Then I would make a fact so disgraceful known, and boldly challenge society to set it right. It appears to me, my dear Mr. Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, forcibly, &ldquo;that what Mr. Micawber has to do, is to throw down the gauntlet to society, and say, in effect, &lsquo;Show me who will take that up. Let the party immediately step forward.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>I ventured to ask Mrs. Micawber how this was to be done.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By advertising,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber&mdash;&ldquo;in all the papers. It appears to me, that what Mr. Micawber has to do, in justice to himself, in justice
<pb n="296" id="p296"/>
to his family, and I will even go so far as to say in justice to society, by which he has been hitherto overlooked, is to advertise in all the papers; to describe himself plainly as so and so, with such and such qualifications, and to put it thus: &lsquo;<hi rend="italics">Now</hi> employ me, on remunerative terms, and address, post-paid, to <hi rend="italics">W. M.,</hi> Post Office, Camden Town.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;This idea of Mrs. Micawber's, my dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, making his shirt-collar meet in front of his chin, and glancing at me sideways, &ldquo;is, in fact, the Leap to which I alluded, when I last had the pleasure of seeing you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Advertising is rather expensive,&rdquo; I remarked, dubiously.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Exactly so!&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, preserving the same logical air. &ldquo;Quite true, my dear Mr. Copperfield! I have made the identical observation to Mr. Micawber. It is for that reason especially, that I think Mr. Micawber ought (as I have already said, in justice to himself, in justice to his family, and in justice to society) to raise a certain sum of money&mdash;on a bill.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber, leaning back in his chair, trifled with his eye-glass, and cast his eyes up at the ceiling; but I thought him observant of Traddles too, who was looking at the fire.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If no member of my family,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;is possessed of sufficient natural feeling to negotiate that bill&mdash;I believe there is a better business-term to express what I mean&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber, with his eyes still cast up at the ceiling, suggested &ldquo;Discount.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To discount that bill,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;then my opinion is, that Mr. Micawber should go into the City, should take that bill into the Money Market, and should dispose of it for what he can get. If the individuals in the Money Market oblige Mr. Micawber to sustain a great sacrifice, that is between themselves and their consciences. I view it, steadily, as an investment. I recommend Mr. Micawber, my dear Mr. Copperfield, to do the same; to regard it as an investment which is sure of return, and to make up his mind to <hi rend="italics">any</hi> sacrifice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt, but I am sure I don't know why, that this was self-denying and devoted in Mrs. Micawber, and I uttered a murmur to that effect. Traddles, who took his tone from me, did likewise, still looking at the fire.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I will not,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, finishing her punch, and gathering her scarf about her shoulders, preparatory to her withdrawal to my bedroom: &ldquo;I will not protract these remarks on the subject of Mr. Micawber's pecuniary affairs. At your fireside, my dear Mr. Copperfield, and in the presence of Mr. Traddles, who, though not so old a friend, is quite one of ourselves, I could not refrain from making you acquainted with the course <hi rend="italics">I</hi> advise Mr. Micawber to take. I feel that the time is arrived when Mr. Micawber should exert himself and&mdash;I will add&mdash;assert himself, and it appears to me that these are the means. I am aware that I am merely a female, and that a masculine judgment is usually considered more competent to the discussion of such questions; still I must not forget that, when I lived at home with my papa and mama, my papa was in the habit of saying, &lsquo;Emma's form is fragile, but her grasp of a subject is inferior to none.&rsquo; That my papa was too partial, I well know; but that he was an observer of character in some degree, my duty and my reason equally forbid me to doubt.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="297" id="p297"/>
<p>With these words, and resisting our entreaties that she would grace the remaining circulation of the punch with her presence, Mrs. Micawber retired to my bed-room. And really I felt that she was a noble woman&mdash;the sort of woman who might have been a Roman matron, and done all manner of heroic things, in times of public trouble.</p>
<p>In the fervor of this impression, I congratulated Mr. Micawber on the treasure he possessed. So did Traddles. Mr. Micawber extended his hand to each of us in succession, and then covered his face with his pocket-handkerchief, which I think had more snuff upon it than he was aware of. He then returned to the punch, in the highest state of exhilaration.</p>
<p>He was full of eloquence. He gave us to understand that in our children we lived again, and that, under the pressure of pecuniary difficulties, any accession to their number was doubly welcome. He said that Mrs. Micawber had latterly had her doubts on this point, but that he had dispelled them, and reassured her. As to her family, they were totally unworthy of her, and their sentiments were utterly indifferent to him, and they might&mdash;I quote his own expression&mdash;go to the Devil.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber then delivered a warm eulogy on Traddles. He said Traddles's was a character, to the steady virtues of which he (Mr. Micawber) could lay no claim, but which, he thanked Heaven, he could admire. He feelingly alluded to the young lady, unknown, whom Traddles had honored with his affection, and who had reciprocated that affection by honoring and blessing Traddles with <hi rend="italics">her</hi> affection. Mr. Micawber pledged her. So did I. Traddles thanked us both, by saying, with a simplicity and honesty I had sense enough to be quite charmed with, &ldquo;I am very much obliged to you indeed. And I do assure you, she's the dearest girl!&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber took an early opportunity, after that, of hinting, with the utmost delicacy and ceremony, at the state of <hi rend="italics">my</hi> affections. Nothing but the serious assurance of his friend Copperfield to the contrary, he observed, could deprive him of the impression that his friend Copperfield loved and was beloved. After feeling very hot and uncomfortable for some time, and after a good deal of blushing, stammering, and denying, I said, having my glass in my hand, &ldquo;Well! I would give them D.!&rdquo; which so excited and gratified Mr. Micawber, that he ran with a glass of punch into my bed-room, in order that Mrs. Micawber might drink D., who drank it with enthusiasm, crying from within, in a shrill voice, &ldquo;Hear, hear! My dear Mr. Copperfield, I am delighted. Hear!&rdquo; and tapping at the wall, by way of applause.</p>
<p>Our conversation, afterwards, took a more worldly turn; Mr. Micawber telling us that he found Camden Town inconvenient, and that the first thing he contemplated doing, when the advertisement should have been the cause of something satisfactory turning up, was to move. He mentioned a terrace at the western end of Oxford Street, fronting Hyde Park, on which he had always had his eye, but which he did not expect to attain immediately, as it would require a large establishment. There would probably be an interval, he explained, in which he should content himself with the upper part of a house, over some respectable place of business,&mdash;say in Piccadilly,&mdash;which would be a cheerful situation for Mrs. Micawber; and where, by throwing out a bow window, or carrying up the roof another story, or making some little alteration of that sort, they might
<pb n="298" id="p298"/>
live, comfortably and reputably, for a few years. Whatever was reserved for him, he expressly said, or wherever his abode might be, we might rely on this&mdash;there would always be a room for Traddles, and a knife and fork for me. We acknowledged his kindness; and he begged us to forgive his having launched into these practical and business-like details, and to excuse it as natural in one who was making entirely new arrangements in life.</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber, tapping at the wall again, to know if tea were ready, broke up this particular phase of our friendly conversation. She made tea for us in a most agreeable manner; and, whenever I went near her, in handing about the tea-cups and bread-and-butter, asked me, in a whisper, whether D. was fair, or dark, or whether she was short, or tall: or something of that kind; which I think I liked. After tea, we discussed a variety of topics before the fire; and Mrs. Micawber was good enough to sing us (in a small, thin, flat voice, which I remember to have considered, when I first knew her, the very table-beer of acoustics) the favorite ballads of &ldquo;The Dashing White Serjeant,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Little Tafflin.&rdquo; For both of these songs Mrs. Micawber had been famous when she lived at home with her papa and mama. Mr. Micawber told us, that when he heard her sing the first one, on the first occasion of his seeing her beneath the parental roof, she had attracted his attention in an extraordinary degree; but that when it came to Little Tafflin, he had resolved to win that woman or perish in the attempt.</p>
<p>It was between ten and eleven o'clock when Mrs. Micawber rose to replace her cap in the whitey-brown paper parcel, and to put on her bonnet. Mr. Micawber took the opportunity of Traddles putting on his great coat, to slip a letter into my hand, with a whispered request that I would read it at my leisure. I also took the opportunity of my holding a candle over the bannisters to light them down, when Mr. Micawber was going first, leading Mrs. Micawber, and Traddles was following with the cap, to detain Traddles for a moment on the top of the stairs.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Traddles,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;Mr. Micawber don't mean any harm, poor fellow; but, if I were you, I wouldn't lend him anything.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Traddles, smiling, &ldquo;I haven't got anything to lend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have got a name, you know,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! You call <hi rend="italics">that</hi> something to lend?&rdquo; returned Traddles, with a thoughtful look.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;Yes, to be sure! I am very much obliged to you, Copperfield; but&mdash;I am afraid I have lent him that already.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For the bill that is to be a certain investment?&rdquo; I inquired.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;Not for that one. This is the first I have heard of that one. I have been thinking that he will most likely propose that one, on the way home. Mine's another.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope there will be nothing wrong about it,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope not,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;I should think not, though, because he told me, only the other day, that it was provided for. That was Mr. Micawber's expression. &lsquo;Provided for.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber looking up at this juncture to where we were standing, I
<pb n="299" id="p299"/>
had only time to repeat my caution. Traddles thanked me, and descended. But I was much afraid, when I observed the good-natured manner in which he went down with the cap in his hand, and gave Mrs. Micawber his arm, that he would be carried into the Money Market neck and heels.</p>
<p>I returned to my fireside, and was musing, half gravely and half laughing, on the character of Mr. Micawber and the old relations between us, when I heard a quick step ascending the stairs. At first, I thought it was Traddles coming back for something Mrs. Micawber had left behind; but as the step approached, I knew it, and felt my heart beat high, and the blood rush to my face, for it was Steerforth's.</p>
<p>I was never unmindful of Agnes, and she never left that sanctuary in my thoughts&mdash;if I may call it so&mdash;where I had placed her from the first. But when he entered, and stood before me with his hand out, the darkness that had fallen on him changed to light, and I felt confounded and ashamed of having doubted one I loved so heartily. I loved her none the less; I thought of her as the same benignant, gentle angel in my life; I reproached myself, not her, with having done him an injury; and I would have made him any atonement if I had known what to make, and how to make it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, Daisy, old boy, dumb-foundered!&rdquo; laughed Steerforth, shaking my hand heartily, and throwing it gaily away. &ldquo;Have I detected you in another feast, you Sybarite! These Doctors' Commons fellows are the gayest men in town, I believe, and beat us sober Oxford people all to nothing!&rdquo; His bright glance went merrily round the room, as he took the seat on the sofa opposite to me, which Mrs. Micawber had recently vacated, and stirred the fire into a blaze.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was so surprised at first,&rdquo; said I, giving him welcome with all the cordiality I felt, &ldquo;that I had hardly breath to greet you with, Steerforth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, the sight of me <hi rend="italics">is</hi> good for sore eyes, as the Scotch say,&rdquo; replied Steerforth, &ldquo;and so is the sight of you, Daisy, in full bloom. How are you, my Bacchanal?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am very well,&rdquo; said I; &ldquo;and not at all Bacchanalian to-night, though I confess to another party of three.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;All of whom I met in the street, talking loud in your praise,&rdquo; returned Steerforth. &ldquo;Who's our friend in the tights?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I gave him the best idea I could, in a few words, of Mr. Micawber. He laughed heartily at my feeble portrait of that gentleman, and said he was a man to know, and he must know him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But who do you suppose our other friend is?&rdquo; said I, in my turn.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Heaven knows,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Not a bore, I hope? I thought he looked a little like one.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Traddles!&rdquo; I replied, triumphantly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who's he?&rdquo; asked Steerforth, in his careless way.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you remember Traddles? Traddles in our room at Salem House?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! That fellow!&rdquo; said Steerforth, beating a lump of coal on the top of the fire, with the poker. &ldquo;Is he as soft as ever? And where the dence did you pick <hi rend="italics">him</hi> up?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I extolled Traddles in reply, as highly as I could; for I felt that Steerforth rather slighted him. Steerforth, dismissing the subject with a light
<pb n="300" id="p300"/>
nod, and a smile, and the remark that he would be glad to see the old fellow too, for he had always been an odd fish, inquired if I could give him anything to eat? During most of this short dialogue, when he had not been speaking in a wild vivacious manner, he had sat idly beating on the lump of coal with the poker. I observed that he did the same thing while I was getting out the remains of the pigeon-pie, and so forth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, Daisy, here's a supper for a king!&rdquo; he exclaimed, starting out of his silence with a burst, and taking his seat at the table. &ldquo;I shall do it justice, for I have come from Yarmouth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought you came from Oxford?&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not I,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;I have been seafaring&mdash;better employed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Littimer was here to-day, to inquire for you,&rdquo; I remarked, &ldquo;and I understood him that you were at Oxford; though, now I think of it, he certainly did not say so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Littimer is a greater fool than I thought him, to have been inquiring for me at all,&rdquo; said Steerforth, jovially pouring out a glass of wine, and drinking to me. &ldquo;As to understanding him, you are a cleverer fellow than most of us, Daisy, if you can do that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's true, indeed,&rdquo; said I, moving my chair to the table. &ldquo;So you have been at Yarmouth, Steerforth!&rdquo; interested to know all about it. &ldquo;Have you been there long?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;An <hi rend="italics">escapade</hi> of a week or so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how are they all? Of course, little Emily is not married yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not yet. Going to be, I believe&mdash;in so many weeks, or months, or something or other. I have not seen much of 'em. By-the-by;&rdquo; he laid down his knife and fork, which he had been using with great diligence, and began feeling in his pockets; &ldquo;I have a letter for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;From whom?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, from your old nurse,&rdquo; he returned, taking some papers out of his breast pocket. &ldquo; &lsquo;J. Steerforth, Esquire, debtor, to the Willing Mind;&rsquo; that's not it. Patience, and we'll find it presently. Old what's-his-name's in a bad way, and it's about that, I believe.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Barkis, do you mean?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes!&rdquo; still feeling in his pockets, and looking over their contents: &ldquo;it's all over with poor Barkis, I am afraid. I saw a little apothecary there&mdash;surgeon, or whatever he is&mdash;who brought your worship into the world. He was mighty learned about the case, to me; but the upshot of his opinion was, that the carrier was making his last journey rather fast.&mdash;Put your hand into the breast pocket of my great coat on the chair yonder, and I think you'll find the letter. Is it there?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here it is!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's right!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was from Peggotty; something less legible than usual, and brief. It informed me of her husband's hopeless state, and hinted at his being &ldquo;a little nearer&rdquo; than heretofore, and consequently more difficult to manage for his own comfort. It said nothing of her weariness and watching, and praised him highly. It was written with a plain, unaffected, homely piety that I knew to be genuine, and ended with &ldquo;my duty to my ever darling&rdquo;&mdash;meaning myself.</p>
<p>While I deciphered it, Steerforth continued to eat and drink.</p>
<pb n="301" id="p301"/>
<p>&ldquo;It's a bad job,&rdquo; he said, when I had done; &ldquo;but the sun sets every day, and people die every minute, and we mustn't be scared by the common lot. If we failed to hold our own, because that equal foot at all men's doors was heard knocking somewhere, every object in this world would slip from us. No! Ride on! Rough-shod if need be, smooth-shod if that will do, but ride on! Ride over all obstacles, and win the race!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And win what race?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The race that one has started in,&rdquo; said he. &ldquo;Ride on!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I noticed, I remember, as he paused, looking at me with his handsome head a little thrown back, and his glass raised in his hand, that, though the freshness of the sea-wind was on his face, and it was ruddy, there were traces in it, made since I last saw it, as if he had applied himself to some habitual strain of the fervent energy which, when roused, was so passionately roused within him. I had it in my thoughts to remonstrate with him upon his desperate way of pursuing any fancy that he took&mdash;such as this buffetting of rough seas, and braving of hard weather, for example&mdash;when my mind glanced off to the immediate subject of our conversation again, and pursued that instead.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I tell you what, Steerforth,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;if your high spirits will listen to me&rdquo;&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They are potent spirits, and will do whatever you like,&rdquo; he answered, moving from the table to the fireside again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then I tell you what, Steerforth. I think I will go down and see my old nurse. It is not that I can do her any good, or render her any real service; but she is so attached to me that my visit will have as much effect on her, as if I could do both. She will take it so kindly that it will be a comfort and support to her. It is no great effort to make, I am sure, for such a friend as she has been to me. Wouldn't you go a day's journey, if you were in my place?&rdquo;</p>
<p>His face was thoughtful, and he sat considering a little before he answered, in a low voice, &ldquo;Well! Go. You can do no harm.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have just come back,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;and it would be in vain to ask you to go with me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;I am for Highgate to-night. I have not seen my mother this long time, and it lies upon my conscience, for it's something to be loved as she loves her prodigal son.&mdash;Bah! Nonsense!&mdash;You mean to go to-morrow, I suppose?&rdquo; he said, holding me out at arm's length, with a hand on each of my shoulders.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I think so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, then, don't go till next day. I wanted you to come and stay a few days with us. Here I am, on purpose to bid you, and you fly off to Yarmouth!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are a nice fellow to talk of flying off, Steerforth, who are always running wild on some unknown expedition or other!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He looked at me for a moment without speaking, and then rejoined, still holding me as before, and giving me a shake:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come! Say the next day, and pass as much of to-morrow as you can with us! Who knows when we may meet again, else? Come! Say the next day! I want you to stand between Rosa Dartle and me, and keep us asunder.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Would you love each other too much, without me?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="302" id="p302"/>
<p>&ldquo;Yes; or hate,&rdquo; laughed Steerforth; &ldquo;no matter which. Come! Say the next day!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said the next day; and he put on his great-coat, and lighted his cigar, and set off to walk home. Finding him in this intention, I put on my own great-coat (but did not light my own cigar, having had enough of that for one while) and walked with him as far as the open road: a dull road, then, at night. He was in great spirits all the way; and when we parted, and I looked after him going so gallantly and airily homeward, I thought of his saying, &ldquo;Ride on over all obstacles, and win the race!&rdquo; and wished, for the first time, that he had some worthy race to run.</p>
<p>I was undressing in my own room, when Mr. Micawber's letter tumbled on the floor. Thus reminded of it, I broke the seal and read as follows. It was dated an hour and a half before dinner. I am not sure whether I have mentioned that, when Mr. Micawber was at any particularly desperate crisis, he used a sort of legal phraseology: which he seemed to think equivalent to winding up his affairs.</p>

<q><text><body><div1 type="letter">
<p>&ldquo;Sir&mdash;for I dare not say, my dear Copperfield,</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is expedient that I should inform you that the undersigned is Crushed. Some flickering efforts to spare you the premature knowledge of his calamitous position, you may observe in him this day; but hope has sunk beneath the horizon, and the undersigned is Crushed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The present communication is penned within the personal range (I cannot call it the society) of an individual, in a state closely bordering on intoxication, employed by a broker. That individual is in legal possession of the premises, under a distress for rent. His inventory includes, not only the chattels and effects of every description belonging to the undersigned, as yearly tenant of this habitation, but also those appertaining to Mr. Thomas Traddles, lodger, a member of the Honourable Society of the Inner Temple.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If any drop of gloom were wanting in the overflowing cup, which is now &lsquo;commended&rsquo; (in the language of an immortal Writer) to the lips of the undersigned, it would be found in the fact, that a friendly acceptance granted to the undersigned, by the before-mentioned Mr. Thomas Traddles, for the sum of &pound;23 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> is over due, and is NOT provided for. Also, in the fact, that the living responsibilities clinging to the undersigned, will, in the course of nature, be increased by the sum of one more helpless victim; whose miserable appearance may be looked for&mdash;in round numbers&mdash;at the expiration of a period not exceeding six lunar months from the present date.</p>
<p>&ldquo;After premising thus much, it would be a work of supererogation to add, that dust and ashes are for ever scattered </p>

<closer> &ldquo;On <lb/> The <lb/> Head <lb/> Of <signed> WILKINS MICAWBER.&rdquo;</signed></closer>
</div1></body></text></q>
<p>Poor Traddles! I knew enough of Mr. Micawber by this time, to foresee that <hi rend="italics">he</hi> might be expected to recover the blow; but my night's rest was sorely distressed by thoughts of Traddles, and of the curate's daughter, who was one of ten, down in Devonshire, and who was such a dear girl, and who would wait for Traddles (ominous praise!) until she was sixty, or any age that could be mentioned.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="303" id="p303"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXIX. <lb/> I VISIT STEERFORTH AT HIS HOME, AGAIN.</head>
<p>I MENTIONED to Mr. Spenlow in the morning, that I wanted leave of absence for a short time; and as I was not in the receipt of any salary, and consequently was not obnoxious to the implacable Jorkins, there was no difficulty about it. I took that opportunity, with my voice sticking in my throat, and my sight failing as I uttered the words, to express my hope that Miss Spenlow was quite well; to which Mr. Spenlow replied, with no more emotion than if he had been speaking of an ordinary human being, that he was much obliged to me, and she was very well.</p>
<p>We articled clerks, as germs of the patrician order of proctors, were treated with so much consideration, that I was almost my own master at all times. As I did not care, however, to get to Highgate before one or two o'clock in the day, and as we had another little excommunication case in court that morning, which was called The office of the Judge promoted by Tipkins against Bullock for his soul's correction, I passed an hour or two in attendance on it with Mr. Spenlow very agreeably. It arose out of a scuffle between two churchwardens, one of whom was alleged to have pushed the other against a pump; the handle of which pump projecting into a school-house, which school-house was under a gable of the churchroof, made the push an ecclesiastical offence. It was an amusing case; and sent me up to Highgate, on the box of the stage-coach, thinking about the Commons, and what Mr. Spenlow had said about touching the Commons and bringing down the country.</p>
<p>Mrs. Steerforth was pleased to see me, and so was Rosa Dartle. I was agreeably surprised to find that Littimer was not there, and that we were attended by a modest little parlor-maid, with blue ribbons in her cap, whose eye it was much more pleasant, and much less disconcerting, to catch by accident, than the eye of that respectable man. But what I particularly observed, before I had been half-an-hour in the house, was the close and attentive watch Miss Dartle kept upon me; and the lurking manner in which she seemed to compare my face with Steerforth's, and Steerforth's with mine, and to lie in wait for something to come out between the two. So surely as I looked towards her, did I see that eager visage, with its gaunt black eyes and searching brow, intent on mine; or passing suddenly from mine to Steerforth's; or comprehending both of us at once. In this lynx-like scrutiny she was so far from faltering when she saw I observed it, that at such a time she only fixed her piercing look upon me with a more intent expression still. Blameless as I was, and knew that I was, in reference to any wrong she could possibly suspect me of, I shrunk before her strange eyes, quite unable to endure their hungry lustre.</p>
<p>All day, she seemed to pervade the whole house. If I talked to
<pb n="304" id="p304"/>
Steerforth in his room, I heard her dress rustle in the little gallery outside. When he and I engaged in some of our old exercises on the lawn behind the house, I saw her face pass from window to window, like a wandering light, until it fixed itself in one, and watched us. When we all four went out walking in the afternoon, she closed her thin hand on my arm like a spring, to keep me back, while Steerforth and his mother went on out of hearing: and then spoke to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have been a long time,&rdquo; she said, &ldquo;without coming here. Is your profession really so engaging and interesting as to absorb your whole attention? I ask because I always want to be informed, when I am ignorant. Is it really, though?</p>
<p>I replied that I liked it well enough, but that I certainly could not claim so much for it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! I am glad to know that, because I always like to be put right when I am wrong,&rdquo; said Rosa Dartle. &ldquo;You mean it is a little dry, perhaps?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Well, I replied; perhaps it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> a little dry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! and that's a reason why you want relief and change&mdash;excitement, and all that?&rdquo; said she. &ldquo;Ah! very true! But isn't it a little&mdash;Eh?&mdash;for him; I don't mean you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>A quick glance of her eye towards the spot where Steerforth was walking, with his mother leaning on his arm, showed me whom she meant; but beyond that, I was quite lost. And I looked so, I have no doubt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't it&mdash;I don't say that it <hi rend="italics">does,</hi> mind I want to know&mdash;don't it rather engross him? Don't it make him, perhaps, a little more remiss than usual in his visits to his blindly doting&mdash;eh?&rdquo; With another quick glance at them, and such a glance at me as seemed to look into my innermost thoughts.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Dartle,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;pray do not think&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't!&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;Oh, dear me, don't suppose that I think anything! I am not suspicious. I only ask a question. I don't state any opinion. I want to found an opinion on what you tell me. Then, it's not so? Well! I am very glad to know it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It certainly is not the fact,&rdquo; said I, perplexed, &ldquo;that I am accountable for Steerforth's having been away from home longer than usual&mdash;if he has been: which I really don't know at this moment, unless I understand it from you. I have not seen him this long while, until last night.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed, Miss Dartle, no!&rdquo;</p>
<p>As she looked full at me, I saw her face grow sharper and paler, and the marks of the old wound lengthen out until it cut through the disfigured lip, and deep into the nether lip, and slanted down the face. There was something positively awful to me in this, and in the brightness of her eyes, as she said, looking fixedly at me:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is he doing?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I repeated the words, more to myself than her, being so amazed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is he doing?&rdquo; she said, with an eagerness that seemed enough to consume her like a fire. &ldquo;In what is that man assisting him, who never looks at me without an inscrutable falsehood in his eyes? If you are honorable and faithful, I don't ask you to betray your friend. I ask
<pb n="305" id="p305"/>
you only to tell me, is it anger, is it hatred, is it pride, is it restlessness, is it some wild fancy, is it love, <hi rend="italics">what is it,</hi> that is leading him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Dartle,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;how shall I tell you, so that you will believe me, that I know of nothing in Steerforth different from what there was when I first came here. I can think of nothing. I firmly believe there is nothing. I hardly understand, even, what you mean.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As she still looked fixedly at me, a twitching or throbbing, from which I could not dissociate the idea of pain, came into that cruel mark; and lifted up the corner of her lip as if with scorn, or with a pity that despised its object. She put her hand upon it hurriedly&mdash;a hand so thin and delicate, that when I had seen her hold it up before the fire to shade her face, I had compared it in my thoughts to fine porcelain&mdash;and saying, in a quick, fierce, passionate way, &ldquo;I swear you to secresy about this!&rdquo; said not a word more.</p>
<p>Mrs. Steerforth was particularly happy in her son's society, and Steerforth was, on this occasion, particularly attentive and respectful to her. It was very interesting to me to see them together, not only on account of their mutual affection, but because of the strong personal resemblance between them, and the manner in which what was haughty or impetuous in him was softened by age and sex, in her, to a gracious dignity. I thought, more than once, that it was well no serious cause of division had ever come between them; or two such natures&mdash;I ought rather to express it, two such shades of the same nature&mdash;might have been harder to reconcile than the two extremest opposites in creation. The idea did not originate in my own discernment, I am bound to confess, but in a speech of Rosa Dartle's.</p>
<p>She said at dinner:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, but do tell me, though, somebody, because I have been thinking about it all day, and I want to know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You want to know what, Rosa?&rdquo; returned Mrs. Steerforth. &ldquo;Pray, pray, Rosa, do not be mysterious.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mysterious!&rdquo; she cried. &ldquo;Oh! really? Do you consider me so?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do I constantly entreat you,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, &ldquo;to speak plainly, in your own natural manner?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! then, this is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> my natural manner?&rdquo; she rejoined. &ldquo;Now you must really bear with me, because I ask for information. We never know ourselves.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It has become a second nature,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, without any displeasure; &ldquo;but I remember,&mdash;and so must you, I think,&mdash;when your manner was different, Rosa; when it was not so guarded, and was more trustful.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure you are right,&rdquo; she returned; &ldquo;and so it is that bad habits grow upon one! Really? Less guarded and more trustful? How <hi rend="italics">can</hi> I, imperceptibly, have changed, I wonder! Well, that's very odd! I must study to regain my former self.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wish you would,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, with a smile.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! I really will, you know!&rdquo; she answered. &ldquo;I will learn frankness from&mdash;let me see&mdash;from James.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You cannot learn frankness, Rosa,&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, quickly&mdash;for there was always some effect of sarcasm in what Rosa Dartle said, though
<pb n="306" id="p306"/>
it was said, as this was, in the most unconscious manner in the world&mdash;&ldquo;in a better school.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That I am sure of,&rdquo; she answered, with uncommon fervour. &ldquo;If I am sure of anything, of course, you know, I am sure of that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Steerforth appeared to me to regret having been a little nettled; for she presently said, in a kind tone:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my dear Rosa, we have not heard what it is that you want to be satisfied about?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That I want to be satisfied about?&rdquo; she replied, with provoking coldness. &ldquo;Oh! It was only whether people, who are like each other in their moral constitution&mdash;is that the phrase?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's as good a phrase as another,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you:&mdash;whether people, who are like each other in their moral constitution, are in greater danger than people not so circumstanced, supposing any serious cause of variance to arise between them, of being divided angrily and deeply?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should say yes,&rdquo; said Steerforth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Should you?&rdquo; she retorted. &ldquo;Dear me! Supposing then, for instance, &mdash; any unlikely thing will do for a supposition &mdash; that you and your mother were to have a serious quarrel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Rosa,&rdquo; interposed Mrs. Steerforth, laughing good-naturedly, &ldquo;suggest some other supposition! James and I know our duty to each other better, I pray Heaven!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; said Miss Dartle, nodding her head thoughtfully. &ldquo;To be sure. <hi rend="italics">That</hi> would prevent it? Why, of course it would. Ex-actly. Now, I am glad I have been so foolish as to put the case, for it is so very good to know that your duty to each other would prevent it! Thank you very much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One other little circumstance connected with Miss Dartle I must not omit; for I had reason to remember it thereafter, when all the irremediable past was rendered plain. During the whole of this day, but especially from this period of it, Steerforth exerted himself with his utmost skill, and that was with his utmost ease, to charm this singular creature into a pleasant and pleased companion. That he should succeed, was no matter of surprise to me. That she should struggle against the fascinating influence of his delightful art&mdash;delightful nature I thought it then&mdash;did not surprise me either; for I knew that she was sometimes jaundiced and perverse. I saw her features and her manner slowly change; I saw her look at him with growing admiration; I saw her try, more and more faintly, but always angrily, as if she condemned a weakness in herself, to resist the captivating power that he possessed; and finally I saw her sharp glance soften, and her smile become quite gentle, and I ceased to be afraid of her as I had really been all day, and we all sat about the fire, talking and laughing together, with as little reserve as if we had been children.</p>
<p>Whether it was because we had sat there so long, or because Steerforth was resolved not to lose the advantage he had gained, I do not know; but we did not remain in the dining-room more than five minutes after her departure. &ldquo;She is playing her harp,&rdquo; said Steerforth, softly, at the
<pb n="307" id="p307"/>
drawing-room door, &ldquo;and nobody but my mother has heard her do that, I believe, these three years.&rdquo; He said it with a curious smile, which was gone directly; and we went into the room and found her alone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't get up!&rdquo; said Steerforth (which she had already done); &ldquo;my dear Rosa, don't! Be kind for once, and sing us an Irish song.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you care for an Irish song?&rdquo; she returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Much!&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Much more than for any other. Here is Daisy, too, loves music from his soul. Sing us an Irish song, Rosa! and let me sit and listen as I used to do.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He did not touch her, or the chair from which she had risen, but sat himself near the harp. She stood beside it for some little while, in a curious way, going through the motion of playing it with her right hand, but not sounding it. At length she sat down, and drew it to her with one sudden action, and played and sang.</p>
<p>I don't know what it was, in her touch or voice, that made that song the most unearthly I have ever heard in my life, or can imagine. There was something fearful in the reality of it. It was as if it had never been written, or set to music, but sprung out of the passion within her; which found imperfect utterance in the low sounds of her voice, and crouched again when all was still. I was dumb when she leaned beside the harp again, playing it, but not sounding it, with her right hand.</p>
<p>A minute more, and this had roused me from my trance:&mdash;Steerforth had left his seat, and gone to her, and had put his arm laughingly about her, and had said, &ldquo;Come, Rosa, for the future we will love each other very much!&rdquo; And she had struck him, and had thrown him off with the fury of a wild cat, and had burst out of the room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is the matter with Rosa?&rdquo; said Mrs. Steerforth, coming in.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She has been an angel, mother,&rdquo; returned Steerforth, &ldquo;for a little while; and has run into the opposite extreme, since, by way of compensation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You should be careful not to irritate her, James. Her temper has been soured, remember, and ought not to be tried.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Rosa did not come back; and no other mention was made of her, until I went with Steerforth into his room to say Good night. Then he laughed about her, and asked me if I had ever seen such a fierce little piece of incomprehensibility.</p>
<p>I expressed as much of my astonishment as was then capable of expression, and asked if he could guess what it was that she had taken so much amiss, so suddenly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, Heaven knows,&rdquo; said Steerforth. &ldquo;Any thing you like&mdash;or nothing! I told you she took every thing, herself included, to a grindstone, and sharpened it. She is an edge-tool, and requires great care in dealing with. She is always dangerous. Good night!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good night!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;my dear Steerforth! I shall be gone before you wake in the morning. Good night!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was unwilling to let me go; and stood, holding me out, with a hand on each of my shoulders, as he had done in my own room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Daisy,&rdquo; he said, with a smile &mdash; &ldquo;for though that's not the
<pb n="308" id="p308"/>
name your Godfathers and Godmothers gave you, it's the name I like best to call you by&mdash;and I wish, I wish, I wish, you could give it to me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why so I can, if I choose,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Daisy, if anything should ever separate us, you must think of me at my best, old boy. Come! Let us make that bargain. Think of me at my best, if circumstances should ever part us!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have no best to me, Steerforth,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;and no worst. You are always equally loved, and cherished in my heart.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So much compunction for having ever wronged him, even by a shapeless thought, did I feel within me, that the confession of having done so was rising to my lips. But for the reluctance I had, to betray the confidence of Agnes, but for my uncertainty how to approach the subject with no risk of doing so, it would have reached them before he said, &ldquo;God bless you, Daisy, and good night!&rdquo; In my doubt, it did <hi rend="italics">not</hi> reach them; and we shook hands, and we parted.</p>
<p>I was up with the dull dawn, and, having dressed as quietly as I could, looked into his room. He was fast asleep; lying, easily, with his head upon his arm, as I had often seen him lie at school.</p>
<p>The time came in its season, and that was very soon, when I almost wondered that nothing troubled his repose, as I looked at him. But he slept&mdash;let me think of him so again&mdash;as I had often seen him sleep at school; and thus, in this silent hour, I left him.</p>
<p>&mdash; Never more, oh God forgive you, Steerforth! to touch that passive hand in love and friendship. Never, never, more!</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXX. <lb/> A LOSS.</head>
<p>I GOT down to Yarmouth in the evening, and went to the inn. I knew that Peggotty's spare room&mdash;my room&mdash;was likely to have occupation enough in a little while, if that great Visitor, before whose presence all the living must give place, were not already in the house; so I betook myself to the inn, and dined there, and engaged my bed.</p>
<p>It was ten o'clock when I went out. Many of the shops were shut, and the town was dull. When I came to Omer and Joram's, I found the shutters up, but the shop door standing open. As I could obtain a perspective view of Mr. Omer inside, smoking his pipe by the parlor-door, I entered, and asked him how he was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, bless my life and soul!&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, &ldquo;how do you find yourself? Take a seat.&mdash;Smoke not disagreeable, I hope?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By no means,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I like it&mdash;in somebody else's pipe.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What, not in your own, eh?&rdquo; Mr. Omer returned, laughing. &ldquo;All the better, sir. Bad habit for a young man. Take a seat. I smoke, myself, for the asthma.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="309" id="p309"/>
<p>Mr. Omer had made room for me, and placed a chair. He now sat down again, very much out of breath, gasping at his pipe as if it contained a supply of that necessary, without which he must perish.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry to have heard bad news of Mr. Barkis,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>Mr. Omer looked at me, with a steady countenance, and shook his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know how he is to-night?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The very question I should have put to you, sir,&rdquo; returned Mr. Omer, &ldquo;but on account of delicacy. It's one of the drawbacks of our line of business. When a party's ill, we <hi rend="italics">can't</hi> ask how the party is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The difficulty had not occurred to me; though I had had my apprehensions too, when I went in, of hearing the old tune. On its being mentioned, I recognised it, however, and said as much.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes, you understand,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, nodding his head. &ldquo;We durstn't do it. Bless you, it would be a shock that the generality of parties mightn't recover, to say &lsquo;Omer and Jorams's compliments, and how do you find yourself this morning&rsquo;&mdash;or this afternoon&mdash;as it may be.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer and I nodded at each other, and Mr. Omer recruited his wind by the aid of his pipe.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's one of the things that cut the trade off from attentions they could often wish to show,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Take myself. If I have known Barkis a year, to move to as he went by, I have known him forty year. But <hi rend="italics">I</hi> can't go and say &lsquo;how is he?&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt it was rather hard on Mr. Omer, and I told him so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'm not more self-interested, I hope, than another man,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Look at me! My wind may fail me at any moment, and it ain't likely that, to my own knowledge, I'd be self-interested under such circumstances. I say it ain't likely, in a man who knows his wind will go, when it <hi rend="italics">does</hi> go, as if a pair of bellows was cut open; and that man a grandfather,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer.</p>
<p>I said, &ldquo;Not at all.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It ain't that I complain of my line of business,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;It ain't that. Some good and some bad goes, no doubt, to all callings. What I wish, is, that parties were brought up stronger-minded.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer, with a very complacent and amiable face, took several puffs in silence; and then said, resuming his first point.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Accordingly we're obleeged, in ascertaining how Barkis goes on, to limit ourselves to Em'ly. She knows what our real objects are, and she don't have any more alarms or suspicions about us, than if we was so many lambs. Minnie and Joram have just stepped down to the house, in fact (she's there, after hours, helping her aunt a bit), to ask her how he is tonight; and if you was to please to wait till they come back, they'd give you full partic'lers. Will you take something? A glass of srub and water, now? I smoke on srub and water, myself,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, taking up his glass, &ldquo;because it's considered softening to the passages, by which this troublesome breath of mine gets into action. But, Lord bless you,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, huskily, &ldquo;it ain't the passages that's out of order! &lsquo;Give me breath enough,&rsquo; says I to my daughter Minnie, &lsquo;and <hi rend="italics">I</hi>'ll find passages, my dear.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>He really had no breath to spare, and it was very alarming to see him laugh. When he was again in a condition to be talked to, I thanked him
<pb n="310" id="p310"/>
for the proffered refreshment, which I declined, as I had just had dinner; and, observing that I would wait, since he was so good as to invite me, until his daughter and his son-in-law came back, I inquired how little Emily was?</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, removing his pipe, that he might rub his chin; &ldquo;I tell you truly, I shall be glad when her marriage has taken place.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why so?&rdquo; I inquired.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, she's unsettled at present,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;It ain't that she's not as pretty as ever, for she's prettier&mdash;I do assure you, she is prettier. It ain't that she don't work as well as ever, for she does. She <hi rend="italics">was</hi> worth any six, and she <hi rend="italics">is</hi> worth any six. But somehow she wants heart. If you understand,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, after rubbing his chin again, and smoking a little, &ldquo;what I mean in a general way by the expression, &lsquo;A long pull, and a strong pull, and a pull altogether, my hearties, hurrah!&rsquo; I should say to you, that <hi rend="italics">that</hi> was&mdash;in a general way&mdash;what I miss in Em'ly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer's face and manner went for so much, that I could conscientiously nod my head, as divining his meaning. My quickness of apprehension seemed to please him, and he went on:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I consider this is principally on account of her being in an unsettled state, you see. We have talked it over a good deal, her uncle and myself, and her sweetheart and myself, after business; and I consider it is principally on account of her being unsettled. You must always recollect of Em'ly,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, shaking his head gently, &ldquo;that she's a most extraordinary affectionate little thing. The proverb says, &lsquo;You can't make a silk purse out of a sow's ear.&rsquo; Well, I don't know about that. I rather think you may, if you begin early in life. She has made a home out of that old boat, sir, that stone and marble couldn't beat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure she has!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To see the clinging of that pretty little thing to her uncle,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer; &ldquo;to see the way she holds on to him, tighter and tighter, and closer and closer, every day, is to see a sight. Now, you know, there's a struggle going on when that's the case. Why should it be made a longer one than is needful?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I listened attentively to the good old fellow, and acquiesced, with all my heart, in what he said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Therefore, I mentioned to them,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, in a comfortable, easy-going tone, &ldquo;this. I said, &lsquo;Now, don't consider Em'ly nailed down in point of time, at all. Make it your own time. Her services have been more valuable than was supposed; her learning has been quicker than was supposed; Omer and Joram can run their pen through what remains; and she's free when you wish. If she likes to make any little arrangement, afterwards, in the way of doing any little thing for us at home, very well. If she don't, very well still. We're no losers, anyhow.&rsquo; For&mdash;don't you see,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, touching me with his pipe, &ldquo;it ain't likely that a man so short of breath as myself, and a grandfather too, would go and strain points with a little bit of a blue-eyed blossom, like <hi rend="italics">her?</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all, I am certain,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<pb n="311" id="p311"/>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all! You're right!&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Well, sir, her cousin&mdash;you know it's a cousin she's going to be married to?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes,&rdquo; I replied. &ldquo;I know him well.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course you do,&rdquo; said Mr. Omer. &ldquo;Well, sir! Her cousin being, as it appears, in good work, and well to do, thanked me in a very manly sort of manner for this (conducting himself altogether, I must say, in a way that gives me a high opinion of him), and went and took as comfortable a little house as you or I could wish to clap eyes on. That little house is now furnished, right through, as neat and complete as a doll's parlor; and but for Barkis's illness having taken this bad turn, poor fellow, they would have been man and wife&mdash;I dare say, by this time. As it is, there's a postponement.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And Emily, Mr. Omer?&rdquo; I inquired. &ldquo;Has she become more settled?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why that, you know,&rdquo; he returned, rubbing his double chin again, &ldquo;can't naturally be expected. The prospect of the change and separation, and all that, is, as one may say, close to her and far away from her, both at once. Barkis's death needn't put it off much, but his lingering might. Anyway, it's an uncertain state of matters, you see.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I see,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Consequently,&rdquo; pursued Mr. Omer, &ldquo;Em'ly's still a little down, and a little fluttered; perhaps, upon the whole, she's more so than she was. Every day she seems to get fonder and fonder of her uncle, and more loth to part from all of us. A kind word from me brings the tears into her eyes; and if you was to see her with my daughter Minnie's little girl, you'd never forget it. Bless my heart alive!&rdquo; said Mr. Omer, pondering, &ldquo;how she loves that child!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having so favourable an opportunity, it occurred to me to ask Mr. Omer, before our conversation should be interrupted by the return of his daughter and her husband, whether he knew anything of Martha.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; he rejoined, shaking his head, and looking very much dejected. &ldquo;No good. A sad story, sir, however you come to know it. I never thought there was harm in the girl. I wouldn't wish to mention it before my daughter Minnie&mdash;for she'd take me up directly&mdash;but I never did. None of us ever did.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Omer, hearing his daughter's footstep before I heard it, touched me with his pipe, and shut up one eye, as a caution. She and her husband came in immediately afterwards.</p>
<p>Their report was, that Mr. Barkis was &ldquo;as bad as bad could be;&rdquo; that he was quite unconscious; and that Mr. Chillip had mournfully said in the kitchen, on going away just now, that the College of Physicians, the College of Surgeons, and Apothecaries' Hall, if they were all called in together, couldn't help him. He was past both Colleges, Mr. Chillip said, and the Hall could only poison him.</p>
<p>Hearing this, and learning that Mr. Peggotty was there, I determined to go to the house at once. I bade good night to Mr. Omer, and to Mr. and Mrs. Joram; and directed my steps thither, with a solemn feeling, which made Mr. Barkis quite a new and different creature.</p>
<p>My low tap at the door was answered by Mr. Peggotty. He was not so much surprised to see me as I had expected. I remarked this in
<pb n="312" id="p312"/>
Peggotty, too, when she came down; and I have seen it since; and I think, in the expectation of that dread surprise, all other changes and surprises dwindle into nothing.</p>
<p>I shook hands with Mr. Peggotty, and passed into the kitchen, while he softly closed the door. Little Emily was sitting by the fire, with her hands before her face. Ham was standing near her.</p>
<p>We spoke in whispers; listening, between whiles, for any sound in the room above. I had not thought of it on the occasion of my last visit, but how strange it was to me now, to miss Mr. Barkis out of the kitchen!</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is very kind of you, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is oncommon kind,&rdquo; said Ham.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Em'ly, my dear,&rdquo; cried Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;See here! Here's Mas'r Davy come! What, cheer up, pretty! Not a wured to Mas'r Davy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a trembling upon her, that I can see now. The coldness of her hand when I touched it, I can feel yet. Its only sign of animation was to shrink from mine; and then she glided from the chair, and, creeping to the other side of her uncle, bowed herself, silently and trembling still, upon his breast.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's such a loving art,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, smoothing her rich hair with his great hard hand, &ldquo;that it can't abear the sorrer of this. It's nat'ral in young folk, Mas'r Davy, when they're new to these here trials, and timid, like my little bird,&mdash;it's nat'ral.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She clung the closer to him, but neither lifted up her face, nor spoke a word.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's getting late, my dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;and here's Ham come fur to take you home. Theer! Go along with t' other loving art! What, Em'ly? Eh, my pretty?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The sound of her voice had not reached me, but he bent his head as if he listened to her, and then said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let you stay with your uncle? Why, you doen't mean to ask me that! Stay with your uncle, Moppet? When your husband that'll be so soon, is here fur to take you home? Now a person wouldn't think it, fur to see this little thing alongside a rough-weather chap like me,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, looking round at both of us, with infinite pride; &ldquo;but the sea ain't more salt in it than she has fondness in her for her uncle&mdash;a foolish little Em'ly!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Em'ly's in the right in that, Mas'r Davy!&rdquo; said Ham. &ldquo;Lookee here! As Em'ly wishes of it, and as she's hurried and frightened, like, besides, I'll leave her till morning. Let me stay too!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;You doen't ought&mdash;a married man like you&mdash;or what's as good&mdash;to take and hull away a day's work. And you doen't ought to watch and work both. That won't do. You go home and turn in. You ain't afeerd of Em'ly not being took good care on, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham yielded to this persuasion, and took his hat to go. Even when he kissed her,&mdash;and I never saw him approach her, but I felt that nature had given him the soul of a gentleman,&mdash;she seemed to cling closer to her uncle, even to the avoidance of her chosen husband. I shut the door after him, that it might cause no disturbance of the quiet that prevailed; and when I turned back, I found Mr. Peggotty still talking to her.</p>
<pb n="313" id="p313"/>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I'm a going up-stairs to tell your aunt as Mas'r Davy's here, and that'll cheer her up a bit,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;Sit ye down by the fire, the while, my dear, and warm these mortal cold hands. You doen't need to be so fearsome, and take on so much. What? You'll go along with me?&mdash;Well! come along with me&mdash;come! If her uncle was turned out of house and home, and forced to lay down in a dyke, Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with no less pride than before, &ldquo;it's my belief she'd go along with him, now! But there'll be some one else, soon,&mdash;some one else, soon, Em'ly!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Afterwards, when I went up-stairs, as I passed the door of my little chamber, which was dark, I had an indistinct impression of her being within it, cast down upon the floor. But, whether it was really she, or whether it was a confusion of the shadows in the room, I don't know now.</p>
<p>I had leisure to think, before the kitchen-fire, of pretty little Em'ly's dread of death&mdash;which, added to what Mr. Omer had told me, I took to be the cause of her being so unlike herself&mdash;and I had leisure, before Peggotty came down, even to think more leniently of the weakness of it: as I sat counting the ticking of the clock, and deepening my sense of the solemn hush around me. Peggotty took me in her arms, and blessed and thanked me over and over again for being such a comfort to her (that was what she said) in her distress. She then entreated me to come up-stairs, sobbing that Mr. Barkis had always liked me and admired me; that he had often talked of me, before he fell into a stupor; and that she believed, in case of his coming to himself again, he would brighten up at sight of me, if he could brighten up at any earthly thing.</p>
<p>The probability of his ever doing so, appeared to me, when I saw him, to be very small. He was lying with his head and shoulders out of bed, in an uncomfortable attitude, half resting on the box which had cost him so much pain and trouble. I learned, that, when he was past creeping out of bed to open it, and past assuring himself of its safety by means of the divining rod I had seen him use, he had required to have it placed on the chair at the bed-side, where he had ever since embraced it, night and day. His arm lay on it now. Time and the world were slipping from beneath him, but the box was there; and the last words he had uttered were (in an explanatory tone) &ldquo;Old clothes!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Barkis, my dear!&rdquo; said Peggotty, almost cheerfully: bending over him, while her brother and I stood at the bed's foot. &ldquo;Here's my dear boy&mdash;my dear boy, Master Davy, who brought us together, Barkis! That you sent messages by, you know! Won't you speak to Master Davy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was as mute and senseless as the box, from which his form derived the only expression it had.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He's a going out with the tide,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty to me, behind his hand.</p>
<p>My eyes were dim, and so were Mr. Peggotty's; but I repeated in a whisper, &ldquo;With the tide?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;People can't die, along the coast,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;except when the tide's pretty nigh out. They can't be born, unless it's pretty nigh in&mdash;not properly born, till flood. He's a going out with the tide. It's ebb at half arter three, slack water half-an-hour. If he lives 'till it turns, he'll hold his own till past the flood, and go out with the next tide.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="314" id="p314"/>
<p>We remained there, watching him, a long time&mdash;hours. What mysterious influence my presence had upon him in that state of his senses, I shall not pretend to say; but when he at last began to wander feebly, it is certain he was muttering about driving me to school.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He's coming to himself,&rdquo; said Peggotty.</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty touched me, and whispered with much awe and reverence, &ldquo;They are both a going out fast.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Barkis, my dear!&rdquo; said Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;C. P. Barkis,&rdquo; he cried, faintly. &ldquo;No better woman anywhere!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Look! Here's Master Davy!&rdquo; said Peggotty. For he now opened his eyes.</p>
<p>I was on the point of asking him if he knew me, when he tried to stretch out his arm, and said to me, distinctly, with a pleasant smile:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Barkis is willin'!&rdquo;</p>
<p>And, it being low water, he went out with the tide.</p>
</div2><div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXXI. <lb/> A GREATER LOSS.</head>
<p>IT was not difficult for me, on Peggotty's solicitation, to resolve to stay where I was, until after the remains of the poor carrier should have made their last journey to Blunderstone. She had long ago bought, out of her own savings, a little piece of ground in our old churchyard near the grave &ldquo;of her sweet girl,&rdquo; as she always called my mother; and there they were to rest.</p>
<p>In keeping Peggotty company, and doing all I could for her (little enough at the utmost), I was as grateful, I rejoice to think, as even now I could wish myself to have been. But I am afraid I had a supreme satisfaction, of a personal and professional nature, in taking charge of Mr. Barkis's will, and expounding its contents.</p>
<p>I may claim the merit of having originated the suggestion that the will should be looked for in the box. After some search, it was found in the box, at the bottom of a horse's nose-bag; wherein (besides hay) there was discovered an old gold watch, with chain and seals, which Mr. Barkis had worn on his wedding-day, and which had never been seen before or since; a silver tobacco-stopper, in the form of a leg; an imitation lemon, full of minute cups and saucers, which I have some idea Mr. Barkis must have purchased to present to me when I was a child, and afterwards found himself unable to part with; eighty-seven guineas and a half, in guineas and half guineas; two hundred and ten pounds, in perfectly clean Bank notes; certain receipts for Bank of England stock; an old horse-shoe, a bad shilling, a piece of camphor, and an oyster-shell. From the circumstance of the latter article having been much polished, and displaying prismatic colours on the inside, I conclude that Mr. Barkis had some
<pb n="315" id="p315"/>
general ideas about pearls, which never resolved themselves into anything definite.</p>
<p>For years and years, Mr. Barkis had carried this box, on all his journeys, every day. That it might the better escape notice, he had invented a fiction that it belonged to &ldquo;Mr. Blackboy,&rdquo; and was &ldquo;to be left with Barkis till called for;&rdquo; a fable he had elaborately written on the lid, in characters now scarcely legible.</p>
<p>He had hoarded, all these years, I found, to good purpose. His property in money amounted to nearly three thousand pounds. Of this he bequeathed the interest of one thousand to Mr. Peggotty for his life; on his decease, the principal to be equally divided between Peggotty, little Emily, and me, or the survivor or survivors of us, share and share alike. All the rest he died possessed of, he bequeathed to Peggotty; whom he left residuary legatee, and sole executrix of that his last will and testament.</p>
<p>I felt myself quite a proctor when I read this document aloud with all possible ceremony, and set forth its provisions, any number of times, to those whom they concerned. I began to think there was more in the Commons than I had supposed. I examined the will with the deepest attention, pronounced it perfectly formal in all respects, made a pencilmark or so in the margin, and thought it rather extraordinary that I knew so much.</p>
<p>In this abstruse pursuit; in making an account for, Peggotty, of all the property into which she had come; in arranging all the affairs in an orderly manner; and in being her referee and adviser on every point, to our joint delight; I passed the week before the funeral. I did not see little Emily in that interval, but they told me she was to be quietly married in a fortnight.</p>
<p>I did not attend the funeral in character, if I may venture to say so. I mean I was not dressed up in a black cloak and a streamer, to frighten the birds; but I walked over to Blunderstone early in the morning, and was in the churchyard when it came, attended only by Peggotty and her brother. The mad gentleman looked on, out of my little window; Mr. Chillip's baby wagged its heavy head, and rolled its goggle eyes, at the clergyman, over its nurse's shoulder; Mr. Omer breathed short in the background; no one else was there; and it was very quiet. We walked about the churchyard for an hour, after all was over; and pulled some young leaves from the tree above my mother's grave.</p>
<p>A dread falls on me here. A cloud is lowering on the distant town, towards which I retraced my solitary steps. I fear to approach it. I cannot bear to think of what did come, upon that memorable night; of what must come again, if I go on.</p>
<p>It is no worse, because I write of it. It would be no better, if I stopped my most unwilling hand. It is done. Nothing can undo it; nothing can make it otherwise than as it was.</p>
<p>My old nurse was to go to London with me next day, on the business of the will. Little Emily was passing that day at Mr. Omer's. We were all to meet in the old boathouse that night. Ham would bring Emily at the usual hour. I would walk back at my leisure. The brother and sister would return as they had come, and be expecting us, when the day closed in, at the fireside.</p>
<pb n="316" id="p316"/>
<p>I parted from them at the wicket-gate, where visionary Straps had rested with Roderick Random's knapsack in the days of yore; and, instead of going straight back, walked a little distance on the road to Lowestoft. Then I turned, and walked back towards Yarmouth. I stayed to dine at a decent alehouse, some mile or two from the Ferry I have mentioned before; and thus the day wore away, and it was evening when I reached it. Rain was falling heavily by that time, and it was a wild night; but there was a moon behind the clouds, and it was not dark.</p>
<p>I was soon within sight of Mr. Peggotty's house, and of the light within it shining through the window. A little floundering across the sand, which was heavy, brought me to the door, and I went in.</p>
<p>It looked very comfortable, indeed. Mr. Peggotty had smoked his evening pipe, and there were preparations for some supper by-and-by. The fire was bright, the ashes were thrown up, the locker was ready for little Emily in her old place. In her own old place sat Peggotty, once more, looking (but for her dress) as if she had never left it. She had fallen back, already, on the society of the work-box with Saint Paul's upon the lid, the yard-measure in the cottage, and the bit of wax candle: and there they all were, just as if they had never been disturbed. Mrs. Gummidge appeared to be fretting a little, in her old corner; and consequently looked quite natural, too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're first of the lot, Mas'r Davy!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with a happy face. &ldquo;Doen't keep in that coat, sir, if it's wet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Mr. Peggotty,&rdquo; said I, giving him my outer coat to hang up. &ldquo;It's quite dry.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So 'tis!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, feeling my shoulders. &ldquo;As a chip! Sit ye down, sir. It ain't o' no use saying welcome to you, but you're welcome, kind and hearty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Mr. Peggotty, I am sure of that. Well, Peggotty!&rdquo; said I, giving her a kiss. &ldquo;And how are you, old woman?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ha, ha!&rdquo; laughed Mr. Peggotty, sitting down beside us, and rubbing his hands in his sense of relief from recent trouble, and in the genuine heartiness of his nature; &ldquo;there's not a woman in the wureld, sir&mdash;as I tell her&mdash;that need to feel more easy in her mind than her! She done her dooty by the departed, and the departed know'd it; and the departed done what was right by her, as she done what was right by the departed; and&mdash;and&mdash;and it's <hi rend="italics">all</hi> right!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Gummidge groaned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cheer up, my pretty mawther!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty. (But he shook his head aside at us, evidently sensible of the tendency of the late occurrences to recal the memory of the old one.) &ldquo;Doen't be down! Cheer up, for your own self, on'y a little bit, and see if a good deal more doen't come nat'ral!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not to me, Dan'l,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Gummidge. &ldquo;Nothink's nat'ral to me but to be lone and lorn.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, soothing her sorrows.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes, Dan'l!&rdquo; said Mrs. Gummidge. &ldquo;I ain't a person to live with them as has had money left. Thinks go too contrairy with me. I had better be a riddance.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="317" id="p317"/>
<p>&ldquo;Why, how should I ever spend it without you?&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with an air of serious remonstrance. &ldquo;What are you a talking on? Doen't I want you more now, than ever I did?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know'd I was never wanted before!&rdquo; cried Mrs. Gummidge, with a pitiable whimper, &ldquo;and now I'm told so! How could I expect to be wanted, being so lone and lorn, and so contrairy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty seemed very much shocked at himself for having made a speech capable of this unfeeling construction, but was prevented from replying, by Peggotty's pulling his sleeve, and shaking her head. After looking at Mrs. Gummidge for some moments, in sore distress of mind, he glanced at the Dutch clock, rose, snuffed the candle, and put it in the window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Theer!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, cheerily. &ldquo;Theer we are, Missis Gummidge!&rdquo; Mrs. Gummidge slightly groaned. &ldquo;Lighted up, accordin' to custom! You're a wonderin' what that's fur, sir! Well, it's fur our little Em'ly. You see, the path ain't over light or cheerful arter dark; and when I'm here at the hour as she's a comin' home, I puts the light in the winder. That, you see,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, bending over me with great glee, &ldquo;meets two objects. She says, says Em'ly, &lsquo;Theer's home!&rsquo; she says. And likewise, says Em'ly, &lsquo;My uncle's theer!&rsquo; Fur if I ain't theer, I never have no light showed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a baby!&rdquo; said Peggotty; very fond of him for it, if she thought so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; returned Mr. Peggotty, standing with his legs pretty wide apart, and rubbing his hands up and down them in his comfortable satisfaction, as he looked alternately at us and at the fire, &ldquo;I doen't know but I am. Not, you see, to look at.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not azackly,&rdquo; observed Peggotty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; laughed Mr. Peggotty, &ldquo;not to look at, but to&mdash;to consider on, you know. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> doen't care, bless you! Now I tell you. When I go a looking and looking about that theer pritty house of our Em'ly's, I'm&mdash;I'm Gormed,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with sudden emphasis&mdash;&ldquo;theer! I can't say more&mdash;if I doen't feel as if the littlest things was her, a'most. I takes 'em up and I puts 'em down, and I touches of 'em as delicate as if they was our Em'ly. So 'tis with her little bonnets and that. I couldn't see one on 'em rough used a purpose&mdash;not fur the whole wureld. There's a babby fur you, in the form of a great Sea Porkypine!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, relieving his earnestness with a roar of laughter.</p>
<p>Peggotty and I both laughed, but not so loud.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's my opinion, you see,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with a delighted face, after some further rubbing of his legs, &ldquo;as this is along of my havin' played with her so much, and made believe as we was Turks, and French, and sharks, and every wariety of forinners&mdash;bless you, yes; and lions and whales, and I don't know what all!&mdash;when she warn't no higher than my knee. I've got into the way on it, you know. Why, this here candle, now!&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, gleefully holding out his hand towards it, &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> know wery well that arter she's married and gone, I shall put that candle theer, just the same as now. I know wery well that when I'm here o' nights (and where else should <hi rend="italics">I</hi> live, bless your arts, whatever fortun' I
<pb n="318" id="p318"/>
come into!) and she ain't here, or I ain't theer, I shall put the candle in the winder, and sit afore the fire, pretending I'm expecting of her, like I'm a doing now. <hi rend="italics">There's</hi> a babby for you,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, with another roar, &ldquo;in the form of a Sea Porkypine! Why, at the present minute, when I see the candle sparkle up, I says to myself, &lsquo;She's a looking at it! Em'ly's a coming!&rsquo; <hi rend="italics">There's</hi> a babby for you, in the form of a Sea Porkypine! Right for all that,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, stopping in his roar, and smiting his hands together; &ldquo;fur here she is!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was only Ham. The night should have turned more wet since I came in, for he had a large sou'wester hat on, slouched over his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where's Em'ly?&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty.</p>
<p>Ham made a motion with his head, as if she were outside. Mr. Peggotty took the light from the window, trimmed it, put it on the table, and was busily stirring the fire, when Ham, who had not moved, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mas'r Davy, will you come out a minute, and see what Em'ly and me has got to show you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>We went out. As I passed him at the door, I saw, to my astonishment and fright, that he was deadly pale. He pushed me hastily into the open air, and closed the door upon us. Only upon us two.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ham! what's the matter!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mas'r Davy!&mdash;&rdquo; Oh, for his broken heart, how dreadfully he wept!</p>
<p>I was paralyzed by the sight of such grief. I don't know what I thought, or what I dreaded. I could only look at him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ham! Poor good fellow! For Heaven's sake tell me what's the matter!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My love, Mas'r Davy&mdash;the pride and hope of my art&mdash;her that I'd have died for, and would die for now&mdash;she's gone!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gone?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Em'ly's run away! Oh, Mas'r Davy, think <hi rend="italics">how</hi> she's run away, when I pray my good and gracious God to kill her (her that is so dear above all things) sooner than let her come to ruin and disgrace!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The face he turned up to the troubled sky, the quivering of his clasped hands, the agony of his figure, remain associated with that lonely waste, in my remembrance, to this hour. It is always night there, and he is the only object in the scene.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a scholar,&rdquo; he said, hurriedly, &ldquo;and know what's right and best. What am I to say, in-doors? How am I ever to break it to him, Mas'r Davy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I saw the door move, and instinctively tried to hold the latch on the outside, to gain a moment's time. It was too late. Mr. Peggotty thrust forth his face; and never could I forget the change that came upon it when he saw us, if I were to live five hundred years.</p>
<p>I remember a great wail and cry, and the women hanging about him, and we all standing in the room; I with a paper in my hand, which Ham had given me; Mr. Peggotty, with his vest torn open, his hair wild, his face and lips quite white, and blood trickling down his bosom (it had sprung from his mouth, I think), looking fixedly at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Read it, sir,&rdquo; he said, in a low shivering voice. &ldquo;Slow, please. I doen't know as I can understand.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="319" id="p319"/>
<p>In the midst of the silence of death, I read thus, from a blotted letter.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;When you, who love me so much better than I ever have deserved, even when my mind was innocent, see this, I shall be far away.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall be fur away,&rdquo; he repeated slowly. &ldquo;Stop! Em'ly fur away. Well!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&lsquo;When I leave my dear home&mdash;my dear home&mdash;oh, my dear home!&mdash;in the morning,&rsquo;</p>
<p>the letter bore date on the previous night:</p>
<q><p>&lsquo;&mdash;it will be never to come back, unless he brings me back a lady. This will be found at night, many hours after, instead of me. Oh, if you knew how my heart is torn. If even you, that I have wronged so much, that never can forgive me, could only know what I suffer! I am too wicked to write about myself. Oh, take comfort in thinking that I am so bad. Oh, for mercy's sake, tell uncle that I never loved him half so dear as now. Oh, don't remember how affectionate and kind you have all been to me&mdash;don't remember we were ever to be married&mdash;but try to think as if I died when I was little, and was buried somewhere. Pray Heaven that I am going away from, have compassion on my uncle! Tell him that I never loved him half so dear. Be his comfort. Love some good girl, that will be what I was once to uncle, and be true to you, and worthy of you, and know no shame but me. God bless all! I'll pray for all, often, on my knees. If he don't bring me back a lady, and I don't pray for my own self, I'll pray for all. My parting love to uncle. My last tears, and my last thanks, for uncle!&rsquo; &rdquo;</p></q>
<p>That was all.</p>
<p>He stood, long after I had ceased to read, still looking at me. At length I ventured to take his hand, and to entreat him, as well as I could, to endeavour to get some command of himself. He replied, &ldquo;I thankee, sir, I thankee!&rdquo; without moving.</p>
<p>Ham spoke to him. Mr. Peggotty was so far sensible of <hi rend="italics">his</hi> affliction, that he wrung his hand; but, otherwise, he remained in the same state, and no one dared to disturb him.</p>
<p>Slowly, at last, he moved his eyes from my face, as if he were waking from a vision, and cast them round the room. Then he said, in a low voice:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who's the man? I want to know his name.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham glanced at me, and suddenly I felt a shock that struck me back.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's a man suspected,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty. &ldquo;Who is it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mas'r Davy!&rdquo; implored Ham. &ldquo;Go out a bit, and let me tell him. what I must. You doen't ought to hear it, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt the shock again. I sank down in a chair, and tried to utter some reply; but my tongue was fettered, and my sight was weak.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I want to know his name!&rdquo; I heard said, once more.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For some time past,&rdquo; Ham faltered, &ldquo;there's been a servant about here, at odd times. There's been a gen'lm'n too. Both of 'em belonged to one another.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty stood fixed as before, but now looking at him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The servant,&rdquo; pursued Ham, &ldquo;was seen along with&mdash;our poor girl&mdash;last night. He's been in hiding about here, this week or over. He was
<pb n="320" id="p320"/>
thought to have gone, but he was hiding. Doen't stay, Mas'r Davy, doen't!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt Peggotty's arm round my neck, but I could not have moved if the house had been about to fall upon me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A strange chay and horses was outside town, this morning, on the Norwich road, a'most afore the day broke,&rdquo; Ham went on. &ldquo;The servant went to it, and come from it, and went to it again. When he went to it again, Em'ly was nigh him. The t'other was inside. He's the man.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For the Lord's love,&rdquo; said Mr. Peggotty, falling back, and putting out his hand, as if to keep off what he dreaded. &ldquo;Doen't tell me his name's Steerforth!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mas'r Davy,&rdquo; exclaimed Ham, in a broken voice, &ldquo;it ain't no fault of yourn&mdash;and I am far from laying of it to you&mdash;but his name is Steerforth, and he's a damned villain!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Peggotty uttered no cry, and shed no tear, and moved no more, until he seemed to wake again, all at once, and pulled down his rough coat from its peg in a corner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bear a hand with this! I'm struck of a heap, and can't do it,&rdquo; he said, impatiently. &ldquo;Bear a hand, and help me. Well!&rdquo; when somebody had done so. &ldquo;Now give me that theer hat!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ham asked him whither he was going.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'm a going to seek my niece. I'm a going to seek my Em'ly. I'm a going, first, to stave in that theer boat, and sink it where I would have drownded <hi rend="italics">him,</hi> as I'm a livin' soul, if I had had one thought of what was in him! As he sat afore me,&rdquo; he said, wildly, holding out his clenched right hand, &ldquo;as he sat afore me, face to face, strike me down dead, but I'd have drownded him, and thought it right!&mdash;I'm a going to seek my niece.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where?&rdquo; cried Ham, interposing himself before the door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Anywhere! I'm a going to seek my niece through the wureld. I'm a going to find my poor niece in her shame, and bring her back. No one stop me! I tell you I'm a going to seek my niece!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no!&rdquo; cried Mrs. Gummidge, coming between them, in a fit of crying. &ldquo;No, no, Dan'l, not as you are now. Seek her in a little while, my lone lorn Dan'l, and that'll be but right; but not as you are now. Sit ye down, and give me your forgiveness for having ever been a worrit to you, Dan'l&mdash;what have <hi rend="italics">my</hi> contrairies ever been to this!&mdash;and let us speak a word about them times when she was first an orphan, and when Ham was too, and when I was a poor widder woman, and you took me in. It'll soften your poor heart, Dan'l,&rdquo; laying her head upon his shoulder, &ldquo;and you'll bear your sorrow better; for you know the promise, Dan'l, &lsquo;As you have done it unto one of the least of these, you have done it unto me&rsquo;; and that can never fail under this roof, that's been our shelter for so many, many year!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was quite passive now; and when I heard him crying, the impulse that had been upon me to go down upon my knees, and ask their pardon for the desolation I had caused, and curse Steerforth, yielded to a better feeling. My overcharged heart found the same relief, and I cried too.</p>
</div2></div1>

</body>
<back>
<div1>
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<head>WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> WHOLESALE AND RETAIL STATIONERS, <lb/> PRINTERS BY STEAM POWER, <lb/> LITHOGRAPHERS &amp; ENGRAVERS ON STONE,</head><p>Draughtsmen and Ornamental Writers, <lb/> COPPER-PLATE ENGRAVERS, AND DIE SINKERS <lb/> MANUFACTURERS OF <lb/> PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS, <lb/> IMPROVED ADHESIVE ENVELOPES, <lb/> TRANSPARENT TRACING PAPER AND CLOTH <lb/> LETTER COPYING MACHINES, <lb/> METALLIC PENS, PURE CUMBERLAND LEAD PENCILS, <lb/> &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., <lb/> 65, 66, 67, &amp; 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON, <lb/> AND <lb/> 49, PARLIAMENT STREET, WESTMINSTER; <lb/> LAW STATIONERS, PARCHMENT DEALERS, AND PUBLISHERS OF <lb/> LAW FORMS, <lb/> AT 24, BIRCHIN LANE, CORNHILL.</p>
<p>Railway and Assurance Companies, Joint Stock and Private Banks, the Legal Profession, Architects, Civil Engineers, Surveyors, Auctioneers, Estate Agents, Bankers, Merchants, and all large Consumers, will derive considerable advantage by supplying themselves from these establishments, all material being purchased by Waterlow and Sons in the first markets, and every article being manufactured under their immediate superintendence.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
<head>WRITING PAPERS,</head><p>OF THE MOST APPROVED MAKERS.</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="6">
<head><hi rend="italics">All qualities, Glazed or Hotpressed.</hi></head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, per ream </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office Letter, highly recommended </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter Note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="6">
<head><hi rend="italics">Note Paper half the price of Letter.</hi></head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cream Laid Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cream Laid Letter Note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Large Cream Laid Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foreign Post, best quality per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Very best Cream or Blue Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 22 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 36 or 42-lined Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 36 or 42-lined, very best Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Wove Draft, folio per rm. </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Wove Draft, 4to per rm. </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Laid, folio per rm. </cell>
<cell> 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Laid, 4to per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>LETTER OR NOTE PAPER HEADED WITH ENGRAVED ADDRESS, AT 5S PER REAM EXTRA.</p>
<p>NO CHARGE BEING MADE FOR THE PLATE, <lb/> Or in Letter Press at 3s. 6d. per ream extra, if two or more Reams are Ordered.</p>
<p>Ruled Papers of every description.</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="13">
<row role="label">
<cell> ENVELOPES. </cell>
<cell cols="6">3 NOTE SIZES. </cell>
<cell cols="6">3 LETTER SIZES. </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 1,000. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 250. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 100. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 1,000. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 250. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 100. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream Laid, very Best </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<head>EXTRA SIZED ENVELOPES.</head>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Wove, 8&frac34; by 3&frac58; </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Laid, 8&frac34; by 3&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, for &frac12; qr. 8&frac34; by 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Cartridge 8&frac34; by 4 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Draft Laid 10&frac14; by 4&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Draft Laid Cartridge 11 by 4&frac78; </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge Brief 13&frac18; by 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge Deed 11&frac34; by 9&frac58; </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>pr.100 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Extra for embossing Official Envelopes,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. per</hi> 250, <hi rend="italics">and larger sizes,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> pr.100</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="2">
<head>Linen-Lined Envelopes at greatly Reduced Prices.</head>
<row>
<cell> No. 1, Letter size, 4&frac34; by 2&frac34; at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2, Letter size, 5&frac18; by 3&frac18; at 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3, Large size, 5&frac34; by 3&frac34; at 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 4, Extra size, 7 by 4 at 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> No. 5, Official, 8&frac34; by 3&frac12; at 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6, Official, &frac12; qr., 8&frac34; by 4 at 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 7, Draft, 10&frac14; by 4&frac12; at 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>IMPROVED ADHESIVE ENVELOPES,</head><p>Saving the expense and trouble of wafers or sealing-wax, yet perfectly secure, embossed with elegant designs of Initial Dies, of from one to four letters, or with Commercial Dies, at the following prices, without any charge for Die.</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="13">
<row role="label">
<cell> ENVELOPES. </cell>
<cell cols="4">PER 1,000. </cell>
<cell cols="4">PER 500. </cell>
<cell cols="4">PER 250. </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> (Embossed with any Initials.) </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream Laid </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>SPECIAL DIES sunk for Coats of Arms, Crests and Devices of every description, from 3s. 6d. upwards, which may be used instead of the Initial Dies as mentioned above (for which <hi rend="italics">no charge is made</hi>). These dies may also be used for embossing note and letter paper to correspond with the envelopes.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Superfine Adhesive Envelopes, embossed with single Initials, and the Commercial</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Adhesive Envelope always in Stock, at</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. per Hundred.</hi></p>
<p>ENVELOPES EMBOSSED IN COLOURS, OR BLACK FOR MOURNING, TWO SHILLINGS PER THOUSAND EXTRA.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
<head>WHATMAN'S DRAWING PAPER,</head>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> <hi rend="italics">Rough or Smooth.</hi> </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian </cell>
<cell> 53 </cell>
<cell> by 31 </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian, 2nd quality </cell>
<cell> 53 </cell>
<cell> by 31 </cell>
<cell> 1 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 40 </cell>
<cell> by 27 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Atlas </cell>
<cell> 34 </cell>
<cell> by 26 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Colombier </cell>
<cell> 34 </cell>
<cell> by 23 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 </cell>
<cell> by 22 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elephant </cell>
<cell> 28 </cell>
<cell> by 23 </cell>
<cell> &pound;0 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Super Royal </cell>
<cell> 27 </cell>
<cell> by 19 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Royal </cell>
<cell> 23 </cell>
<cell> by 19 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Medium </cell>
<cell> 22 </cell>
<cell> by 17 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Demy </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> by 15 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Outside Drawing Papers, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per lb.; 80<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per cwt. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Thick Rough Drawing Imperial, per quire, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>CONTINUOUS DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<p>The largest Drawing Paper ever made: it is 4 feet 6 inches wide, and of any required length, without a joint. This paper preserves its surface against the action of India-rubber, and will colour as well as the best Drawing Paper. It will be found invaluable for Railway Plans and Sections, Contract Drawings, Manufacturers' Designs, &amp;c., and is admirably adapted for Cartoons, or large Water-colour Drawings.</p>
<p>54 inches wide.....per yard run. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>54 inches wide second quality ..per yard run. 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="5">
<head>WHATMAN'S DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 40 </cell>
<cell> by 27 </cell>
<cell> &pound;0 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 </cell>
<cell> by 22 </cell>
<cell> 0 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="5">
<head>SUPERFINE STRONG DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge </cell>
<cell> 26 by 21 </cell>
<cell> quire 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> ream &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 by 22 </cell>
<cell> quire 5 0 </cell>
<cell> ream 4 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dble. Elepht. </cell>
<cell> 40 by 27 </cell>
<cell> quire 7 6 </cell>
<cell> ream 6 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>MOUNTED DRAWING PAPER.</head>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> per foot sq. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian, on very best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2nd Antiquarian, and 1st quality, Double Elephant to Demy (inclusive), on very best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2nd Antiquarian, and 1st quality, Double Elephant to Demy (inclusive), on very best linen or holland 2nd linen </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Continuous Drawing Cartridge, on best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Plans mounted on fine linen </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tracings mounted on mounted paper </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The following mounted Drawing Papers, on second linen, at 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per foot square, are always <hi rend="italics">kept in stock</hi>:&mdash;</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 26 inches wide </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 39 inches wide </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 52 inches wide </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>IMPROVED TRANSPARENT TRACING PAPER,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Warranted of the very best material. Samples will be sent free, upon application.</hi></p>
<p>The following extracts from the <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Art Union,&rdquo;</hi> and <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Magazine of Science,&rdquo;</hi> will be sufficient guarantee of the excellent quality of these papers, and the great celebrity to which they have attained:</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Art Union.</hi>&mdash;&ldquo;Messrs. Waterlow and Sons' Tracing Paper is certainly the best we have ever tried, being perfectly transparent, though sufficiently thick for all practical purposes, and perfectly free from that oiliness we generally meet with in paper of a similar description, taking the ink as readily as ordinary writing paper. It must be invaluable to all who require the use of such an article.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Magazine of Science.</hi>&mdash;&ldquo;To those very numerous classes of the public&mdash;artists, architects, engineers, map-makers, pattern-drawers&mdash;indeed to all who, whether professionally or otherwise, have occasion to employ tracing paper, we would, with earnestness, urge the extreme worth and merits of that manufactured by Messrs. Waterlow and Sons. In happy contrast to the paper of a like nature, too frequently to be met with, theirs is entirely devoid of all nasty, unclean greasiness; it is thoroughly transparent, and can be traced over either by the pencil, or&mdash;a great desideratum&mdash;by pen and ink, Assuredly this is a very admirable article.&rdquo;</p>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="3">
<head>TRACING PAPER.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Double Crown, yel. or blue wove </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, yel. or blue wove </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 60 by 40 Dble. dble. dble. Crown, yel. wove </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> yel. or bl. wove </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> yel. or bl. wove Retree, 30 by 40 and 30 by 20, half-price. </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Double Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 60 by 40 Dble. dble. dble. Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, extra thick </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, double thick </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div4 type="section">
<head>PATENT TRACING LINEN.</head>
<p>This article is manufactured at one operation, and will be found very valuable for permanent tracings. The texture is remarkably fine and transparent.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> No. 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 inches wide per yard </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 28 inches wide per yard </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 36 inches wide per yard </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div4>
<div4 type="section">
<head>TRACING CLOTH PAPER.</head>
<p>This article may be had of any continuous length, without a joint, and is warranted to take pencil, ink and colour, as well as drawing paper.</p>
<p>38 inches wide ..... per yard 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div4>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
<head>IMPROVED PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS,</head><p>Made of the Patent Vellum Sized Cream Laid Paper, which is manufactured of extra strength and finish, expressly for these account books, or of first-class blue laid Paper, bound with patent backs, in Russia, calf, vellum, white or green forrel, bazil (plain or grained), and warranted to open flat. They are also made with bands, iron backs, brass corners, and patent locks, with or without printed or lithographed headings, and paged or folio'd in type, by a machine of ingenious construction, which produces a clear and bold figure, of unequalled regularity. The following price list is intended as a guide for books termed extra, the very best that can be manufactured, and whole-bound. Contracts taken for the supply of large establishments and exporters; or tenders given for any particular book or set of books that may be required.</p>
<p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>FOOLSCAP.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Broad Folio,</hi> 12&frac12; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 8; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 15&frac12; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 6.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> if in Russia Bands, viz., 3 straps over the back, 8<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> if Double Bands or Russia along the Top and Bottom and one Band in the centre, 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 7 q. or 656 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>DEMY.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Broad Folio,</hi> 14&frac12; by 9&frac12;; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 7&frac14;&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 9 q. or 848 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>MEDIUM.&mdash;16 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 10&frac14;&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 24 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 9 q. or 848 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>ROYAL.&mdash;18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 11.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 3 q. or 272 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 750 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 23 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>SUPER-ROYAL.&mdash;18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 13.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> Extra, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> Extra, 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> Extra, 25 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>IMPERIAL.&mdash;20&frac14; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 14&frac14;.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> Extra, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> Extra, 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> Extra, 29 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="2">
<head>PRINTED HEADINGS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Three quires or under </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire, extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Over three quires and under six quires </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per quire extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Over six quires and under eight quires </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Eight quires and upwards </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per quire. extra. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Parchment Books made in a superior manner, properly ruled and red-lined, for <lb/> Copyhold Court Rolls, Company's Deeds, Awards, &amp;c.</p>
<p>An assortment of <hi rend="italics">Ledgers, Journals, Day Books, Cash Books, Letter Books, Minute Books, &amp;c., &amp;c.,</hi> of different sized papers, whole and half-bound, in various styles, are kept in stock, <hi rend="italics">and being well seasoned,</hi> can be confidently recommended.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5a"/>
<head>PURE CUMBERLAND LEAD PENCILS,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Warranted free from grit, and to retain the point.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The very best Drawing Pencils that can be manufactured, <hi rend="italics">French polished,</hi> HHHH. HHH. HH. H. HB. F. FS. B. BB. BBB. per doz. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Second quality, ditto, equal to those usually sold at 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> HHH. HH. H. HB. F. FS. B. BB. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Waterlow's original Office and Commercial Pencil, French polished </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Second quality, ditto, ditto </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Penny Pencils </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> School Pencils </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brookman and Langdon's best Drawing </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="subchapter">
<head>METALLIC PENS,</head><p>WARRANTED OF PURE DAMASCUS STEEL, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Selected, after many years' experience, from the best Makers, and</hi>
<lb/> Manufactured with all the LATEST IMPROVEMENTS.</p>
<p>A Sample Card of 13 sorts of these beautiful Pens will be forwarded by post, free, upon receipt of Eight Postage Stamps.</p><p>
<table rows="23" cols="8">
<row role="label">
<cell> No. on Card. </cell>
<cell> DESCRIPTION OF THE PENS. </cell>
<cell> Per Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Half-Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Qrtr. Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 47 </cell>
<cell> Correspondence Pen, for general letter writing </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 65 </cell>
<cell> Bank Pen, highly recommended for mercantile use </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66 </cell>
<cell> LAW Pen, fine point </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 67 </cell>
<cell> LAW Pen, medium point, for parchment </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 68 </cell>
<cell> Serrated Pen, for fine rapid writing </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 70 </cell>
<cell> Imitation Quill Pen, very pliant </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 71 </cell>
<cell> Commercial Pen, admirable for bold writing </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 83 </cell>
<cell> National Pen, for a light hand </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 84 </cell>
<cell> Eagle Pen, a firm pen, of extra hardened steel </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 85 </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref1" target="B1">*</ref><note id="B1" target="ref1"><p>* Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The Magnum Bonum, a better pen cannot be had for book-keeping
 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> The Magnum Bonum, second quality </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 98 </cell>
<cell> THE 2-HOLE RAVEN PEN; much attention has always been paid to the manufacture of this pen, and from the great sale it has had since the introduction of it by W. &amp; Sons, they can safely assert that a more <hi rend="italics">useful</hi> pen is not to be obtained </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 99 </cell>
<cell> THE 2-HOLE RAVEN PEN; medium point, particularly recommended for the use of the <hi rend="italics">Legal</hi> profession </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> WATERLOW AND SONS <hi rend="italics">have also introduced the following Pens, of whom only they can be obtained:&mdash;</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 1, for small engrossing hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 2, for large engrossing or small text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 3, for ordinary text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 4, for large bold text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref2" target="B2">*</ref><note id="B2" target="ref2"><p>* Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The Drawing and Mapping Pen, also for Ladies' use
 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref3" target="B3">&dagger;</ref><note id="B3" target="ref3"><p>&dagger; Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The <hi rend="italics">extra fine</hi> Drawing and Mapping Pen, for the finest drawings, on paper and ivory
 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> QUILL PENS, at 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per 100. Turkey Quills, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> ditto. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Any of the above Pens will be sent, post free, at</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. per Gross extra.</hi></p>
<p>The Patent Expanding Pen Holder will fit any pen, in Cedar, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen; Ebony and German <lb/> Silver, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per dozen. Ivory and German Silver Pen Holders, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen.</p>
<p>Porcupine Holders, mounted and tipped, 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each; 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen.</p>
<p>Superior Black Ink, adapted for Steel Pens, warranted not to change color, or corrode the pen, gallons, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi>
<lb/> quarts, 2<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> pints, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> half-pints, 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> and gallon bottles, in baskets for the country, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Copying Ink, warranted to give perfect copies, quarts 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> pints, 2<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and in gallon bottles, 9<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> <lb/> or packed in baskets for the country, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Glass Cone Inkstand is the most economical ever offered to the public. It presents so small a surface of ink to the atmosphere, that no evaporation takes place, and the ink is always fresh to the last.</p>
<p>Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> &amp; 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Logger head Inkstands, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Logger, with Cap only. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Logger, no Cap or Plate 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6a"/>
<head>SURVEYORS' MEASURING BOOKS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Doz. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, ruled or plain, whole bound, made of Metallic Paper, 160 pages, and fitted with pencil, 8vo. </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, ruled or plain, half-bound, made of Spfine. Paper, 160 pp 8vo. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, ruled or plain, half-bound, made of Spfine. Paper, 160 pp 6to. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, whole-bound and clasped 8vo. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, whole-bound and clasped 6to. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Levelling Books, ruled and printed, each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>BLOTTING PAPERS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Ream. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White or Pink Wove </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White or Pink Laid </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> *Patent White Wove, of considerable strength and durability, per quire 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 45 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> *Patent Salmon Wove ..per quire 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 65 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SURVEYORS' MEASURING TAPES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66-Feet Railway Tapes, with Enamel Leather Case and Folding Brass Handle </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66-Feet Railway Tapes, with Brass Rim </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 12-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>WRAPPING PAPERS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brown Papers per cwt. </cell>
<cell> 50 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, demy, per rm. </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, royal per rm. </cell>
<cell> 28 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, imperial per rm. </cell>
<cell> 35 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hand Paper, (white brown) per rm. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SUNDRIES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="54" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine Wax, red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parcel red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, best mixed per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, patent mixed per lb. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, Vermillion Chequered, for affixing to paper deeds per box </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Fcap. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Post 4to  </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Fcap. 4to  </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Clips each 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, large blue, lined each </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, small blue, lined each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, large crimson, lined each </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, small crimson, lined each </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boxwood Rulers, bound-brass, 42 inches long, and engraved inches each </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Ebony Office Rules per inch </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1&frac12; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Patent Indorsement Boxes, supplied with liquid ink, dampers, cleaning brushes, &amp;c. for the better use of brass stamps, ea. </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wax Vesta Lights </cell>
<cell> per 1,000 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vermillion Fluid, for red lining skins </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vermillion Powders </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 16 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 24 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 32 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Silk Ferret, green per piece </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Silk Ferret, green narrow per piece </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cotton Ferret per piece </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> China Grass, green narrow per piece </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Union Cord, green narrow per reel </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Green Silk Tags, for files, and Bankruptcy Proceedings per dozen </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pounce Boxes, japanned, with rubber, each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Desk Knives, cocoa handles each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Erasers, cocoa handles each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Hones, in mahogany case each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Rubber Bottle, prime thick, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Rubber Patent per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Runners, box handles each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bodkins, box handles, with or without eyes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Seal Chisels, box handles, with or without eyes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tin Pens, for ruling Parchment each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Skinholders each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parchment Knives each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paper Pounce per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parchment Pounce per lb. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solid Writing Pads, demy folio each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Sand Boxes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafer Seals, ebony each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Ink per stick, 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drawing Pins per dozen </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drawing Pins Albata per dozen </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ivory Folders, or Paper Knives each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Outsides Writing Paper per lb. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String and Twine per lb. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drawing Vellums at all prices. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>POSTAGE SCALES AND BALANCES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weigh 8 oz </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weigh 16 oz </cell>
<cell> 16 0 per pair. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weigh 2 lbs </cell>
<cell> 21 0 per pair. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Improved Balances, to weigh 16 oz. ....17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Improved Balances, for deeds and parcels, to weigh 2lbs. &pound;1 10</p>
<p>These scales and balances, <hi rend="italics">originally introduced by</hi> WATERLOW &amp; SONS, are recommended for simplicity and accuracy of construction; with fair usage, they will never get out of order, and are lower in price than any machines or scales ever before offered.</p>
<pb n="7" id="p7a"/>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<head>LETTER CAGES,</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 divisions, with drawer and date box, </cell>
<cell> each 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 divisions, without drawer and date box </cell>
<cell> each 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>CASH BOXES, <lb/> With Patent Locks, Japanned and Cilt, with divisions for Notes, Gold, Silver, and Copper.</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> 8 inches by 5 </cell>
<cell> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 10 inches by 6 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<head>JAPANNED DEED BOXES.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 14 by 10 by 10 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 18 by 12&frac12; by 14 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 24 by 16 by 17 </cell>
<cell> 22 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> Pen Trays, Ebony each </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pen Trays, Gutta Percha, beautifully moulded to imitate marble each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, brass fist, 4&frac12; by 2&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, brass fist, 6 by 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, lion knob </cell>
<cell> 4&frac12; by 2&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, lion knob </cell>
<cell> 6 by 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>String or Tape Winder, with fixed knife <lb/> 2 sizes, 5s 6d. and 6s. 6d</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, 1lb. each </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> Spring Taper </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, &frac12;lb. each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Stands, ea. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, &frac14;lb. each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Candles for ditto. per box(18) 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Pen Racks, Ebony, <lb/> each 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Japanned Date Boxes, <lb/> each 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lady's Hand Paper Weights </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="1" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> Bird Paper Weights </cell>
<cell> each 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A great variety of other Paper Weights, in elegant designs of Berlin Iron, Japan, &amp;c.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8a"/>
<head>PATENT LETTER COPYING MACHINES,</head><p><hi rend="italics">(The working parts manufactured of Steel, and finished with the greatest accuracy,)</hi>
<lb/> AT CONSIDERABLY REDUCED PRICES.</p>
<p>SCREW PRESS.</p>
<p>LEVER PRESS.</p>
<p>The increasing demand for these Presses, and the great satisfaction which they have universally given, have induced us to manufacture a large stock of the most useful sizes; we are therefore enabled to offer them at much lower prices than heretofore; the large sale which they have met with has convinced us of the impolicy of endeavouring to maintain the old and extravagant scale of prices charged at a time when it was the exception, instead of as at present the rule, for every Counting-house or Gentleman's Library to be furnished with a Copying Machine. These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="12">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Lever Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Mach. wrt. iron beam. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Damping Boxes. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large 4to </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 11s. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foolscap Folio </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 12s. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Post Folio </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 14s. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Larger Sizes for Railway Companies to order.</p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="9">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Quarto Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Book or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="9">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Foolscap Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Book or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="9">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Folio Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Books or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Copying Books, Type-Paged and Indexed,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Half-Bound Calf, Lettered.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="2">
<head>POST QUARTO.</head>
<row>
<cell> 300 leaves </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 400 leaves </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 750 leaves </cell>
<cell> 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<head>FOOLSCAP FOLIO.</head>
<row>
<cell> 300 leaves </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Copying Books, Type-Paged and Indexed,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Quarter-Bound.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 750 leaves </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Skeleton Guard Books, Half-Bound, with Index,</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">to hold</hi> 500 <hi rend="italics">letters.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Quarto </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foolscap </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<head>COPYING INK.</head>
<row>
<cell> Quarts </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pints </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gallons </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gallons packed </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Copying Paper, English (blue wove) or French (pure white) at 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per ream, or 1000 &frac12;-sheets letter.</p>
<p>THE PATENT CAPILLARY INSTANTANEOUS COPYING PAPER DAMPER renders unnecessary the use of a basin of water and sponge, or brush, is much cleaner, and always ready for use. Price 7s. 6d.</p>
<closer>65, 66, 67 &amp; 68, London Wall. London.</closer>
</div2>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>THE WINTER OF 1814.</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Two neighbours, meeting, talk'd about the cold,</l>
<l>The one was young, and one was rather old.</l>
<l>&ldquo;Good morning (said the young one&mdash;Mr. Phizz,)</l>
<l>What's the best news? How cold the weather is!&rdquo;</l>
<l>&ldquo;Yes (said the other,) it is rather cold;</l>
<l>But nothing like it was in times of old.</l>
<l>This winter's not a fifteenth part so keen</l>
<l>As that which happen'd in the year 'Fourteen;</l>
<l>'Twas then the river Thames was frozen o'er,</l>
<l>While people pass'd on foot from shore to shore.</l>
<l>The ships were all in icy fetters pinn'd,</l>
<l>Unable to be moved by tide or wind.</l>
<l>Talk of cold winters! <hi rend="italics">that</hi> was one, I own,</l>
<l>'Twould scarcely have disgraced the Frigid Zone.</l>
<l>Large fairs were held on Thames's icy floor,</l>
<l>Throng'd by enormous crowds; and, what is more,</l>
<l>Upon the ice was lit a &lsquo;furnace-fire&rsquo;</l>
<l>Which roasted a stupendous ox entire.</l>
<l>It was a most exciting scene to quiz!&rdquo;</l>
<l>&ldquo;So I should think&rdquo; (said Mr. Philip Phizz).</l>
<l>&ldquo;Ah! (said his friend, addressing him again,)</l>
<l>We'd not the benefit of MOSES' <hi rend="italics">then;</hi></l>
<l>How well would MOSES' winter coats have sold</l>
<l>In such a season's memorable cold.</l>
<l>Many poor creatures suffered most severely</l>
<l>Through winter clothing being sold so dearly.</l>
<l>MOSES and SON would certainly have been</l>
<l>Of vast advantage in the year 'Fourteen.</l>
<l>But never mind! we've got these tradesmen <hi rend="italics">now,</hi></l>
<l>And that's a famous thing, you must allow.</l>
<l>I've just now been an over-coat to buy;&rdquo;</l>
<l>&ldquo;Indeed (replied the other,) so have <hi rend="italics">I.</hi>&rdquo;</l>
<l>Much more was said by each, as you'll suppose,</l>
<l>But, as I've no more space my lines must close.</l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome style of Overcoats </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Shooting Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lounging and Morning Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Youths' and Boys' Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suit </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys' Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cassimere in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Dress Coats, from </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Frock </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> H. and T. Suit, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from &pound;3 to &pound;20.</p>
<p>NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Minion of the Million,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be bad on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON</head>
<p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is opened till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p10a" n="10"/>
<opener>The NOVELTY most recently introduced <lb/> by Messrs. NICOLL is called</opener><head>NICOLL'S PATENT <lb/> EIDER DOWN PALETOT,</head><p>such novelty consisting in the adaptation of Eider Down in the formation of NICOLL'S PALETOT, the original elegance and utility of which is, however, faithfully preserved.</p>
<p>Eiders are found in greatest numbers in Iceland and the Fern Islands, where their beautiful and delicate down is well known to be proof against the most severe cold, and even the small quantity which can be compressed and concealed between the two hands will serve in the formation of a Paletot, which, while it has most extraordinary lightness, has, nevertheless, more warmth than the finest and thickest blanket, the great desideratum for a winter garment being thus accomplished, namely, personal warmth without fatigue.</p>
<p>Public Inspection is invited at Messrs. NICOLL'S Wholesale and Retail Warerooms.</p>
<p>114, 116, 118, 120, <lb/> REGENT-STREET, &amp; <lb/> 22, CORNHILL, <lb/> LONDON.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
