<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VI:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Brooke Phillips</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.   235 K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. VI</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent> 54 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1849</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.
 </p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>


<change>
<date>2002-11-11, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-30, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>


<titlePage>

<docTitle><titlePart> No.  VI. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> OCTOBER.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>
<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>

<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of Bedding, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest stock and greatest variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES, <lb/> Of which they were the Original Introducers: these Mattresses are made of the finest material, quite equal to the best made in Paris. Also, <lb/> GERMAN SPRING MATTRESSES.</p>
<p>These HEAL and SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are selling at a much lower price than any other house, and can recommend one of them, with a FRENCH MATTRESS on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>THE EIDER DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen <hi rend="italics">only</hi> at their House. It is the warmest, the lightest, and the most elegant covering ever introduced, suitable to the <hi rend="italics">Bed,</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Couch,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">Carriage.</hi> All who have travelled on the Continent are aware that no covering produces such extreme warmth with the same weight; so that for Invalids they are a perfect luxury. Their <lb/> BED FEATHERS <lb/> are also PURIFIED BY STEAM, WITH PATENT MACHINERY, by which the offensive properties of the quill are evaporated and carried off, without subjecting the Feathers to the unpleasant smell of the stove, to which all Feathers dressed in the ordinary way are liable.</p>
<p>HEAL and SON are now enabled to sell Grey Goose Feathers at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per lb., Poultry, 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foreign Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Grey Goose </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White Goose </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dantzic Goose </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>OLD FEATHER-BEDS re-dressed by this process are perfectly freed from all impurities; and, by expanding the Feathers, the bulk is greatly increased, and the Bed consequently rendered much fuller and softer, at 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb.</p>
<p>OLD AND MOTHY MATTRESSES effectually cured and re-made.</p>
<p>Every description of BLANKETS, QUILTS, and SHEETINGS.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S LIST OF BEDDING.</head>
<p>It contains full particulars of WEIGHTS, SIZES, and PRICES, of every description of Bedding, and is so arranged that purchasers are enabled to judge of the articles best suitable to make a comfortable Bed. Sent free by post on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196, (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL,) <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb id="p1" n="[1]"/>
<opener>No. VI.&mdash;OCTOBER, 1849.</opener>
<head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<head>VALUABLE STANDARD BOOKS.</head>
<p>TOMLINS' (G.F.) HISTORY of ENGLAND; combining the various Histories by Rapin, Henry, Hume, Smollett, and Belsham; corrected by reference to Turner, Lingard, Hallam, Brodie, and others. From the Invasion by the Romans, B.C. 55, to the Birth of the Prince of Wales, A.D. 1841. Embellished with Portraits of all the Kings and Queens of England from William the Conqueror to Queen Victoria, and other Engravings. 6 vols. 8vo, handsomely half-bound in calf, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10s.</p>
<p>The same book, bound in cloth, with full gilt backs, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A full, copious, and excellent History.&rdquo;</p>
<p>J. K. respectfully informs the Public, that the above History of England is undoubtedly one of the cheapest, most recent, and best now published, and parties wishing to obtain a good one should lose no time in becoming a purchaser of the book.</p>
<p>ARMITAGE'S PLOT AND PEERAGE; or, LORD VISCOUNT PETERSHAM. 12mo, cloth, gilt edges, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>), or by post, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE MOTHER COUNTRY; or, THE SPADE, THE WASTES, AND THE ELDEST SON. Being an Examination of the Condition of England. By SIDNEY SMITH. his volume embraces Home Colonisation, Spade Husbandry, the Improvement of Waste Lands, the Allotment System, Entails, Primogeniture, the Land Monopoly, &amp;c. &amp;c. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, or by post, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE WORKS OF HENRY MACKENZIE, containing The Man of Feeling, The Man of the World, and Julia De Roubign&eacute;. Complete. Illustrated with four beautiful wood engravings. 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>, or by post, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>LONDON ON THE THAMES; or, LIFE ABOVE AND BELOW BRIDGE. BY ANGUS B. REACH. With 62 Illustrations by HINE, GAVARNI, and others. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE PUPPET-SHOWMAN'S ALBUM. With contributions by the most eminent Light and Heavy Writers of the Day. Illustrated by GAVARNI. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>CROLY'S, DR., MARRIAGE WITH THE SISTER OF A DECEASED WIFE INJURIOUS TO MORALS. AND UNAUTHORISED BY HOLY SCRIPTURE. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (Only 500 printed.)</p>
<p>REAL LIFE IN IRELAND. Coloured Plates. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE LIFE AND EXPLOITS OF DON QUIXOTE. Translated from the Spanish. By CHARLES JARVIS. Illustrated by 24 Designs by R. CRUICKSHANK. A beautiful clear type. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE BASKET OF FLOWERS. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> A very beautiful and useful story.</p>
<p>EDINBURGH CABINET LIBRARY.&mdash;ITALY, AND THE ITALIAN ISLANDS, from the earliest Ages to the present time. By W. SPALDING. Woodcuts and Maps. 3 vols. cloth, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>HISTORICAL AND DESCRIPTIVE ACCOUNT OF BRITISH AMERICA; comprehending Upper and Lower Canada, Nova Scotia, the Far Countries, &amp;c. With a detail of the Principles and best Modes of Emigration. By HUGH MURRAY. 6 Maps and 10 Engravings. 3 vols. cloth, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>SCANDINAVIA, ANCIENT AND MODERN; being a HISTORY OF DENMARK, SWEDEN, AND NORWAY, &amp;c. &amp;c. By ANDREW CRICHTON and HENRY WHEATON. Map and Woodcuts. 2 vols. cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>TREASURY (THE) OF NATURAL AND EXPERIMENTAL PHILOSOPHY; containing Facts and Observations on various subjects. By Sir W. HERSCHELL, Sir H. DAVY, FARADAY, Dr. YOUNG, and others. 12mo, cloth, pp. 700. 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (pub. at 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>)</p>
<p>SOUTH AFRICA AND AUSTRALIA.&mdash;WHETHER TO GO, AND WHITHER; or, THE CAPE AND THE GREAT SOUTH LAND. By SIDNEY SMITH. Embracing the whole Southern Fields of Emigration, and the most recent information relating to Australia, &amp;c. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, or by post, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>TOUR (THE) OF THE THAMES; or, THE SIGHTS AND SONGS OF THE KING OF RIVERS; containing numerous original BALLADS AND TALES relating to the River Thames. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>, or by post, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Well adapted to afford amusement in travelling.&rdquo; A very witty, clever book.</p>
<p>MILTON'S POETICAL WORKS, with a Life of the Author. Complete Edition. Large type, 658 pages, cloth. Post 8vo, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>The same book, with 7 Plates, elegantly bound in cloth, with full gilt sides. 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Gilt edges.</p>
<p>A very handsome volume, well adapted for a <lb/> Present, Birth-Day Gift, &amp;c.</p>
<p>COLBURN'S MODERN STANDARD NOVELISTS.&mdash;A Select Collection of the best Works of Fiction, by the most distinguished English writers. (3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each. Published at 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>MRS. ARMYTAGE; or, Female Domination. By Mrs. GORE.</p>
<p>EMILIA WYNDHAM. By the Author of &ldquo;Two Old Men's Tales.&rdquo;</p>
<p>MR. WARD'S TREMAINE.</p>
<p>CAPT. MARRVAT'S FRANK MILDMAY.</p>
<p>MR. H. SMITH'S BRAMBLETYE HOUSE.</p>
<p>_____ ZILLAH. A Tale of the Holy City.</p>
<p>SIR E. L. BULWER'S PELHAM.</p>
<p>_____ DISOWNED.</p>
<p>_____ DEVEREUX.</p>
<p>LADY MORGAN'S O'DONNELL.</p>
<p>_____ FLORENCE MACARTHY.</p>
<p>_____ WILD IRISH GIRL.</p>
<p>MR. GLEIG'S CHELSEA PENSIONERS.</p>
<p>MR. LISTER'S GRANBY.</p>
<p>MR. JAMES'S RICHELIEU.</p>
<p>MR. HOOK'S GURNEY MARRIED.</p>
<p>_____ SAVINGS AND DOINGS. First Series, comprising Danvers, The Friend of the Family, Merton, &amp;c.</p>
<p>_____ SAYINGS AND DOINGS. Second Series, comprising The Sutherlands, The Man of Many Friends, Doubts and Fears, and Passion and Principle.</p>
<p>_____ SAYINGS AND DOINGS. Third Series, comprising Cousin William, and Gervase Skinner. MISS PORTER'S LAKE OF KILLARNEY.</p>
<p>ADAM BROWN. By HORACE SMITH, Esq., Author of &ldquo;Brambletye House.&rdquo; 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>ARTHUR ARUNDEL. By HORACE SMITH, K-q., Author of &ldquo;Zillah.&rdquo; 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>THE HUSSAR. By Mr. GLEIG, Author of &ldquo;The Chelsea Pensioners.&rdquo; 3<hi rend="italics">s</hi> (pub. at 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>)</p>
<p>CRICHTON. By W. H. AINSWORTH, with Illustrations by H. K. BROWNE. 8vo. 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> (pub. at 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>A PICTURESQUE TOUR OF THE RIVER THAMES IN ITS WESTERN COURSE. Including particular descriptions of Richmond, Windsor, and Hampton Court. By JOHN FISHER MURRAY. Illustrated with upwards of 100 highly finished Wood Engravings. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<closer>JOHN KENDRICK, No. 4, CHARLOTTE ROW, MANSION HOUSE, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Just published, in Foolscap 8vo, price 5s.,</hi></opener><head>A SHORT INQUIRY <lb/> INTO <lb/> THE HISTORY OF AGRICULTURE, <lb/> IN ANCIENT, MEDI&AElig;VAL, AND MODERN TIMES.</head>
<p>BY <lb/> CHANDOS WREN HOSKYNS, ESQ.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Work now published is executed with great ability, and displays an intimate knowledge of the subject.&rdquo; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We feel assured there is not a landowner or practical farmer extant, who will not confess himself both pleased and edified after reading Mr. Hoskyns' very acceptable contribution to Agricultural literature.&rdquo; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in Foolscap 8vo, price 4s. 6d. cloth,</hi></opener><head>THE <lb/> POETICAL WORKS OF ALEXANDER POPE.</head>
<p>Revised and Arranged expressly for Young Persons and Schools.</p>
<p>BY <lb/> W C. MACREADY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This neat little volume has peculiar claims to public attention, and the Work of expurgation is very carefully done. Mr. Macready has left no blanks, considering them as so many temptations to pry into unclean places, and while providing the family library with a new and useful volume, he has at the same time produced a monument of his own taste and discernment.&rdquo; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>The Political Movements on the Continent, and their Bearing on <lb/> British Interests.</head>
<p>A SERIES OF ORIGINAL ESSAYS.</p>
<p>BY THOMAS C. BANFIELD, ESQ., <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Author of a Course of Lectures on the Organisation of Industry, delivered in the University of</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Cambridge, &ldquo;Industry of the Rhine,&rdquo; &amp;c.,</hi>
<lb/> IS NOW IN COURSE OF PUBLICATION <lb/> IN <lb/> THE WEEKLY NEWS <lb/> AND <lb/> FINANCIAL ECONOMIST, <lb/> A Journal aiming to elucidate the events of the time, by intellectual comment and illustration, <lb/> AND POSSESSING FACILITIES FOR OBTAINING <lb/> The earliest and most authentic information on all Foreign and Domestic, Political and Commercial <lb/> movements, and <lb/> DEVOTING SPECIAL ATTENTION TO THE AFFAIRS OF BRITISH INDIA.</p>
<p>Together with copious Notices of New Books, Works of Art, &amp;c., and a careful condensation of all the News.</p>
<p>Published every Saturday, price 6d. Order of any Newsman.</p>
<closer>OFFICE FOR ADVERTISEMENTS, <lb/> 17, UPPER WELLINGTON STREET, STRAND, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<head>SMITH, ELDER &amp; CO.'S <lb/> NEW PUBLICATIONS.</head>
<div3>
<head>NEW WORK BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;JANE EYRE.&rdquo;</head><p>In three volumes post 8vo.</p>
<p>SHIRLEY. A Tale. By CURRER BELL, Author of &ldquo;Jane Eyre.&rdquo; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Just ready.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>An Account of the Settlement of NEW PLYMOUTH, in NEW ZEALAND.</head>
<p>By CHARLES HURSTHOUSE, JUN. Post 8vo., with a Plan and Five Views. Price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The merit of this book consists in the full and impartial account it gives of the settlement, and the sound advice which accompanies it.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The field Mr. Hursthouse surveys is not a wide one, but his view of it is complete and exact.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Britannia.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>ERNESTO DI RIPALTA;</head><p>A TALE OF THE ITALIAN REVOLUTION. By the Author of &ldquo;Notes of a Two Years' Residence in Italy.&rdquo; In 3 Vols., post 8vo.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A true and philosophical view of politics in Italy. Presented in the form of a tale, which is well sustained and often powerful and interesting.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Spectator.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;An interesting narrative of the affairs of Italy during the past two years.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Britannia.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;An eloquent and interesting book.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>THE SEVEN LAMPS OF ARCHITECTURE.</head>
<p>By JOHN RUSKIN, Author of &ldquo;Modern Painters.&rdquo; 1 Vol. imp. 8vo., with Fourteen Etchings by <lb/> the Author. Price One Guinea, bound in embossed cloth, with top edge gilt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By the &lsquo;Seven Lamps of Architecture,&rsquo; we understand Mr. Ruskin to mean the seven fundamental and cardinal laws, the observance of and obedience to which are indispensable to the architect who would deserve the name. The politician, the moralist, the divine, will find in it ample store of instructive matter, as well as the artist.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A noble and splendid production. Faith, truthfulness, and thought, are stamped in every line of it.&rdquo;&mdash; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Atlas.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Truths are evoked which all have felt, but which few have had the power to analyse.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Daily News.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Ruskin's mind is of that vigorous and searching nature which can be satisfied with nothing less than the elucidation of pure principles in art. He observes and investigates for himself, and expresses himself in a strain of eloquence which rivets the mind by its fulness of meaning, and fascinates the fancy by its singular appropriateness of language and richness of imagery.&rdquo;&mdash; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Britannia.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;It cannot but tell powerfully in producing a more religious view of the uses of architecture, and a deeper insight into its artistic principles.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Guardian.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TOWN:</head><p>ITS MEMORABLE CHARACTERS AND EVENTS. (St. Paul's to St. James's.) By LEIGH HUNT. 2 Vols., post 8vo., with Forty-five Illustrations. Price 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We will allow no higher enjoyment for a rational Englishman than to stroll leisurely through this marvellous town arm-in-arm with Mr. Leigh Hunt. He gives us the outpourings of a mind enriched with the most agreeable knowledge. There is not a page of this book which does not glow with interest. It is a series of pictures from life, representing scenes in which every inhabitant of the metropolis has an interest far greater than he suspects.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>MODERN PAINTERS.</head>
<p>By a GRADUATE OF OXFORD. Volume the First. Fourth Edition, imp. 8vo. Price 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth. Volume the Second. Second Edition, imp. 8vo. Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A generous and impassioned review of the works of living painters. A hearty and earnest work, full of deep thought, and developing great and striking truths in art.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">British Quarterly Review.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A very extraordinary and delightful book, full of truth and goodness, of power and beauty.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">North British Review.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the most remarkable works on art which has appeared in our time.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Edinburgh Review.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>WORKS IN THE PRESS.</head>
<p>MR. LEIGH HUNT'S AUTOBIOGRAPHY.</p>
<p>REMINISCENCES AND TABLE TALK.</p>
<p>By LEIGH HUNT. In Two Vols. post 8vo, with Portrait.</p>
<p>WOMAN IN FRANCE <lb/> DURING THE EIGHTEENTH CENTURY. By JULIA KAVANAGH. 2 Vols., post 8vo, with Portraits of <lb/> remarkable French Women.</p>
<closer>SMITH, ELDER AND CO., 65, CORNHILL, LONDON; <lb/> OLIVER AND BOYD, EDINBURGH; J. McGLASHAN, DUBLIN.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p4" n="4"/>
<opener>Now Ready at all the Libraries, in Three Vols.</opener>
<head>MRS. TROLLOPE'S NEW NOVEL, <lb/> &ldquo;THE OLD WORLD AND THE NEW.&rdquo;</head><p>Also, Just Published, in Two Vols.</p>
<p>ERNEST VANE.</p>
<p>BY ALEXANDER BAILLIE COCHRANE, M.P.</p>
<closer>HENRY COLBURN, Publisher, 13, Great Marlborough Street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>SECOND EDITION, REVISED AND ENLARGED.<lb/>On the 8th of October will be Published, Second Edition, considerably Enlarged, with Portrait of the Author <lb/> Cloth, Gilt lettered. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>RUINS OF MANY LANDS.</head>
<p>BY ALEXANDER MICHELL.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;Babylon&mdash;Nineveh&mdash;Petra&mdash;Nubia&mdash;Egypt&mdash;Ruined Cities of America&mdash;Rock-Temples of India&mdash;Athens&mdash;Corinth&mdash;Sparta&mdash;Greek Isles&mdash;Troy&mdash;Rome&mdash;Pompeii&mdash;P&aelig;stum&mdash;Roman Amphitheatres&mdash;Roman Ruins in the South of France&mdash;Carthage&mdash;Ephesus&mdash;Tyre&mdash;Baalbec&mdash;Palmyra&mdash;Persepolis&mdash;Jerusalem, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the most interesting and exquisite volumes of modern days.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Era.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;It conveys in a delightful manner a rich store of information.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG, and Co., Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE EXHIBITION OF WORKS OF MANUFACTURE AND ART.</head>
<p>THE EXHIBITION OF MANUFACTURED ART, NOW OPEN IN <lb/> BIRMINGHAM, <lb/> Will be treated at considerable length in the OCTOBER Number of <lb/> THE ART-JOURNAL.</p>
<p>IT will be Illustrated by upwards of ONE HUNDRED AND FIFTY Engravings on Wood, comprising a large majority of the leading works contained in the Exposition&mdash;in silver, electro-silver, bronze, brass (cast and pressed), iron, porcelain, earthenware, and glass; of objects in papier-m&acirc;ch&eacute;; of japanned goods; carvings in wood; and the several productions of metal which constitute the main staple of British industry, and render Birmingham the great capital of British manufactures.</p>
<p>These will evidence an astonishing advance in Art within the last few years; and sufficiently prove the power of the English manufacturer to compete with the best fabricants of France.</p>
<p>The Exhibition at Birmingham cannot fail to have great influence on the future course of Manufactured Art in England&mdash;extending its repute and augmenting its mercantile value.</p>
<p>The Editor of the &ldquo;ART-JOURNAL&rdquo; has, therefore, considered it his duty to make arrangements for reporting this Exposition on a scale somewhat commensurate with the magnitude and liberality of the enterprise.</p>
<p>The October number of the &ldquo;ARY-JOURNAL&rdquo; will also contain three engravings on steel&mdash;&ldquo;Malvoli,&rdquo; engraved by Staines, from the painting by Maclise, R.A.; &ldquo;The Truant,&rdquo; engraved by Phillibrown, from the painting by Webster, R.A.&mdash;both in the &ldquo;VERNON GALLERY; and of &ldquo;Sabrina,&rdquo; engraved by Artlett from the statue, by Marshall, A.R.A.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;ART-JOURNAL&rdquo; of the past eight months contains, besides several hundred engravings on wood, no fewer than twenty-five engravings on steel; each of which may be regarded as a fine and beautiful specimen of Art: they consist chiefly of line engravings from the best pictures of the best British artists, contained in the VERNON GALLERY&mdash;the collection presented by the late Robert Vernon, Esq., to the British people.</p>
<p>To the amateur, the connoisseur, the artist, and the public generally, this work cannot fail to be an acquisition of considerable value; the purest and best Art is thus circulated at the smallest possible cost to the purchaser. &ldquo;Mr. VERNON'S magnificent gift is thus made doubly the property of the people. To the humblest classes throughout the whole kingdom, it becomes in some degree accessible, and a source of enjoyment and instruction.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The ART-JOURNAL may be ordered of any Bookseller in town or country.</p>
<closer>Publisher, GEORGE VIRTUE, 25, Paternoster Row.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<opener>Early in October will be Published,</opener><head>THE CAXTONS: <lb/> A FAMILY PICTURE.</head>
<p>BY THE AUTHOR of &ldquo;RIENZI,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>In Three Volumes, Post 8vo.</p>
<p>WILLIAM BLACKWOOD AND SONS, EDRNBURGH AND LONDON.</p>
<closer>Orders Received by all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Warren's Sketches of Character.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the CHARACTER of Individuals from their HANDWRITING.</p>
<p>Specimens of Writing, with the fee of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's sex to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>Frocks, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>USE KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Cos
<lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/>
 WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES.</p>
<p>Sold by every Draper, &amp;c, in the United Kingdom.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>EASIEST AND QUICKEST METHOD OF <lb/> ACQUIRING FRENCH.</head>
<p>MONS. LE PAGE'S FRENCH, EDUCATIONAL, and CONVERSATIONAL WORKS, designed to obviate the necessity of going to France to acquire the Parisian accent.</p>
<list>
<item>Le Page's French Master for Beginners. cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's L'Echo de Paris. Cloth, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's Gift of Conversation. Cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's French Grammar. Cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's Ready Guide to French Composition. Cloth, 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's French Prompter. Cloth, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></item>
<item>Le Page's Petit Musee de Literature Francaise. Cloth, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></item>
</list><p>MONS. LE PAGE'S method of teaching the French Language is in accordance with nature. A child acquires its native language intuitively, and is not at first perplexed with the niceties of Grammar; so in following the system of M. Le Page, it gradually <sic corr="becomes">beicomes</sic> acquainted with the usual mode of expression in ordinary conversation, and then, when the <hi rend="italics">idiom</hi> is virtually mastered, comes last of all the Grammar.</p>
<closer>LONDON: EFFINGHAM WILSON, Publisher, <lb/> 11, Royal Exchange.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>INDERWICK'S <lb/> NEW HYDRAULIC PIPE TUBE.</head>
<p>REGISTERED NOVEMBER 4th, 1848.</p>
<p>PRESENTING all the advantages of the Persian Hookah, within the space, and at the cost of an ordinary Pipe Tube. The principle is that of drawing the smoke up a cylindrical glass in the centre of the tube, from whence it passes down a second cylinder into the water, and then it ascends purified to the lips of the smoker.</p>
<p>To be had at L INDERWICK'S Wholesale Pipe and Snuff-Box Warehouse, No. 58, Princes-street, Leicester Square. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;FOR INDIGESTION, STOMACH AND LIVER COMPLAINTS, TAKE HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>Persons suffering from any derangement of the liver, stomach, or the organs of digestion, should have recourse to Holloway's Pills, as there is no other medicine that acts on these particular complaints with such certain success. Its peculiar properties strengthen the tone of the stomach, increase the appetite, and purify the liver. For bowel complaints it is admirable, as it removes every primary cause of them, thereby restoring the patient to the soundest health and strength. Nervous or sick headaches and lowness of spirits may be easily cured by taking a course of Holloway's Pills.&mdash;Sold by all druggists, and at Professor Holloway's establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p>and all other Medicines of a nauseous character, may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT ORGANIC CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHER, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom. Ask for the Patent Flexible Capsules.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well-known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>KEATING'S <lb/> COUGH LOZENGES.</head>
<p>HAVE immediate influence over the following cases:&mdash;Asthmatic and Consumptive Complaints, Coughs, Shortness of Breath, Hoarseness, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Prepared and sold in Boxes, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>., and Tins, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> each, by THOMAS KEATING, Chemist, &amp;c., No. 79, St. Paul's Church Yard, London. And Retail by all Chemists, &amp;c.</p>
<p>N.B. To prevent spurious imitations, please to observe that the words &ldquo;KEATING'S COUGH LOZENGES&rdquo; are engraven on the Government Stamp of each Box.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FORD'S <lb/> &lsquo;EUREKA&rsquo; <lb/> SHIRT</head><p>185 STRAND.</p>
<p>The attention of gentlemen is solicited to this truly unique article, being the only perfect fitting shirt made.</p>
<p>Six very superior Shirts for 30<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> also all the new patterns in Coloured Shirts, six for 27<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Detailed catalogues, with patterns and directions for self-measurement, sent post-free.</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Balance Ivory Table Knives, 10s. per Dozen.</head>
<p>DESSERT ditto, 9<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Carvers, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair. White Bone Table Knives, 6<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Dessert knives, 4<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> Carvers, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per pair. Superior Kitchen Table Knives and Forks, from 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per dozen. Table Knives with pure Nickel Silver&mdash;Tables, 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen; Dessert ditto, 18<hi rend="italics">s.:</hi> Carvers, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair, all marked Richard and John Slack, and warranted, <lb/> FENDERS AND FIRE IRONS, <lb/> The greatest variety in London, at Prices that defy competition.</p>
<p>Bronzed Scroll Fenders, with Steel Bar, from 10s.</p>
<p>SILVER SUPERSEDED BY RICHARD AND JOHN SLACK'S <lb/> CHEMICALLY PURIFIED NICKEL SILVER, <lb/> Acknowledged to be the purest metal in existence, made into every article for the table, as spoons, forks, candlesticks, cruet frames, tea-pots, &amp;c., at one-twelfth the price of silver. Send 10 postage stamps, and by return of post you will receive a sample spoon of their metal free; try it, and then send your orders. Their illustrated catalogue may be had gratis, and sent post free to any part.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell>
<cell> Strongest Fiddle. </cell>
<cell> Thread Pattern. </cell>
<cell> King's Pattern. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 19<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons and Forks, per dozen </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>RICHARD AND JOHN SLACK, <lb/> 336, Strand, opposite Somerset House.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Their Book, containing upwards of</hi> 200 <hi rend="italics">Engravings, may be had gratis, or sent to any part post free.</hi></p>
<closer>ESTABLISHED 1818.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head>
<p>THE economy both in the cost and wear of this Umbrella has been fully borne out by the experience of these last 18 months, and which can be testified by some thousands of purchasers to whom they have given universal satisfaction. They may be obtained of most Umbrella Dealers in the United Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Patentees, 140, Regent-street, <lb/> 94, Fleet-street, <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</p>
<p>Warehouse, 75, Cheapside.</p>
<p>CHEAP SILK UMBRELLAS, from 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p>
<p>N.B. Certain parties who are not licensed by the Patentees of the Alpaca Umbrella have been selling an inferior imitation of it. The public are therefore requested to observe that the Patentees' names are affixed inside each Umbrella.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS</head>
<p>The QUEEN, <lb/> H. R. H. Prince Albert, <lb/> Queen Adelaide, <lb/> King Louis Philippe, <lb/> and the <lb/> Duchess of Kent.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">DOUDNEYS.</hi></p>
<p>WATERPROOFERS TO <lb/> THE QUEEN.</p>
<p>GREAT COAT MAKERS TO <lb/> PRINCE ALBERT.</p>
<p>The efforts of the Doudneys to overcome old fashioned prejudices having resulted in their obtaining the continued patronage and unqualified approbation of the principal Sovereigns, Royalty and Nobility of Europe; they henceforth proudly point to this fact, and say, BEHOLD THE TRIUMPH OF CASH PAYMENTS OVER THE OLD CREDIT SYSTEM! And forget not, that,&mdash;To be Cheap things must be Good.</p>
<p>The Queens Victoria and Adelaide, and the Royal and Noble Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge Sutherland and Buceleuch, constantly wear Doudney's elegant Registered Cloak, in a variety of Waterproof materials for Winter Wraps and the Promenade.&mdash;&ldquo;Every Lady should see these graceful Garments.&rdquo; <hi rend="italics">(Vide Morning Post, Sep. 26th.)</hi> They surpass all others as School Cloaks for the Sons and Daughters.</p>
<p>For Gentlemen.&mdash;The Royal Registered Cloak, as made for H.R H. Prince Albert, the Nobility, the Army, and Navy, and all who study comfort, coupled with a truly Gentlemanly exterior. These cloaks are pronounced by those who understand the matter, &ldquo;The most sensible Garment ever introduced,&rdquo; at prices to suit all customers from the Superb down to the useful Guinea Cloak.</p>
<p>Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria, and the Ladies of the Court. A Superfine Cloth Habit for 4 Guineas.</p>
<p>The New Patent Belt for Riding or general exercise, the only really effectual protection against rupture, the support commencing at the <hi rend="italics">bottom edge</hi> of the belt, and producing an uniform upward pressure. They may be enlarged or tightened to the extent of six inches at pleasure, and never produce indigestion either in Ladies or Gentlemen. They are attached to Drawers with excellent effect. The most eminent of the Faculty are recommending these in preference to all others.</p>
<p>LIVERIES. Three Guineas the Plain Suit of Best Quality. <hi rend="italics">Ready Money does it!!!</hi> and a very extensive practice among families of first distinction insures satisfactory results.</p>
<p>Waterproof Irish Poplin.&mdash;The DOUDNEYS are the sole manufacturers of this beautiful article to HER MAJESTY AND THE PRINCE CONSORT. Gentlemen's Coats, Ladies' Cloaks, and lengths for Dresses can be obtained only at their Establishments,</p>
<closer>17, OLD BOND STREET, <lb/> Extending into BURLINGTON ARCADE, (No. 25,) and at <lb/> 49, LOMBARD STREET, Established 1784.</closer>
<trailer><hi rend="italics">Ladies and Gentlemen in the Country should send for a book of details.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">I return to the Doctor's after the party.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Somebody turns up.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="narrative">
<pb n="161" id="p161"/>


<head>[THE 
<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head>

<div2 type="chapter"><head>CHAPTER XVI. <lb/> I AM A NEW BOY IN MORE SENSES THAN ONE.</head>
<p>NEXT morning, after breakfast, I entered on school life again. I went, accompanied by Mr. Wickfield, to the scene of my future studies&mdash;a grave building in a court-yard, with a learned air about it that seemed very well suited to the stray rooks and jackdaws who came down from the Cathedral towers to walk with a clerkly bearing on the grass-plot&mdash;and was introduced to my new master, Doctor Strong.</p>
<p>Doctor Strong looked almost as rusty, to my thinking, as the tall iron rails and gates outside the house; and almost as stiff and heavy as the great stone urns that flanked them, and were set up, on the top of the red-brick wall, at regular distances all round the court, like sublimated skittles, for Time to play at. He was in his library (I mean Doctor Strong was), with his clothes not particularly well brushed, and his hair not particularly well combed; his knee-smalls unbraced; his long black gaiters unbuttoned; and his shoes yawning like two caverns on the hearth-rug. Turning upon me a lustreless eye, that reminded me of a long-forgotten blind old horse who once used to crop the grass, and tumble over the graves, in Blunderstone churchyard, he said he was glad to see me: and then he gave me his hand; which I didn't know what to do with, as it did nothing for itself.</p>
<p>But, sitting at work, not far off from Doctor Strong, was a very pretty young lady&mdash;whom he called Annie, and who was his daughter, I supposed&mdash;who got me out of my difficulty by kneeling down to put Doctor Strong's shoes on, and button his gaiters, which she did with great cheerfulness and quickness. When she had finished, and we were going out to the school-room, I was much surprised to hear Mr. Wickfield, in bidding her good morning, address her as &ldquo;Mrs. Strong;&rdquo; and I was wondering could she be Doctor Strong's son's wife, or could she be Mrs. Doctor Strong, when Doctor Strong himself unconsciously enlightened me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By the bye, Wickfield,&rdquo; he said, stopping in a passage with his hand on my shoulder; &ldquo;you have not found any suitable provision for my wife's cousin yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;No. Not yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I could wish it done as soon as it <hi rend="italics">can</hi> be done, Wickfield,&rdquo; said Doctor Strong, &ldquo;for Jack Maldon is needy, and idle; and of those two bad things, worse things sometimes come. What does Doctor Watts say,&rdquo; he added, looking at me, and moving his head to the time of his quotation, &ldquo; &lsquo;Satan finds some mischief still, for idle hands to do.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Egad, doctor,&rdquo; returned Mr. Wickfield, &ldquo;if Doctor Watts knew mankind, he might have written, with as much truth, &lsquo;Satan finds some mischief still, for busy hands to do.&rsquo; The busy people achieve their full share of mischief in the world, you may rely upon it. What have the people been about, who have been the busiest in getting money, and in getting power, this century or two? No mischief?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="162" id="p162"/>
<p>&ldquo;Jack Maldon will never be very busy in getting either, I expect,&rdquo; said Doctor Strong, rubbing his chin thoughtfully.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps not,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield; &ldquo;and you bring me back to the question, with an apology for digressing. No, I have not been able to dispose of Mr. Jack Maldon yet. I believe,&rdquo; he said this with some hesitation, &ldquo;I penetrate your motive, and it makes the thing more difficult.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My motive,&rdquo; returned Dr. Strong, &ldquo;is to make some suitable provision for a cousin, and an old playfellow, of Annie's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I know,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield; &ldquo;at home or abroad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye!&rdquo; replied the Doctor, apparently wondering why he emphasised those words so much. &ldquo;At home or abroad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your own expression, you know,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;Or abroad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Surely,&rdquo; the Doctor answered. &ldquo;Surely. One or other.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;One or other? Have you no choice?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; returned the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No?&rdquo; with astonishment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not the least.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No motive,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, &ldquo;for meaning abroad, and not at home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; returned the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am bound to believe you, and of course I do believe you,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;It might have simplified my office very much, if I had known it before. But I confess I entertained another impression.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Doctor Strong regarded him with a puzzled and doubting look, which almost immediately subsided into a smile that gave me great encouragement; for it was full of amiability and sweetness, and there was a simplicity in it, and indeed in his whole manner, when the studious, pondering frost upon it was got through, very attractive and hopeful to a young scholar like me. Repeating &ldquo;no,&rdquo; and &ldquo;not the least,&rdquo; and other short assurances to the same purport, Doctor Strong jogged on before us, at a queer, uneven pace; and we followed: Mr. Wickfield looking grave, I observed, and shaking his head to himself, without knowing that I saw him.</p>
<p>The school-room was a pretty large hall, on the quietest side of the house, confronted by the stately stare of some half-dozen of the great urns, and commanding a peep of an old secluded garden belonging to the Doctor, where the peaches were ripening on the sunny south wall. There were two great aloes, in tubs, on the turf outside the windows; the broad hard leaves of which plant (looking as if they were made of painted tin) have ever since, by association, been symbolical to me of silence and retirement. About five-and-twenty boys were studiously engaged at their books when we went in, but they rose to give the Doctor good morning, and remained standing when they saw Mr. Wickfield and me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A new boy, young gentlemen,&rdquo; said the Doctor; &ldquo;Trotwood Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One Adams, who was the head-boy, then stepped out of his place and welcomed me. He looked like a young clergyman, in his white cravat, but he was very affable and good-humored; and he showed me my place, and presented me to the masters, in a gentlemanly way that would have put me at my ease, if anything could.</p>
<p>It seemed to me so long, however, since I had been among such boys, or among any companions of my own age, except Mick Walker and Mealey
<pb n="163" id="p163"/>
Potatoes, that I felt as strange as ever I have done in all my life. I was so conscious of having passed through scenes of which they could have no knowledge, and of having acquired experiences foreign to my age, appearance, and condition, as one of them, that I half believed it was an imposture to come there as an ordinary little schoolboy. I had become, in the Murdstone and Grinby time, however short or long it may have been, so unused to the sports and games of boys, that I knew I was awkward and inexperienced in the commonest things belonging to them. Whatever I had learnt, had so slipped away from me in the sordid cares of my life from day to night, that now, when I was examined about what I knew, I knew nothing, and was put into the lowest form of the school. But, troubled as I was, by my want of boyish skill, and of book-learning too, I was made infinitely more uncomfortable by the consideration, that, in what I did know, I was much farther removed from my companions than in what I did not. My mind ran upon what they would think, if they knew of my familiar acquaintance with the King's Bench Prison? Was there anything about me which would reveal my proceedings in connexion with the Micawber family&mdash;all those pawnings, and sellings, and suppers&mdash;in spite of myself? Suppose some of the boys had seen me coming through Canterbury, wayworn and ragged, and should find me out? What would they say, who made so light of money, if they could know how I had scraped my halfpence together, for the purchase of my daily saveloy and beer, or my slices of pudding? How would it affect them, who were so innocent of London life, and London streets, to discover how knowing I was (and was ashamed to be) in some of the meanest phases of both? All this ran in my head so much, on that first day at Doctor Strong's, that I felt distrustful of my slightest look and gesture; shrunk within myself whensoever I was approached by one of my new schoolfellows; and hurried off the minute school was over, afraid of committing myself in my response to any friendly notice or advance.</p>
<p>But there was such an influence in Mr. Wickfield's old house, that when I knocked at it, with my new school-books under my arm, I began to feel my uneasiness softening away. As I went up to my airy old room, the grave shadow of the staircase seemed to fall upon my doubts and fears, and to make the past more indistinct. I sat there, sturdily conning my books, until dinner time (we were out of school for good at three); and went down, hopeful of becoming a passable sort of boy yet.</p>
<p>Agnes was in the drawing-room, waiting for her father, who was detained by some one in his office. She met me with her pleasant smile, and asked me how I liked the school. I told her I should like it very much, I hoped; but I was a little strange to it at first.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">You</hi> have never been to school,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;have you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, yes! Every day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, but you mean here, at your own home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Papa couldn't spare me to go anywhere else,&rdquo; she answered, smiling and shaking her head. &ldquo;His housekeeper must be in his house, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is very fond of you, I am sure,&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>She nodded &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; and went to the door to listen for his coming up, that she might meet him on the stairs. But, as he was not there, she came back again.</p>
<pb n="164" id="p164"/>
<p>&ldquo;Mama has been dead ever since I was born,&rdquo; she said, in her quiet way. &ldquo;I only know her picture, down stairs. I saw you looking at it yesterday. Did you think whose it was?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I told her yes, because it was so like herself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Papa says so, too,&rdquo; said Agnes, pleased. &ldquo;Hark! That's papa now!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Her bright calm face lighted up with pleasure as she went to meet him, and as they came in, hand in hand. He greeted me cordially; and told me I should certainly be happy under Doctor Strong, who was one of the gentlest of men.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There may be some, perhaps&mdash;I don't know that there are&mdash;who abuse his kindness,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;Never be one of those, Trotwood, in anything. He is the least suspicious of mankind; and whether that's a merit, or whether it's a blemish, it deserves consideration in all dealings with the Doctor, great or small.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He spoke, I thought, as if he were weary, or dissatisfied with something; but I did not pursue the question in my mind, for dinner was just then announced, and we went down and took the same seats as before.</p>
<p>We had scarcely done so, when Uriah Heep put in his red head and his lank hand at the door, and said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here's Mr. Maldon begs the favor of a word, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am but this moment quit of Mr. Maldon,&rdquo; said his master.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir,&rdquo; returned Uriah; &ldquo;but Mr. Maldon has come back, and he begs the favor of a word.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As he held the door open with his hand, Uriah looked at me, and looked at Agnes, and looked at the dishes, and looked at the plates, and looked at every object in the room, I thought,&mdash;yet seemed to look at nothing; he made such an appearance all the while of keeping his red eyes dutifully on his master.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon. It's only to say, on reflection,&rdquo; observed a voice behind Uriah, as Uriah's head was pushed away, and the speaker's substituted&mdash;&ldquo;pray excuse me for this intrusion&mdash;that as it seems I have no choice in the matter, the sooner I go abroad, the better. My cousin Annie did say, when we talked of it, that she liked to have her friends within reach rather than to have them banished, and the old Doctor&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Strong, was that?&rdquo; Mr. Wickfield interposed, gravely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Strong of course,&rdquo; returned the other; &ldquo;I call him the old Doctor&mdash;it's all the same, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I <hi rend="italics">don't</hi> know,&rdquo; returned Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Doctor Strong,&rdquo; said the other&mdash;&ldquo;Doctor Strong was of the same mind, I believed. But as it appears from the course you take with me that he has changed his mind, why there's no more to be said, except that the sooner I am off, the better. Therefore, I thought I'd come back and say, that the sooner I am off, the better. When a plunge is to be made into the water, it's of no use lingering on the bank.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There shall be as little lingering as possible, in your case, Mr. Maldon, you may depend upon it,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank'ee,&rdquo; said the other. &ldquo;Much obliged. I don't want to look a gift-horse in the mouth, which is not a gracious thing to do; otherwise, I dare say, my cousin Annie could easily arrange it in her own way. I suppose Annie would only have to say to the old Doctor&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Meaning that Mrs. Strong would only have to say to her husband&mdash;do I follow you?&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield.</p>
<pb n="165" id="p165"/>
<p>&ldquo;Quite so,&rdquo; returned the other, &ldquo;&mdash;would only have to say, that she wanted such and such a thing to be so and so; and it would be so and so, as a matter of course.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And why as a matter of course, Mr. Maldon?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield, sedately eating his dinner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, because Annie's a charming young girl, and the old Doctor&mdash;Doctor Strong, I mean&mdash;is not quite a charming young boy,&rdquo; said Mr. Jack Maldon, laughing. &ldquo;No offence to anybody, Mr. Wickfield. I only mean that I suppose some compensation is fair and reasonable, in that sort of marriage.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Compensation to the lady, sir?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield gravely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To the lady, sir,&rdquo; Mr. Jack Maldon answered, laughing. But appearing to remark that Mr. Wickfield went on with his dinner in the same sedate, immoveable manner, and that there was no hope of making him relax a muscle of his face, he added:</p>
<p>&ldquo;However, I have said what I came back to say, and, with another apology for this intrusion, I may take myself off. Of course I shall observe your directions, in considering the matter as one to be arranged between you and me solely, and not to be referred to, up at the Doctor's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you dined?&rdquo; asked Mr. Wickfield, with a motion of his hand towards the table.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank'ee. I am going to dine,&rdquo; said Mr. Maldon, &ldquo;with my cousin Annie. Good bye!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Wickfield, without rising, looked after him thoughtfully as he went out. He was rather a shallow sort of young gentleman, I thought, with a handsome face, a rapid utterance, and a confident, bold air. And this was the first I ever saw of Mr. Jack Maldon; whom I had not expected to see so soon, when I heard the Doctor speak of him that morning.</p>
<p>When we had dined, we went up-stairs again, where everything went on exactly as on the previous day. Agnes set the glasses and decanters in the same corner, and Mr. Wickfield sat down to drink, and drank a good deal. Agnes played the piano to him, sat by him, and worked and talked, and played some games at dominoes with me. In good time she made tea; and afterwards, when I brought down my books, looked into them, and showed me what she knew of them (which was no slight matter, though she said it was), and what was the best way to learn and understand them. I see her, with her modest, orderly, placid manner, and I hear her beautiful calm voice, as I write these words. The influence for all good, which she came to exercise over me at a later time, begins already to descend upon my breast. I love little Em'ly, and I don't love Agnes&mdash;no, not at all in that way&mdash;but I feel that there are goodness, peace, and truth, wherever Agnes is; and that the soft light of the colored window in the church, seen long ago, falls on her always, and on me when I am near her, and on every thing around.</p>
<p>The time having come for her withdrawal for the night, and she having left us, I gave Mr. Wickfield my hand, preparatory to going away myself. But he checked me and said: &ldquo;Should you like to stay with us, Trotwood, or to go elsewhere?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To stay&rdquo; I answered, quickly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are sure?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you please. If I may!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="166" id="p166"/>
<p>&ldquo;Why, it's but a dull life that we lead here, boy, I am afraid,&rdquo; he said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not more dull for me than Agnes, sir. Not dull at all!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Than Agnes,&rdquo; he repeated, walking slowly to the great chimney-piece, and leaning against it. &ldquo;Than Agnes!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had drank wine that evening (or I fancied it), until his eyes were bloodshot. Not that I could see them now, for they were cast down, and shaded by his hand; but I had noticed them a little while before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now I wonder,&rdquo; he muttered, &ldquo;whether my Agnes tires of me. When should I ever tire of her! But that's different&mdash;that's quite different.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was musing&mdash;not speaking to me; so I remained quiet,</p>
<p>&ldquo;A dull old house,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;and a monotonous life; but I must have her near me. I must keep her near me. If the thought that I may die and leave my darling, or that my darling may die and leave me, comes, like a spectre, to distress my happiest hours, and is only to be drowned in&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>He did not supply the word; but pacing slowly to the place where he had sat, and mechanically going through the action of pouring wine from the empty decanter, set it down and paced back again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If it is miserable to bear, when she is here,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;what would it be, and she away? No, no, no. I can not try that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He leaned against the chimney-piece, brooding so long that I could not decide whether to run the risk of disturbing him by going, or to remain quietly where I was, until he should come out of his reverie. At length he aroused himself, and looked about the room until his eyes encountered mine.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stay with us, Trotwood, eh?&rdquo; he said, in his usual manner, and as if he were answering something I had just said. &ldquo;I am glad of it. You are company to us both. It is wholesome to have you here. Wholesome for me, wholesome for Agnes, wholesome perhaps for all of us.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure it is for me, sir,&rdquo; I said. &ldquo;I am so glad to be here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a fine fellow!&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;As long as you are glad to be here, you shall stay here.&rdquo; He shook hands with me upon it, and clapped me on the back; and told me that when I had anything to do at night after Agnes had left us, or when I wished to read for my own pleasure, I was free to come down to his room, if he were there and if I desired it for company's sake, and to sit with him. I thanked him for his consideration; and, as he went down soon afterwards, and I was not tired, went down too, with a book in my hand, to avail myself, for half-an-hour, of his permission.</p>
<p>But, seeing a light in the little round office, and immediately feeling myself attracted towards Uriah Heep, who had a sort of fascination for me, I went in there instead. I found Uriah reading a great fat book, with such demonstrative attention, that his lank fore-finger followed up every line as he read, and made clammy tracks along the page (or so I fully believed) like a snail.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are working late to-night, Uriah,&rdquo; says I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; says Uriah.</p>
<p>As I was getting on the stool opposite, to talk to him more conveniently, I observed that he had not such a thing as a smile about him, and that he could only widen his mouth and make two hard creases down his cheeks, one on each side, to stand for one.</p>
<pb n="167" id="p167"/>
<p>&ldquo;I am not doing office-work, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What work, then?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am improving my legal knowledge, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;I am going through Tidd's Practice. Oh, what a writer Mr. Tidd is, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>My stool was such a tower of observation, that as I watched him reading on again, after this rapturous exclamation, and following up the lines with his fore-finger, I observed that his nostrils, which were thin and pointed, with sharp dints in them, had a singular and most uncomfortable way of expanding and contracting themselves&mdash;that they seemed to twinkle, instead of his eyes, which hardly ever twinkled at all.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose you are quite a great lawyer?&rdquo; I said, after looking at him for some time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Me, Master Copperfield?&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;Oh, no! I'm a very umble person.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was no fancy of mine about his hands, I observed; for he frequently ground the palms against each other as if to squeeze them dry and warm, besides often wiping them, in a stealthy way, on his pocket-handkerchief.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am well aware that I am the umblest person going,&rdquo; said Uriah Heep, modestly; &ldquo;let the other be where he may. My mother is likewise a very umble person. We live in a numble abode, Master Copperfield, but have much to be thankful for. My father's former calling was umble. He was a sexton.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is he now?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is a partaker of glory at present, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah Heep. &ldquo;But we have much to be thankful for. How much have I to be thankful for, in living with Mr. Wickfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I asked Uriah if he had been with Mr. Wickfield long?</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been with him, going on four year, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah; shutting up his book, after carefully marking the place where he had left off. &ldquo;Since a year after my father's death. How much have I to be thankful for, in that! How much have I to be thankful for, in Mr. Wickfield's kind intention to give me my articles, which would otherwise not lay within the umble means of mother and self!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, when your articled time is over, you'll be a regular lawyer, I suppose?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With the blessing of Providence, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps you'll be a partner in Mr. Wickfield's business, one of these days,&rdquo; I said, to make myself agreeable; &ldquo;and it will be Wickfield and Heep, or Heep late Wickfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, no, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Uriah, shaking his head, &ldquo;I am much too umble for that!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He certainly did look uncommonly like the carved face on the beam outside my window, as he sat, in his humility, eyeing me sideways, with his mouth widened, and the creases in his cheeks.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Wickfield is a most excellent man, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;If you have known him long, you know it, I am sure, much better than I can inform you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I replied that I was certain he was; but that I had not known him long myself, though he was a friend of my aunt's.</p>
<pb n="168" id="p168"/>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, indeed, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;Your aunt is a sweet lady, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had a way of writhing when he wanted to express enthusiasm, which was very ugly; and which diverted my attention from the compliment he had paid my relation, to the snaky twistings of his throat and body.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A sweet lady, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; said Uriah Heep. &ldquo;She has a great admiration for Miss Agnes, Master Copperfield, I believe?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; boldly; not that I knew anything about it, Heaven forgive me!</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope you have, too, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;But I am sure you must have.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Everybody must have,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, thank you, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah Heep, &ldquo;for that remark! It is so true! Umble as I am, I know it is <hi rend="italics">so</hi> true! Oh, thank you, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He writhed himself quite off his stool in the excitement of his feelings, and, being off, began to make arrangements for going home.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mother will be expecting me,&rdquo; he said, referring to a pale, inexpressive-faced watch in his pocket, &ldquo;and getting uneasy; for though we are very umble, Master Copperfield, we are much attached to one another. If you would come and see us, any afternoon, and take a cup of tea at our lowly dwelling, mother would be as proud of your company as I should be.</p>
<p>I said I should be glad to come.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Uriah, putting his book away upon a shelf.&mdash;&ldquo;I suppose you stop here, some time, Master Copperfield?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said I was going to be brought up there, I believed, as long as I remained at school.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, indeed!&rdquo; exclaimed Uriah. &ldquo;I should think <hi rend="italics">you</hi> would come into the business at last, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I protested that I had no views of that sort, and that no such scheme was entertained in my behalf by anybody; but Uriah insisted on blandly replying to all my assurances, &ldquo;Oh, yes, Master Copperfield, I should think you would, indeed!&rdquo; and, &ldquo;Oh, indeed, Master Copperfield, I should think you would, certainly!&rdquo; over and over again. Being, at last, ready to leave the office for the night, he asked me if it would suit my convenience to have the light put out; and on my answering &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; instantly extinguished it. After shaking hands with me&mdash;his hand felt like a fish, in the dark&mdash;he opened the door into the street a very little, and crept out, and shut it, leaving me to grope my way back into the house: which cost me some trouble and a fall over his stool. This was the proximate cause, I suppose, of my dreaming about him, for what appeared to me to be half the night; and dreaming, among other things, that he had launched Mr. Peggotty's house on a piratical expedition, with a black flag at the mast-head, bearing the inscription &ldquo;Tidd's Practice,&rdquo; under which diabolical ensign he was carrying me and little Em'ly to the Spanish Main, to be drowned.</p>
<p>I got a little the better of my uneasiness when I went to school next day, and a good deal the better next day, and so shook it off by degrees that in less than a fortnight I was quite at home, and happy, among my new companions. I was awkward enough in their games, and backward enough in their studies; but custom would improve me in the first respect, I hoped,
<pb n="169" id="p169"/>
and hard work in the second. Accordingly, I went to work very hard, both in play and in earnest, and gained great commendation. And, in a very little while, the Murdstone and Grinby life became so strange to me that I hardly believed in it, while my present life grew so familiar, that I seemed to have been leading it a long time.</p>
<p>Doctor Strong's was an excellent school; as different from Mr. Creakle's as good is from evil. It was very gravely and decorously ordered, and on a sound system; with an appeal, in everything, to the honour and good faith of the boys, and an avowed intention to rely on their possession of those qualities unless they proved themselves unworthy of it, which worked wonders. We all felt that we had a part in the management of the place, and in sustaining its character and dignity. Hence, we soon became warmly attached to it&mdash;I am sure I did for one, and I never knew, in all my time, of any other boy being otherwise&mdash;and learnt with a good will, desiring to do it credit. We had noble games out of hours, and plenty of liberty; but even then, as I remember, we were well spoken of in the town, and rarely did any disgrace, by our appearance or manner, to the reputation of Doctor Strong and Doctor Strong's boys.</p>
<p>Some of the higher scholars boarded in the Doctor's house, and through them I learnt, at second hand, some particulars of the Doctor's history&mdash;as how he had not yet been married twelve months to the beautiful young lady I had seen in the study, whom he had married for love; as she had not a six-pence, and had a world of poor relations (so our fellows said) ready to swarm the Doctor out of house and home. Also, how the Doctor's cogitating manner was attributable to his being always engaged in looking out for Greek roots; which, in my innocence and ignorance, I supposed to be a botanical furor on the Doctor's part, especially as he always looked at the ground when he walked about&mdash;until I understood that they were roots of words, with a view to a new Dictionary, which he had in contemplation. Adams, our head-boy, who had a turn for mathematics, had made a calculation, I was informed, of the time this Dictionary would take in completing, on the Doctor's plan, and at the Doctor's rate of going. He considered that it might be done in one thousand six hundred and forty-nine years, counting from the Doctor's last, or sixty-second, birthday.</p>
<p>But the Doctor himself was the idol of the whole school: and it must have been a badly composed school if he had been anything else, for he was the kindest of men; with a simple faith in him that might have touched the stone hearts of the very urns upon the wall. As he walked up and down that part of the court-yard which was at the side of the house, with the stray rooks and jackdaws looking after him with their heads cocked slyly, as if they knew how much more knowing they were in worldly affairs than he, if any sort of vagabond could only get near enough to his creaking shoes to attract his attention to one sentence of a tale of distress, that vagabond was made for the next two days. It was so notorious in the house, that the masters and head-boys took pains to cut these marauders off at angles, and to get out of windows, and turn them out of the court-yard, before they could make the Doctor aware of their presence; which was sometimes happily effected within a few yards of him, without his knowing anything of the matter, as he jogged to and fro. Outside his own domain, and unprotected, he was a very sheep for the shearers. He would have taken his gaiters off his legs, to give away. In
<pb n="170" id="p170"/>
fact, there was a story current among us (I have no idea, and never had, on what authority, but I have believed it for so many years that I feel quite certain it is true), that on a frosty day, one winter time, he actually did bestow his gaiters on a beggar-woman, who occasioned some scandal in the neighbourhood by exhibiting a fine infant from door to door, wrapped in those garments, which were universally recognised, being as well known in the vicinity as the Cathedral. The legend added that the only person who did not identify them was the Doctor himself, who, when they were shortly afterwards displayed at the door of a little second-hand shop of no very good repute, where such things were taken in exchange for gin, was more than once observed to handle them approvingly, as if admiring some curious novelty in the pattern, and considering them an improvement on his own.</p>
<p>It was very pleasant to see the Doctor with his pretty young wife. He had a fatherly, benignant way of showing his fondness for her, which seemed in itself to express a good man. I often saw them walking in the garden where the peaches were, and I sometimes had a nearer observation of them in the study or the parlor. She appeared to me to take great care of the Doctor, and to like him very much, though I never thought her vitally interested in the Dictionary: some cumbrous fragments of which work the Doctor always carried in his pockets, and in the lining of his hat, and generally seemed to be expounding to her as they walked about.</p>
<p>I saw a good deal of Mrs. Strong, both because she had taken a liking for me on the morning of my introduction to the Doctor, and was always afterwards kind to me, and interested in me; and because she was very fond of Agnes, and was often backwards and forwards at our house. There was a curious constraint between her and Mr. Wickfield, I thought (of whom she seemed to be afraid), that never wore off. When she came there of an evening, she always shrunk from accepting his escort home, and ran away with me instead. And sometimes, as we were running gaily across the Cathedral yard together, expecting to meet nobody, we would meet Mr. Jack Maldon, who was always surprised to see us.</p>
<p>Mrs. Strong's mama was a lady I took great delight in. Her name was Mrs. Markleham; but our boys used to call her the Old Soldier, on account of her generalship, and the skill with which she marshalled great forces of relations against the Doctor. She was a little, sharp-eyed woman, who used to wear, when she was dressed, one unchangeable cap, ornamented with some artificial flowers, and two artificial butterflies supposed to be hovering above the flowers. There was a superstition among us that this cap had come from France, and could only originate in the workmanship of that ingenious nation: but all I certainly know about it, is, that it always made its appearance of an evening, wheresoever Mrs. Markleham made <hi rend="italics">her</hi> appearance; that it was carried about to friendly meetings in a Hindoo basket; that the butterflies had the gift of trembling constantly; and that they improved the shining hours at Doctor Strong's expense, like busy bees.</p>
<p>I observed the Old Soldier&mdash;not to adopt the name disrespectfully&mdash;to pretty good advantage, on a night which is made memorable to me by something else I shall relate. It was the night of a little party at the Doctor's, which was given on the occasion of Mr. Jack Maldon's departure for India, whither he was going as a cadet, or something of that kind: Mr. Wickfield
<pb n="171" id="p171"/>
having at length arranged the business. It happened to be the Doctor's birthday, too. We had had a holiday, had made presents to him in the morning, had made a speech to him through the head-boy, and had cheered him until we were hoarse, and until he had shed tears. And now, in the evening, Mr. Wickfield, Agnes, and I, went to have tea with him in his private capacity.</p>
<p>Mr. Jack Maldon was there, before us. Mrs. Strong, dressed in white, with cherry-colored ribbons, was playing the piano, when we went in; and he was leaning over her to turn the leaves. The clear red and white of her complexion was not so blooming and flower-like as usual, I thought, when she turned round; but she looked very pretty, wonderfully pretty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have forgotten, Doctor,&rdquo; said Mrs. Strong's mama, when we were seated, &ldquo;to pay you the compliments of the day&mdash;though they are, as you may suppose, very far from being mere compliments in my case. Allow me to wish you many happy returns.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thank you, ma'am,&rdquo; replied the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Many, many, many, happy returns,&rdquo; said the Old Soldier. &ldquo;Not only for your own sake, but for Annie's, and John Maldon's, and many other peoples'. It seems but yesterday to me, John, when you were a little creature, a head shorter than Master Copperfield, making baby love to Annie behind the gooseberry bushes in the back-garden.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear mama,&rdquo; said Mrs. Strong, &ldquo;never mind that now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Annie, don't be absurd,&rdquo; returned her mother. &ldquo;If you are to blush to hear of such things, now you are an old married woman, when are you not to blush to hear of them?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Old?&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Jack Maldon. &ldquo;Annie? Come!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, John,&rdquo; returned the Soldier. &ldquo;Virtually, an old married woman. Although not old by years&mdash;for when did you ever hear me say, or who has ever heard me say, that a girl of twenty was old by years!&mdash;your cousin is the wife of the Doctor, and, as such, what I have described her. It is well for you, John, that your cousin <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the wife of the Doctor. You have found in him an influential and kind friend, who will be kinder yet, I venture to predict, if you deserve it. I have no false pride. I never hesitate to admit, frankly, that there are some members of our family who want a friend. You were one yourself, before your cousin's influence raised up one for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Doctor, in the goodness of his heart, waved his hand as if to make light of it, and save Mr. Jack Maldon from any further reminder. But Mrs. Markleham changed her chair for one next the Doctor's, and putting her fan on his coat-sleeve, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, really, my dear Doctor, you must excuse me if I appear to dwell on this rather, because I feel so very strongly. I call it quite my monomania, it is such a subject of mine. You are a blessing to us. You really are a Boon, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nonsense, nonsense,&rdquo; said the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, I beg your pardon,&rdquo; retorted the Old Soldier. &ldquo;With nobody present, but our dear and confidential friend Mr. Wickfield, I cannot consent to be put down. I shall begin to assert the privileges of a mother-in-law, if you go on like that, and scold you. I am perfectly honest and outspoken. What I am saying, is what I said when you first overpowered me with surprise&mdash;you remember how surprised I was?&mdash;by proposing for Annie. Not that there was anything so very much out of the way, in the mere
<pb n="172" id="p172"/>
act of the proposal&mdash;it would be ridiculous to say that!&mdash;but because, you having known her poor father, and having known her from a baby six months old, I hadn't thought of you in such a light at all, or indeed as a marrying man in any way,&mdash;simply that, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye, aye,&rdquo; returned the Doctor, good-humoredly. &ldquo;Never mind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But I <hi rend="italics">do</hi> mind,&rdquo; said the Old Soldier, laying her fan upon his lips. &ldquo;I mind very much. I recal these things that I may be contradicted if I am wrong. Well! Then I spoke to Annie, and I told her what had happened. I said, &lsquo;My dear, here's Doctor Strong has positively been and made you the subject of a handsome declaration and an offer.&rsquo; Did I press it in the least? No. I said, &lsquo;Now, Annie, tell me the truth this moment; is your heart free?&rsquo; &lsquo;Mama,&rsquo; she said, crying, &lsquo;I am extremely young&rsquo;&mdash;which was perfectly true&mdash;&lsquo;and I hardly know if I have a heart at all.&rsquo; &lsquo;Then, my dear,&rsquo; I said, &lsquo;you may rely upon it, it's free. At all events, my love,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;Doctor Strong is in an agitated state of mind, and must be answered. He cannot be kept in his present state of suspense.&rsquo; &lsquo;Mama,&rsquo; said Annie, still crying, &lsquo;would he be unhappy without me? If he would, I honor and respect him so much, that I think I will have him.&rsquo; So it was settled. And then, and not till then, I said to Annie, &lsquo;Annie, Doctor Strong will not only be your husband, but he will represent your late father: he will represent the head of our family, he will represent the wisdom and station, and I may say the means, of our family; and will be, in short, a Boon to it.&rsquo; I used the word at the time, and I have used it again, to-day. If I have any merit, it is consistency.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The daughter had sat quite silent and still during this speech, with her eyes fixed on the ground; her cousin standing near her, and looking on the ground too. She now said very softly, in a trembling voice:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mama, I hope you have finished?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my dear Annie,&rdquo; returned the Soldier, &ldquo;I have not quite finished. Since you ask me, my love, I reply that I have <hi rend="italics">not.</hi> I complain that you really are a little unnatural towards your own family; and, as it is of no use complaining to you, I mean to complain to your husband. Now, my dear Doctor, do look at that silly wife of yours.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the Doctor turned his kind face, with its smile of simplicity and gentleness, towards her, she drooped her head more. I noticed that Mr. Wickfield looked at her steadily.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I happened to say to that naughty thing, the other day,&rdquo; pursued her mother, shaking her head and her fan at her, playfully, &ldquo;that there was a family circumstance she might mention to you&mdash;indeed, I think, was bound to mention&mdash;she said, that to mention it was to ask a favor; and that, as you were too generous, and as for her to ask was always to have, she wouldn't.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Annie, my dear,&rdquo; said the Doctor. &ldquo;That was wrong. It robbed me of a pleasure.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Almost the very words I said to her!&rdquo; exclaimed her mother. &ldquo;Now really, another time, when I know what she would tell you but for this reason, and won't, I have a great mind, my dear Doctor, to tell you myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall be glad if you will,&rdquo; returned the Doctor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Shall I?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="173" id="p173"/>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, then, I will!&rdquo; said the Old Soldier. &ldquo;That's a bargain.&rdquo; And having, I suppose, carried her point, she tapped the Doctor's hand several times with her fan (which she kissed first), and returned triumphantly to her former station.</p>
<p>Some more company coming in, among whom were the two masters and Adams, the talk became general; and it naturally turned on Mr. Jack Maldon, and his voyage, and the country he was going to, and his various plans and prospects. He was to leave that night, after supper, in a postchaise, for Gravesend; where the ship, in which he was to make the voyage, lay; and was to be gone&mdash;unless he came home on leave, or for his health&mdash;I don't know how many years. I recollect it was settled by general consent that India was quite a misrepresented country, and had nothing objectionable in it, but a tiger or two, and a little heat in the warm part of the day. For my own part, I looked on Mr. Jack Maldon as a modern Sinbad, and pictured him the bosom friend of all the Rajahs in the east, sitting under canopies, smoking curly golden pipes&mdash;a mile long, if they could be straightened out.</p>
<p>Mrs. Strong was a very pretty singer: as I knew, who often heard her singing by herself. But, whether she was afraid of singing before people, or was out of voice that evening, it was certain that she couldn't sing at all. She tried a duet, once, with her cousin Maldon, but could not so much as begin; and afterwards, when she tried to sing by herself, although she began sweetly, her voice died away on a sudden, and left her quite distressed, with her head hanging down over the keys. The good Doctor said she was nervous, and, to relieve her, proposed a round game at cards; of which he knew as much as of the art of playing the trombone. But I remarked that the Old Soldier took him into custody directly, for her partner; and instructed him, as the first preliminary of initiation, to give her all the silver he had in his pocket.</p>
<p>We had a merry game, not made the less merry by the Doctor's mistakes, of which he committed an innumerable quantity, in spite of the watchfulness of the butterflies, and to their great aggravation. Mrs. Strong had declined to play, on the ground of not feeling very well; and her cousin Maldon had excused himself because he had some packing to do. When he had done it, however, he returned, and they sat together, talking, on the sofa. From time to time she came and looked over the Doctor's hand, and told him what to play. She was very pale, as she bent over him, and I thought her finger trembled as she pointed out the cards; but the Doctor was quite happy in her attention, and took no notice of this, if it were so.</p>
<p>At supper, we were hardly so gay. Every one appeared to feel that a parting of that sort was an awkward thing, and that the nearer it approached, the more awkward it was. Mr. Jack Maldon tried to be very talkative, but was not at his ease, and made matters worse. And they were not improved, as it appeared to me, by the Old Soldier: who continually recalled passages of Mr. Jack Maldon's youth.</p>
<p>The Doctor, however, who felt, I am sure, that he was making everybody happy, was well pleased, and had no suspicion, but that we were all at the utmost height of enjoyment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Annie, my dear,&rdquo; said he, looking at his watch, and filling his
<pb n="174" id="p174"/>
glass, &ldquo;it is past your cousin Jack's time, and we must not detain him, since time and tide&mdash;both concerned in this case&mdash;wait for no man. Mr. Jack Maldon, you have a long voyage, and a strange country, before you; but many men have had both, and many men will have both, to the end of time. The winds you are going to tempt, have wafted thousands upon thousands to fortune, and brought thousands upon thousands happily back.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's an affecting thing,&rdquo; said Mrs. Markleham&mdash;&ldquo;however it's viewed, it's affecting&mdash;to see a fine young man one has known from an infant, going away to the other end of the world, leaving all he knows behind, and not knowing what's before him. A young man really well deserves constant support and patronage,&rdquo; looking at the Doctor, &ldquo;who makes such sacrifices.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Time will go fast with you, Mr. Jack Maldon,&rdquo; pursued the Doctor, &ldquo;and fast with all of us. Some of us can hardly expect, perhaps, in the natural course of things, to greet you on your return. The next best thing is to hope to do it, and that's my case. I shall not weary you with good advice. You have long had a good model before you, in your cousin Annie. Imitate her virtues as nearly as you can.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Markleham fanned herself, and shook her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Farewell, Mr. Jack,&rdquo; said the Doctor, standing up; on which we all stood up. &ldquo;A prosperous voyage out, a thriving career abroad, and a happy return home!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We all drank the toast, and all shook hands with Mr. Jack Maldon; after which he hastily took leave of the ladies who were there, and hurried to the door, where he was received, as he got into the chaise, with a tremendous broadside of cheers discharged by our boys, who had assembled on the lawn for the purpose. Running in among them to swell the ranks, I was very near the chaise when it rolled away; and I had a lively impression made upon me, in the midst of the noise and dust, of having seen Mr. Jack Maldon rattle past with an agitated face, and something cherry-colored in his hand.</p>
<p>After another broadside for the Doctor, and another for the Doctor's wife, the boys dispersed, and I went back into the house, where I found the guests all standing in a group about the Doctor, discussing how Mr. Jack Maldon had gone away, and how he had borne it, and how he had felt it, and all the rest of it. In the midst of these remarks, Mrs. Markleham cried: &ldquo;Where's Annie!&rdquo;</p>
<p>No Annie was there; and when they called to her, no Annie replied. But all pressing out of the room, in a crowd, to see what was the matter, we found her lying on the hall floor. There was great alarm at first, until it was found that she was in a swoon, and that the swoon was yielding to the usual means of recovery; when the Doctor, who had lifted her head upon his knee, put her curls aside with his hand, and said, looking around:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Poor Annie! She's so faithful and tender-hearted! It's the parting from her old playfellow and friend&mdash;her favorite cousin&mdash;that has done this. Ah! It's a pity! I am very sorry!&rdquo;</p>
<p>When she opened her eyes, and saw where she was, and that we were all standing about her, she arose with assistance: turning her head, as she did so, to lay it on the Doctor's shoulder&mdash;or to hide it, I don't know which. We went into the drawing-room, to leave her with the Doctor and her mother; but she said, it seemed, that she was better than
<pb n="175" id="p175"/>
she had been since morning, and that she would rather be brought among us; so they brought her in, looking very white and weak, I thought, and sat her on a sofa.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Annie, my dear,&rdquo; said her mother, doing something to her dress. &ldquo;See here! You have lost a bow. Will anybody be so good as find a ribbon; a cherry-colored ribbon?&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was the one she had worn at her bosom. We all looked for it&mdash;I myself looked everywhere, I am certain&mdash;but nobody could find it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you recollect where you had it last, Annie?&rdquo; said her mother.</p>
<p>I wondered how I could have thought she looked white, or anything but burning red, when she answered that she had had it safe, a little while ago, she thought, but it was not worth looking for.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it was looked for again, and still not found. She entreated that there might be no more searching; but it was still sought for, in a desultory way, until she was quite well, and the company took their departure.</p>
<p>We walked very slowly home, Mr. Wickfield, Agnes, and I&mdash;Agnes and I admiring the moonlight, and Mr. Wickfield scarcely raising his eyes from the ground. When we, at last, reached our own door, Agnes discovered that she had left her little reticule behind. Delighted to be of any service to her, I ran back to fetch it.</p>
<p>I went into the supper-room where it had been left, which was deserted and dark. But a door of communication between that and the Doctor's study, where there was a light, being open, I passed on there, to say what I wanted, and to get a candle.</p>
<p>The Doctor was sitting in his easy chair by the fireside, and his young wife was on a stool at his feet. The Doctor, with a complacent smile, was reading aloud some manuscript explanation or statement of a theory out of that interminable Dictionary, and she was looking up at him. But, with such a face as I never saw. It was so beautiful in its form, it was so ashy pale, it was so fixed in its abstraction, it was so full of a wild, sleep-walking, dreamy horror of I don't know what. The eyes were wide open, and her brown hair fell in two rich clusters on her shoulders, and on her white dress, disordered by the want of the lost ribbon. Distinctly as I recollect her look, I cannot say of what it was expressive. I cannot even say of what it is expressive to me now, rising again before my older judgment. Penitence, humiliation, shame, pride, love, and trustfulness&mdash;I see them all; and in them all, I see that horror of I don't know what.</p>
<p>My entrance, and my saying what I wanted, roused her. It disturbed the Doctor too, for when I went back to replace the candle I had taken from the table, he was patting her head, in his fatherly way, and saying he was a merciless drone to let her tempt him into reading on; and he would have her go to bed.</p>
<p>But she asked him, in a rapid, urgent manner, to let her stay&mdash;to let her feel assured (I heard her murmur some broken words to this effect) that she was in his confidence that night. And, as she turned again towards him, after glancing at me as I left the room and went out at the door, I saw her cross her hands upon his knee, and look up at him with the same face, something quieted, as he resumed his reading.</p>
<p>It made a great impression on me, and I remembered it a long time afterwards; as I shall have occasion to narrate when the time comes.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="176" id="p176"/>
<head>CHAPTER XVII. <lb/> SOMEBODY TURNS UP.</head>
<p>IT has not occurred to me to mention Peggotty since I ran away; but, of course, I wrote her a letter almost as soon as I was housed at Dover, and another, and a longer letter, containing all particulars fully related, when my aunt took me formally under her protection. On my being settled at Doctor Strong's I wrote to her again, detailing my happy condition and prospects. I never could have derived anything like the pleasure from spending the money Mr. Dick had given me, that I felt in sending a gold half-guinea to Peggotty, per post, inclosed in this last letter, to discharge the sum I had borrowed of her: in which epistle, not before, I mentioned about the young man with the donkey-cart.</p>
<p>To these communications Peggotty replied as promptly, if not as concisely, as a merchant's clerk. Her utmost powers of expression (which were certainly not great in ink) were exhausted in the attempt to write what she felt on the subject of my journey. Four sides of incoherent and interjectional beginnings of sentences, that had no end, except blots, were inadequate to afford her any relief. But the blots were more expressive to me than the best composition; for they showed me that Peggotty had been crying all over the paper, and what could I have desired more?</p>
<p>I made out, without much difficulty, that she could not take quite kindly to my aunt yet. The notice was too short after so long a prepossession the other way. We never knew a person, she wrote; but to think that Miss Betsey should seem to be so different from what she had been thought to be, was a Moral!&mdash;that was her word. She was evidently still afraid of Miss Betsey, for she sent her grateful duty to her but timidly; and she was evidently afraid of me, too, and entertained the probability of my running away again soon: if I might judge from the repeated hints she threw out, that the coach-fare to Yarmouth was always to be had of her for the asking.</p>
<p>She gave me one piece of intelligence which affected me very much, namely, that there had been a sale of the furniture at our old home, and that Mr. and Miss Murdstone were gone away, and the house was shut up, to be let or sold. God knows I had had no part in it while they remained there, but it pained me to think of the dear old place as altogether abandoned; of the weeds growing tall in the garden, and the fallen leaves lying thick and wet upon the paths. I imagined how the winds of winter would howl round it, how the cold rain would beat upon the window-glass, how the moon would make ghosts on the walls of the empty rooms, watching their solitude all night. I thought afresh of the grave in the churchyard, underneath the tree: and it seemed as if the house were dead too, now, and all connected with my father and mother were faded away.</p>
<p>There was no other news in Peggotty's letters. Mr. Barkis was an excellent husband, she said, though still a little near; but we all had our
<pb n="177" id="p177"/>
faults, and she had plenty (though I am sure I don't know what they were); and he sent his duty, and my little bedroom was always ready for me. Mr. Peggotty was well, and Ham was well, and Mrs. Gummidge was but poorly, and little Em'ly wouldn't send her love, but said that Peggotty might send it, if she liked.</p>
<p>All this intelligence I dutifully imparted to my aunt, only reserving to myself the mention of little Em'ly, to whom I instinctively felt that she would not very tenderly incline. While I was yet new at Doctor Strong's, she made several excursions over to Canterbury to see me, and always at unseasonable hours: with the view, I suppose, of taking me by surprise. But, finding me well employed, and bearing a good character, and hearing on all hands that I rose fast in the school, she soon discontinued these visits. I saw her on a Saturday, every third or fourth week, when I went over to Dover for a treat; and I saw Mr. Dick every alternate Wednesday, when he arrived by stage-coach at noon, to stay until next morning.</p>
<p>On these occasions Mr. Dick never travelled without a leathern writing-desk, containing a supply of stationery and the Memorial; in relation to which document he had a notion that time was beginning to press now, and that it really must be got out of hand.</p>
<p>Mr. Dick was very partial to gingerbread. To render his visits the more agreeable, my aunt had instructed me to open a credit for him at a cake-shop, which was hampered with the stipulation that he should not be served with more than one shilling's-worth in the course of any one day. This, and the reference of all his little bills at the county inn where he slept, to my aunt, before they were paid, induced me to suspect that he was only allowed to rattle his money, and not to spend it. I found on further investigation that this was so, or at least there was an agreement between him and my aunt that he should account to her for all his disbursements. As he had no idea of deceiving her, and always desired to please her, he was thus made chary of launching into expense. On this point, as well as on all other possible points, Mr. Dick was convinced that my aunt was the wisest and most wonderful of women; as he repeatedly told me with infinite secresy, and always in a whisper.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trotwood,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, with an air of mystery, after imparting this confidence to me, one Wednesday; &ldquo;who's the man that hides near our house and frightens her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Frightens my aunt, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Dick nodded. &ldquo;I thought nothing would have frightened her,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;for she's&mdash;&rdquo; here he whispered softly, &ldquo;dont' mention it&mdash;the wisest and most wonderful of women.&rdquo; Having said which, he drew back, to observe the effect which this description of her made upon me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The first time he came,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, &ldquo;was&mdash;let me see&mdash;sixteen hundred and forty-nine was the date of King Charles's execution. I think you said sixteen hundred and forty-nine?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know how it can be,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, sorely puzzled and shaking his head. &ldquo;I don't think I am as old as that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Was it in that year that the man appeared, sir?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, really,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, &ldquo;I don't see how it can have been in that year, Trotwood. Did you get that date out of history?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="178" id="p178"/>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose history never lies, does it?&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, with a gleam of hope.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear, no, sir!&rdquo; I replied, most decisively. I was ingenuous and young, and I thought so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can't make it out,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, shaking his head. &ldquo;There's something wrong, somewhere. However, it was very soon after the mistake was made of putting some of the trouble out of King Charles's head into my head, that the man first came. I was walking out with Miss Trotwood after tea, just at dark, and there he was, close to our house.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walking about?&rdquo; I inquired.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walking about?&rdquo; repeated Mr. Dick. &ldquo;Let me see. I must recollect a bit. N&mdash;no, no; he was not walking about.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I asked, as the shortest way to get at it, what he <hi rend="italics">was</hi> doing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, he wasn't there at all,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, &ldquo;until he came up behind her, and whispered. Then she turned round and fainted, and I stood still and looked at him, and he walked away; but that he should have been hiding ever since (in the ground or somewhere), is the most extraordinary thing!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Has</hi> he been hiding ever since?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To be sure he has,&rdquo; retorted Mr. Dick, nodding his head gravely. &ldquo;Never came out, till last night! We were walking last night, and he came up behind her again, and I knew him again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And did he frighten my aunt again?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;All of a shiver,&rdquo; said Mr. Dick, counterfeiting that affection and making his teeth chatter. &ldquo;Held by the palings. Cried. But Trotwood, come here,&rdquo; getting me close to him, that he might whisper very softly; &ldquo;why did she give him money, boy, in the moonlight?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was a beggar, perhaps.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Dick shook his head, as utterly renouncing the suggestion; and having replied a great many times, and with great confidence, &ldquo;No beggar, no beggar, no beggar, sir!&rdquo; went on to say, that from his window he had afterwards, and late at night, seen my aunt give this person money outside the garden rails in the moonlight, who then slunk away&mdash;into the ground again, as he thought probable&mdash;and was seen no more: while my aunt came hurriedly and secretly back into the house, and had, even that morning, been quite different from her usual self; which preyed on Mr. Dick's mind.</p>
<p>I had not the least belief, in the outset of this story, that the unknown was anything but a delusion of Mr. Dick's, and one of the line of that ill-fated Prince who occasioned him so much difficulty; but after some reflection I began to entertain the question whether an attempt, or threat of an attempt, might have been twice made to take poor Mr. Dick himself from under my aunt's protection, and whether my aunt, the strength of whose kind feeling towards him I knew from herself, might have been induced to pay a price for his peace and quiet. As I was already much attached to Mr. Dick, and very solicitous for his welfare, my fears favored this supposition; and for a long time his Wednesday hardly ever came round, without my entertaining a misgiving that he would not be on the coachbox as usual. There he always appeared, however, grey-headed, laughing, and happy; and he never had anything more to tell of the man who could frighten my aunt.</p>
<p>These Wednesdays were the happiest days of Mr. Dick's life; they were far from being the least happy of mine. He soon became known to every
<pb n="179" id="p179"/>
boy in the school; and though he never took an active part in any game but kite-flying, was as deeply interested in all our sports as any one among us. How often have I seen him, intent upon a match at marbles or pegtop, looking on with a face of unutterable interest, and hardly breathing at the critical times! How often, at hare and hounds, have I seen him mounted on a little knoll, cheering the whole field on to action, and waving his hat above his grey head, oblivious of King Charles the Martyr's head, and all belonging to it! How many a summer-hour have I known to be but blissful minutes to him in the cricket-field! How many winter days have I seen him, standing blue-nosed in the snow and east wind, looking at the boys going down the long slide, and clapping his worsted gloves in rapture!</p>
<p>He was an universal favorite, and his ingenuity in little things was transcendant. He could cut oranges into such devices as none of us had an idea of. He could make a boat out of anything, from a skewer upwards. He could turn crampbones into chessmen; fashion Roman chariots from old court cards; make spoked wheels out of cotton reels, and birdcages of old wire. But he was greatest of all, perhaps, in the articles of string and straw; with which we were all persuaded he could do anything that could be done by hands.</p>
<p>Mr. Dick's renown was not long confined to us. After a few Wednesdays, Doctor Strong himself made some inquiries of me about him, and I told him all my aunt had told me; which interested the Doctor so much that he requested, on the occasion of his next visit, to be presented to him. This ceremony I performed; and the Doctor begging Mr. Dick, whensoever he should not find me at the coach-office, to come on there, and rest himself until our morning's work was over, it soon passed into a custom for Mr. Dick to come on as a matter of course, and, if we were a little late, as often happened on a Wednesday, to walk about the courtyard, waiting for me. Here he made the acquaintance of the Doctor's beautiful young wife (paler than formerly, all this time; more rarely seen by me or any one, I think; and not so gay, but not less beautiful), and so became more and more familiar by degrees, until, at last, he would come into the school and wait. He always sat in a particular corner, on a particular stool, which was called &ldquo;Dick,&rdquo; after him; here he would sit, with his grey head bent forward, attentively listening to whatever might be going on, with a profound veneration for the learning he had never been able to acquire.</p>
<p>This veneration Mr. Dick extended to the Doctor, whom he thought the most subtle and accomplished philosopher of any age. It was long before Mr. Dick ever spoke to him otherwise than bare-headed; and even when he and the Doctor had struck up quite a friendship, and would walk together by the hour, on that side of the courtyard which was known among us as The Doctor's Walk, Mr. Dick would pull off his hat at intervals to show his respect for wisdom and knowledge. How it ever came about, that the Doctor began to read out scraps of the famous Dictionary, in these walks, I never knew; perhaps he felt it all the same, at first, as reading to himself. However, it passed into a custom too; and Mr. Dick, listening with a face shining with pride and pleasure, in his heart of hearts believed the Dictionary to be the most delightful book in the world.</p>
<p>As I think of them going up and down before those school-room windows&mdash;the Doctor reading with his complacent smile, an occasional
<pb n="180" id="p180"/>
flourish of the manuscript, or grave motion of his head; and Mr. Dick listening, enchained by interest, with his poor wits calmly wandering God knows where, upon the wings of hard words&mdash;I think of it as one of the pleasantest things, in a quiet way, that I have ever seen. I feel as if they might go walking to and fro for ever, and the world might somehow be the better for it&mdash;as if a thousand things it makes a noise about, were not one-half so good for it, or me.</p>
<p>Agnes was one of Mr. Dick's friends, very soon; and in often coming to the house, he made acquaintance with Uriah. The friendship between himself and me increased continually, and it was maintained on this odd footing: that, while Mr. Dick came professedly to look after me as my guardian, he always consulted me in any little matter of doubt that arose, and invariably guided himself by my advice; not only having a high respect for my native sagacity, but considering that I inherited a good deal from my aunt.</p>
<p>One Thursday morning, when I was about to walk with Mr. Dick from the hotel to the coach-office before going back to school (for we had an hour's school before breakfast), I met Uriah in the street, who reminded me of the promise I had made to take tea with himself and his mother: adding, with a writhe, &ldquo;But I didn't expect you to keep it, Master Copperfield, we're so very umble.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I really had not yet been able to make up my mind whether I liked Uriah or detested him; and I was very doubtful about it still, as I stood looking him in the face in the street. But I felt it quite an affront to be supposed proud, and said I only wanted to be asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, if that's all, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah, &ldquo;and it really isn't our umbleness that prevents you, will you come this evening? But if it is our umbleness, I hope you won't mind owning to it, Master Copperfield; for we are well aware of our condition.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said I would mention it to Mr. Wickfield, and if he approved, as I had no doubt he would, I would come with pleasure. So, at six o'clock that evening, which was one of the early office evenings, I announced myself as ready, to Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mother will be proud indeed,&rdquo; he said, as we walked away together. &ldquo;Or she would be proud, if it wasn't sinful, Master Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yet you didn't mind supposing <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was proud this morning,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear no, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; returned Uriah. &ldquo;Oh, believe me, no! Such a thought never came into my head! I shouldn't have deemed it at all proud if you had thought <hi rend="italics">us</hi> too umble for you. Because we are so very umble.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you been studying much law lately?&rdquo; I asked, to change the subject.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he said, with an air of self-denial, &ldquo;my reading is hardly to be called study. I have passed an hour or two in the evening, sometimes, with Mr. Tidd.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rather hard, I suppose?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is hard to <hi rend="italics">me</hi> sometimes,&rdquo; returned Uriah. &ldquo;But I don't know what he might be, to a gifted person.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After beating a little tune on his chin as we walked on, with the two fore-fingers of his skeleton right hand, he added:</p>
<p>&ldquo;There are expressions, you see, Master Copperfield&mdash;Latin words and terms&mdash;in Mr. Tidd, that are trying to a reader of my umble attainments.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Would you like to be taught Latin?&rdquo; I said, briskly. &ldquo;I will teach it you with pleasure, as I learn it.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="181" id="p181"/>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, thank you, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he answered, shaking his head. &ldquo;I am sure it's very kind of you to make the offer, but I am much too umble to accept it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What nonsense, Uriah!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, indeed you must excuse me, Master Copperfield! I am greatly obliged, and I should like it of all things, I assure you; but I am far too umble. There are people enough to tread upon me in my lowly state, without my doing outrage to their feelings by possessing learning. Learning ain't for me. A person like myself had better not aspire. If he is to get on in life, he must get on umbly, Master Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I never saw his mouth so wide, or the creases in his cheeks so deep, as when he delivered himself of these sentiments: shaking his head all the time, and writhing modestly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think you are wrong, Uriah,&rdquo; I said. &ldquo;I dare say there are several things that I could teach you, if you would like to learn them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, I don't doubt that, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he answered; &ldquo;not in the least. But not being umble yourself, you don't judge well, perhaps, for them that are. I won't provoke my betters with knowledge, thank you. I'm much too umble. Here is my umble dwelling, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We entered a low, old-fashioned room, walked straight into from the street, and found there, Mrs. Heep, who was the dead image of Uriah, only short. She received me with the utmost humility, and apologised to me for giving her son a kiss, observing that, lowly as they were, they had their natural affections, which they hoped would give no offence to any one. It was a perfectly decent room, half parlor and half kitchen, but not at all a snug room. The tea-things were set upon the table, and the kettle was boiling on the hob. There was a chest of drawers with an escrutoire top, for Uriah to read or write at of an evening; there was Uriah's blue bag lying down and vomiting papers; there was a company of Uriah's books, commanded by Mr. Tidd; there was a corner cupboard; and there were the usual articles of furniture. I don't remember that any individual object had a bare, pinched, spare look; but I do remember that the whole place had.</p>
<p>It was perhaps a part of Mrs. Heep's humility, that she still wore weeds. Notwithstanding the lapse of time that had occurred since Mr. Heep's decease, she still wore weeds. I think there was some compromise in the cap; but otherwise she was as weedy as in the early days of her mourning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a day to be remembered, my Uriah, I am sure,&rdquo; said Mrs. Heep, making the tea, &ldquo;when Master Copperfield pays us a visit.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I said you'd think so, mother,&rdquo; said Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If I could have wished father to remain among us for any reason,&rdquo; said Mrs. Heep, &ldquo;it would have been, that he might have known his company this afternoon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt embarrassed by these compliments; but I was sensible, too, of being entertained as an honored guest, and I thought Mrs. Heep an agreeable woman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My Uriah,&rdquo; said Mrs. Heep, &ldquo;has looked forward to this, sir, a long while. He had his fears that our umbleness stood in the way, and I joined in them myself. Umble we are, umble we have been, umble we shall ever be,&rdquo; said Mrs. Heep.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure you have no occasion to be so, ma'am,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;unless you like.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="182" id="p182"/>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, sir,&rdquo; retorted Mrs. Heep. &ldquo;We know our station and are thankful in it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I found that Mrs. Heep gradually got nearer to me, and that Uriah gradually got opposite to me, and that they respectfully plied me with the choicest of the eatables on the table. There was nothing particularly choice there, to be sure; but I took the will for the deed, and felt that they were very attentive. Presently they began to talk about aunts, and then I told them about mine; and about fathers and mothers, and then I told them about mine; and then Mrs. Heep began to talk about fathers-in-law, and then I began to tell her about mine&mdash;but stopped, because my aunt had advised me to observe a silence on that subject. A tender young cork, however, would have had no more chance against a pair of corkscrews, or a tender young tooth against a pair of dentists, or a little shuttlecock against two battledores, than I had against Uriah and Mrs. Heep. They did just what they liked with me; and wormed things out of me that I had no desire to tell, with a certainty I blush to think of: the more especially as, in my juvenile frankness, I took some credit to myself for being so confidential, and felt that I was quite the patron of my two respectful entertainers.</p>
<p>They were very fond of one another: that was certain. I take it that had its effect upon me, as a touch of nature; but the skill with which the one followed up whatever the other said, was a touch of art which I was still less proof against. When there was nothing more to be got out of me about myself (for on the Murdstone and Grinby life, and on my journey, I was dumb), they began about Mr. Wickfield and Agnes. Uriah threw the ball to Mrs. Heep, Mrs. Heep caught it and threw it back to Uriah, Uriah kept it up a little while, then sent it back to Mrs. Heep, and so they went on tossing it about until I had no idea who had got it, and was quite bewildered. The ball itself was always changing too. Now it was Mr. Wickfield, now Agnes, now the excellence of Mr. Wickfield, now my admiration of Agnes; now the extent of Mr. Wickfield's business and resources, now our domestic life after dinner; now, the wine that Mr. Wickfield took, the reason why he took it, and the pity that it was he took so much; now one thing, now another, then everything at once; and all the time, without appearing to speak very often, or to do anything but sometimes encourage them a little, for fear they should be overcome by their humility and the honor of my company, I found myself perpetually letting out something or other that I had no business to let out, and seeing the effect of it in the twinkling of Uriah's dinted nostrils.</p>
<p>I had begun to be a little uncomfortable, and to wish myself well out of the visit, when a figure coming down the street passed the door&mdash;it stood open to air the room, which was warm, the weather being close for the time of year&mdash;came back again, looked in, and walked in, exclaiming loudly, &ldquo;Copperfield! Is it possible!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was Mr. Micawber! It was Mr. Micawber, with his eye-glass, and his walking-stick, and his shirt-collar, and his genteel air, and the condescending roll in his voice, all complete!</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, putting out his hand, &ldquo;this is indeed a meeting which is calculated to impress the mind with a sense of the instability and uncertainty of all human&mdash;in short, it is a most extraordinary meeting. Walking along the street, reflecting upon the probability of something turning up (of which I am at present rather
<pb n="183" id="p183"/>
sanguine), I find a young, but valued friend turn up, who is connected with the most eventful period of my life; I may say, with the turning point of my existence. Copperfield, my dear fellow, how do you do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I cannot say&mdash;I really can<hi rend="italics">not</hi> say&mdash;that I was glad to see Mr. Micawber there; but I was glad to see him too, and shook hands with him heartily, inquiring how Mrs. Micawber was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, waving his hand as of old, and settling his chin in his shirt-collar. &ldquo;She is tolerably convalescent. The twins no longer derive their sustenance from Nature's founts&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, in one of his bursts of confidence, &ldquo;they are weaned&mdash;and Mrs. Micawber is, at present, my travelling companion. She will be rejoiced, Copperfield, to renew her acquaintance with one who has proved himself in all respects a worthy minister at the sacred altar of friendship.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said I should be delighted to see her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are very good,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber then smiled, settled his chin again, and looked about him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have discovered my friend Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber genteelly, and without addressing himself particularly to any one, &ldquo;not in solitude, but partaking of a social meal in company with a widow lady, and one who is apparently her offspring&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, in another of his bursts of confidence, &ldquo;her son. I shall esteem it an honor to be presented.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I could do no less, under these circumstances, than make Mr. Micawber known to Uriah Heep and his mother; which I accordingly did. As they abased themselves before him, Mr. Micawber took a seat, and waved his hand in his most courtly manner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Any friend of my friend Copperfield's,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;has a personal claim upon myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We are too umble, sir,&rdquo; said Mrs. Heep, &ldquo;my son and me, to be the friends of Master Copperfield. He has been so good as take his tea with us, and we are thankful to him for his company; also to you, sir, for your notice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ma'am,&rdquo; returned Mr. Micawber, with a bow, &ldquo;you are very obliging: and what are you doing, Copperfield? Still in the wine trade?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was excessively anxious to get Mr. Micawber away; and replied, with my hat in my hand, and a very red face I have no doubt, that I was a pupil at Doctor Strong's.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A pupil?&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, raising his eyebrows. &ldquo;I am extremely happy to hear it. Although a mind like my friend Copperfield's&rdquo;&mdash;to Uriah and Mrs. Heep&mdash;&ldquo;does not require that cultivation which, without his knowledge of men and things, it would require, still it is a rich soil teeming with latent vegetation&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, smiling, in another burst of confidence, &ldquo;it is an intellect capable of getting up the classics to any extent.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Uriah, with his long hands slowly twining over one another, made a ghastly writhe from the waist upwards, to express his concurrence in this estimation of me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Shall we go and see Mrs. Micawber, sir?&rdquo; I said, to get Mr. Micawber away.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you will do her that favor, Copperfield,&rdquo; replied Mr. Micawber, rising. &ldquo;I have no scruple in saying, in the presence of our friends here, that I am a man who has, for some years, contended against the pressure
<pb n="184" id="p184"/>
of pecuniary difficulties,&rdquo; I knew he was certain to say something of this kind; he always would be so boastful about his difficulties. &ldquo;Sometimes I have risen superior to my difficulties. Sometimes my difficulties have&mdash;in short, have floored me. There have been times when I have administered a succession of facers to them; there have been times when they have been too many for me, and I have given in, and said to Mrs. Micawber in the words of Cato, &lsquo;Plato, thou reasonest well. It's all up now. I can show fight no more.&rsquo; But at no time of my life,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;have I enjoyed a higher degree of satisfaction than in pouring my griefs (if I may describe difficulties, chiefly arising out of warrants of attorney and promissory notes at two and four months, by that word) into the bosom of my friend Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber closed this handsome tribute by saying, &ldquo;Mr. Heep! Good evening. Mrs. Heep! Your servant,&rdquo; and then walking out with me in his most fashionable manner, making a good deal of noise on the pavement with his shoes, and humming a tune as we went.</p>
<p>It was a little inn where Mr. Micawber put up, and he occupied a little room in it, partitioned off from the commercial room, and strongly flavored with tobacco smoke. I think it was over the kitchen, because a warm greasy smell appeared to come up through the chinks in the floor, and there was a flabby perspiration on the walls. I know it was near the bar, on account of the smell of spirits and gingling of glasses. Here, recumbent on a small sofa, underneath a picture of a race-horse, with her head close to the fire, and her feet pushing the mustard off the dumb-waiter at the other end of the room, was Mrs. Micawber, to whom Mr. Micawber entered first, saying, &ldquo;My dear, allow me to introduce to you a pupil of Doctor Strong's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I noticed, by-the-by, that although Mr. Micawber was just as much confused as ever about my age and standing, he always remembered, as a genteel thing, that I was a pupil of Doctor Strong's.</p>
<p>Mrs. Micawber was amazed, but very glad to see me. I was very glad to see her too, and after an affectionate greeting on both sides, sat down on the small sofa near her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;if you will mention to Copperfield what our present position is, which I have no doubt he will like to know, I will go and look at the paper the while, and see whether any thing turns up among the advertisements.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought you were at Plymouth, ma'am,&rdquo; I said to Mrs. Micawber, as he went out.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Master Copperfield,&rdquo; she replied, &ldquo;we went to Plymouth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To be on the spot,&rdquo; I hinted.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just so,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;To be on the spot. But, the truth is, talent is not wanted in the Custom House. The local influence of my family was quite unavailing to obtain any employment in that department, for a man of Mr. Micawber's abilities. They would rather <hi rend="italics">not</hi> have a man of Mr. Micawber's abilities. He would only show the deficiency of the others. Apart from which,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;I will not disguise from you, my dear Master Copperfield, that when that branch of my family which is settled in Plymouth became aware that Mr. Micawber was accompanied by myself, and by little Wilkins and his sister, and by the twins, they did not receive him with that ardor which he might have expected,
<pb n="185" id="p185"/>
being so newly released from captivity. In fact,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, lowering her voice,&mdash;&ldquo;this is between ourselves&mdash;our reception was cool.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;It is truly painful to contemplate mankind in such an aspect, Master Copperfield, but our reception was, decidedly, cool. There is no doubt about it. In fact, that branch of my family which is settled in Plymouth became quite personal to Mr. Micawber, before we had been there a week.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said, and thought, that they ought to be ashamed of themselves.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Still, so it was,&rdquo; continued Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;Under such circumstances, what could a man of Mr. Micawber's spirit do? But one obvious course was left. To borrow, of that branch of my family, the money to return to London, and to return at any sacrifice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then you all came back again, ma'am?&rdquo; I said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We all came back again,&rdquo; replied Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;Since then, I have consulted other branches of my family on the course which it is most expedient for Mr. Micawber to take&mdash;for I maintain that he must take some course, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, argumentatively. &ldquo;It is clear that a family of six, not including a domestic, cannot live upon air.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly, ma'am,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The opinion of those other branches of my family,&rdquo; pursued Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;is, that Mr. Micawber should immediately turn his attention to coals.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To what, ma'am?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To coals,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber. &ldquo;To the coal trade. Mr. Micawber was induced to think, on inquiry, that there might be an opening for a man of his talent in the Medway Coal Trade. Then, as Mr. Micawber very properly said, the first step to be taken clearly was, to come and <hi rend="italics">see</hi> the Medway. Which we came and saw. I say &lsquo;we,&rsquo; Master Copperfield; for I never will,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber with emotion, &ldquo;I never will desert Mr. Micawber.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I murmured my admiration and approbation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We came,&rdquo; repeated Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;and saw the Medway. My opinion of the coal trade on that river, is, that it may require talent, but that it certainly requires capital. Talent, Mr. Micawber has; capital, Mr. Micawber has not. We saw, I think, the greater part of the Medway; and that is my individual conclusion. Being so near here, Mr. Micawber was of opinion that it would be rash not to come on, and see the Cathedral. Firstly, on account of its being so well worth seeing, and our never having seen it; and secondly, on account of the great probability of something turning up in a cathedral town. We have been here,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, &ldquo;three days. Nothing has, as yet, turned up; and it may not surprise you, my dear Master Copperfield, so much as it would a stranger, to know that we are at present waiting for a remittance from London, to discharge our pecuniary obligations at this hotel. Until the arrival of that remittance,&rdquo; said Mrs. Micawber, with much feeling, &ldquo;I am cut off from my home (I allude to lodgings in Pentonville), from my boy and girl, and from my twins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt the utmost sympathy for Mr. and Mrs. Micawber in this anxious extremity, and said as much to Mr. Micawber, who now returned: adding that I only wished I had money enough, to lend them the amount they needed. Mr. Micawber's answer expressed the disturbance of his mind. He said, shaking hands with me, &ldquo;Copperfield, you are a true friend; but when the worst comes to the worst, no man is without a friend
<pb n="186" id="p186"/>
who is possessed of shaving materials.&rdquo; At this dreadful hint Mrs. Micawber threw her arms round Mr. Micawber's neck and entreated him to be calm. He wept; but so far recovered, almost immediately, as to ring the bell for the waiter, and bespeak a hot kidney pudding and a plate of shrimps for breakfast in the morning.</p>
<p>When I took my leave of them, they both pressed me so much to come and dine before they went away, that I could not refuse. But, as I knew I could not come next day, when I should have a good deal to prepare in the evening, Mr. Micawber arranged that he would call at Doctor Strong's in the course of the morning (having a presentiment that the remittance would arrive by that post), and propose the day after, if it would suit me better. Accordingly I was called out of school next forenoon, and found Mr. Micawber in the parlor; who had called to say that the dinner would take place as proposed. When I asked him if the remittance had come, he pressed my hand and departed.</p>
<p>As I was looking out of window that same evening, it surprised me, and made me rather uneasy, to see Mr. Micawber and Uriah Heep walk past, arm in arm: Uriah humbly sensible of the honor that was done him, and Mr. Micawber taking a bland delight in extending his patronage to Uriah. But I was still more surprised, when I went to the little hotel next day at the appointed dinner hour, which was four o'clock, to find, from what Mr. Micawber said, that he had gone home with Uriah, and had drunk brandy-and-water at Mrs. Heep's.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I'll tell you what, my dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;your friend Heep is a young fellow who might be attorney-general. If I had known that young man, at the period when my difficulties came to a crisis, all I can say is, that I believe my creditors would have been a great deal better managed than they were.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I hardly understood how this could have been, seeing that Mr. Micawber had paid them nothing at all as it was; but I did not like to ask. Neither did I like to say, that I hoped he had not been too communicative to Uriah; or to inquire if they had talked much about me. I was afraid of hurting Mr. Micawber's feelings, or, at all events, Mrs. Micawber's, she being very sensitive; but I was uncomfortable about it, too, and often thought about it afterwards.</p>
<p>We had a beautiful little dinner. Quite an elegant dish of fish; the kidney-end of a loin of veal, roasted; fried sausage-meat; a partridge, and a pudding. There was wine, and there was strong ale; and after dinner Mrs. Micawber made us a bowl of hot punch with her own hands.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber was uncommonly convivial. I never saw him such good company. He made his face shine with the punch, so that it looked as if it had been varnished all over. He got cheerfully sentimental about the town, and proposed success to it; observing, that Mrs. Micawber and himself had been made extremely snug and comfortable there, and that he never should forget the agreeable hours they had passed in Canterbury. He proposed me afterwards; and he, and Mrs. Micawber, and I, took a review of our past acquaintance, in the course of which we sold the property all over again. Then I proposed Mrs. Micawber; or, at least, said, modestly, &ldquo;If you'll allow me, Mrs. Micawber, I shall now have the pleasure of drinking <hi rend="italics">your</hi> health, ma'am.&rdquo; On which Mr. Micawber delivered an eulogium on Mrs. Micawber's character, and said she had ever been his
<pb n="187" id="p187"/>
guide, philosopher, and friend, and that he would recommend me, when I came to a marrying time of life, to marry such another woman, if such another woman could be found.</p>
<p>As the punch disappeared, Mr. Micawber became still more friendly and convivial. Mrs. Micawber's spirits becoming elevated, too, we sang &ldquo;Auld Lang Syne.&rdquo; When we came to &ldquo;Here's a hand, my trusty frere,&rdquo; we all joined hands round the table; and when we declared we would &ldquo;take a right gude Willie Waught,&rdquo; and hadn't the least idea what it meant, we were really affected.</p>
<p>In a word, I never saw any body so thoroughly jovial as Mr. Micawber was, down to the very last moment of the evening, when I took a hearty farewell of himself and his amiable wife. Consequently, I was not prepared, at seven o'clock next morning, to receive the following communication, dated half-past nine in the evening; a quarter of an hour after I had left him.</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="letter">
<opener>
<salute>&ldquo;MY DEAR YOUNG FRIEND,</salute>
</opener>
<p>&ldquo;The die is cast&mdash;all is over. Hiding the ravages of care with a sickly mask of mirth, I have not informed you, this evening, that there is no hope of the remittance! Under these circumstances, alike humiliating to endure, humiliating to contemplate, and humiliating to relate, I have discharged the pecuniary liability contracted at this establishment, by giving a note of hand, made payable fourteen days after date, at my residence, Pentonville, London. When it becomes due, it will not be taken up. The result is destruction. The bolt is impending, and the tree must fall.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let the wretched man who now addresses you, my dear Copperfield, be a beacon to you through life. He writes with that intention, and in that hope. If he could think himself of so much use, one gleam of day might, by possibility, penetrate into the cheerless dungeon of his remaining existence&mdash;though his longevity is, at present (to say the least of it), extremely problematical.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is the last communication, my dear Copperfield, you will ever receive</p>
<closer>
<salute>&ldquo;From <lb/> The <lb/> Beggared Outcast,</salute>
<signed>&ldquo;WILKINS MICAWBER.&rdquo;</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</q>
<p>I was so shocked by the contents of this heart-rending letter, that I ran off directly towards the little hotel with the intention of taking it on my way to Doctor Strong's, and trying to soothe Mr. Micawber with a word of comfort. But, half-way there, I met the London coach with Mr. and Mrs. Micawber up behind; Mr. Micawber, the very picture of tranquil enjoyment, smiling at Mrs. Micawber's conversation, eating walnuts out of a paper bag, with a bottle sticking out of his breast pocket. As they did not see me, I thought it best, all things considered, not to see them. So, with a great weight taken off my mind, I turned into a by-street that was the nearest way to school, and felt, upon the whole, relieved that they were gone; though I still liked them very much, nevertheless.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="188" id="p188"/>
<head>CHAPTER XVIII. <lb/> A RETROSPECT.</head>
<p>My school-days! The silent gliding on of my existence&mdash;the unseen, unfelt progress of my life&mdash;from childhood up to youth! Let me think, as I look back upon that flowing water, now a dry channel overgrown with leaves, whether there are any marks along its course, by which I can remember how it ran.</p>
<p>A moment, and I occupy my place in the Cathedral, where we all went together, every Sunday morning, assembling first at school for that purpose. The earthy smell, the sunless air, the sensation of the world being shut out, the resounding of the organ through the black and white arched galleries and aisles, are wings that take me back, and hold me hovering above those days, in a half-sleeping and half-waking dream.</p>
<p>I am not the last boy in the school. I have risen, in a few months, over several heads. But the first boy seems to me a mighty creature, dwelling afar off, whose giddy height is unattainable. Agnes says &ldquo;No,&rdquo; but I say &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; and tell her that she little thinks what stores of knowledge have been mastered by the wonderful Being, at whose place she thinks I, even I, weak aspirant, may arrive in time. He is not my private friend and public patron, as Steerforth was, but I hold him in a reverential respect. I chiefly wonder what he'll be, when he leaves Doctor Strong's, and what mankind will do to maintain any place against him.</p>
<p>But who is this that breaks upon me? This is Miss Shepherd, whom I love.</p>
<p>Miss Shepherd is a boarder at the Misses Nettingalls' establishment. I adore Miss Shepherd. She is a little girl, in a spencer, with a round face and curly flaxen hair. The Misses Nettingalls' young ladies come to the Cathedral too. I cannot look upon my book, for I must look upon Miss Shepherd. When the choristers chaunt, I hear Miss Shepherd. In the service I mentally insert Miss Shepherd's name&mdash;I put her in among the Royal Family. At home, in my own room, I am sometimes moved to cry out, &ldquo;Oh, Miss Shepherd!&rdquo; in a transport of love.</p>
<p>For some time, I am doubtful of Miss Shepherd's feelings, but, at length, Fate being propitious, we meet at the dancing-school. I have Miss Shepherd for my partner. I touch Miss Shepherd's glove, and feel a thrill go up the right arm of my jacket, and come out at my hair. I say nothing tender to Miss Shepherd, but we understand each other. Miss Shepherd and myself live but to be united.</p>
<p>Why do I secretly give Miss Shepherd twelve Brazil nuts for a present, I wonder? They are not expressive of affection, they are difficult to pack into a parcel of any regular shape, they are hard to crack, even in room doors, and they are oily when cracked; yet I feel that they are appropriate to Miss Shepherd. Soft, seedy biscuits, also, I bestow upon Miss Shepherd; and oranges innumerable. Once, I kiss Miss Shepherd in the cloak room. Ecstacy! What are my agony and indignation next day, when I hear a flying rumour that the Misses Nettingall have stood Miss Shepherd in the stocks for turning in her toes!</p>
<p>Miss Shepherd being the one pervading theme and vision of my life, how
<pb n="189" id="p189"/>
do I ever come to break with her? I can't conceive. And yet a coolness grows between Miss Shepherd and myself. Whispers reach me of Miss Shepherd having said she wished I wouldn't stare so, and having avowed a preference for Master Jones&mdash;for Jones! a boy of no merit whatever! The gulf between me and Miss Shepherd widens. At last, one day, I meet the Misses Nettingalls' establishment out walking. Miss Shepherd makes a face as she goes by, and laughs to her companion. All is over. The devotion of a life&mdash;it seems a life, it is all the same&mdash;is at an end; Miss Shepherd comes out of the morning service, and the Royal Family know her no more.</p>
<p>I am higher in the school, and no one breaks my peace. I am not at all polite, now, to the Misses Nettingalls' young ladies, and shouldn't dote on any of them, if they were twice as many and twenty times as beautiful. I think the dancing-school a tiresome affair, and wonder why the girls can't dance by themselves and leave us alone. am growing great in Latin verses, and neglect the laces of my boots. Doctor Strong refers to me in public as a promising young scholar. Mr. Dick is wild with joy, and my aunt remits me a guinea by the next post.</p>
<p>The shade of a young butcher rises, like the apparition of an armed head in Macbeth. Who is this young butcher? He is the terror of the youth of Canterbury. There is a vague belief abroad, that the beef suet with which he anoints his hair gives him unnatural strength, and that he is a match for a man. He is a broad-faced, bull-necked young butcher, with rough red cheeks, an ill-conditioned mind, and an injurious tongue. His main use of this tongue, is, to disparage Doctor Strong's young gentlemen. He says, publicly, that if they want anything he'll give it 'em. He names individuals among them (myself included), whom he could undertake to settle with one hand, and the other tied behind him. He waylays the smaller boys to punch their unprotected heads, and calls challenges after me in the open streets. For these sufficient reasons I resolve to fight the butcher.</p>
<p>It is a summer evening, down in a green hollow, at the corner of a wall. I meet the butcher by appointment. I am attended by a select body of our boys; the butcher, by two other butchers, a young publican, and a sweep. The preliminaries are adjusted, and the butcher and myself stand face to face. In a moment the butcher lights ten thousand candles out of my left eyebrow. In another moment, I don't know where the wall is, or where I am, or where anybody is. I hardly know which is myself and which the butcher, we are always in such a tangle and tustle, knocking about upon the trodden grass. Sometimes I see the butcher, bloody but confident; sometimes I see nothing, and sit gasping on my second's knee; sometimes I go in at the butcher madly, and cut my knuckles open against his face, without appearing to discompose him at all. At last I awake, very queer about the head, as from a giddy sleep, and see the butcher walking off, congratulated by the two other butchers and the sweep and publican, and putting on his coat as he goes; from which I augur, justly, that the victory is his.</p>
<p>I am taken home in a sad plight, and I have beef-steaks put to my eyes, and am rubbed with vinegar and brandy, and find a great white puffy place bursting out on my upper lip, which swells immoderately. For three or four days I remain at home, a very ill-looking subject, with a green shade
<pb n="190" id="p190"/>
over my eyes; and I should be very dull, but that Agnes is a sister to me, and condoles with me, and reads to me, and makes the time light and happy. Agnes has my confidence completely, always; I tell her all about the butcher, and the wrongs he has heaped upon me; and she thinks I couldn't have done otherwise than fight the butcher, while she shrinks and trembles at my having fought him.</p>
<p>Time has stolen on unobserved, for Adams is not the head-boy in the days that are come now, nor has he been this many and many a day. Adams has left the school so long, that when he comes back, on a visit to Doctor Strong, there are not many there, besides myself, who know him. Adams is going to be called to the bar almost directly, and is to be an advocate, and to wear a wig. I am surprised to find him a meeker man than I had thought, and less imposing in appearance. He has not staggered the world yet, either; for it goes on (as well as I can make out) pretty much the same as if he had never joined it.</p>
<p>A blank, through which the warriors of poetry and history march on in stately hosts that seem to have no end&mdash;and what comes next! <hi rend="italics">I</hi> am the head boy, now; and look down on the line of boys below me, with a condescending interest in such of them as bring to my mind the boy I was myself, when I first came there. That little fellow seems to be no part of me; I remember him as something left behind upon the road of life&mdash;as something I have passed, rather than have actually been&mdash;and almost think of him as of some one else.</p>
<p>And the little girl I saw on that first day at Mr. Wickfield's, where is she? Gone also. In her stead, the perfect likeness of the picture, a child likeness no more, moves about the house; and Agnes&mdash;my sweet sister, as I call her in my thoughts, my counsellor and friend, the better angel of the lives of all who come within her calm, good, self-denying influence&mdash;is quite a woman.</p>
<p>What other changes have come upon me, besides the changes in my growth and looks, and in the knowledge I have garnered all this while? I wear a gold watch and chain, a ring upon my little finger, and a long-tailed coat; and I use a great deal of bear's grease&mdash;which, taken in conjunction with the ring, looks bad. Am I in love again? I am. I worship the eldest Miss Larkins.</p>
<p>The eldest Miss Larkins is not a little girl. She is a tall, dark, blackeyed, fine figure of a woman. The eldest Miss Larkins is not a chicken; for the youngest Miss Larkins is not that, and the eldest must be three or four years older. Perhaps the eldest Miss Larkins may be about thirty. My passion for her is beyond all bounds.</p>
<p>The eldest Miss Larkins knows officers. It is an awful thing to bear. I see them speaking to her in the street. I see them cross the way to meet her, when her bonnet (she has a bright taste in bonnets) is seen coming down the pavement, accompanied by her sister's bonnet. She laughs and talks, and seems to like it. I spend a good deal of my own spare time in walking up and down to meet her. If I can bow to her once in the day (I know her to bow to, knowing Mr. Larkins), I am happier. I deserve a bow now and then. The raging agonies I suffer on the night of the Race Ball, where I know the eldest Miss Larkins will be dancing with the military, ought to have some compensation, if there be even-handed justice in the world.</p>
<p>My passion takes away my appetite, and makes me wear my newest
<pb n="191" id="p191"/>
silk neck-kerchief continually. I have no relief but in putting on my best clothes, and having my boots cleaned over and over again. I seem, then, to be worthier of the eldest Miss Larkins. Everything that belongs to her, or is connected with her, is precious to me. Mr. Larkins (a gruff old gentleman with a double chin, and one of his eyes immoveable in his head) is fraught with interest to me. When I can't meet his daughter, I go where I am likely to meet him. To say &ldquo;How do you do, Mr. Larkins? Are the young ladies and all the family quite well?&rdquo; seems so pointed, that I blush.</p>
<p>I think continually about my age. Say I am seventeen, and say that seventeen is young for the eldest Miss Larkins, what of that? Besides, I shall be one-and-twenty in no time almost. I regularly take walks outside Mr. Larkins's house in the evening, though it cuts me to the heart to see the officers go in, or to hear them up in the drawing-room, where the eldest Miss Larkins plays the harp. I even walk, on two or three occasions, in a sickly, spoony manner, round and round the house after the family are gone to bed, wondering which is the eldest Miss Larkins's chamber (and pitching, I dare say now, on Mr. Larkins's instead); wishing that a fire would burst out; that the assembled crowd would stand appalled; that I, dashing through them with a ladder, might rear it against her window, save her in my arms, go back for something she had left behind, and perish in the flames. For I am generally disinterested in my love, and think I could be content to make a figure before Miss Larkins, and expire.</p>
<p>&mdash;Generally, but not always. Sometimes brighter visions rise before me. When I dress (the occupation of two hours), for a great ball given at the Larkins's (the anticipation of three weeks), I indulge my fancy with pleasing images. I picture myself taking courage to make a declaration to Miss Larkins. I picture Miss Larkins sinking her head upon my shoulder, and saying, &ldquo;Oh, Mr. Copperfield, can I believe my ears!&rdquo; I picture Mr. Larkins waiting on me next morning, and saying, &ldquo;My dear Copperfield, my daughter has told me all. Youth is no objection. Here are twenty thousand pounds. Be happy!&rdquo; I picture my aunt relenting, and blessing us; and Mr. Dick and Doctor Strong being present at the marriage ceremony. I am a sensible fellow, I believe&mdash;I believe, on looking back, I mean&mdash;and modest I am sure; but all this goes on notwithstanding.</p>
<p>I repair to the enchanted house, where there are lights, chattering, music, flowers, officers (I am sorry to see), and the eldest Miss Larkins, a blaze of beauty. She is dressed in blue, with blue flowers in her hair&mdash;forget-me-nots&mdash;as if <hi rend="italics">she</hi> had any need to wear forget-me-nots! It is the first really grown-up party that I have ever been invited to, and I am a little uncomfortable; for I appear not to belong to anybody, and nobody appears to have anything to say to me, except Mr. Larkins, who asks me how my schoolfellows are, which he needn't do, as I have not come there to be insulted. But after I have stood in the doorway for some time, and feasted my eyes upon the goddess of my heart, she approaches me&mdash;she, the eldest Miss Larkins!&mdash;and asks me, pleasantly, if I dance.</p>
<p>I stammer, with a bow, &ldquo;With you, Miss Larkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With no one else?&rdquo; enquires Miss Larkins.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should have no pleasure in dancing with any one else.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Larkins laughs and blushes (or I think she blushes), and says, &ldquo;Next time but one, I shall be very glad.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="192" id="p192"/>
<p>The time arrives. &ldquo;It is a waltz, I think,&rdquo; Miss Larkins doubtfully observes, when I present myself. &ldquo;Do you waltz? If not, Captain Bailey &mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>But I do waltz (pretty well, too, as it happens), and I take Miss Larkins out. I take her sternly from the side of Captain Bailey. He is wretched, I have no doubt; but he is nothing to me. I have been wretched, too. I waltz with the eldest Miss Larkins! I don't know where, among whom, or how long. I only know that I swim about in space, with a blue angel, in a state of blissful delirium, until I find myself alone with her in a little room, resting on a sofa. She admires a flower (pink camelia japonica, price half-a-crown), in my button hole. I give it her, and say:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I ask an inestimable price for it, Miss Larkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed! What is that?&rdquo; returns Miss Larkins.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A flower of yours, that I may treasure it as a miser does gold.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a bold boy,&rdquo; says Miss Larkins. &ldquo;There.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She gives it me, not displeased; and I put it to my lips, and then into my breast. Miss Larkins, laughing, draws her hand through my arm, and says, &ldquo;Now take me back to Captain Bailey.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am lost in the recollection of this delicious interview, and the waltz, when she comes to me again, with a plain elderly gentleman, who has been playing whist all night, upon her arm, and says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! here is my bold friend! Mr. Chestle wants to know you, Mr. Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I feel at once that he is a friend of the family, and am much gratified.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I admire your taste, sir,&rdquo; says Mr. Chestle. &ldquo;It does you credit. I suppose you don't take much interest in hops; but I am a pretty large grower myself; and if you ever like to come over to our neighbourhood&mdash;neighbourhood of Ashford&mdash;and take a run about our place, we shall be glad for you to stop as long as you like.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thank Mr. Chestle warmly, and shake hands. I think I am in a happy dream. I waltz with the eldest Miss Larkins once again&mdash;she says I waltz so well! I go home in a state of unspeakable bliss, and waltz in imagination, all night long, with my arm round the blue waist of my dear divinity. For some days afterwards, I am lost in rapturous reflections; but I neither see her in the street, nor when I call. I am imperfectly consoled for this disappointment by the sacred pledge, the perished flower.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trotwood,&rdquo; says Agnes, one day after dinner. &ldquo;Who do you think is going to be married to-morrow? Some one you admire.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not you, I suppose, Agnes?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not me!&rdquo; raising her cheerful face from the music she is copying. &ldquo;Do you hear him, Papa?&mdash;The eldest Miss Larkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To&mdash;to Captain Bailey?&rdquo; I have just power enough to ask.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No; to no Captain. To Mr. Chestle, a hop-grower.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am terribly dejected for about a week or two. I take off my ring, I wear my worst clothes, I use no bear's grease, and I frequently lament over the late Miss Larkins's faded flower. Being, by that time, rather tired of this kind of life, and having received new provocation from the butcher, I throw the flower away, go out with the butcher, and gloriously defeat him.</p>
<p>This, and the resumption of my ring, as well as of the bear's grease in moderation, are the last marks I can discern, now, in my progress to seventeen.</p>
</div2>
</div1>


</body>
<back>
<div1>
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<head>WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> WHOLESALE AND RETAIL STATIONERS,</head><p>PRINTERS BY STEAM POWER, <lb/> LITHOGRAPHERS &amp; ENGRAVERS ON STONE, <lb/> Draughtsmen and Ornamental Writers, <lb/> COPPER-PLATE ENGRAVERS, AND DIE SINKERS, <lb/> MANUFACTURERS OF <lb/> PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS, <lb/> IMPROVED ADHESIVE ENVELOPES, <lb/> TRANSPARENT TRACING PAPER AND CLOTH, <lb/> LETTER COPYING MACHINES, <lb/> METALLIC PENS, PURE CUMBERLAND LEAD PENCILS, <lb/> &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., <lb/> 65, 66, 67, &amp; 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON, <lb/> AND <lb/> 49, PARLIAMENT STREET, WESTMINSTER; <lb/> LAW STATIONERS, PARCHMENT DEALERS, AND PUBLISHERS OF <lb/> LAW FORMS, <lb/> AT 24, BIRCHIN LANE, CORNHILL.</p>
<p>Railway and Assurance Companies, Joint Stock and Private Banks, the Legal Profession, Architects, Civil Engineers, Surveyors, Auctioneers, Estate Agents, Bankers, Merchants, and all large Consumers, will derive considerable advantage by supplying themselves from these establishments, all material being purchased by Waterlow and Sons in the first markets, and every article being manufactured under their immediate superintendence.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
<head>WRITING PAPERS,</head><p>OF THE MOST APPROVED MAKERS.</p>
<p>
<table rows="11" cols="3">
<head>All qualities, Glazed or Hotpressed.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, per ream </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large B. W. Commercial Letter, 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office Letter, highly recommended </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Note 5 quire packets </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="3">
<head>Note Paper half the price of Letter.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cream Laid Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cream Laid Letter Note per rm. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Large Cream Laid Letter per rm. </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foreign Post, best quality per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Very best Cream or Blue Laid Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 22 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 36 or 42-lined Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 36 or 42-lined, very best Foolscap per rm. </cell>
<cell> 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Wove Draft, folio per rm. </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Wove Draft, 4to per rm. </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Laid, folio per rm. </cell>
<cell> 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Blue Laid, 4to per rm. </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>LETTER OR NOTE PAPER HEADED WITH ENGRAVED ADDRESS, AT 5S PER REAM EXTRA.</p>
<p>NO CHARGE BEING MADE FOR THE PLATE, <lb/> Or in Letter Press at 3s. 6d. per ream extra, if two or more Reams are Ordered.</p>
<p>Ruled Papers of every description.</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="13">
<row role="label">
<cell> ENVELOPES. </cell>
<cell> 3 NOTE SIZES. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 LETTER SIZES. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 1,000. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 250. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 100. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 1,000. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 250. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per 100. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream Laid, very Best </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="9" cols="5">
<head>EXTRA SIZED ENVELOPES.</head>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Wove, </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 3&frac58; </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Laid, </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 3&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Laid, for &frac12; qr. </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Official or Foolscap, Laid, Cartridge </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 4 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Draft Laid </cell>
<cell> 10&frac78; by 4&frac23; </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Draft Laid Cartridge </cell>
<cell> 11 by 4&frac78; </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge Brief </cell>
<cell> 13&frac12; by 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge Deed </cell>
<cell> 11&frac34; by 9&frac58; </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 pr. 100 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Extra for embossing Official Envelopes,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. per</hi> 250, <hi rend="italics">and larger sizes,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. pr. 100.</hi></p><p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<head>Linen-Lined Envelopes at greatly Reduced Prices.</head>
<row>
<cell> No. 1, Letter size, </cell>
<cell> 4&frac34; by 2&frac34; </cell>
<cell> at 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2, Letter size, </cell>
<cell> 5&frac13; by 3&frac18; </cell>
<cell> at 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3, Large size, </cell>
<cell> 5&frac34; by 3&frac34; </cell>
<cell> at 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 4, Extra size, </cell>
<cell> 7 by 4 </cell>
<cell> at 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> No. 5, Official, </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 3&frac12; </cell>
<cell> at 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6, Official, &frac12; qr., </cell>
<cell> 8&frac34; by 4 </cell>
<cell> at 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 7, Draft, </cell>
<cell> 10&frac14; by 4&frac12; </cell>
<cell> at 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 per 100 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>IMPROVED ADHESIVE ENVELOPES,</head><p>Saving the expense and trouble of wafers or sealing-wax, yet perfectly secure, embossed with elegant designs of Initial Dies, of from one to four letters, or with Commercial Dies, at the following prices, without any charge for Die.</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="13">
<row role="label">
<cell> ENVELOPES. </cell>
<cell> PER 1,000. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> PER 500. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> PER 250. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> (Embossed with any Initials.) </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 letter sizes. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream Laid </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>SPECIAL DIES sunk for Coats of Arms, Crests and Devices of every description, from 3s. 6d. upwards, which may be used instead of the Initial Dies as mentioned above (for which <hi rend="italics">no charge is made</hi>). These dies may also be used for embossing note and letter paper to correspond with the envelopes.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Superfine Adhesive Envelopes, embossed with single Initials, and the Commercial</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Adhesive Envelope always in Stock, at</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. per Hundred.</hi></p>
<p>ENVELOPES EMBOSSED IN COLOURS, OR BLACK FOR MOURNING, TWO SHILLINGS PER THOUSAND EXTRA.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
<head>WHATMAN'S DRAWING PAPER,</head>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> <hi rend="italics">Rough or Smooth.</hi> </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Per Quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian </cell>
<cell> 53 by 31 </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian, 2nd quality </cell>
<cell> 53 by 31 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 40 by 27 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Atlas </cell>
<cell> 34 by 26 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Colombier </cell>
<cell> 34 by 23 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 by 22 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elephant </cell>
<cell> 28 by 23 </cell>
<cell> &pound;0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Super Royal </cell>
<cell> 27 by 19 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Royal </cell>
<cell> 23 by 19 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Medium </cell>
<cell> 22 by 17 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Demy </cell>
<cell> 20 by 15 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Outside Drawing Papers, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per lb.; 80<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per cwt. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Thick Rough Drawing Imperial, per quire, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>CONTINUOUS DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<p>The largest Drawing Paper ever made: it is 4 feet 6 inches wide, and of any required length, without a joint. This paper preserves its surface against the action of India-rubber, and will colour as well as the best Drawing Paper. It will be found invaluable for Railway Plans and Sections, Contract Drawings, Manufacturers' Designs, &amp;c., and is admirably adapted for Cartoons, or large Water-colour Drawings.</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">54</hi> inches wide </cell>
<cell> per yard run. 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">54</hi> inches wide second quality </cell>
<cell> per yard run. 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="5">
<head>WHATMAN'S DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant </cell>
<cell> 40 by 27 </cell>
<cell> &pound;0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 by 22 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="6">
<head>SUPERFINE STRONG DRAWING CARTRIDGE.</head>
<row>
<cell> Cartridge </cell>
<cell> 26 by 21 </cell>
<cell> quire 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> ream </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial </cell>
<cell> 30 by 22 </cell>
<cell> quire 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 ream </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dble. Elepht </cell>
<cell> 40 by 27 </cell>
<cell> quire 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 ream </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>MOUNTED DRAWING PAPER.</head>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="2">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> per foot sq. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Antiquarian, on very best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2nd Antiquarian and 1st quality, Double Elephant to Demy (inclusive), on very best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2nd Antiquarian and 1st quality, Double Elephant to Demy (inclusive), 2nd linen </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Continuous Drawing Cartridge, on best linen or holland </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Plans mounted on fine linen </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tracings mounted on mounted paper </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The following mounted Drawing Papers, on second linen, at 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per foot square, are always <hi rend="italics">kept in stock:&mdash;</hi></p>
<list>
<item>Double Elephant, 26 inches wide</item>
<item>Double Elephant, 39 inches wide</item>
<item>Double Elephant, 52 inches wide</item>
</list>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>IMPROVED TRANSPARENT TRACING PAPER,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Warranted of the very best material. Samples will be sent free, upon application.</hi></p>
<p>The following extracts from the <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Art Union,&rdquo;</hi> and <hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Magazine of Science,&rdquo;</hi> will be sufficient guarantee of the excellent quality of these papers, and the great celebrity to which they have attained:</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Art Union.</hi>&mdash;&ldquo;Messrs. Waterlow and Sons' Tracing Paper is certainly the best we have ever tried, being perfectly transparent, though sufficiently thick for all practical purposes, and perfectly free from that oiliness we generally meet with in paper of a similar description, taking the ink as readily as ordinary writing paper. It must be invaluable to all who require the use of such an article.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Magazine of Science.</hi>&mdash;&ldquo;To those very numerous classes of the public&mdash;artists, architects, engineers, map-makers, pattern-drawers&mdash;indeed to all who, whether professionally or otherwise, have occasion to employ tracing paper, we would, with earnestness, urge the extreme worth and merits of that manufactured by Messrs. Waterlow and Sons. In happy contrast to the paper of a like nature, too frequently to be met with, theirs is entirely devoid of all nasty, unclean greasiness; it is thoroughly transparent, and can be traced over either by the pencil, or&mdash;a great desideratum&mdash;by pen and ink. Assuredly this is a very admirable article.&rdquo;</p>
</div3><div3 type="section">
<head>TRACING PAPER.</head>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Per quire. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Double Crown, yel. or blue wove </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, yel. or blue wove </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 60 by 40 Dble. dble. dble. Crown, yel. wove </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> yel. or bl. wove </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> yel. or bl. wove </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Retree, 30 by 40 and 30 by 20, half-price. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Double Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. able. Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 60 by 40 Dble. dble. dble. Crown, thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 20 Dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">5</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, <hi rend="italics">glazed,</hi> thick, yellow wove </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, extra thick </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 by 40 Dble. dble. Crown, double thick </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3><div3 type="section">
<head>PATENT TRACING LINEN.</head>
<p>This article is manufactured at one operation, and will be found very valuable for permanent tracings. The texture is remarkably fine and transparent.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="5">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> No. 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 inches wide </cell>
<cell> per yard </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 28 inches wide </cell>
<cell> per yard </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 36 inches wide </cell>
<cell> per yard </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>TRACING CLOTH PAPER.</head>
<p>This article may be had of any continuous length, without a joint, and is warranted to take pencil, ink and colour, as well as drawing paper.</p>
<p>38 inches wide per yard 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
<p>IMPROVED PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS, <lb/> Made of the Patent Vellum Sized Cream Laid Paper, which is manufactured of extra strength and finish, expressly for these account books, or of first-class blue laid Paper, bound with patent backs, in Russia, calf, vellum, white or green forrel, bazil (plain or grained), and warranted to open flat. They are also made with bands, iron backs, brass corners, and patent locks, with or without printed or lithographed headings, and paged or folio'd in type, by a machine of ingenious construction, which produces a clear and bold figure, of unequalled regularity. The following price list is intended as a guide for books termed extra, the very best that can be manufactured, and whole-bound. Contracts taken for the supply of large establishments and exporters; or tenders given for any particular book or set of books that may be required.</p>
<p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>FOOLSCAP.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bround Folio,</hi> 12&frac12; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 8; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 15&frac12; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 6.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head><row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back  </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back  </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; if in Russia Bands, viz., 3 straps over the back, 8<hi rend="italics">s</hi>; if Double Bands or Russia along the Top and Bottom and one Band in the centre, 16s. Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back  </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back  </cell>
<cell> 7 q. or 656 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back  </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>DEMY.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Broad Folio,</hi> 14&frac12; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 9&frac12;; <hi rend="italics">Long Folio,</hi> 18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 7&frac14;.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 9 q. or 848 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>MEDIUM.&mdash;16 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 10&frac14;.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 2 q. or 176 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 24 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 9 q. or 848 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>ROYAL.&mdash;18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 11.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 3 q. or 272 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Extras. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 750 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands </cell>
<cell> 23 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>SUPER-ROYAL.&mdash;18 <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 13.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia Extra, </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands Extra, </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands Extra, </cell>
<cell> 25 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="37" cols="8">
<head>IMPERIAL.&mdash;20&frac14; <hi rend="italics">by</hi> 14&frac14;.&mdash;(Ruled to any Pattern.)</head>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 4 q. or 368 pp. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If in Russia Extra, </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 6 q. or 560 pp. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> If Russia Bands Extra, </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 8 q. or 752 pp. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> If Double Bands Extra, </cell>
<cell> 29 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bound in Rough Calf, White or Green Vellum, or Stamped Bazil, and Lettered, with or without Iron Back </cell>
<cell> 10 q. or 944 pp. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> Type paging or folioing, per quire, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="2">
<head>PRINTED HEADINGS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Three quires or under </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire, extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Over three quires and under six quires </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per quire extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Over six quires and under eight quires </cell>
<cell> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire extra. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Eight quires and upwards </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per quire. extra. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Parchment Books made in a superior manner, properly ruled and red-lined, for <lb/> Copyhold Court Rolls, Company's Deeds, Awards, &amp;c.</p>
<p>An assortment of <hi rend="italics">Ledgers, Journals, Day Books, Cash Books, Letter Books, Minute Books, &amp;c., &amp;c.,</hi> of different sized papers, whole and half-bound, in various styles, are kept in stock, <hi rend="italics">and being well seasoned,</hi> can be confidently recommended.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5a"/>
<head>PURE CUMBERLAND LEAD PENCILS,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Warranted free from grit, and to retain the point.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The very best Drawing Pencils that can be manufactured, <hi rend="italics">French polished,</hi> HHHH. HHH. HH. H. HB. F. FS. B. BB. BBB. per doz. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Second quality, The very best Drawing Pencils that can be manufactured, equal to those usually sold at 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> HHH. HH. H. HB. F. FS. B. BB. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Waterlow's original Office and Commercial Pencil, French polished </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Second quality, Waterlow's original Office and Commercial Pencil, French polished </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Penny Pencils </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> School Pencils </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brookman and Langdon's best Drawing </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>METALLIC PENS,</head><p>WARRANTED OF PURE DAMASCUS STEEL, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Selected, after many years' experience, from the best Makers, and</hi>
<lb/> Manufactured with all the LATEST IMPROVEMENTS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Sample Card of</hi> 13 <hi rend="italics">sorts of these beautiful Pens will be forwarded by post, free, upon receipt of Eight Postage Stamps.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="23" cols="8">
<row role="label">
<cell> No. on Card. </cell>
<cell> DESCRIPTION OF THE PENS. </cell>
<cell> Per Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Half-Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Qrtr-Gross. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 47 </cell>
<cell> Correspondence Pen, for general letter writing </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 65 </cell>
<cell> Bank Pen, highly recommended for mercantile use </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66 </cell>
<cell> LAW Pen, fine point </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 67 </cell>
<cell> LAW Pen, medium point, for parchment </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 68 </cell>
<cell> Serrated Pen, for fine rapid writing </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 70 </cell>
<cell> Imitation Quill Pen, very pliant </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 71 </cell>
<cell> Commercial Pen, admirable for bold writing </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 83 </cell>
<cell> National Pen, for a light hand </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 84 </cell>
<cell> Eagle Pen, a firm pen, of extra hardened steel </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 85 </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref1" target="B1">*</ref><note id="B1" target="ref1"><p>* Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The Magnum Bonum, a better pen cannot be had for book-keeping
 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref2" target="B2">*</ref><note id="B2" target="ref2"><p>* Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The Magnum Bonum, second quality
 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 98 </cell>
<cell> THE 2-HOLE RAVEN PEN; much attention has always been paid to the manufacture of this pen, and from the great sale it has had since the introduction of it by W. &amp; Sons, they can safely assert that a more <hi rend="italics">useful</hi> pen is not to be obtained </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 99 </cell>
<cell> THE 2-HOLE medium point, particularly recommended for the use of the <hi rend="italics">Legal</hi> profession </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> WATERLOW AND SONS <hi rend="italics">have also introduced the following Pens, of whom only they can be obtained:</hi>&mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 1, for small engrossing hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 2, for large engrossing or small text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 3, for ordinary text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Engrossing or Text Pen, No. 4, for large bold text hand </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 30 </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref3" target="B3">*</ref><note id="B3" target="ref3"><p>* Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The Drawing and Mapping Pen, also for Ladies' use
 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <ref id="ref4" target="B4">&dagger;</ref><note id="B4" target="ref4"><p>&dagger; Also on cards of 1 dozen, with holder, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p></note>The <hi rend="italics">extra fine</hi> Drawing and Mapping Pen, for the finest drawings, on paper and ivory
 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>QUILL PENS, at 4<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per 100. Turkey Quills, 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> ditto.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Any of the above Pens will be sent, post free, at</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. per Gross extra.</hi></p>
<p>The Patent Expanding Pen Holder will fit any pen, in Cedar, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen; Ebony and German <lb/> Silver, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per dozen. Ivory and German Silver Pen Holders, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen.</p>
<p>Porcupine Holders, mounted and tipped, 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each; 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per dozen.</p>
<p>Superior Black Ink, adapted for Steel Pens, warranted not to change color, or corrode the pen, gallons, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi>
<lb/> quarts, 2<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> pints, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> half-pints, 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi>
<lb/> and gallon bottles, in baskets for the country, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Copying Ink, warranted to give perfect copies, quarts, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> pints, 2<hi rend="italics">s.;</hi> and in gallon bottles, 9<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> or packed in baskets for the country, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Glass Cone Inkstand is the most economical ever offered to the public. It presents so small a surface of ink to the atmosphere, that no evaporation takes place, and the ink is always fresh to the last.</p>
<p>Price 3<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> &amp; 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>

<p>Loggerhead Inkstands, 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Loggerhead Inkstands, with Cap only .. 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Loggerhead Inkstands, no Cap or Plate .. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6a"/>
<head>SURVEYORS' MEASURING BOOKS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Doz. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, ruled or plain, whole bound, made of Metallic Paper, 160 pages, and fitted with pencil, 8vo. </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, ruled or plain, half-bound, made of Spfine. Paper, 160 pp 8vo. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, Paper, 160 pp 6to. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, whole-bound and clasped 8vo. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Measuring Books, whole-bound and clasped 6to. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Levelling Books, ruled and printed, each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>BLOTTING PAPERS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Per Ream. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White or Pink Wove </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White or Pink Laid </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> *Patent White Wove, of considerable strength and durability, per quire 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 45 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> *Patent Salmon Wove ..per quire 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 65 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SURVEYORS' MEASURING TAPES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66-Feet Railway Tapes, with Enamel Leather Case and Folding Brass Handle </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 66-Feet Railway Tapes, with Brass Rim </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6-Feet Patent Self-acting Spring Tape Measures, in Brass Case </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3-Feet in Brass Case </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 12-Feet in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6-Feet in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 3-Feet in Brass Case with Spring Stop </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>WRAPPING PAPERS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brown Papers per cwt. </cell>
<cell> 50 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, demy, per rm. </cell>
<cell> 20 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, royal per rm. </cell>
<cell> 28 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solicitors' strong Cartridge, imperial per rm. </cell>
<cell> 35 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hand Paper, (white brown) per rm. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SUNDRIES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="55" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine Wax, red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parcel red or black, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, best mixed per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, patent mixed per lb. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafers, Vermillion Chequered, for affixing to paper deeds per box </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Fcap. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Post 4to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Files or Clamps Fcap. 4to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Letter and Invoice Clips each 8<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, large blue, lined each </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, small blue, lined each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, large crimson, lined each </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Bags, small crimson, lined each </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boxwood Rulers, bound-brass, 42 inches long, and engraved inches each </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Ebony Office Rules per inch </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1&frac12; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Patent Indorsement Boxes, supplied with liquid ink, dampers, cleaning brushes, &amp;c. for the better use of brass stamps, ea. </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wax Vesta Lights per 1,000 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vermillion Fluid, for red lining skins </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vermillion Powders </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 16 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 24 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Red Tape, 32 per dozen </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Silk Ferret, green per piece </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Silk Ferret, green narrow per piece </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cotton Ferret per piece </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> China Grass, Ferret per piece </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Union Cord, Ferret per reel </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Green Silk Tags, for files, and Bankruptcy Proceedings per dozen </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pounce Boxes, japanned, with rubber, each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Desk Knives, cocoa handles each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Erasers, cocoa handles each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Office Hones, in mahogany case each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Rubber Bottle, prime thick, per lb. </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Rubber Patent per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Runners, box handles each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bodkins, box with or without eyes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Seal Chisels, with or without eyes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tin Pens, for ruling Parchment each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Skinholders each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parchment Knives each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paper Pounce per lb. </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Parchment Pounce per lb. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Solid Writing Pads, demy folio each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Sand Boxes each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Wafer Seals, ebony each </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Indian Ink per stick, 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drawing Pins per dozen </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drawing Pins Albata per dozen </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ivory Folders, or Paper Knives each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Outsides Writing Paper per lb. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String and Twine per lb. </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Drawing Vellums at all prices.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>POSTAGE SCALES AND BALANCES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weight 8 oz 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per pair. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weight 16 oz 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 per pair. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Beam Scales, to weight 2 lbs 21 </cell>
<cell> 0 per pair. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Improved Balances, to weigh 16 oz 17<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Improved Balances, for deeds and parcels, to weigh 21bs. &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>These scales and balances, <hi rend="italics">originally introduced by</hi> WATERLOW &amp; SONS, are recommended for simplicity and accuracy of construction; with fair usage, they will never get out of order, and are lower in price than any machines or scales ever before offered.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7a"/>
<p>LETTER CAGES,</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 divisions, with drawer and date box, each </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 2 divisions, without drawer and date box each </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>CASH BOXES, <lb/> With Patent Locks, Japanned and Gilt, with divisions for Notes, Gold, Silver, and Copper.</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> 8 inches by 5 </cell>
<cell> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 10 inches by 6 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>JAPANNED DEED BOXES.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 14 by 10 by 10 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 18 by 12&frac12; by 14 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> With Patent Tumbler Lock, 24 by 16 by 17 </cell>
<cell> 22 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> Pen Trays, Ebony each </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pen Trays, Gutta Percha, beautifully moulded to imitate marble each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, brass fist, 4&frac12; by 2&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed Paper Weight, brass fist, 6 by 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> Bronzed, lion knob 4&frac12; by 2&frac12; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bronzed lion knob 6 by 3 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A great variety of other Paper Weights, in elegant designs of Berlin Iron, Japan, &amp;c.</p>
<p>String or Tape Winder, with fixed knife, <lb/> 2 sizes, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6d. and 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, 1lb. each </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, &frac12;lb. each </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> String Boxes, &frac14;lb. each </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Spring Taper Stands, ea. 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Candles for ea 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per box(18) 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>Pen Racks, Ebony, <lb/> each 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Japanned Date Boxes, <lb/> each 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="2" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lady's Hand Paper Weights </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="1" cols="3">
<row>
<cell> Bird Paper Weights each </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8a"/>
<head>PATENT LETTER COPYING MACHINES,</head><p><hi rend="italics">(The working parts manufactured of Steel, and finished with the greatest accuracy,)</hi>
<lb/> AT CONSIDERABLY REDUCED PRICES.</p>
<p>SCREW PRESS.</p>
<p>LEVER PRESS.</p>
<p>The increasing demand for these Presses, and the great satisfaction which they have universally given, have induced us to manufacture a large stock of the most useful sizes; we are therefore enabled to offer them at much lower prices than heretofore; the large sale which they have met with has convinced us of the impolicy of endeavouring to maintain the old and extravagant scale of prices charged at a time when it was the exception, instead of as at present the rule, for every Counting-house or Gentleman's Library to be furnished with a Copying Machine. These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="12">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Lever Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Mach. wrt.iron beam. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Damping Boxes. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large 4to </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 11s. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foolscap Folio </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 12s </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Post Folio </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 14s. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Larger Sizes for Railway Companies to order.</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="3">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Quarto Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Book or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="15" cols="3">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Foolscap Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Book or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="15" cols="3">
<head><hi rend="italics">Fittings for Folio Machine.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Pads, per pair </cell>
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Damping Brush </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Drying Books or Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 6 Oiled Sheets </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Copying Books, Type-Paged and Indexed, Half-Bound Calf, Lettered.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="22" cols="2">
<head>POST QUARTO.</head>
<row>
<cell> 300 leaves </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 400 leaves </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 750 leaves </cell>
<cell> 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="22" cols="2">
<head>FOOLSCAP FOLIO.</head>
<row>
<cell> 300 leaves </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="22" cols="2">
<head><hi rend="italics">Copying Books, Type-Paged and Indexed, Quarter-Bound.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> 500 leaves </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 750 leaves </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> 1000 leaves </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="22" cols="2">
<head><hi rend="italics">Skeleton Guard Books, Half-Bound, with Index, to hold</hi> 500 <hi rend="italics">letters.</hi></head>
<row>
<cell> Quarto </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foolscap </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="22" cols="2">
<head>COPYING INK.</head>
<row>
<cell> Quarts </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pints </cell>
<cell> 1 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gallons </cell>
<cell> 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gallons packed </cell>
<cell> 11 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Copying Paper, English (blue wove) or French (pure white) at 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per ream, or 1000 &frac12;-sheets letter.</p>
<p>THE PATENT CAPILLARY INSTANTANEOUS COPYING <lb/> PAPER DAMPER renders unnecessary the <lb/> use of a basin of water and sponge, or brush, <lb/> is much cleaner, and always ready for use, <lb/> Price 7s. 7d.</p>
<p>65, 66, 67 &amp; 68, London Wall, London.</p>
</div2>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>TWENTY YEARS AGO.</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>LEND, Memory, lend thy retrospective glass,</l>
<l>To view the changes that have come to pass:</l>
<l>Bring back the scenes of by gone years&mdash;and show</l>
<l>The trade of London &ldquo;twenty years ago.&rdquo;</l>
<l>How different, then, was London's trading scene,</l>
<l>To what its glorious prospect <hi rend="italics">since</hi> has been!</l>
<l>We scarce can think that one score years could do,</l>
<l>What plain reality has brought to view.</l>
<l>Twenty brief years have wrought a mighty change,</l>
<l>And caused a renovation &ldquo;passing strange;&rdquo;</l>
<l>Who would have fancied, &ldquo;twenty years ago,&rdquo;</l>
<l>So great a Mart as Moses' famed Dep&ocirc;t?</l>
<l>Yet there the vast Establishment appears,</l>
<l>The mighty growth of less than twenty years!</l>
<l>A retrospect of twenty years' extent,</l>
<l>A wond'rous change in clothing will present.</l>
<l>That was Monopoly's sad reign, in which</l>
<l>Dress could be purchased chiefly by the rich.</l>
<l>But MOSES hove in sight&mdash;the scene was shifted.</l>
<l>And an important curtain timely lifted.</l>
<l>We cannot look at &ldquo;twenty years ago,&rdquo;</l>
<l>Without admiring MOSES' vast Depot.</l>
<l>Which, like a monument, is now display'd,</l>
<l>Declaring reformation in the trade.</l>
<l>Well may the public aid it as they do,</l>
<l>While such immense advantages they view;</l>
<l>Well may it daily meet with more success,</l>
<l>In all its various articles of dress&mdash;</l>
<l>Dress which Monopoly could never show.</l>
<l>For such low prices &ldquo;Twenty years ago.&rdquo;</l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Spring and Summer Wrappers, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, Pacha, Paletot, and every description of Light Overcoat from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture, and handsomely trimmed from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture lined with Silk from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cloth Overcoats of a light Texture superior quality &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Jean and Holland Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fancy Victoria Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tweed Blouses &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock Coats &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spring and Summer Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin and Buckskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spring and Summer Vests. in every variety &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black and Figured Satin Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black superior quality &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> White Marcella Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Cloth Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys' Hussar and Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys' Spring and Summer Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Fishing Coats, in every variety &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paletots, made from a variety of materials, fitted for Summer wear from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paletots, in every style, elegantly trimmed, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Cloth in every style, of a light texture &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Cloth in every style lined with Silk &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Dress Coat &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Dress Coat for </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Frock Coat from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Frock Coat for </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fancy Doeskin Trousers from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Doeskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Doeskin Trousers &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Cloth Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Cloth Vests for </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Splendid Satin Cloth Vests from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Splendid Satin Cloth Vests for </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Tunic Suits &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's White Marcella Vests &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fishing Coats, to endless variety, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes, in great variety, from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>LIVERIES, NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, &amp;<hi rend="italics">c.</hi></p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Clothes complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Great Fact,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Parasol Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON</head><p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p10a" n="10"/>
<head>THE <lb/> NICOLL PALETOT</head><p>(Registered 6 &amp; 7 Vic. c. 65)</p>
<p>WAREROOMS, 114, 116, 120, REGENT <lb/> STREET, and 22, CORNHILL.</p>
<p>Also for NICOLL'S Morning Coat, now in almost universal request for the country, riding, walking, &amp;c. Shooting Jackets adapted for the Season. Many have assumed the use of the word PALETOT, but Messrs. NICOLL are the sole Patentees of the design and material. As also of the <lb/> PATENT TREBLE GARMENT; <lb/> Or, Paletot (called The Nicoll) which retains all the characteristics of the famed Palet&ocirc;t in its exterior, and has the additional advantages of being convertible from a warm to a light Overcoat, or vice vers&acirc;, at the pleasure of the wearer, or, as the mild or cold nature of the weather may require. This garment must be seen and worn to be properly appreciated; it will be found, perhaps, the best preservative of health in this variable climate.</p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
