<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XIV:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Ingrid Pohl</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.   165K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">  The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. XIV</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>  50 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1850</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2002-11-20, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-10-09, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>


<titlePage>
<docTitle><titlePart> No.  XIV. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> JUNE.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) <lb/> No. XIV. </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>

<docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
</docAuthor><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash;J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> BEDDING MANUFACTORY</head>
<p>THE peculiar feature of their Establishment is, that it is confined exclusively to the Manufacture of BEDDING, and consequently they are enabled to keep the largest Stock and greatest Variety of any House in London, including their <lb/> FRENCH WOOL MATTRESSES: <lb/> ALSO <lb/> THE GERMAN SPRING MATTRESS.</p>
<p>This article HEAL AND SON have succeeded in greatly improving, and are Selling at a much LOWER PRICE than any other House; and can recommend one of them, with a French Mattress on the top, as a permanently elastic, soft, and most luxurious Bed.</p>
<p>THE EIDER-DOWN QUILT <lb/> also, is to be seen ONLY at their House; it is the warmest, lightest, and most elegant covering ever introduced; suitable to the Bed, the Couch, or the Carriage.</p>
<p>EVERY DESCRIPTION OF ENGLISH BEDDING, <lb/> AND OF <lb/> BLANKETS, QUILTS, AND SHEETING.</p>
<p>Their Bed Feathers are all Purified by Steam, <lb/> With Patent Machinery; which process is also employed in the Re-Dressing <lb/> of Old Beds.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S <lb/> LIST OF BEDDING,</head><p>Containing a full description of weights, sizes and prices of every description of Bedding, sent free by Post, on application to their Factory,</p><closer>196 (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL), <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="[1]" id="p1"/>
<opener>No. XIV.&mdash;JUNE, 1850.</opener><head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<head>J. &amp; D. DARLING have Just Published,</head><p>Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
<lb/> PENELOPE WEDGEBONE, <lb/> THE SUPPOSED HEIRESS.</p>
<p>By Lieut.-Col. HORT.</p>
<p>Author of &ldquo;The Horse Guards,&rdquo; &ldquo;The Days when we had Tails on us,&rdquo; &ldquo;The White Charger,&rdquo; &amp;c. Handsomely bound in cloth, illustrated with Eight Coloured Etchings on Steel by ALFRED ASHLEY.</p>
<p>Price 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>THE HORSE GUARDS, <lb/> BY THE TWO MOUNTED SENTRIES.</p>
<p>Embellished with Twelve Coloured Illustrations.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thus saith the Duke&mdash;thus hath the Duke inferred.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Horse Guards proves to be a work written evidently by an officer, and which contains a vast amount of practical knowledge, sound sense, and truisms not easily refuted. Severe and satirical in its tone; elegant and terse in its arrangement; and profoundly convincing in the arguments, based upon correct data. No military man can arise from a perusal without acknowledging that in this volume he has found a graphic detail of the grievances of the profession, and a just animadversion upon the many wrongs perpetrated upon officers. The book itself must be purchased by subalterns as well as general officers, and carefully read.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">British Army Dispatch.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;&lsquo;The Two Mounted Sentries&rsquo; is the taking title of a capital satire upon the mismanagement of the Horse Guards. It embraces a wide field of commentary upon all the existing army abuses. We hope to have a little more space at our command next, and to bestow upon the work the full notice it appears to deserve.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Read extensively it will be, if only on account of the title it bears.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Naval and Military Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE WHITE CHARGER, <lb/> THAT COST ME &pound;200; LOST ME &pound;70,000; DROVE ME FROM SOCIETY; EVENTUALLY DEPRIVED ME OF <lb/> MY FRIENDS; AND FINALLY COMPELLED ME TO QUIT THE SERVICE.</p>
<p>By the author of &ldquo;The Horse Guards,&rdquo; &ldquo;The Days when we had Tails on us,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>With Two Coloured Illustrations, etched on Steel by ALFRED ASHLEY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Opportunities make us known to ourselves and others.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Rochefoucault.</hi></p>
<p>To be ready on the 15th June, and may be had at all Circulating Libraries.</p>
<p>THE SECRETARY, <lb/> A NOVEL, in 3 vols. By Lieut.-Col. HORT.</p>
<p>Author of &ldquo;The Horse Guards,&rdquo; &ldquo;The days when we had Tails on us,&rdquo; &ldquo;The White Charger,&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Penelope Wedgebone,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<closer>LONDON: 126, BISHOPSGATE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SMITH, ELDER, &amp; Co., have Just Published,</head><p>I. <lb/> THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF LEIGH HUNT.</p>
<p>In 3 vols., post 8vo, with Three Portraits, price 31<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6d, in embossed cloth.</p>
<p>II. <lb/> WOMAN IN FRANCE during the 18th Century.</p>
<p>BY JULIA KAVANAGH.</p>
<p>In 2 vols., post Svo, with Eight Portraits of Remarkable French Women, price 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in embossed cloth.</p>
<p>III. <lb/> JANE EYRE: an Autobiography. By CURRER BELL.</p>
<p>4th Edition, 1 vol., post 8vo, 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> cloth.</p>
<closer>LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, AND CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<head>NEW BOOKS OF TRAVEL.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Just published, in two vols., post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, cloth,</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE SHOE AND CANOE.</p>
<p>Pictures' of Crabel in the Canadas'.</p>
<p>Illustrative of Scenery and Colonial Life, with facts and Opinions on Emigration, State Policy, and other <lb/> points of Public Interest, &amp;c. <lb/> BY JOHN J. BIGSBY, M.D., <lb/> Honorary Member of the American Geological Society, and late British Secretary to the Boundary Commission. <lb/> With Twenty Engravings on Steel, and four Maps.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In post</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">s. cloth,</hi>
<lb/> TWO YEARS' RESIDENCE IN A LEVANTINE <lb/> FAMILY.</p>
<p>By BAYLE ST. JOHN. Author of &ldquo;Adventures in the Libyan Desert,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>Forming the new volume of Chapman &amp; Hall's Series of Original Works.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Differs essentially from books of travel in the concentration of its materials. Nestling himself in an Oriental family, aloof from European prejudices, and European habits, the author <hi rend="italics">lived</hi> himself, so to speak, into Orientalism; and his pictures of every-day life in the East surpass, in truth and comprehensiveness, those of ordinary travellers. * * * His book is a panorama of the East, in its domestic aspects.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">The Leader.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Foolscap cloth, 5s.</hi></p>
<p>THE TARANTAS.</p>
<p>TRAVELLING IMPRESSIONS OF YOUNG RUSSIA.</p>
<p>By COUNT SOLLOGUB. With Eight Illustrations.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Count Sollogub is a more than ordinarily welcome guest, well qualified to share the honours of &lsquo;the Season's&rsquo; lionship with Mr. Cumming, the lion-hunter, &amp;<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> There is no ill-nature in the tone or humour of the writer, and his book will furnish a pleasant evening's entertainment.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHEAP EDITIONS of Mr. GALT'S TALES.</head>
<p>This day is published, <lb/> ANNALS OF THE PARISH AND <lb/> AYRSHIRE LEGATEES.</p>
<p>Fcap. 8vo, price <hi rend="italics">3s. 6d.</hi></p>
<p>SIR ANDREW WYLIE.</p>
<p>Fcap. 8vo, <hi rend="italics">3s. 6d.</hi></p>
<p>THE PROVOST, and Other Tales.</p>
<p>Fcap. 8vo, <hi rend="italics">3s. 6d.</hi></p>
<p>THE ENTAIL.</p>
<p>Fcap. 8vo, <hi rend="italics">3s. 6d.</hi></p>
<closer>WILLIAM BLACKWOOD &amp; SONS, Edinburgh and <lb/> London.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just Published,</opener><head>CLARENDON:</head>
<p>A Cale.</p>
<p>BY WILLIAM DODSWORTH.</p>
<p>Three Vols. post 8vo. &pound;1 11<hi rend="italics">s. 6d.</hi></p>
<closer>London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just Published, Third Edition, price <hi rend="italics">7s.</hi></opener>
<head>THE LITTLE ENGLISH FLORA,</head><p>or a Botanical and Popular Account of all our common Field Flowers, with Engravings on Steel of every Species, and numerous Woodcuts. By G. W. FRANCIS, F.L.S.</p>
<closer>SIMPEIN, MARSHALL, &amp; Co., Stationers'-hall-court; D. FRANCIS, 21, Mile End road: and all Book sellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>This day is published, in one vol, post Svo, with numerous Illustrations, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>. handsomely bound and gilt.</opener>
<head>NINEVEH AND PERSEPOLIS:</head><p>An Historical Sketch of Ancient Assyria and Persia, with an Account of the recent researches in those Countries. By W. S. W. VAUX, M.A., of the British Museum.</p>
<closer>London: ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUS, &amp; Co., <lb/> 25, Paternoster-row.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>On the 1st of June, Part 1., price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> (to be followed by other important works, at prices varying according to the quantity of matter in each),</opener>
<head>CHURTON'S LIBRARY for the MILLION, containing a HISTORY of CHARLEMAGNE.</head><p>By G. P. R. JAMES, Esq., Author of &ldquo;Richelieu,&rdquo; &ldquo;Darnley,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>PROSPECTUS.&mdash;It is so true that &ldquo;a man's time is his money,&rdquo; that he may be considered a public benefactor, who can devise the means of obtaining an object at the least possible cost of time; but he who can point out the means of saving both time and money, confers a double benefit on the community. It is the aim of the projector of this library to attain these ends, by reproducing, in an abbreviated form. carefully condensed and rewritten, such standard authors as are at present too voluminous to suit the time, or, by reprinting in their entirety, such as are too expensive to suit the purse of the general reader.</p>
<closer>London: E. CHURTON, 26, Holles-street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>On the 22nd, Part I., containing <lb/> THE FIRST VOL. OF THE ORIGINAL.</opener>
<head>THE DECLINE OF ENGLAND.</head>
<p>BY LEDRU ROLLIN.</p>
<closer>E. CHURTON, Library, 26, Holles-street,</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<head>PUBLISHED on the FIRST of JUNE.</head>
<p>THE LADIES' COMPANION. Part V.</p>
<p>Edited by MRS. LOUDON. With numerous Illustrations. Price Fourteenpence.</p>
<p>THE LADIES' COMPANION. No. 24.</p>
<p>Price 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> Stamped, 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> [<hi rend="italics">Weekly.</hi></p>
<p>PENDENNIS.</p>
<p>By W. M. THACKERAY. No. XVII. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Vol. 1, Price 13<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> in cloth, is now ready. [<hi rend="italics">Monthly.</hi></p>
<p>PAXTON'S FLOWER-GARDEN.</p>
<p>Edited by DR. LINDLEY and JOSEPH PAXTON. No. IV., Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> Beautifully Illustrated. [<hi rend="italics">Monthly.</hi></p>
<p>THE CATSPAW.</p>
<p>A Comedy in Five Acts, as performing at the T. R. Haymarket. By DOUGLAS JERROLD. Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE INVISIBLE VENTILATING HEADS OF HAIR.</head>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<head>ROSS &amp; SONS' METHOD OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the Head </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From Ear to Ear </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From Forehead to Poll </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>These Inimitable works of art, for both Ladies and Gentlemen, from One Guinea-and-a-half.</p>
<p>ROSS &amp; SONS, No. 119 &amp; 120, Bishopsgate-street Within, London, Hair Cutters, Hair Dyers, and Peruque Makers to the Royal Family; Sole Inventors of the Invisible Ventilating Peruques for both Ladies and Gentlemen; Importers of all Foreign, and Manufacturers of English, Perfumery of the finest quality, Wholesale, Retail, and for Exportation; Inventors and Manufacturers of the Union and Treble Hair Brushes, the Toothpick Tooth Brushes, the Hair Warranted not to come out; the Double Anti-pressure Nail Brushes, Medium Shaving Brushes; Renovator Clothes Brushes, &amp;c. &amp;c. Likewise, the only Parties who really Fatten and Kill Bears for their Grease, and sole Inventors of the Botanic Water, for cleansing and stimulating the Growth of the Hair; likewise of the Atrapilatory or Liquid Hair Dye, for Producing all Shades, from the Deepest Black to the Lightest Brown.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>ENGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. ENGLAND's newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. ENGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BALSAM COPAIBA,</head><p>and all other Medicines of a nauseous character may now be taken without inconvenience, by means of the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES. These Capsules will be found superior to those made with Gelatine. They remain entire until they have passed through the stomach into the intestines; and the medicine being efficiently brought in contact with the organs it is intended to affect, the usual nausea and unpleasant eructations are avoided. EVANS &amp; LESCHEE, London, Patentees; and all Medicine Vendors throughout the kingdom.</p>
<p>The recent discovery that the low priced Gelatine Capsules contain a compound of train and other oils, and in many cases no Copaiba whatever, renders it important that the public should be made aware that the PATENT FLEXIBLE CAPSULES are guaranteed to contain <hi rend="italics">Genuine Copaiba only.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>WATERLOW'S PATENT COPYING PRESSES,</head><p>AT CONSIDERABLY REDUCED PRICES.</p>
<p>Lever Press.</p>
<p>Screw Press.</p>
<p>First Quality Screw.</p>
<p>Wrt. Iron Beam Screw.</p>
<p>These Presses, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged if any fault is discovered.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="11">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Lever Press. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell><cell> Screw Press: </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Press, wrt.iron beam. </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell><cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Damping Boxes. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large 4to </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Foolscap Folio </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Post Folio </cell>
<cell> &mdash; </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Copying Paper, very best quality, 2 reams for 17s.&mdash;Ditto French, 2 reams for 16s.</p>
<p>WATERLOW'S <lb/> INSTANTANEOUS COMMUNICATIVE INK, <lb/> FOR COPYING LETTERS, IS THE BEST YET INTRODUCED.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Pints,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.; Quarts,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.; per Dozen Quarts,</hi> 30<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<closer>WATERLOW AND SONS, <lb/> WHOLESALE &amp; RETAIL MANUFACTURING STATIONERS, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, AND 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head>
<p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets, Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambric Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<head>Robson's Choice&mdash;&ldquo;Chat or none.&rdquo;</head>
<p>THERE are few persons who are unacquainted with this proverb: the author of it, a friend of the poet Milton, who wrote his epitaph, lies buried within the Parish Church of Saint Benedict at Cambridge. This is one of the oldest Ecclesiastical Structures in the Kingdom: the tower is, without any doubt, a very fine and rare specimen of Anglo-Saxon Architecture. A great desire has been felt of late to restore this Church, both on account of its many interesting associations, and, more particularly, its present wretched state of repair. An earnest appeal is therefore made to the Public in general, and those connected with the University of Cambridge in particular, to aid in this good work, as the sum required is too large for the Parishioners to raise unaided.</p>
<p>Subscriptions, even of the smallest amount, will be most thankfully received by</p>
<list>
<item>THE REV. JOSEPH PULLEN, Minister.</item>
<item>THE CHURCHWARDENS.</item>
<item>JAMES HOUGH, Esq., Corpus Buildings, Cambridge.</item><item>EDWARD CRANWELL, Esq.Regent-street, Cambridge.</item>
<item>At Messrs. MORTLOCK'S, and the LONDON and COUNTY JOINT STOCK BANKS, Cambridge.</item>
<item>And at Messrs. PARSONS' OLD BANK, Oxford.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RAMSGATE.&mdash;</head><p>To all persons who appreciate the comforts of a good Family Residence at a very low rent, &ldquo;WEST CLIFF TERRACE&rdquo; presents an opportunity seldom to be met with. These Houses have been purchased lately, and the Proprietor now offers them to the Public at half price, viz., 50 Guineas per annum. The houses contain Thirteen Rooms each, and command extensive Sea and Land Views, and are fitted up with great taste, presenting in style an elegance scarcely ever met with where the rent is 100 Guineas a year. The houses are within an easy distance of Christchurch, the Catholic Chapel, and other places of worship, and are supplied with good water, a piece of garden, and the general use of the pleasure grounds.</p>
<p>For particulars apply to Mr. T. T. SADLER, House and Estate Agent, Spencer-square, Ramsgate.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strength- <lb/> ening the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well-known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight, Fainting Fits Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>KIRBY, BEARD, &amp; CO.,</head><p>ORIGINAL PATENTEES &amp; MANUFACTURERS OF THE NE PLUS ULTRA &amp; ROYAL DIAMOND PATENT <lb/> PINS AND NEEDLES, <lb/> TO HER MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY QUEEN VICTORIA.</p>
<p>THE acknowledged excellence of the above Pins and Needles, manufactured solely by KIRBY, BEARD, &amp; Co. under their immediate superintendence, has justly rendered them worthy of the extensive patronage and high reputation which they have so long maintained.</p>
<p>The combined efforts of mechanical ingenuity and long practical experience, have brought them to the highest possible perfection; and K., B., and Co. confidently recommend them as superior to all others, from their possessing all the requisites sought after in these very useful articles.</p>
<p>K., B., &amp; Co., in presenting themselves as long established manufacturers, beg most respectfully to caution Ladies,&mdash;to prevent their being deceived by imperfect productions in imitation of, and purporting to be of their manufacture,&mdash;that they have, to distinguish them, affixed to their</p>
<p>Ne Plus Ultra and Royal Diamond <lb/> PATENT PINS AND NEEDLES, <lb/> A Gold Label, bearing the name of the Firm in full, <lb/> WITHOUT WHICH NONE ARE GENUINE.</p>
<p>Sold by all the principal Haberdashers, Silk Mercers, and Drapers in the United Kingdom&mdash;and Wholesale and for Exportation by</p>
<closer>KIRBY, BEARD, &amp; CO, 46, CANNON STREET, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>TRELOAR'S<lb/>COCOA-NUT-FIBRE<lb/>WAREHOUSE,<lb/>42<lb/>LUDGATE HILL</head><p>The Articles made of <lb/> COCOA-NUT FIBRE, are <lb/> Matting, Mattresses, <lb/> HEARTH-RUGS, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Door and Carriage Mats,</hi>
<lb/> Netting for Sheepfolos, <lb/> CORDAGE, <lb/> Brushes and Brooms, <lb/> For Household and Stab'e <lb/> use, &amp;c.; <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">A Catalogue of which may</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">be had gratis.</hi></p>
<p>As there are many worthless imitations of these goods, it is necessary to notice the Name and Address of the Manufacturer,</p><closer>T. TRELOAR, <lb/> 42, LUDGATE HILL, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">London.</hi></closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p6" n="6"/>
<opener>Invalids Remember This!<lb/>THE ONLY RATIONAL REMEDY <lb/> IS THAT FINE HERBAL MEDICINE,</opener><head>PARR'S LIFE PILLS.</head>
<p>THE ADVANTAGES DERIVED FROM TAKING PARR'S <lb/> LIFE PILLS, ARE</p>
<list>
<item>1ST.&mdash;LONG LIFE, AND HAPPINESS!</item>
<item>2ND.&mdash;SOUND AND REFRESHING SLEEP!</item>
<item>3RD.&mdash;GOOD APPETITE!</item>
<item>4TH.&mdash;ENERGY OF MIND AND CLEARNESS OF PERCEPTION!</item>
<item>5TH.&mdash;GENERAL GOOD HEALTH AND COMFORT.</item>
<item>6TH.&mdash;THEY ARE FOUND, AFTER GIVING THEM A FAIR TRIAL FOR A FEW WEEKS, TO POSSESS THE MOST ASTONISHING AND INVIGORATING PROPERTIES.</item>
</list><p>OLD PARE GATHERING HERBS.</p>
<p>See &ldquo;The Life and Times of Thomas Parr,&rdquo; which may be had, Gratis, of all Agents.</p><p>To have produced a medicine so benign and mild in its operation and effects, and yet so effectual in searching out and curing disease, exhibits on the part of Old Parr deep research and a thorough knowledge of his subject.</p>
<p>None are genuine unless the words &ldquo;PARR'S LIFE PILLS&rdquo; are in WHITE LETTERS on a RED GROUND, on the Government Stamp, pasted round each box; also the fac-simile of the signature of the Proprietors, &ldquo;T. ROBERTS and Co., Crane Court, Fleet Street, London,&rdquo; on the Directions.</p>
<p>Sold in Boxes at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and family packets at 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>N.B.&mdash;A NEW THEORY.&mdash;A new and startling theory as regards the natural duration of human life, appears in a little book called &ldquo;The Extraordinary Life and Times of Thomas Parr,&rdquo; generally called Old Parr; this little work, besides the said theory, contains much that is instructive and profitable as regards the means of ensuring good health, and may be obtained gratuitously of any agent for PARR'S LIFE PILLS.</p>
<closer>Agents for this highly esteemed Medicine are treated liberally.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FREEMAN'S NEW WAX CANDLES</head>
<p>ARE THE MOST ECONOMICAL, AND AN EXCELLENT IMITATION OF <lb/> REAL WAX.</p>
<p>24lbs. and box, 23s. cash.</p>
<p>Only at 3, WIGMORE STREET, 3 doors from CAVENDISH <lb/> SQUARE.</p>
<p>FREEMANS, Purveyors to Her Majesty by Warrant, also 'beg to submit to the Nobility and Gentry their Best Stamped Wax, and other Goods, in the Candle, Soap, and Oil Trade, which, by manufacturing on their Premises, they can supply of very superior quality, at lowest prices. Lists sent. Established 1695.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>AN EXCELLENT cure of a DISORDER IN THE STOMACH effected by HOLLOWAY'S PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>A Lady, an intimate friend of the family of General Rosas, Governor of the Republic of La Plata, declares that she was lately cured of a disorder in the stomach, and restored to perfect health, by the use of this admirable remedy. She had consulted the most eminent physicians in the country, but had not been able to obtain any relief from the complaint that was killing her by inches, until she took Holloway's Pills. John Eastman, Esq., an eminent merchant of Buenos Ayres, communicated these particulars to Professor HOLLOWAY in a letter dated the 4th September, 1849.&mdash;Sold by all druggists, and at Professor HOLLOWAY'S Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p7" n="7"/>
<head>PARASOLS.</head>
<p>W. AND J. SANGSTER</p>
<p>Respectfully solicit an inspection of their extensive Stock of Parasols, manufactured expressly for this season, consisting of the most elegant and fashionable colours in Glac&eacute; and Striped Silks, Plain and Moir&eacute;, Lined and Unlined.</p>
<p>PATENTEES OF THE ALPACA PARASOL, which gave such universal satisfaction last year, 30,000 having been sold during the season.</p>
<closer>140, Regent-street; 94, Fleet-street; 10, Royal Exchange; <lb/> 75 Cheapside.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NORWICH SHAWLS.</head>
<p>BLAKELY'S ANGLO-INDIAN SHAWLS <lb/> SHAWL MANUFACTORY AND PRINT WORKS, <lb/> THE RIVER HOUSE, DUKE'S PALACE, NORWICH;</p><closer>Retail Establishment, 15 &amp; 16, London Street, Norwich.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p8" n="8"/>
<epigraph><p>FIVE SPECIAL APPOINTMENTS.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>LOUIS PHILLIPPE &amp; THE ROYAL FAMILIES OF ENGLAND &amp; FRANCE.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>THE LATE QUEEN DOWAGER.</p></epigraph>
<epigraph><p>THE QUEEN, PRINCE ALBERT, THE DUCHESS OF KENT</p></epigraph>
<head>REFORM YOUR TAILOR'S BILLS.</head>
<p>THE BEST IS THE CHEAPEST. Always keeping this in view in connexion with their scale of READY MONEY LOW CHARGES (A BOOK GRATIS) The DOUDNEYS have raised their Business to greater extent and higher respectability than any other House can boast, as a proof of which, they point to their FIVE ROYAL APPOINTMENTS, and their Patronage Book of Royal, Illustrious, and Noble Names.</p>
<p>WATERPROOF IRISH POPLIN. The Royal Registered Cloak constantly worn by the QUEEN, PRINCE ALBERT, the Duchesses of Kent and Cambridge, Sutherland and Buccleugh. &ldquo;Every Lady should see these graceful garments.&rdquo; (<hi rend="italics">Vide Morning Post, Sept.</hi> 26<hi rend="italics">th</hi>). The Overcoat for Gentlemen, or their New Cape, admirably adapted for the RACES, to keep off wet and Dust. The Workmanship is not to be equalled, and needs only to be seen to be approved&mdash;made exclusively at the DOUDNEYS.</p>
<p>THE OLYMPIC GIRTH, for Riding, Hunting, or general exercise. Effectual PROTECTION AGAINST RUPTURE. The support commencing at the bottom edge of the Belt, and producing uniform upward pressure; enlarged or tightened six inches unobserved. They are attached to drawers with excellent effect. 10s. 6d. each.</p>
<p>DOUDNEYS 17,OLD BOND S<hi rend="superscript">T.</hi>&mdash;25, BURLINGTON ARCADE AND 49, LOMBARD S<hi rend="superscript">T.</hi> ESTAB<hi rend="superscript">O.</hi> 1784.</p>
<p>LIVERIES. One of the Leading Articles of the DOUDNEYS ESTABLISHMENT, for which they are so celebrated by Families of the First Distinction. FOOTMAN'S SUIT, &pound;3 3s. Best Quality.</p>
<p>The NEW PATTERNS for SPRING and SUMMER Wear at the OLD PRICES, so famous in Seasons past, viz.&mdash;Summer Waistcoats, 7s. each, or 3 for 20s.&mdash;Summer Trousers, 10s. 6d. per pair, or 3 for 30s.&mdash;Summer Coats, the beautiful light material, 10s. 6d., 21s., and 30s.</p>
<p>Habit Makers by Special Appointment to Queen Victoria and the Ladies of the Court. A SUPERFINE CLOTH HABIT for 4 Guineas.</p>
<p>The DOUDNEYS have been long CELEBRATED for YOUNG GENTLEMEN'S CLOTHING, tastefully made at remarkably Low Prices.</p>
<p>COUNTRY GENTLEMEN wishing to be Respectably Dressed at Low Prices, should send for a Book of Detail, Self-measurement, and all the System of Business, or if 3 or 4 Gentlemen unite, a Traveller will wait upon them.</p>
<p>TROWSER STRAPS superseded by the DOUDNEY SPRING. Nothing under the feet, easily attached, require no cleaning, and make the Trowsers fit better. 6d. per pair.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">I am Married.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Traddles and I in conference with the Misses Spenlow.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>

<div1 type="section">
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<opener>&ldquo;Familiar in their Mouths as HOUSEHOLD WORDS.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Shakespeare.</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italics">Publishing weekly, price 2d., or Stamped for post, 3d.;</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">also in Monthly Parts.</hi></opener>
<head>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head><p>A WEEKLY JOURNAL, <lb/> Designed for the Instruction and Entertainment of all <lb/> Classes of Readers.</p>
<p>CONDUCTED BY</p>
<p>CHARLES DICKENS.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>CONTENTS OF PART I.&mdash;PRICE 11d.</head>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. I.</head>
<item>A Preliminary Word.</item>
<item>Lizzie Leigh.&mdash;In Four Chapters.&mdash;Chapter I.</item>
<item>Valentine's Day at the Post-Office.</item>
<item>Abraham and the Fire-Worshipper.&mdash;a Dramatic Parable.</item>
<item>The Amusements of the People.</item>
<item>An Incident in the Life of Madlle. Clairon.</item>
<item>The Wayside Well.</item>
<item>A Bundle of Emigrants' Letters.</item>
<item>Milking in Australia.</item>
<item>Metal in Sea-Water.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. II.</head>
<item>A Child's Dream of a Star.</item>
<item>The True Story of a Coal Fire.&mdash;In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chap. I.</item>
<item>Lizzie Leigh.&mdash;In Four Chapters.&mdash;Chapter II.</item>
<item>Work! An Anecdote.</item>
<item>Good Verses of a Bad Poet.</item>
<item>Perfect Felicity.&mdash;In a Bird's-Eye View.</item>
<item>A Dialogue of Shadows.</item>
<item>An Australian Ploughman's Story.</item>
<item>Heathen and Christian Burial.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. III.</head>
<item>The Household Narrative.</item>
<item>The Troubled Water Question.</item>
<item>Illustrations of Cheapness.&mdash;The Lucifer Match.</item>
<item>The Amusements of the People.</item>
<item>Sonnet.&mdash;To Lord Denman.</item>
<item>Lizzie Leigh.&mdash;In Four Chapters &mdash; Chap. III.</item>
<item>The Seasons.</item>
<item>Short Cuts across the Globe</item>
<item>The True Story of a Coal Fire.&mdash;In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chap. II.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. IV.</head>
<item>Some Account of an Extraordinary Traveller.</item>
<item>Loaded Dice.</item>
<item>Dream within Dream; or, Evil Minimised.</item>
<item>The Schoolmaster at Home and Abroad.</item>
<item>The Lady Alice.</item>
<item>Illustrations of Cheapness.&mdash;A Globe.</item>
<item>The Ghost of the late Mr. James Barber.&mdash;A Yarn Ashore.</item>
<item>The True Story of a Coal Fire.&mdash;In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chapter the Last.</item>
<item>Supposing!</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. V.</head>
<item>Pet Prisoners.</item>
<item>A Tale of the Good Old Times.</item>
<item>Baptismal Rituals.</item>
<item>Arctic Heroes.&mdash;A Fragment of Naval History</item>
<item>A Coroner's Inquest.</item>
<item>Francis Jeffrey.</item>
<item>The Young Jew of Tunis.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
<head>CONTENTS OF PART II.&mdash;PRICE 9d.</head>
<p>(<hi rend="italics">Published 1st June.</hi>)</p>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. VI.</head>
<item>The Heart of Mid-London.</item>
<item>The Miner's Daughters.&mdash;A Tale of the Peak.&mdash;In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chap. I.</item>
<item>New Life and Old Learning.</item>
<item>The Railway Station.</item>
<item>The Brown Hat.</item>
<item>Alchemy and Gunpowder.</item>
<item>&ldquo;A Good Plain Cook.&rdquo;</item>
<item>Two-Handed Dick the Stockman. &mdash; An Adventure in the Bush.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. VII.</head>
<item>The Fire Brigade of London.</item>
<item>Poetry in the Bye-Ways.</item>
<item>The Miner's Daughters.&mdash;A Tale of the Peak. &mdash; In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chap. II.</item>
<item>The Uses of Sorrow.</item>
<item>From the Raven in the Happy Family.</item>
<item>Illustrations of Cheapness.&mdash;Eggs.</item>
<item>Music in Humble Life.</item>
<item>A Paris Newspaper.</item>
<item>Lines by Robert Southey.</item>
<item>Short Cuts Across the Globe.</item>
<item>Curious Epitaph.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. VIII.</head>
<item>The Begging-Letter Writer.</item>
<item>The Great Cat and Dog Question.</item>
<item>A Card from Mr. Booley.</item>
<item>Law at a Low Price.</item>
<item>Swedish Folk-Songs. &mdash; Fair Carin.</item>
<item>A Visit to the Arctic Discovery Ships.</item>
<item>The Miner's Daughters.&mdash;A Tale of the Peak. &mdash; In Three Chapters.&mdash;Chap. III.</item>
<item>Letter from a Highly Respectable Old Lady.</item>
<item>A Sample of the Old School.</item>
</list>
<list type="section">
<head>NO. IX.</head>
<item>The Sickness and Health of the People of Bleaburn. - In Three Parts.&mdash;Chapter I.</item>
<item>Spring-Time in the Court.</item>
<item>The Planeta-Watchers of Greenwich.</item>
<item>Swedish Folk-Songs.&mdash;The Dove on the Lily.</item>
<item>A Walk in a Workhouse.</item>
<item>The &ldquo;Irish Difficulty&rdquo; solved by Con Me Nale.</item>
<item>William Wordsworth.</item>
<item>Father and Son.</item>
</list>
<closer>OFFICE, 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH, STRAND; <lb/> AND ALL BOOKSELLERS AND NEWSMEN. </closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
<opener>
<dateline>OFFICE, 16, Wellington Street, North. <lb/> April 12, 1850.</dateline>
Published Monthly, with the Magazines, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Price 2d., or Stamped, 3d.,</hi></opener>
<head>THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE <lb/> OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS.</head><p>BEING <lb/> A Monthly Supplement to &ldquo;Household Words,&rdquo; <lb/> CONDUCTED BY <lb/> CHARLES DICKENS.</p>
<p>WE take this opportunity of announcing a design closely associated with our Household Words, which we have now matured, and which we hope will be acceptable to our readers.</p>
<p>We propose publishing, at the end of each month, as a Supplementary Number to the monthly part of Household Words, a comprehensive Abstract or History of all the occurrences of that month, native and foreign, under the title of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF CURRENT EVENTS.</p>
<p>The size and price of each of these numbers will be the same as the size and price of a single number of &ldquo;HOUSEHOLD WORDS.&rdquo; Twelve numbers will necessarily be published in the course of the year&mdash;one for each month&mdash;and on the completion of the Annual Volume, a copious Index will appear, and a title-page for the volume; which will then be called THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE of such a year. It will form a complete Chronicle of all that year's events, carefully compiled, thoroughly digested, and systematically arranged for easy reference; presenting a vast mass of information that must be interesting to all, at a price that will render it accessible to the humblest purchasers of books, and at which only our existing machinery in
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
connexion with our Weekly Miscellany would enable us to produce it.</p>
<p>The first number of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE will appear as a Supplement to the first monthly part of &ldquo;Household Words,&rdquo; published at the end of the present month of APRIL. As the Volume for 1850 would be incomplete (in consequence of our not having commenced this publication at the beginning of a year) without a backward reference to the three months of JANUARY, FEBRUARY, and MARCH, a similar number of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE for each of those months will be published before the year is out.</p>
<p>It is scarcely necessary to explain that it is not proposed to render the purchase of THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE compulsory on the purchasers of Household Words; and that the Supplementary Number, though always published at the same time as our Monthly Part, will therefore be detached from it, and published separately.</p>
<p>Nor is it necessary for us, we believe, to expatiate on our leading reasons for adding this new undertaking to our present enterprise. The intimate connexion between the facts and realities of the time, and the means by which we aim, in &ldquo;HOUSEHOLD WORDS,&rdquo; to soften what is hard in them, to exalt what is held in little consideration, and to show the latent hope there is in what may seem unpromising, needs not to be pointed out. All that we sought to express in our Preliminary Word, in reference to this work, applies, we think, to its proposed companion. As another humble means of enabling those who accept us for their friend, to bear the world's rough-cast events to the anvil of courageous duty, and there beat them into a shape, we enter on the project, and confide in its success.</p>
<p>The Number for MAY will be <lb/> published on the 1st of June.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Number for APRIL (published on the 1st of May)</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">may be had of all Booksellers and Newsmen.</hi></p>
<closer>[Bradbury &amp; Evans, Printers, Whitefriars</closer>
</div1>


<div1 type="narrative">
<pb n="417" id="p417"/>

<head>[THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head>
<div2 type="chapter"><head>CHAPTER XLI. <lb/> DORA'S AUNTS.</head>
<p>AT last, an answer came from the two old ladies. They presented their compliments to Mr. Copperfield, and informed him that they had given his letter their best consideration, &ldquo;with a view to the happiness of both parties&rdquo;&mdash;which I thought rather an alarming expression, not only because of the use they had made of it in relation to the family difference before-mentioned, but because I had (and have all my life) observed that conventional phrases are a sort of fireworks, easily let off, and liable to take a great variety of shapes and colors not at all suggested by their original form. The Misses Spenlow added that they begged to forbear expressing, &ldquo;through the medium of correspondence,&rdquo; an opinion on the subject of Mr. Copperfield's communication; but that if Mr. Copperfield would do them the favor to call, upon a certain day, (accompanied, if he thought proper, by a confidential friend), they would be happy to hold some conversation on the subject.</p>
<p>To this favor, Mr. Copperfield immediately replied, with his respectful compliments, that he would have the honor of waiting on the Misses Spenlow, at the time appointed; accompanied, in accordance with their kind permission, by his friend Mr. Thomas Traddles of the Inner Temple. Having dispatched which missive, Mr. Copperfield fell into a condition of strong nervous agitation; and so remained until the day arrived.</p>
<p>It was a great augmentation of my uneasiness to be bereaved, at this eventful crisis, of the inestimable services of Miss Mills. But Mr. Mills, who was always doing something or other to annoy me&mdash;or I felt as if he were, which was the same thing&mdash;had brought his conduct to a climax, by taking it into his head that he would go to India. Why should he go to India, except to harass me? To be sure he had nothing to do with any other part of the world, and had a good deal to do with that part; being entirely in the India trade, whatever that was (I had floating dreams myself concerning golden shawls and elephant's teeth); having been at Calcutta in his youth; and designing now to go out there again, in the capacity of resident partner. But this was nothing to me. However, it was so much to him that for India he was bound, and Julia with him; and Julia went into the country to take leave of her relations; and the house was put into a perfect suit of bills, announcing that it was to be let or sold, and that the furniture (Mangle and all) was to be taken at a valuation. So, here was another earthquake of which I became the sport, before I had recovered from the shock of its predecessor!</p>
<p>I was in several minds how to dress myself on the important day; being divided between my desire to appear to advantage, and my apprehensions of putting on anything that might impair my severely practical character in the eyes of the Misses Spenlow. I endeavoured to hit a happy medium between these two extremes; my aunt approved the result;
<pb n="418" id="p418"/>
and Mr. Dick threw one of his shoes after Traddles and me, for luck, as we went down-stairs.</p>
<p>Excellent fellow as I knew Traddles to be, and warmly attached to him as I was, I could not help wishing, on that delicate occasion, that he had never contracted the habit of brushing his hair so very upright. It gave him a surprised look&mdash;not to say a hearth-broomy kind of expression&mdash;which, my apprehensions whispered, might be fatal to us.</p>
<p>I took the liberty of mentioning it to Traddles, as we were walking to Putney; and saying that if he <hi rend="italics">would</hi> smooth it down a little&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Traddles, lifting off his hat, and rubbing his hair all kinds of ways, &ldquo;nothing would give me greater pleasure. But it won't.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't be smoothed down?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;Nothing will induce it. If I was to carry a half-hundred-weight upon it, all the way to Putney, it would be up again the moment the weight was taken off. You have no idea what obstinate hair mine is, Copperfield. I am quite a fretful porcupine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was a little disappointed, I must confess, but thoroughly charmed by his good-nature too. I told him how I esteemed his good-nature; and said that his hair must have taken all the obstinacy out of his character, for <hi rend="italics">he</hi> had none.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh!&rdquo; returned Traddles, laughing, &ldquo;I assure you, it's quite an old story, my unfortunate hair. My uncle's wife couldn't bear it. She said it exasperated her. It stood very much in my way, too, when I first fell in love with Sophy. Very much!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did she object to it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">She</hi> didn't,&rdquo; rejoined Traddles; &ldquo;but her eldest sister&mdash;the one that's the Beauty&mdash;quite made game of it, I understand. In fact, all the sisters laugh at it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Agreeable!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; returned Traddles with perfect innocence, &ldquo;it's a joke for us. They pretend that Sophy has a lock of it in her desk, and is obliged to shut it in a clasped book, to keep it down. We laugh about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By-the-bye, my dear Traddles,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;your experience may suggest something to me. When you became engaged to the young lady whom you have just mentioned, did you make a regular proposal to her family? Was there anything like&mdash;what we are going through to-day, for instance?&rdquo; I added, nervously.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why,&rdquo; replied Traddles, on whose attentive face a thoughtful shade had stolen, &ldquo;it was rather a painful transaction, Copperfield, in my case. You see, Sophy being of so much use in the family, none of them could endure the thought of her ever being married. Indeed, they had quite settled among themselves that she never was to be married, and they called her the old maid. Accordingly, when I mentioned it, with the greatest precaution, to Mrs. Crewler&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The mamma?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The mamma,&rdquo; said Traddles&mdash;&ldquo;Reverend Horace Crewler&mdash;when I mentioned it with every possible precaution to Mrs. Crewler, the effect upon her was such that she gave a scream and became insensible. I couldn't approach the subject again, for months.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="419" id="p419"/>
<p>&ldquo;You did at last?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, the Reverend Horace did,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;He is an excellent man, most exemplary in every way; and he pointed out to her that she ought, as a Christian, to reconcile herself to the sacrifice (especially as it was so uncertain), and to bear no uncharitable feeling towards me. As to myself, Copperfield, I give you my word, I felt a perfect bird of prey towards the family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The sisters took your part, I hope, Traddles?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I can't say they did,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;When we had comparatively reconciled Mrs. Crewler to it, we had to break it to Sarah. You recollect my mentioning Sarah, as the one that has something the matter with her spine?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perfectly!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She clenched both her hands,&rdquo; said Traddles, looking at me in dismay; &ldquo;shut her eyes; turned lead-color; became perfectly stiff; and took nothing for two days, but toast-and-water administered with a teaspoon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a very unpleasant girl, Traddles!&rdquo; I remarked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, I beg your pardon, Copperfield!&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;She is a very charming girl, but she has a great deal of feeling. In fact, they all have. Sophy told me afterwards, that the self-reproach she underwent while she was in attendance upon Sarah, no words could describe. I know it must have been severe, by my own feelings, Copperfield; which were like a criminal's. After Sarah was restored, we still had to break it to the other eight; and it produced various effects upon them of a most pathetic nature. The two little ones, whom Sophy educates, have only just left off de-testing me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At any rate, they are all reconciled to it now, I hope?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ye&mdash;yes, I should say they were, on the whole, resigned to it,&rdquo; said Traddles, doubtfully. &ldquo;The fact is, we avoid mentioning the subject; and my unsettled prospects and indifferent circumstances are a great consolation to them. There will be a deplorable scene, whenever we are married. It will be much more like a funeral, than a wedding. And they'll all hate me for taking her away!&rdquo;</p>
<p>His honest face, as he looked at me with a serio-comic shake of his head, impresses me more in the remembrance than it did in the reality, for I was by this time in a state of such excessive trepidation and wandering of mind, as to be quite unable to fix my attention on anything. On our approaching the house where the Misses Spenlow lived, I was at such a discount in respect of my personal looks and presence of mind, that Traddles proposed a gentle stimulant in the form of a glass of ale. This having been administered at a neighbouring public-house, he conducted me, with tottering steps, to the Misses Spenlow's door.</p>
<p>I had a vague sensation of being, as it were, on view, when the maid opened it; and of wavering, somehow, across a hall with a weather-glass in it, into a quiet little drawing-room on the ground-floor, commanding a neat garden. Also of sitting down here, on a sofa, and seeing Traddles's hair start up, now his hat was removed, like one of those obtrusive little figures made of springs, that fly out of fictitious snuff-boxes when the lid is taken off. Also of hearing an old-fashioned clock ticking away on the
<pb n="420" id="p420"/>
chimney-piece, and trying to make it keep time to the jerking of my heart,&mdash;which it wouldn't. Also of looking round the room for any sign of Dora, and seeing none. Also of thinking that Jip once barked in the distance, and was instantly choked by somebody. Ultimately I found myself backing Traddles into the fire-place, and bowing in great confusion to two dry little elderly ladies, dressed in black, and each looking wonderfully like a preparation in chip or tan of the late Mr. Spenlow.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray,&rdquo; said one of the two little ladies, &ldquo;be seated.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When I had done tumbling over Traddles, and had sat upon something which was not a cat&mdash;my first seat was&mdash;I so far recovered my sight, as to perceive that Mr. Spenlow had evidently been the youngest of the family; that there was a disparity of six or eight years between the two sisters; and that the younger appeared to be the manager of the conference, inasmuch as she had my letter in her hand&mdash;so familiar as it looked to me, and yet so odd!&mdash;and was referring to it through an eye-glass. They were dressed alike, but this sister wore her dress with a more youthful air than the other; and perhaps had a trifle more frill, or tucker, or brooch, or bracelet, or some little thing of that kind, which made her look more lively. They were both upright in their carriage, formal, precise, composed, and quiet. The sister who had not my letter, had her arms crossed on her breast, and resting on each other, like an Idol.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfield, I believe,&rdquo; said the sister who had got my letter, addressing herself to Traddles.</p>
<p>This was a frightful beginning. Traddles had to indicate that I was Mr. Copperfield, and I had to lay claim to myself, and they had to divest themselves of a preconceived opinion that Traddles was Mr. Copperfield, and altogether we were in a nice condition. To improve it, we all distinctly heard Jip give two short barks, and receive another choke.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfield!&rdquo; said the sister with the letter.</p>
<p>I did something&mdash;bowed, I suppose&mdash;and was all attention, when the other sister struck in.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My sister Lavinia,&rdquo; said she, &ldquo;being conversant with matters of this nature, will state what we consider most calculated to promote the happiness of both parties.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I discovered afterwards that Miss Lavinia was an authority in affairs of the heart, by reason of there having anciently existed a certain Mr. Pidger, who played short whist, and was supposed to have been enamoured of her. My private opinion is, that this was entirely a gratuitous assumption, and that Pidger was altogether innocent of any such sentiments&mdash;to which he had never given any sort of expression that I could ever hear of. Both Miss Lavinia and Miss Clarissa had a superstition, however, that he would have declared his passion, if he had not been cut short in his youth (at about sixty) by over-drinking his constitution, and overdoing an attempt to set it right again by swilling Bath water. They had a lurking suspicion even, that he died of secret love; though I must say there was a picture of him in the house with a damask nose, which concealment did not appear to have ever preyed upon.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We will not,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia, &ldquo;enter on the past history of this matter. Our poor brother Francis's death has cancelled that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We had not,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;been in the habit of frequent
<pb n="421" id="p421"/>
association with our brother Francis; but there was no decided division or disunion between us. Francis took his road; we took ours. We considered it conducive to the happiness of all parties that it should be so. And it was so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Each of the sisters leaned a little forward to speak, shook her head after speaking, and became upright again when silent. Miss Clarissa never moved her arms. She sometimes played tunes upon them with her fingers&mdash;minuets and marches I should think&mdash;but never moved them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Our niece's position, or supposed position, is much changed by our brother Francis's death,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia; &ldquo;and therefore we consider our brother's opinions as regarded her position as being changed too. We have no reason to doubt, Mr. Copperfield, that you are a young gentleman possessed of good qualities and honorable character; or that you have an affection&mdash;or are fully persuaded that you have an affection&mdash;for our niece.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I replied, as I usually did whenever I had a chance, that nobody had ever loved anybody else as I loved Dora. Traddles came to my assistance with a confirmatory murmur.</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia was going on to make some rejoinder, when Miss Clarissa, who appeared to be incessantly beset by a desire to refer to her brother Francis, struck in again:</p>
<p>&ldquo;If Dora's mamma,&rdquo; she said, &ldquo;when she married our brother Francis, had at once said that there was not room for the family at the dinner-table, it would have been better for the happiness of all parties.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sister Clarissa,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia. &ldquo;Perhaps we needn't mind that now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sister Lavinia,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;it belongs to the subject. With your branch of the subject, on which alone you are competent to speak, I should not think of interfering. On this branch of the subject I have a voice and an opinion. It would have been better for the happiness of all parties, if Dora's mamma, when she married our brother Francis, had mentioned plainly what her intentions were. We should then have known what we had to expect. We should have said &lsquo;pray do not invite us, at any time;&rsquo; and all possibility of misunderstanding would have been avoided.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When Miss Clarissa had shaken her head, Miss Lavinia resumed: again referring to my letter through her eye-glass. They both had little bright round twinkling eyes, by the way, which were like birds' eyes. They were not unlike birds, altogether; having a sharp, brisk, sudden manner, and a little short, spruce way of adjusting themselves, like canaries.</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia, as I have said, resumed:</p>
<p>&ldquo;You ask permission of my sister Clarissa and myself, Mr. Copperfield, to visit here, as the accepted suitor of our niece.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If our brother Francis,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, breaking out again, if I may call anything so calm a breaking out, &ldquo;wished to surround himself with an atmosphere of Doctors' Commons, and of Doctors' Commons only, what right or desire had we to object? None, I am sure. We have ever been far from wishing to obtrude ourselves on any one. But why not say so? Let our brother Francis and his wife have their society. Let my sister Lavinia and myself have our society. We can find it for ourselves, I hope!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="422" id="p422"/>
<p>As this appeared to be addressed to Traddles and me, both Traddles and I made some sort of reply. Traddles was inaudible. I think I observed, myself, that it was highly creditable to all concerned. I don't in the least know what I meant.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sister Lavinia,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, having now relieved her mind, &ldquo;you can go on, my dear.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia proceeded:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfield, my sister Clarissa and I have been very careful indeed in considering this letter; and we have not considered it without finally showing it to our niece, and discussing it with our niece. We have no doubt that you think you like her very much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Think, ma'am,&rdquo; I rapturously began, &ldquo;oh!&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>But Miss Clarissa giving me a look (just like a sharp canary), as requesting that I would not interrupt the oracle, I begged pardon.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Affection,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia, glancing at her sister for corroboration, which she gave in the form of a little nod to every clause, &ldquo;mature affection, homage, devotion, does not easily express itself. Its voice is low. It is modest and retiring, it lies in ambush, waits and waits. Such is the mature fruit. Sometimes a life glides away, and finds it still ripening in the shade.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Of course I did not understand then that this was an allusion to her supposed experience of the stricken Pidger; but I saw, from the gravity with which Miss Clarissa nodded her head, that great weight was attached to these words.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The light&mdash;for I call them, in comparison with such sentiments, the light&mdash;inclinations of very young people,&rdquo; pursued Miss Lavinia, &ldquo;are dust, compared to rocks. It is owing to the difficulty of knowing whether they are likely to endure or have any real foundation, that my sister Clarissa and myself have been very undecided how to act, Mr. Copperfield, and Mr.&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Traddles,&rdquo; said my friend, finding himself looked at.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg pardon. Of the Inner Temple, I believe?&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, again glancing at my letter.</p>
<p>Traddles said, &ldquo;Exactly so,&rdquo; and became pretty red in the face.</p>
<p>Now, although I had not received any express encouragement as yet, I fancied that I saw in the two little sisters, and particularly in Miss Lavinia, an intensified enjoyment of this new and fruitful subject of domestic interest, a settling down to make the most of it, a disposition to pet it, in which there was a good bright ray of hope. I thought I perceived that Miss Lavinia would have uncommon satisfaction in superintending two young lovers, like Dora and me; and that Miss Clarissa would have hardly less satisfaction in seeing her superintend us, and in chiming in with her own particular department of the subject whenever that impulse was strong upon her. This gave me courage to protest most vehemently that I loved Dora better than I could tell, or any one believe; that all my friends knew how I loved her; that my aunt, Agnes, Traddles, every one who knew me, knew how I loved her, and how earnest my love had made me. For the truth of this, I appealed to Traddles. And Traddles, firing up as if he were plunging into a Parliamentary Debate, really did come out nobly: confirming me in good
<pb n="423" id="p423"/>
round terms, and in a plain sensible practical manner, that evidently made a favorable impression.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I speak, if I may presume to say so, as one who has some little experience of such things,&rdquo; said Traddles, &ldquo;being myself engaged to a young lady&mdash;one of ten, down in Devonshire&mdash;and seeing no probability, at present, of our engagement coming to a termination.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may be able to confirm what I have said, Mr. Traddles,&rdquo; observed Miss Lavinia, evidently taking a new interest in him, &ldquo;of the affection that is modest and retiring; that waits and waits?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Entirely, ma'am,&rdquo; said Traddles.</p>
<p>Miss Clarissa looked at Miss Lavinia, and shook her head gravely. Miss Lavinia looked consciously at Miss Clarissa, and heaved a little sigh.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sister Lavinia,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;take my smelling-bottle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia revived herself with a few whiffs of aromatic vinegar&mdash;Traddles and I looking on with great solicitude the while; and then went on to say, rather faintly:</p>
<p>&ldquo;My sister and myself have been in great doubt, Mr. Traddles, what course we ought to take in reference to the likings, or imaginary likings, of such very young people as your friend Mr. Copperfield, and our niece.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Our brother Francis's child,&rdquo; remarked Miss Clarissa. &ldquo;If our brother Francis's wife had found it convenient in her life-time (though she had an unquestionable right to act as she thought best) to invite the family to her dinner-table, we might have known our brother Francis's child better at the present moment. Sister Lavinia, proceed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia turned my letter, so as to bring the superscription towards herself, and referred through her eye-glass to some orderly-looking notes she had made on that part of it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It seems to us,&rdquo; said she, &ldquo;prudent, Mr. Traddles, to bring these feelings to the test of our own observation. At present we know nothing of them, and are not in a situation to judge how much reality there may be in them. Therefore we are inclined so far to accede to Mr. Copperfield's proposal, as to admit his visits here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall never, dear ladies,&rdquo; I exclaimed, relieved of an immense load of apprehension, &ldquo;forget your kindness!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But,&rdquo; pursued Miss Lavinia,&mdash;&ldquo;but, we would prefer to regard those visits, Mr. Traddles, as made, at present, to us. We must guard ourselves from recognising any positive engagement between Mr. Copperfield and our niece, until we have had an opportunity&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Until <hi rend="italics">you</hi> have had an opportunity, sister Lavinia,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Be it so,&rdquo; assented Miss Lavinia, with a sigh,&mdash;&ldquo;until I have had an opportunity of observing them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; said Traddles, turning to me, &ldquo;you feel, I am sure, that nothing could be more reasonable or considerate.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing!&rdquo; cried I. &ldquo;I am deeply sensible of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In this position of affairs,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia, again referring to her notes, &ldquo;and admitting his visits on this understanding only, we must require from Mr. Copperfield a distinct assurance, on his word of honor, that no communication of any kind shall take place between him and our niece without our knowledge. That no project whatever shall be entertained with regard to our niece, without being first submitted to us&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="424" id="p424"/>
<p>&ldquo;To you, sister Lavinia,&rdquo; Miss Clarissa interposed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Be it so, Clarissa!&rdquo; assented Miss Lavinia resignedly&mdash;&ldquo;to me&mdash;and receiving our concurrence. We must make this a most express and serious stipulation, not to be broken on any account. We wished Mr. Copperfield to be accompanied by some confidential friend to-day,&rdquo; with an inclination of her head towards Traddles, who bowed, &ldquo;in order that there might be no doubt or misconception on this subject. If Mr. Copperfield, or if you, Mr. Traddles, feel the least scruple, in giving this promise, I beg you to take time to consider it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I exclaimed, in a state of high ecstatic fervor, that not a moment's consideration could be necessary. I bound myself by the required promise, in a most impassioned manner; called upon Traddles to witness it; and denounced myself as the most atrocious of characters if I ever swerved from it in the least degree.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stay!&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia, holding up her hand; &ldquo;we resolved, before we had the pleasure of receiving you two gentlemen, to leave you alone for a quarter of an hour, to consider this point. You will allow us to retire.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was in vain for me to say that no consideration was necessary. They persisted in withdrawing for the specified time. Accordingly, these little birds hopped out with great dignity; leaving me to receive the congratulations of Traddles, and to feel as if I were translated to regions of exquisite happiness. Exactly at the expiration of the quarter of an hour, they reappeared with no less dignity than they had disappeared. They had gone rustling away as if their little dresses were made of autumn-leaves: and they came rustling back, in like manner.</p>
<p>I then bound myself once more to the prescribed conditions.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sister Clarissa,&rdquo; said Miss Lavinia, &ldquo;the rest is with you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Clarissa, unfolding her arms for the first time, took the notes and glanced at them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We shall be happy,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;to see Mr. Copperfield to dinner, every Sunday, if it should suit his convenience. Our hour is three.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I bowed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the course of the week,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;we shall be happy to see Mr. Copperfield to tea. Our hour is half-past six.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I bowed again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Twice in the week,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;but, as a rule, not oftener.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I bowed again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Trotwood,&rdquo; said Miss Clarissa, &ldquo;mentioned in Mr. Copperfield's letter, will perhaps call upon us. When visiting is better for the happiness of all parties, we are glad to receive visits, and return them. When it is better for the happiness of all parties that no visiting should take place, (as in the case of our brother Francis, and his establishment) that is quite different.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I intimated that my aunt would be proud and delighted to make their acquaintance; though I must say I was not quite sure of their getting on very satisfactorily together. The conditions being now closed, I expressed my acknowledgments in the warmest manner; and, taking the hand, first of Miss Clarissa, and then of Miss Lavinia, pressed it, in each case, to my lips.</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia then arose, and begging Mr. Traddles to excuse us for a
<pb n="425" id="p425"/>
minute, requested me to follow her. I obeyed, all in a tremble, and was conducted into another room. There, I found my blessed darling stopping her ears behind the door, with her dear little face against the wall; and Jip in the plate-warmer with his head tied up in a towel.</p>
<p>Oh! How beautiful she was in her black frock, and how she sobbed and cried at first, and wouldn't come out from behind the door! How fond we were of one another, when she did come out at last; and what a state of bliss I was in, when we took Jip out of the plate-warmer, and restored him to the light, sneezing very much, and were all three reunited!</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dearest Dora! Now, indeed, my own for ever!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh DON'T!&rdquo; pleaded Dora. &ldquo;Please!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are you not my own for ever, Dora?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes, of course I am!&rdquo; cried Dora, &ldquo;but I am so frightened!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Frightened, my own?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes! I don't like him,&rdquo; said Dora. &ldquo;Why don't he go?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who, my life?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your friend,&rdquo; said Dora. &ldquo;It isn't any business of his. What a stupid he must be!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My love!&rdquo; (There never was anything so coaxing as her childish ways.) &ldquo;He is the best creature!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, but we don't want any best creatures!&rdquo; pouted Dora.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; I argued, &ldquo;you will soon know him well, and like him of all things. And here is my aunt coming soon; and you'll like her of all things too, when you know her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, please don't bring her!&rdquo; said Dora, giving me a horrified little kiss, and folding her hands. &ldquo;Don't. I know she's a naughty, mischief-making old thing! Don't let her come here, Doady!&rdquo; which was a corruption of David.</p>
<p>Remonstrance was of no use, then; so I laughed, and admired, and was very much in love and very happy; and she showed me Jip's new trick of standing on his hind legs in a corner&mdash;which he did for about the space of a flash of lightning, and then fell down&mdash;and I don't know how long I should have stayed there, oblivious of Traddles, if Miss Lavinia had not come in to take me away. Miss Lavinia was very fond of Dora (she told me Dora was exactly like what she had been herself at her age&mdash;she must have altered a good deal), and she treated Dora just as if she had been a toy. I wanted to persuade Dora to come and see Traddles, but on my proposing it she ran off to her own room and locked herself in; so I went to Traddles without her, and walked away with him on air.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing could be more satisfactory,&rdquo; said Traddles; &ldquo;and they are very agreeable old ladies, I am sure. I shouldn't be at all surprised if you were to be married years before me, Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does your Sophy play on any instrument, Traddles?&rdquo; I enquired, in the pride of my heart.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She knows enough of the piano to teach it to her little sisters,&rdquo; said Traddles.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does she sing at all?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, she sings ballads, sometimes, to freshen up the others a little when they're out of spirits,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;Nothing scientific.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She doesn't sing to the guitar?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<pb n="426" id="p426"/>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear no!&rdquo; said Traddles.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Paint at all?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all,&rdquo; said Traddles.</p>
<p>I promised Traddles that he should hear Dora sing, and see some of her flower-painting. He said he should like it very much, and we went home arm in arm in great good humour and delight. I encouraged him to talk about Sophy, on the way; which he did with a loving reliance on her that I very much admired. I compared her in my mind with Dora, with considerable inward satisfaction; but I candidly admitted to myself that she seemed to be an excellent kind of girl for Traddles, too.</p>
<p>Of course my aunt was immediately made acquainted with the successful issue of the conference, and with all that had been said and done in the course of it. She was happy to see me so happy, and promised to call on Dora's aunts without loss of time. But she took such a long walk up and down our rooms that night, while I was writing to Agnes, that I began to think she meant to walk till morning.</p>
<p>My letter to Agnes was a fervent and grateful one, narrating all the good effects that had resulted from my following her advice. She wrote, by return of post, to me. Her letter was hopeful, earnest, and cheerful. She was always cheerful from that time.</p>
<p>I had my hands more full than ever, now. My daily journies to Highgate considered, Putney was a long way off; and I naturally wanted to go there as often as I could. The proposed tea-drinkings being quite impracticable, I compounded with Miss Lavinia for permission to visit every Saturday afternoon, without detriment to my privileged Sundays. So, the close of every week was a delicious time for me; and I got through the rest of the week by looking forward to it.</p>
<p>I was wonderfully relieved to find that my aunt and Dora's aunts rubbed on, all things considered, much more smoothly than I could have expected. My aunt made her promised visit within a few days of the conference; and within a few more days, Dora's aunts called upon her, in due state and form. Similar but more friendly exchanges took place afterwards, usually at intervals of three or four weeks. I know that my aunt distressed Dora's aunts very much, by utterly setting at naught the dignity of fly-conveyance, and walking out to Putney at extraordinary times, as shortly after breakfast or just before tea; likewise by wearing her bonnet in any manner that happened to be comfortable to her head, without at all deferring to the prejudices of civilisation on that subject. But Dora's aunts soon agreed to regard my aunt as an eccentric and somewhat masculine lady, with a strong understanding; and although my aunt occasionally ruffled the feathers of Dora's aunts, by expressing heretical opinions on various points of ceremony, she loved me too well not to sacrifice some of her little peculiarities to the general harmony.</p>
<p>The only member of our small society, who positively refused to adapt himself to circumstances, was Jip. He never saw my aunt without immediately displaying every tooth in his head, retiring under a chair, and growling incessantly: with now and then a doleful howl, as if she really were too much for his feelings. All kinds of treatment were tried with him, coaxing, scolding, slapping, bringing him to Buckingham Street (where he instantly dashed at the two cats, to the terror of all beholders);
<pb n="427" id="p427"/>
but he never could prevail upon himself to bear my aunt's society. He would sometimes think he had got the better of his objection, and be amiable for a few minutes; and then would put up his snub nose, and howl to that extent, that there was nothing for it but to blind him and put him in the plate-warmer. At length, Dora regularly muffled him in a towel and shut him up there, whenever my aunt was reported at the door.</p>
<p>One thing troubled me much, after we had fallen into this quiet train. It was, that Dora seemed by one consent to be regarded like a pretty toy or plaything. My aunt, with whom she gradually became familiar, always called her Little Blossom; and the pleasure of Miss Lavinia's life was to wait upon her, curl her hair, make ornaments for her, and treat her like a pet child. What Miss Lavinia did, her sister did as a matter of course. It was very odd to me; but they all seemed to treat Dora, in her degree, much as Dora treated Jip in his.</p>
<p>I made up my mind to speak to Dora about this; and one day when we were out walking (for we were licensed by Miss Lavinia, after a while, to go out walking by ourselves), I said to her that I wished she could get them to behave towards her differently.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because you know, my darling,&rdquo; I remonstrated, &ldquo;you are not a child.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There!&rdquo; said Dora. &ldquo;Now you're going to be cross!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cross, my love?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure they're very kind to me,&rdquo; said Dora, &ldquo;and I am very happy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well! But my dearest life!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;you might be very happy, and yet be treated rationally.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dora gave me a reproachful look&mdash;the prettiest look!&mdash;and then began to sob, saying if I didn't like her, why had I ever wanted so much to be engaged to her? And why didn't I go away, now, if I couldn't bear her?</p>
<p>What could I do, but kiss away her tears, and tell her how I doted on her, after that!</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure I am very affectionate,&rdquo; said Dora; &ldquo;you oughtn't to be cruel to me, Doady!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cruel, my precious love! As if I would&mdash;or could&mdash;be cruel to you, for the world!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then don't find fault with me,&rdquo; said Dora, making a rosebud of her mouth; &ldquo;and I'll be good.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was charmed by her presently asking me, of her own accord, to give her that cookery-book I had once spoken of, and to show her how to keep accounts as I had once promised I would. I brought the volume with me on my next visit (I got it prettily bound, first, to make it look less dry and more inviting); and as we strolled about the Common, I showed her and old housekeeping-book of my aunt's, and gave her a set of tablets, and a pretty little pencil case and box of leads, to practise house-keeping with.</p>
<p>But the cookery-book made Dora's head ache, and the figures made her cry. They wouldn't add up, she said. So she rubbed them out, and drew little nosegays, and likenesses of me and Jip, all over the tablets.</p>
<pb n="428" id="p428"/>
<p>Then I playfully tried verbal instruction in domestic matters, as we walked about on a Saturday afternoon. Sometimes, for example, when we passed a butcher's shop, I would say:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now suppose, my pet, that we were married, and you were going to buy a shoulder of mutton for dinner, would you know how to buy it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>My pretty little Dora's face would fall, and she would make her mouth into a bud again, as if she would very much prefer to shut mine with a kiss.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Would you know how to buy it, my darling?&rdquo; I would repeat, perhaps, if I were very inflexible.</p>
<p>Dora would think a little, and then reply, perhaps, with great triumph:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, the butcher would know how to sell it, and what need <hi rend="italics">I</hi> know? Oh, you silly boy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>So, when I once asked Dora, with an eye to the cookery-book, what she would do, if we were married, and I were to say I should like a nice Irish stew, she replied that she would tell the servant to make it; and then clapped her little hands together across my arm, and laughed in such a charming manner that she was more delightful than ever.</p>
<p>Consequently, the principal use to which the cookery-book was devoted, was being put down in the corner for Jip to stand upon. But Dora was so pleased, when she had trained him to stand upon it without offering to come off, and at the same time to hold the pencil case in his mouth, that I was very glad I had bought it.</p>
<p>And we fell back on the guitar-case, and the flower-painting, and the songs about never leaving off dancing, Ta ra la! and were as happy as the week was long. I occasionally wished I could venture to hint to Miss Lavinia, that she treated the darling of my heart a little too much like a plaything; and I sometimes awoke, as it were, wondering to find that I had fallen into the general fault, and treated her like a plaything too&mdash;but not often.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XLII. <lb/> MISCHIEF.</head>
<p>I FEEL as if it were not for me to record, even though this manuscript is intended for no eyes but mine, how hard I worked at that tremendous short-hand, and all improvement appertaining to it, in my sense of responsibility to Dora and her aunts. I will only add, to what I have already written of my perseverance at this time of my life, and of a patient and continuous energy which then began to be matured within me, and which I know to be the strong part of my character, if it have any strength at all, that there, on looking back, I find the source of my success. I have been very fortunate in worldly matters; many men have worked much harder, and not succeeded half so well; but I never could have done what I have done, without the habits of punctuality, order, and diligence, without the determination to concentrate myself on one object at a time, no matter how quickly its successor should come upon its heels, which I then formed. Heaven knows I write this, in no spirit of self-laudation.
<pb n="429" id="p429"/>
The man who reviews his own life, as I do mine, in going on here, from page to page, had need to have been a good man indeed, if he would be spared the sharp consciousness of many talents neglected, many opportunities wasted, many erratic and perverted feelings constantly at war within his breast, and defeating him. I do not hold one natural gift, I dare say, that I have not abused. My meaning simply is, that whatever I have tried to do in life, I have tried with all my heart to do well; that whatever I have devoted myself to, I have devoted myself to completely; that, in great aims and in small, I have always been thoroughly in earnest. I have never believed it possible that any natural or improved ability can claim immunity from the companionship of the steady, plain, hardworking qualities, and hope to gain its end. There is no such thing as such fulfilment on this earth. Some happy talent, and some fortunate opportunity, may form the two sides of the ladder on which some men mount, but the rounds of that ladder must be made of stuff to stand wear and tear; and there is no substitute for thorough-going, ardent, and sincere earnestness. Never to put one hand to anything, on which I could throw my whole self; and never to affect depreciation of my work, whatever it was; I find, now, to have been my golden rules.</p>
<p>How much of the practice I have just reduced to precept, I owe to Agnes, I will not repeat here. My narrative proceeds to Agnes, with a thankful love.</p>
<p>She came on a visit of a fortnight to the Doctor's. Mr. Wickfield was the Doctor's old friend, and the Doctor wished to talk with him, and do him good. It had been matter of conversation with Agnes when she was last in town, and this visit was the result. She and her father came together. I was not much surprised to hear from her that she had engaged to find a lodging in the neighbourhood for Mrs. Heep, whose rheumatic complaint required change of air, and who would be charmed to have it in such company. Neither was I surprised when, on the very next day, Uriah, like a dutiful son, brought his worthy mother to take possession.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You see, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said he, as he forced himself upon my company for a turn in the Doctor's garden, &ldquo;where a person loves, a person is a little jealous&mdash;leastways, anxions to keep an eye on the beloved one.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of whom are you jealous, now?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thanks to you, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he returned, &ldquo;of no one in particular just at present&mdash;no male person, at least.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you mean that you are jealous of a female person?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He gave me a sidelong glance out of his sinister red eyes, and laughed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;&mdash;I should say Mister, but I know you'll excuse the abit I've got into&mdash;you're so insinuating, that you draw me like a corkscrew! Well, I don't mind telling you,&rdquo; putting his fish-like hand on mine, &ldquo;I'm not a lady's man in general, sir, and I never was, with Mrs. Strong.&rdquo;</p>
<p>His eyes looked green now, as they watched mine with a rascally cunning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you mean?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, though I am a lawyer, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he replied, with a dry grin, &ldquo;I mean, just at present, what I say.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="430" id="p430"/>
<p>&ldquo;And what do you mean by your look?&rdquo; I retorted, quietly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By my look? Dear me, Copperfield, that's sharp practice! What do I mean by my look?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;By your look.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He seemed very much amused, and laughed as heartily as it was in his nature to laugh. After some scraping of his chin with his hand, he went on to say, with his eyes cast downward&mdash;still scraping, very slowly:</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I was but a numble clerk, she always looked down upon me. She was for ever having my Agnes backwards and forwards at her ouse, and she was for ever being a friend to you, Master Copperfield; but I was too far beneath her, myself, to be noticed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well?&rdquo; said I; &ldquo;suppose you were!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash;And beneath him, too,&rdquo; pursued Uriah, very distinctly, and in a meditative tone of voice, as he continued to scrape his chin.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you know the Doctor better,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;than to suppose him conscious of your existence, when you were not before him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He directed his eyes at me in that sidelong glance again, and he made his face very lantern-jawed, for the greater convenience of scraping, as he answered:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear, I am not referring to the Doctor! Oh no, poor man! I mean Mr. Maldon!&rdquo;</p>
<p>My heart quite died within me. All my old doubts and apprehensions on that subject, all the Doctor's happiness and peace, all the mingled possibilities of innocence and compromise, that I could not unravel, I saw, in a moment, at the mercy of this fellow's twisting.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He never could come into the office, without ordering and shoving me about,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;One of your fine gentlemen he was! I was very meek and umble&mdash;and I am. But I didn't like that sort of thing&mdash;and I don't!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He left off scraping his chin, and sucked in his cheeks until they seemed to meet inside; keeping his sidelong glance upon me all the while.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is one of your lovely women, she is,&rdquo; he pursued, when he had slowly restored his face to its natural form; &ldquo;and ready to be no friend to such as me, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> know. She's just the person as would put my Agnes up to higher sort of game. Now, I ain't one of your lady's men, Master Copperfield; but I've had eyes in my ed, a pretty long time back. We umble ones have got eyes, mostly speaking&mdash;and we look out of 'em.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I endeavoured to appear unconscious and not disquieted, but, I saw in his face, with poor success.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I'm not a going to let myself be run down, Copperfield,&rdquo; he continued, raising that part of his countenance where his red eyebrows would have been if he had had any, with malignant triumph, &ldquo;and I shall do what I can to put a stop to this friendship. I don't approve of it. I don't mind acknowledging to you that I've got rather a grudging disposition, and want to keep off all intruders. I ain't a going, if I know it, to run the risk of being plotted against.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are always plotting, and delude yourself into the belief that everybody else is doing the like, I think,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps so, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he replied. &ldquo;But I've got a motive, as my fellow-partner used to say; and I go at it tooth and nail. I
<pb n="431" id="p431"/>
mustn't be put upon, as a numble person, too much. I can't allow people in my way. Really they must come out of the cart, Master Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't understand you,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you, though?&rdquo; he returned, with one of his jerks. &ldquo;I'm astonished at that, Master Copperfield, you being usually so quick! I'll try to be plainer, another time.&mdash;Is that Mr. Maldon a-norseback, ringing at the gate, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It looks like him,&rdquo; I replied, as carelessly as I could.</p>
<p>Uriah stopped short, put his hands between his great knobs of knees, and doubled himself up with laughter. With perfectly silent laughter. Not a sound escaped from him. I was so repelled by his odious behaviour, particularly by this concluding instance, that I turned away without any ceremony; and left him doubled up in the middle of the garden, like a scarecrow in want of support.</p>
<p>It was not on that evening; but, as I well remember, on the next evening but one, which was a Saturday; that I took Agnes to see Dora. I had arranged the visit, beforehand, with Miss Lavinia; and Agnes was expected to tea.</p>
<p>I was in a flutter of pride and anxiety; pride in my dear little betrothed, and anxiety that Agnes should like her. All the way to Putney, Agnes being inside the stage-coach, and I outside, I pictured Dora to myself in every one of the pretty looks I knew so well; now making up my mind that I should like her to look exactly as she looked at such a time, and then doubting whether I should not prefer her looking as she looked at such another time; and almost worrying myself into a fever about it.</p>
<p>I was troubled by no doubt of her being very pretty, in any case; but it fell out that I had never seen her look so well. She was not in the drawing-room when I presented Agnes to her little aunts, but was shyly keeping out of the way. I knew where to look for her, now; and sure enough I found her stopping her cars again, behind the same dull old door.</p>
<p>At first she wouldn't come at all; and then she pleaded for five minutes by my watch. When at length she put her arm through mine, to be taken to the drawing-room, her charming little face was flushed, and had never been so pretty. But, when we went into the room, and it turned pale, she was ten thousand times prettier yet.</p>
<p>Dora was afraid of Agnes. She had told me that she knew Agnes was &ldquo;too clever.&rdquo; But when she saw her looking at once so cheerful and so earnest, and so thoughtful, and so good, she gave a faint little cry of pleased surprise, and just put her affectionate arms round Agnes's neck, and laid her innocent cheek against her face.</p>
<p>I never was so happy. I never was so pleased as when I saw those two sit down together, side by side. As when I saw my little darling looking up so naturally to those cordial eyes. As when I saw the tender, beautiful regard which Agnes cast upon her.</p>
<p>Miss Lavinia and Miss Clarissa partook, in their way, of my joy. It was the pleasantest tea-table in the world. Miss Clarissa presided. I cut and handed the sweet seed-cake&mdash;the little sisters had a bird-like fondness for picking up seeds and pecking at sugar; Miss Lavinia looked on with
<pb n="432" id="p432"/>
benignant patronage, as if our happy love were all her work; and we were perfectly contented with ourselves and one another.</p>
<p>The gentle cheerfulness of Agnes went to all their hearts. Her quiet interest in everything that interested Dora; her manner of making acquaintance with Jip (who responded instantly); her pleasant way, when Dora was ashamed to come over to her usual seat by me; her modest grace and ease, eliciting a crowd of blushing little marks of confidence from Dora; seemed to make our circle quite complete.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am so glad,&rdquo; said Dora, after tea, &ldquo;that you like me. I didn't think you would; and I want, more than ever, to be liked, now Julia Mills is gone.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have omitted to mention it, by-the-bye. Miss Mills had sailed, and Dora and I had gone aboard a great East Indiaman at Gravesend to see her; and we had had preserved ginger, and guava, and other delicacies of that sort for lunch; and we had left Miss Mills weeping on a camp-stool on the quarter-deck, with a large new diary under her arm, in which the original reflections awakened by the contemplation of Ocean were to be recorded under lock and key.</p>
<p>Agnes said, she was afraid I must have given her an unpromising character; but Dora corrected that directly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh no!&rdquo; she said, shaking her curls at me; &ldquo;it was all praise. He thinks so much of your opinion, that I was quite afraid of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My good opinion cannot strengthen his attachment to some people whom he knows,&rdquo; said Agnes, with a smile; &ldquo;it is not worth their having.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But please let me have it,&rdquo; said Dora, in her coaxing way, &ldquo;if you can!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We made merry about Dora's wanting to be liked, and Dora said I was a goose, and she didn't like me at any rate, and the short evening flew away on gossamer-wings. The time was at hand when the coach was to call for us. I was standing alone before the fire, when Dora came stealing softly in, to give me that usual precious little kiss before I went.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you think, if I had had her for a friend a long time ago, Doady,&rdquo; said Dora, her bright eyes shining very brightly, and her little right hand idly busying itself with one of the buttons of my coat, &ldquo;I might have been more clever perhaps?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My love!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;what nonsense!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think it is nonsense?&rdquo; returned Dora, without looking at me. &ldquo;Are you sure it is?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course I am!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have forgotten,&rdquo; said Dora, still turning the button round and round, &ldquo;what relation Agnes is to you, you dear bad boy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No blood-relation,&rdquo; I replied; &ldquo;but we were brought up together, like brother and sister.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wonder why you ever fell in love with me?&rdquo; said Dora, beginning on another button of my coat.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps because I couldn't see you, and not love you, Dora!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Suppose you had never seen me at all,&rdquo; said Dora, going to another button.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Suppose we had never been born!&rdquo; said I, gaily.</p>
<pb n="433" id="p433"/>
<p>I wondered what she was thinking about, as I glanced in admiring silence at the little soft hand travelling up the row of buttons on my coat, and at the clustering hair that lay against my breast, and at the lashes of her downcast eyes, slightly rising as they followed her idle fingers. At length her eyes were lifted up to mine, and she stood on tiptoe to give me, more thoughtfully than usual, that precious little kiss&mdash;once, twice, three times&mdash;and went out of the room.</p>
<p>They all came back together within five minutes afterwards, and Dora's unusual thoughtfulness was quite gone then. She was laughingly resolved to put Jip through the whole of his performances, before the coach came. They took some time (not so much on account of their variety, as Jip's reluctance), and were still unfinished when it was heard at the door. There was a hurried but affectionate parting between Agnes and herself; and Dora was to write to Agnes (who was not to mind her letters being foolish, she said), and Agnes was to write to Dora; and they had a second parting at the coach-door, and a third when Dora, in spite of the remonstrances of Miss Lavinia, would come running out once more to remind Agnes at the coach-window about writing, and to shake her curls at me on the box.</p>
<p>The stage-coach was to put us down near Covent Garden, where we were to take another stage-coach for Highgate. I was impatient for the short walk in the interval, that Agnes might praise Dora to me. Ah! what praise it was! How lovingly and fervently did it commend the pretty creature I had won, with all her artless graces best displayed, to my most gentle care! How thoughtfully remind me, yet with no pretence of doing so, of the trust in which I held the orphan child!</p>
<p>Never, never, had I loved Dora so deeply and truly, as I loved her that night. When we had again alighted, and were walking in the starlight along the quiet road that led to the Doctor's house, I told Agnes it was her doing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When you were sitting by her,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;you seemed to be no less <hi rend="italics">her</hi> guardian angel than mine; and you seem so now, Agnes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A poor angel,&rdquo; she returned, &ldquo;but faithful.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The clear tone of her voice, going straight to my heart, made it natural to me to say:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The cheerfulness that belongs to you, Agnes (and to no one else that ever I have seen), is so restored, I have observed to-day, that I have begun to hope you are happier at home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am happier in myself,&rdquo; she said; &ldquo;I am quite cheerful and light-hearted.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I glanced at the serene face looking upward, and thought it was the stars that made it seem so noble.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There has been no change at home,&rdquo; said Agnes, after a few moments.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No fresh reference,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;to&mdash;I wouldn't distress you, Agnes, but I cannot help asking&mdash;to what we spoke of, when we parted last?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, none,&rdquo; she answered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have thought so much about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You must think less about it. Remember that I confide in simple love and truth at last. Have no apprehensions for me, Trotwood,&rdquo; she added, after a moment; &ldquo;the step you dread my taking, I shall never take.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Although I think I had never really feared it, in any season of cool
<pb n="434" id="p434"/>
reflection, it was an unspeakable relief to me to have this assurance from her own truthful lips. I told her so, earnestly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And when this visit is over,&rdquo; said I,&mdash;&ldquo;for we may not be alone another time,&mdash;how long is it likely to be, my dear Agnes, before you come to London again?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Probably a long time,&rdquo; she replied; &ldquo;I think it will be best&mdash;for papa's sake&mdash;to remain at home. We are not likely to meet often, for some time to come; but I shall be a good correspondent of Dora's, and we shall frequently hear of one another that way.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We were now within the little court-yard of the Doctor's cottage. It was growing late. There was a light in the window of Mrs. Strong's chamber, and Agnes, pointing to it, bade me good night.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do not be troubled,&rdquo; she said, giving me her hand, &ldquo;by our misfortunes and anxieties. I can be happier in nothing than in your happiness. If you can ever give me help, rely upon it I will ask you for it. God bless you always!&rdquo;</p>
<p>In her beaming smile, and in these last tones of her cheerful voice, I seemed again to see and hear my little Dora in her company. I stood awhile, looking through the porch at the stars, with a heart full of love and gratitude, and then walked slowly forth. I had engaged a bed at a decent alehouse close by, and was going out at the gate, when, happening to turn my head, I saw a light in the Doctor's study. A half-reproachful fancy came into my mind, that he had been working at the Dictionary without my help. With the view of seeing if this were so, and, in any case, of bidding him good night, if he were yet sitting among his books, I turned back, and going softly across the hall, and gently opening the door, looked in.</p>
<p>The first person whom I saw, to my surprise, by the sober light of the shaded lamp, was Uriah. He was standing close beside it, with one of his skeleton hands over his mouth, and the other resting on the Doctor's table. The Doctor sat in his study chair, covering his face with his hands. Mr. Wickfield, sorely troubled and distressed, was leaning forward, irresolutely touching the Doctor's arm.</p>
<p>For an instant, I supposed that the Doctor was ill. I hastily advanced a step under that impression, when I met Uriah's eye, and saw what was the matter. I would have withdrawn, but the Doctor made a gesture to detain me, and I remained.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At any rate,&rdquo; observed Uriah, with a writhe of his ungainly person, &ldquo;we may keep the door shut. We needn't make it known to ALL the town.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Saying which, he went on his toes to the door, which I had left open, and carefully closed it. He then came back, and took up his former position. There was an obtrusive show of compassionate zeal in his voice and manner, more intolerable&mdash;at least to me&mdash;than any demeanour he could have assumed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have felt it incumbent upon me, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah, &ldquo;to point out to Doctor Strong what you and me have already talked about. You didn't exactly understand me, though?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I gave him a look, but no other answer; and, going to my good old master, said a few words that I meant to be words of comfort and encouragement.
<pb n="435" id="p435"/>
He put his hand upon my shoulder, as it had been his custom to do when I was quite a little fellow, but did not lift his grey head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As you didn't understand me, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; resumed Uriah in the same officious manner, &ldquo;I may take the liberty of umbly mentioning, being among friends, that I have called Doctor Strong's attention to the goings-on of Mrs. Strong. It's much against the grain with me, I assure you, Copperfield, to be concerned in anything so unpleasant; but really, as it is, we're all mixing ourselves up with what oughtn't to be. That was what my meaning was, sir, when you didn't understand me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I wonder now, when I recall his leer, that I did not collar him, and try to shake the breath out of his body.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I dare say I didn't make myself very clear,&rdquo; he went on, &ldquo;nor you neither. Naturally, we was both of us inclined to give such a subject a wide berth. Hows'ever, at last I have made up my mind to speak plain; and I have mentioned to Doctor Strong that&mdash;did you speak, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was to the Doctor, who had moaned. The sound might have touched any heart, I thought, but it had no effect upon Uriah's.</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash; mentioned to Doctor Strong,&rdquo; he proceeded, &ldquo;that any one may see that Mr. Maldon, and the lovely and agreeable lady as is Doctor Strong's wife, are too sweet on one another. Really the time is come (we being at present all mixing ourselves up with what oughtn't to be), when Doctor Strong must be told that this was full as plain to everybody as the sun, before Mr. Maldon went to India; that Mr. Maldon made excuses to come back, for nothing else; and that he's always here, for nothing else. When you come in, sir, I was just putting it to my fellow-partner,&rdquo; towards whom he turned, &ldquo;to say to Doctor Strong upon his word and honor, whether he'd ever been of this opinion long ago, or not. Come, Mr. Wickfield, sir! Would you be so good as tell us? Yes or no, sir? Come, partner!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For God's sake, my dear Doctor,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, again laying his irresolute hand upon the Doctor's arm, &ldquo;don't attach too much weight to any suspicions I may have entertained.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There!&rdquo; cried Uriah, shaking his head. &ldquo;What a melancholy confirmation: ain't it? Him! Such an old friend! Bless your soul, when I was nothing but a clerk in his office, Copperfield, I've seen him twenty times, if I've seen him once, quite in a taking about it&mdash;quite put out, you know (and very proper in him as a father; I'm sure <hi rend="italics">I</hi> can't blame him), to think that Miss Agnes was mixing herself up with what oughtn't to be.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Strong,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield in a tremulous voice, &ldquo;my good friend, I needn't tell you that it has been my vice to look for some one master motive in everybody, and to try all actions by one narrow test. I may have fallen into such doubts as I have had, through this mistake.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have had doubts, Wickfield,&rdquo; said the Doctor, without lifting up his head. &ldquo;You have had doubts.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Speak up, fellow-partner,&rdquo; urged Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I had, at one time, certainly,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;I&mdash;God forgive me&mdash;I thought <hi rend="italics">you</hi> had.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, no!&rdquo; returned the Doctor, in a tone of most pathetic grief.</p>
<pb n="436" id="p436"/>
<p>&ldquo;I thought, at one time,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, &ldquo;that you wished to send Maldon abroad to effect a desirable separation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, no!&rdquo; returned the Doctor. &ldquo;To give Annie pleasure, by making some provision for the companion of her childhood. Nothing else.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So I found,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield. &ldquo;I couldn't doubt it, when you told me so. But I thought&mdash;I implore you to remember the narrow construction which has been my besetting sin&mdash;that, in a case where there was so much disparity in point of years&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the way to put it, you see, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; observed Uriah, with fawning and offensive pity.</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash; a lady of such youth, and such attractions, however real her respect for you, might have been influenced in marrying, by worldly considerations only. I made no allowance for innumerable feelings and circumstances that may have all tended to good. For Heaven's sake remember that!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How kind he puts it!&rdquo; said Uriah, shaking his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Always observing her from one point of view,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield; &ldquo;but by all that is dear to you, my old friend, I entreat you to consider what it was; I am forced to confess now, having no escape&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No! There's no way out of it, Mr. Wickfield, sir,&rdquo; observed Uriah, &ldquo;when it's got to this.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash; that I did,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, glancing helplessly and distractedly at his partner, &ldquo;that I did doubt her, and think her wanting in her duty to you; and that I did sometimes, if I must say all, feel averse to Agnes being in such a familiar relation towards her, as to see what I saw, or in my diseased theory fancied that I saw. I never mentioned this to any one. I never meant it to be known to any one. And though it is terrible to you to hear,&rdquo; said Mr. Wickfield, quite subdued, &ldquo;if you knew how terrible it is to me to tell, you would feel compassion for me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Doctor, in the perfect goodness of his nature, put out his hand. Mr. Wickfield held it for a little while in his, with his head bowed down.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sure,&rdquo; said Uriah, writhing himself into the silence like a Conger-eel, &ldquo;that this is a subject full of unpleasantness to everybody. But since we have got so far, I ought to take the liberty of mentioning that Copperfield has noticed it too.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I turned upon him, and asked him how he dared refer to me!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! it's very kind of you, Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Uriah, undulating all over, &ldquo;and we all know what an amiable character yours is; but you know that the moment I spoke to you the other night, you knew what I meant. You know you knew what I meant, Copperfield. Don't deny it! You deny it with the best intentions; but don't do it, Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I saw the mild eye of the good old Doctor turned upon me for a moment, and I felt that the confession of my old misgivings and remembrances was too plainly written in my face to be overlooked. It was of no use raging. I could not undo that. Say what I would, I could not unsay it.</p>
<p>We were silent again, and remained so, until the Doctor rose and
<pb n="437" id="p437"/>
walked twice or thrice across the room. Presently he returned to where his chair stood; and, leaning on the back of it, and occasionally putting his handkerchief to his eyes, with a simple honesty that did him more honor, to my thinking, than any disguise he could have affected, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been much to blame. I believe I have been very much to blame. I have exposed one whom I hold in my heart, to trials and &lsquo;aspersions&mdash;I call them aspersions, even to have been conceived in anybody's inmost mind&mdash;of which she never, but for me, could have been the object.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Uriah Heep gave a kind of snivel. I think to express sympathy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of which my Annie,&rdquo; said the Doctor, &ldquo;never, but for me, could have been the object. Gentlemen, I am old now, as you know; I do not feel, to-night, that I have much to live for. But my life&mdash;my Life&mdash;upon the truth and honor of the dear lady who has been the subject of this conversation!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I do not think that the best embodiment of chivalry, the realisation of the handsomest and most romantic figure ever imagined by painter, could have said this, with a more impressive and affecting dignity than the plain old Doctor did.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But I am not prepared,&rdquo; he went on, &ldquo;to deny&mdash;perhaps I may have been, without knowing it, in some degree prepared to admit&mdash;that I may have unwittingly ensnared that lady into an unhappy marriage. I am a man quite unaccustomed to observe; and I cannot but believe that the observation of several people, of different ages and positions, all too plainly tending in one direction (and that so natural), is better than mine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I had often admired, as I have elsewhere described, his benignant manner towards his youthful wife; but the respectful tenderness he manifested in every reference to her on this occasion, and the almost reverential manner in which he put away from him the lightest doubt of her integrity, exalted him, in my eyes, beyond description.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I married that lady,&rdquo; said the Doctor, &ldquo;when she was extremely young. I took her to myself when her character was scarcely formed. So far as it was developed, it had been my happiness to form it. I knew her father well. I knew her well. I had taught her what I could, for the love of all her beautiful and virtuous qualities. If I did her wrong; as I fear I did, in taking advantage (but I never meant it) of her gratitude and her affection; I ask pardon of that lady, in my heart!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He walked across the room, and came back to the same place; holding the chair with a grasp that trembled, like his subdued voice, in its earnestness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I regarded myself as a refuge, for her, from the dangers and vicissitudes of life. I persuaded myself that, unequal though we were in years, she would live tranquilly and contentedly with me. I did not shut out of my consideration the time when I should leave her free, and still young and still beautiful, but with her judgment more matured&mdash;no, gentlemen&mdash;upon my truth!&rdquo;</p>
<p>His homely figure seemed to be lightened up by his fidelity and generosity. Every word he uttered had a force that no other grace could have imparted to it.</p>
<pb n="438" id="p438"/>
<p>&ldquo;My life with this lady has been very happy. Until to-night, I have had uninterrupted occasion to bless the day on which I did her great injustice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>His voice, more and more faltering in the utterance of these words, stopped for a few moments; then he went on:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Once awakened from my dream&mdash;I have been a poor dreamer, in one way or other, all my life&mdash;I see how natural it is that she should have some regretful feeling towards her old companion and her equal. That she does regard him with some innocent regret, with some blameless thoughts of what might have been, but for me, is, I fear, too true. Much that I have seen, but not noted, has come back upon me with new meaning, during this last trying hour. But, beyond this, gentlemen, the dear lady's name never must be coupled with a word, a breath, of doubt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>For a little while, his eye kindled and his voice was firm; for a little while he was again silent. Presently, he proceeded as before:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It only remains for me, to bear the knowledge of the unhappiness I have occasioned, as submissively as I can. It is she who should reproach; not I. To save her from misconstruction, cruel misconstruction, that even my friends have not been able to avoid, becomes my duty. The more retired we live, the better I shall discharge it. And when the time comes&mdash;may it come soon, if it be His merciful pleasure!&mdash;when my death shall release her from constraint, I shall close my eyes upon her honored face, with unbounded confidence and love; and leave her, with no sorrow then, to happier and brighter days.</p>
<p>I could not see him for the tears which his earnestness and goodness, so adorned by, and so adorning, the perfect simplicity of his manner, brought into my eyes. He had moved to the door, when he added:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen, I have shown you my heart. I am sure you will respect it. What we have said to-night is never to be said more. Wickfield, give me an old friend's arm up-stairs!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Wickfield hastened to him. Without interchanging a word they went slowly out of the room together, Uriah looking after them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; said Uriah, meekly turning to me. &ldquo;The thing hasn't took quite the turn that might have been expected, for the old Scholar&mdash;what an excellent man!&mdash;is as blind as a brickbat; but <hi rend="italics">this</hi> family's out of the cart, I think!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I needed but the sound of his voice to be so madly enraged as I never was before, and never have been since.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You villain,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;what do you mean by entrapping me into your schemes? How dare you appeal to me just now, you false rascal, as if we had been in discussion together?&rdquo;</p>
<p>As we stood, front to front, I saw so plainly, in the stealthy exultation of his face, what I already so plainly knew; I mean that he forced his confidence upon me, expressly to make me miserable, and had set a deliberate trap for me in this very matter; that I couldn't bear it. The whole of his lank cheek was invitingly before me, and I struck it with my open hand with that force that my fingers tingled as if I had burnt them.</p>
<p>He caught the hand in his, and we stood, in that connexion, looking at each other. We stood so, a long time; long enough for me to see the
<pb n="439" id="p439"/>
white marks of my fingers die out of the deep red of his cheek, and leave it a deeper red.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; he said at length, in a breathless voice, &ldquo;have you taken leave of your senses?</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have taken leave of you,&rdquo; said I, wresting my hand away. &ldquo;You dog, I'll know no more of you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't you?&rdquo; said he, constrained by the pain of his cheek to put his hand there. &ldquo;Perhaps you won't be able to help it. Isn't this ungrateful of you, now?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have shown you often enough,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;that I despise you. I have shown you now, more plainly, that I do. Why should I dread your doing your worst to all about you? What else do you ever do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He perfectly understood this allusion to the considerations that had hitherto restrained me in my communications with him. I rather think that neither the blow, nor the allusion, would have escaped me, but for the assurance I had had from Agnes that night. It is no matter.</p>
<p>There was another long pause. His eyes, as he looked at me, seemed to take every shade of color that could make eyes ugly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; he said, removing his hand from his cheek, &ldquo;you have always gone against me. I know you always used to be against me at Mr. Wickfield's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may think what you like,&rdquo; said I, still in a towering rage. &ldquo;If it is not true, so much the worthier you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And yet I always liked you, Copperfield!&rdquo; he rejoined.</p>
<p>I deigned to make him no reply; and, taking up my hat, was going out to bed, when he came between me and the door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Copperfield,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;there must be two parties to a quarrel. I won't be one.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may go to the devil!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't say that!&rdquo; he replied. &ldquo;I know you'll be sorry afterwards. How can you make yourself so inferior to me, as to show such a bad spirit? But I forgive you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You forgive me!&rdquo; I repeated disdainfully.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do, and you can't help yourself,&rdquo; replied Uriah. &ldquo;To think of your going and attacking <hi rend="italics">me,</hi> that have always been a friend to you! But there can't be a quarrel without two parties, and I won't be one. I will be a friend to you, in spite of you. So now you know what you've got to expect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The necessity of carrying on this dialogue (his part in which was very slow; mine very quick) in a low tone, that the house might not be disturbed at an unseasonable hour, did not improve my temper; though my passion was cooling down. Merely telling him that I should expect from him what I always had expected, and had never yet been disappointed in, I opened the door upon him, as if he had been a great walnut put there to be cracked, and went out of the house. But he slept out of the house too, at his mother's lodging; and before I had gone many hundred yards, came up with me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You know, Copperfield,&rdquo; he said, in my ear (I did not turn my head), &ldquo;you're in quite a wrong position;&rdquo; which I felt to be true, and that made me chafe the more; &ldquo;you can't make this a brave thing,
<pb n="440" id="p440"/>
and you can't help being forgiven. I don't intend to mention it to mother, nor to any living soul. I'm determined to forgive you. But I do wonder that you should lift your hand against a person that you knew to be so umble!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt only less mean than he. He knew me better than I knew myself. If he had retorted, or openly exasperated me, it would have been a relief and a justification; but he had put me on a slow fire, on which I lay tormented half the night.</p>
<p>In the morning, when I came out, the early church bell was ringing, and he was walking up and down with his mother. He addressed me as if nothing had happened, and I could do no less than reply. I had struck him hard enough to give him the toothache, I suppose. At all events his face was tied up in a black silk handkerchief, which, with his hat perched on the top of it, was far from improving his appearance. I heard that he went to a dentist's in London on the Monday morning, and had a tooth out. I hope it was a double one.</p>
<p>The Doctor gave out that he was not quite well; and remained alone, for a considerable part of every day, during the remainder of the visit. Agnes and her father had been gone a week, before we resumed our usual work. On the day preceding its resumption, the Doctor gave me with his own hands a folded note not sealed. It was addressed to myself; and laid an injunction on me, in a few affectionate words, never to refer to the subject of that evening. I had confided it to my aunt, but to no one else. It was not a subject I could discuss with Agnes, and Agnes certainly had not the least suspicion of what had passed.</p>
<p>Neither, I felt convinced, had Mrs. Strong then. Several weeks elapsed before I saw the least change in her. It came on slowly, like a cloud when there is no wind. At first, she seemed to wonder at the gentle compassion with which the Doctor spoke to her, and at his wish that she should have her mother with her, to relieve the dull monotony of her life. Often, when we were at work, and she was sitting by, I would see her pausing and looking at him with that memorable face. Afterwards, I sometimes observed her rise, with her eyes full of tears, and go out of the room. Gradually, an unhappy shadow fell upon her beauty, and deepened every day. Mrs. Markleham was a regular inmate of the cottage then; but she talked and talked, and saw nothing.</p>
<p>As this change stole on Annie, once like sunshine in the Doctor's house, the Doctor became older in appearance, and more grave; but the sweetness of his temper, the placid kindness of his manner, and his benevolent solicitude for her, if they were capable of any increase, were increased. I saw him once, early on the morning of her birthday, when she came to sit in the window while we were at work (which she had always done, but now began to do with a timid and uncertain air that I thought very touching), take her forehead between his hands, kiss it, and go hurriedly away, too much moved to remain. I saw her stand where he had left her, like a statue; and then bend down her head, and clasp her hands, and weep, I cannot say how sorrowfully.</p>
<p>Sometimes, after that, I fancied that she tried to speak even to me, in intervals when we were left alone. But she never uttered word. The Doctor always had some new project for her participating in amusements
<pb n="441" id="p441"/>
away from home, with her mother; and Mrs. Markleham, who was very fond of amusements, and very easily dissatisfied with anything else, entered into them with great good will, and was loud in her commendations. But Annie, in a spiritless unhappy way, only went whither she was led, and seemed to have no care for anything.</p>
<p>I did not know what to think. Neither did my aunt; who must have walked, at various times, a hundred miles in her uncertainty. What was strangest of all was, that the only real relief which seemed to make its way into the secret region of this domestic unhappiness, made its way there in the person of Mr. Dick.</p>
<p>What his thoughts were on the subject, or what his observation was, I am as unable to explain, as I dare say he would have been to assist me in the task. But, as I have recorded in the narrative of my school days, his veneration for the Doctor was unbounded; and there is a subtlety of perception in real attachment, even when it is borne towards man by one of the lower animals, which leaves the highest intellect behind. To this mind of the heart, if I may call it so, in Mr. Dick, some bright ray of the truth shot straight.</p>
<p>He had proudly resumed his privilege, in many of his spare hours, of walking up and down the garden with the Doctor; as he had been accustomed to pace up and down The Doctor's Walk at Canterbury. But matters were no sooner in this state, than he devoted all his spare time (and got up earlier to make it more) to these perambulations. If he had never been so happy as when the Doctor read that <sic corr="marvellous">mavellous</sic> performance, the Dictionary, to him; he was now quite miserable unless the Doctor pulled it out of his pocket, and began. When the Doctor and I were engaged, he now fell into the custom of walking up and down with Mrs. Strong, and helping her to trim her favorite flowers, or weed the beds. I dare say he rarely spoke a dozen words in an hour: but his quiet interest, and his wistful face, found immediate response in both their breasts; each knew that the other liked him, and that he loved both; and he became what no one else could be&mdash;a link between them.</p>
<p>When I think of him, with his impenetrably wise face, walking up and down with the Doctor, delighted to be battered by the hard words in the Dictionary; when I think of him carrying huge watering-pots after Annie; kneeling down, in very paws of gloves, at patient microscopic work among the little leaves; expressing as no philosopher could have expressed, in every thing he did, a delicate desire to be her friend; showering sympathy, trustfulness, and affection, out of every hole in the watering-pot; when I think of him never wandering in that better mind of his to which unhappiness addressed itself, never bringing the unfortunate King Charles into the garden, never wavering in his grateful service, never diverted from his knowledge that there was something wrong, or from his wish to set it right&mdash;I really feel almost ashamed of having known that he was not quite in his wits, taking account of the utmost I have done with mine.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nobody but myself, Trot, knows what that man is!&rdquo; my aunt would proudly remark, when we conversed about it. &ldquo;Dick will distinguish himself yet!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I must refer to one other topic before I close this chapter. While the
<pb n="442" id="p442"/>
visit at the Doctor's was still in progress, I observed that the postman brought two or three letters every morning for Uriah Heep, who remained at Highgate until the rest went back, it being a leisure time; and that these were always directed in a business-like manner by Mr. Micawber, who now assumed a round legal hand. I was glad to infer, from these slight premises, that Mr. Micawber was doing well; and consequently was much surprised to receive, about this time, the following letter from his amiable wife.</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="letter">
<opener>
<dateline>&ldquo;CANTERBURY, Monday Evening.</dateline>
</opener>
<p>&ldquo;You will doubtless be surprised, my dear Mr. Copperfield, to receive this communication. Still more so, by its contents. Still more so, by the stipulation of implicit confidence which I beg to impose. But my feelings as a wife and mother require relief; and as I do not wish to consult my family (already obnoxious to the feelings of Mr. Micawber), I know no one of whom I can better ask advice than my friend and former lodger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may be aware, my dear Mr. Copperfield, that between myself and Mr. Micawber (whom I will never desert), there has always been preserved a spirit of mutual confidence. Mr. Micawber may have occasionally given a bill without consulting me, or he may have misled me as to the period when that obligation would become due. This has actually happened. But, in general, Mr. Micawber has had no secrets from the bosom of affection&mdash;I allude to his wife&mdash;and has invariably, on our retirement to rest, recalled the events of the day.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will picture to yourself, my dear Mr. Copperfield, what the poignancy of my feelings must be, when I inform you that Mr. Micawber is entirely changed. He is reserved. He is secret. His life is a mystery to the partner of his joys and sorrows&mdash;I again allude to his wife&mdash;and if I should assure you that beyond knowing that it is passed from morning to night at the office, I now know less of it than I do of the man in the south, connected with whose mouth the thoughtless children repeat an idle tale respecting cold plum porridge, I should adopt a popular fallacy to express an actual fact.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But this is not all. Mr. Micawber is morose. He is severe. He is estranged from our eldest son and daughter, he has no pride in his twins, he looks with an eye of coldness even on the unoffending stranger who last became a member of our circle. The pecuniary means of meeting our expenses, kept down to the utmost farthing, are obtained from him with great difficulty, and even under fearful threats that he will Settle himself (the exact expression); and he inexorably refuses to give any explanation whatever of this distracting policy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is hard to bear. This is heart-breaking. If you will advise me, knowing my feeble powers such as they are, how you think it will be best to exert them in a dilemma so unwonted, you will add another friendly obligation to the many you have already rendered me. With loves from the children, and a smile from the happily-unconscious stranger, I remain, dear Mr. Copperfield,</p>
<closer>
<salute>&ldquo;Your afflicted</salute>
<signed>&ldquo;EMMA MICAWBER.&rdquo;</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</q>
<pb n="443" id="p443"/>
<p>I did not feel justified in giving a wife of Mrs. Micawber's experience any other recommendation, than that she should try to reclaim Mr. Micawber by patience and kindness (as I knew she would in any case); but the letter set me thinking about him very much.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XLIII. <lb/> ANOTHER RETROSPECT.</head>
<p>ONCE again, let me pause upon a memorable period of my life. Let me stand aside, to see the phantoms of those days go by me, accompanying the shadow of myself, in dim procession.</p>
<p>Weeks, months, seasons, pass along. They seem little more than a summer day and a winter evening. Now, the Common where I walk with Dora is all in bloom, a field of bright gold; and now the unseen heather lies in mounds and bunches underneath a covering of snow. In a breath, the river that flows through our Sunday walks is sparkling in the summer sun, is ruffled by the winter wind, or thickened with drifting heaps of ice. Faster than ever river ran towards the sea, it flashes, darkens, and rolls away.</p>
<p>Not a thread changes, in the house of the two little bird-like ladies. The clock ticks over the fire-place, the weather-glass hangs in the hall. Neither clock nor weather-glass is ever right; but we believe in both, devoutly.</p>
<p>I have come legally to man's estate. I have attained the dignity of twenty-one. But this is a sort of dignity that may be thrust upon one. Let me think what I have achieved.</p>
<p>I have tamed that savage stenographic mystery. I make a respectable income by it. I am in high repute for my accomplishment in all pertaining to the art, and am joined with eleven others in reporting the debates in Parliament for a Morning Newspaper. Night after night, I record predictions that never come to pass, professions that are never fulfilled, explanations that are only meant to mystify. I wallow in words. Britannia, that unfortunate female, is always before me, like a trussed fowl: skewered through and through with office-pens, and bound hand and foot with red tape. I am sufficiently behind the scenes to know the worth of political life. I am quite an Infidel about it, and shall never be converted.</p>
<p>My dear old Traddles has tried his hand at the same pursuit, but it is not in Traddles's way. He is perfectly good-humoured respecting his failure, and reminds me that he always did consider himself slow. He has occasional employment on the same newspaper, in getting up the facts of dry subjects, to be written about and embellished by more fertile minds. He is called to the bar; and with admirable industry and self-denial has scraped another hundred pounds together, to fee a Conveyancer whose chambers he attends. A great deal of very hot port wine was consumed
<pb n="444" id="p444"/>
at his call; and, considering the figure, I should think the Inner Temple must have made a profit by it.</p>
<p>I have come out in another way. I have taken with fear and trembling to authorship. I wrote a little something, in secret, and sent it to a magazine, and it was published in the magazine. Since then, I have taken heart to write a good many trifling pieces. Now, I am regularly paid for them. Altogether, I am well off; when I tell my income on the fingers of my left hand, I pass the third finger and take in the fourth to the middle joint.</p>
<p>We have removed, from Buckingham Street, to a pleasant little cottage very near the one I looked at, when my enthusiasm first came on. My aunt, however (who has sold the house at Dover, to good advantage), is not going to remain here, but intends removing herself to a still more tiny cottage close at hand. What does this portend? My marriage? Yes!</p>
<p>Yes! I am going to be married to Dora! Miss Lavinia and Miss Clarissa have given their consent; and if ever canary birds were in a flutter, they are. Miss Lavinia, self-charged with the superintendence of my darling's wardrobe, is constantly cutting out brown-paper cuirasses, and differing in opinion from a highly respectable young man, with a long bundle, and a yard measure under his arm. A dressmaker, always stabbed in the breast with a needle and thread, boards and lodges in the house; and seems to me, eating, drinking, or sleeping, never to take her thimble off. They make a lay-figure of my dear. They are always sending for her to come and try something on. We can't be happy together for five minutes in the evening, but some intrusive female knocks at the door, and says, &ldquo;Oh, if you please, Miss Dora, would you step up-stairs!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Clarissa and my aunt roam all over London, to find out articles of furniture for Dora and me to look at. It would be better for them to buy the goods at once, without this ceremony of inspection; for, when we go to see a kitchen fender and meat-screen, Dora sees a Chinese house for Jip, with little bells on the top, and prefers that. And it takes a long time to accustom Jip to his new residence, after we have bought it; whenever he goes in or out, he makes all the little bells ring, and is horribly frightened.</p>
<p>Peggotty comes up to make herself useful, and falls to work immediately. Her department appears to be, to clean everything over and over again. She rubs everything that can be rubbed, until it shines, like her own honest forehead, with perpetual friction. And now it is, that I begin to see her solitary brother passing through the dark streets at night, and looking, as he goes, among the wandering faces. I never speak to him at such an hour. I know too well, as his grave figure passes onward, what he seeks, and what he dreads.</p>
<p>Why does Traddles look so important when he calls upon me this afternoon in the Commons&mdash;where I still occasionally attend, for form's sake, when I have time? The realisation of my boyish day-dreams is at hand. I am going to take out the license.</p>
<p>It is a little document to do so much; and Traddles contemplates it, as it lies upon my desk, half in admiration, half in awe. There are the names, in the sweet old visionary connexion, David Copperfield and Dora Spenlow;
<pb n="445" id="p445"/>
and there, in the corner, is that Parental Institution, the Stamp Office, which is so benignantly interested in the various transactions of human life, looking down upon our Union; and there is the Archbishop of Canterbury invoking a blessing on us in print, and doing it as cheap as could possibly be expected.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, I am in a dream, a flustered, happy, hurried dream. I can't believe that it is going to be; and yet I can't believe but that everyone I pass in the street, must have some kind of perception, that I am to be married the day after to-morrow. The Surrogate knows me, when I go down to be sworn; and disposes of me easily, as if there were a Masonic understanding between us. Traddles is not at all wanted, but is in attendance as my general backer.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope the next time you come here, my dear fellow,&rdquo; I say to Traddles, &ldquo;it will be on the same errand for yourself. And I hope it will be soon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you for your good wishes, my dear Copperfield,&rdquo; he replies. &ldquo;I hope so too. It's a satisfaction to know that she'll wait for me any length of time, and that she really is the dearest girl&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When are you to meet her at the coach?&rdquo; I ask.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At seven,&rdquo; says Traddles, looking at his plain old silver watch&mdash;the very watch he once took a wheel out of, at school, to make a water-mill. &ldquo;That is about Miss Wickfield's time, is it not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A little earlier. Her time is half-past eight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I assure you, my dear boy,&rdquo; says Traddles, &ldquo;I am almost as pleased as if I were going to be married myself, to think that this event is coming to such a happy termination. And really the great friendship and consideration of personally associating Sophy with the joyful occasion, and inviting her to be a bridesmaid in conjunction with Miss Wickfield, demands my warmest thanks. I am extremely sensible of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I hear him, and shake hands with him; and we talk, and walk, and dine, and so on; but I don't believe it. Nothing is real.</p>
<p>Sophy arrives at the house of Dora's aunts, in due course. She has the most agreeable of faces,&mdash;not absolutely beautiful, but extraordinarily pleasant,&mdash;and is one of the most genial, unaffected, frank, engaging creatures I have ever seen. Traddles presents her to us with great pride; and rubs his hands for ten minutes by the clock, with every individual hair upon his head standing on tiptoe, when I congratulate him in a corner on his choice.</p>
<p>I have brought Agnes from the Canterbury coach, and her cheerful and beautiful face is among us for the second time. Agnes has a great liking for Traddles, and it is capital to see them meet, and to observe the glory of Traddles as he commends the dearest girl in the world to her acquaintance.</p>
<p>Still I don't believe it. We have a delightful evening, and are supremely happy; but I don't believe it yet. I can't collect myself. I can't check off my happiness as it takes place. I feel in a misty and unsettled kind of state; as if I had got up very early in the morning a week or two ago, and had never been to bed since. I can't make out when yesterday was. I seem to have been carrying the licence about, in my pocket, many months.</p>
<pb n="446" id="p446"/>
<p>Next day, too, when we all go in a flock to see the house&mdash;our house&mdash;Dora's and mine&mdash;I am quite unable to regard myself as its master. I seem to be there, by permission of somebody else. I half expect the real master to come home presently, and say he is glad to see me. Such a beautiful little house as it is, with everything so bright and new; with the flowers on the carpets looking as if freshly gathered, and the green leaves on the paper as if they had just come out; with the spotless muslin curtains, and the blushing rose-coloured furniture, and Dora's garden hat with the blue ribbon&mdash;do I remember, now, how I loved her in such another hat when I first knew her!&mdash;already hanging on its little peg; the guitarcase quite at home on its heels in a corner; and everybody tumbling over Jip's Pagoda, which is much too big for the establishment.</p>
<p>Another happy evening, quite as unreal as all the rest of it, and I steal into the usual room before going away. Dora is not there. I suppose they have not done trying on yet. Miss Lavinia peeps in, and tells me mysteriously that she will not be long. She is rather long, notwithstanding; but by-and-by I hear a rustling at the door, and some one taps.</p>
<p>I say, &ldquo;Come in!&rdquo; but some one taps again.</p>
<p>I go to the door, wondering who it is; there, I meet a pair of bright eyes, and a blushing face; they are Dora's eyes and face, and Miss Lavinia has dressed her in to-morrow's dress, bonnet and all, for me to see. I take my little wife to my heart; and Miss Lavinia gives a little scream because I tumble the bonnet, and Dora laughs and cries at once, because I am so pleased; and I believe it less than ever.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think it pretty, Doady?&rdquo; says Dora.</p>
<p>Pretty! I should rather think I did.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And are you sure you like me very much?&rdquo; says Dora.</p>
<p>The topic is fraught with such danger to the bonnet, that Miss Lavinia gives another little scream, and begs me to understand that Dora is only to be looked at, and on no account to be touched. So Dora stands in a delightful state of confusion for a minute or two, to be admired; and then takes off her bonnet&mdash;looking so natural without it!&mdash;and runs away with it in her hand; and comes dancing down again in her own familiar dress, and asks Jip if I have got a beautiful little wife, and whether he'll forgive her for being married, and kneels down to make him stand upon the cookery-book, for the last time in her single life.</p>
<p>I go home, more incredulous than ever, to a lodging that I have hard by; and get up very early in the morning, to ride to the Highgate road and fetch my aunt.</p>
<p>I have never seen my aunt in such state. She is dressed in lavender-colored silk, and has a white bonnet on, and is amazing. Janet has dressed her, and is there to look at me. Peggotty is ready to go to church, intending to behold the ceremony from the gallery. Mr. Dick, who is to give my darling to me at the altar, has had his hair curled. Traddles, whom I have taken up by appointment at the turnpike, presents a dazzling combination of cream color and light blue; and both he and Mr. Dick have a general effect about them of being all gloves.</p>
<p>No doubt I see this, because I know it is so; but I am astray, and seem to see nothing. Nor do I believe anything whatever. Still, as we
<pb n="447" id="p447"/>
drive along in an open carriage, this fairy marriage is real enough to fill me with a sort of wondering pity for the unfortunate people who have no part in it, but are sweeping out the shops, and going to their daily occupations.</p>
<p>My aunt sits with my hand in hers all the way. When we stop a little way short of the church, to put down Peggotty, whom we have brought on the box, she gives it a squeeze, and me a kiss.</p>
<p>&ldquo;God bless you, Trot! My own boy never could be dearer. I think of poor dear Baby this morning.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So do I. And of all I owe to you, dear aunt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tut, child!&rdquo; says my aunt; and gives her hand in overflowing cordiality to Traddles, who then gives his to Mr. Dick, who then gives his to me, who then give mine to Traddles, and then we come to the church door.</p>
<p>The church is calm enough, I am sure; but it might be a steampower loom in full action, for any sedative effect it has on me. I am too far gone for that.</p>
<p>The rest is all a more or less incoherent dream.</p>
<p>A dream of their coming in with Dora; of the pew-opener arranging us, like a drill-serjeant, before the altar rails; of my wondering, even then, why pew-openers must always be the most disagreeable females procurable, and whether there is any religious dread of a disastrous infection of good-humour which renders it indispensable to set those vessels of vinegar upon the road to Heaven.</p>
<p>Of the clergyman and clerk appearing; of a few boatmen and some other people strolling in; of an ancient mariner behind me, strongly flavoring the church with rum; of the service beginning in a deep voice, and our all being very attentive.</p>
<p>Of Miss Lavinia, who acts as a semi-auxiliary bridesmaid, being the first to cry, and of her doing homage (as I take it) to the memory of Pidger, in sobs; of Miss Clarissa applying a smelling-bottle; of Agnes taking care of Dora; of my aunt endeavouring to represent herself as a model of sternness, with tears rolling down her face; of little Dora trembling very much, and making her responses in faint whispers.</p>
<p>Of our kneeling down together, side by side; of Dora's trembling less and less, but always clasping Agnes by the hand; of the service being got through, quietly and gravely; of our all looking at each other in an April state of smiles and tears, when it is over; of my young wife being hysterical in the vestry, and crying for her poor papa, her dear papa.</p>
<p>Of her soon cheering up again, and our signing the register all round. Of my going into the gallery for Peggotty to bring <hi rend="italics">her</hi> to sign it; of Peggotty's hugging me in a corner, and telling me she saw my own dear mother married; of its being over, and our going away.</p>
<p>Of my walking so proudly and lovingly down the aisle with my sweet wife upon my arm, through a mist of half-seen people, pulpits, monuments, pews, fonts, organs, and church windows, in which there flutter faint airs of association with my childish church at home, so long ago.</p>
<p>Of their whispering, as we pass, what a youthful couple we are, and what a pretty little wife she is. Of our all being so merry and talkative in the carriage going back. Of Sophy telling us that when she
<pb n="448" id="p448"/>
saw Traddles (whom I had entrusted with the licence) asked for it, she almost fainted, having been convinced that he would contrive to lose it, or to have his pocket picked. Of Agnes laughing gaily; and of Dora being so fond of Agnes that she will not be separated from her, but still keeps her hand.</p>
<p>Of there being a breakfast, with abundance of things, pretty and substantial, to eat and drink, whereof I partake, as I should do in any other dream, without the least perception of their flavor; eating and drinking, as I may say, nothing but love and marriage, and no more believing in the viands than in anything else.</p>
<p>Of my making a speech in the same dreamy fashion, without having an idea of what I want to say, beyond such as may be comprehended in the full conviction that I haven't said it. Of our being very sociably and simply happy (always in a dream though); and of Jip's having wedding cake, and its not agreeing with him afterwards.</p>
<p>Of the pair of hired post-horses being ready, and of Dora's going away to change her dress. Of my aunt and Miss Clarissa remaining with us; and our walking in the garden; and my aunt, who has made quite a speech at breakfast touching Dora's aunts, being mightily amused with herself, but a little proud of it too.</p>
<p>Of Dora's being ready, and of Miss Lavinia's hovering about her, loth to lose the pretty toy that has given her so much pleasant occupation. Of Dora's making a long series of surprised discoveries that she has forgotten all sorts of little things; and of everybody's running everywhere to fetch them.</p>
<p>Of their all closing about Dora, when at last she begins to say goodbye, looking, with their bright colors and ribbons, like a bed of flowers. Of my darling being almost smothered among the flowers, and coming out, laughing and crying both together, to my jealous arms.</p>
<p>Of my wanting to carry Jip (who is to go along with us), and Dora's saying no, that she must carry him, or else he'll think she don't like him any more, now she is married, and will break his heart. Of our going, arm in arm, and Dora stopping and looking back, and saying, &ldquo;If I have ever been cross or ungrateful to anybody, don't remember it!&rdquo; and bursting into tears.</p>
<p>Of her waving her little hand, and our going away once more. Of her once more stopping, and looking back, and hurrying to Agnes, and giving Agnes, above all the others, her last kisses and farewells.</p>
<p>We drive away together, and I awake from the dream. I believe it at last. It is my dear, dear, little wife beside me, whom I love so well!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are you happy now, you foolish boy?&rdquo; says Dora, &ldquo;and sure you don't repent?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have stood aside to see the phantoms of those days go by me. They are gone, and I resume the journey of my story.</p>
</div2>

</div1>




</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1b" n="1"/>
<head>THE POWDERED-HEADED GENTLEMAN.</head>
<lg type="poem">
<l>I SCARCE need tell, what ev'ry one must know,</l>
<l>That powder'd heads were one time &ldquo;all the go:&rdquo;</l>
<l>Such was the case: and not to have a <hi rend="italics">snow</hi> head</l>
<l>Was almost tantamount to having <hi rend="italics">no</hi> head.</l>
<l>In fact, a man without a dusty &ldquo;nob&rdquo;</l>
<l>Was scarce view'd higher than a &ldquo;Dusty Bob.&rdquo;</l>
<l>But heads no longer are with powder loaded,</l>
<l>The powder-box has now, long since, exploded.</l>
<l>Yet Mr. White&mdash;a man whom well I know&mdash;</l>
<l>Wore powder till a week or two ago.</l>
<l>Wear it he would, in spite of what was said,</l>
<l>Making a laugh of every other head.</l>
<l>But one thing altered this eccentric man,</l>
<l>Which I'll explain as briefly as I can.</l>
<l>He bought a suit of MOSES'&mdash;such a one</l>
<l>As none could equal&mdash;save E.M. and SON.</l>
<l>The cloth was elegant, the style &ldquo;all right&rdquo;</l>
<l>(To use the homely phrase of Mr. White;)</l>
<l>And so delighted was the powder'd man</l>
<l>With garments made on such a first-rate plan,</l>
<l>That he began to fear that powder'd hair</l>
<l>Would be a most destructive thing to wear.</l>
<l>&ldquo;This coat (thought he,) is far too good to spoil,</l>
<l>Suppose I change my powder into oil.&rdquo;</l>
<l>He thought and thought, till on that very day</l>
<l>His powder pride and prejudice gave way.</l>
<l>A fact like this you'll readily contess</l>
<l>Speaks volumes for the worth of MOSES' dress.</l>
<l>And should the anecdote which thus I've told</l>
<l>Tempt you to go where MOSES' dress is sold,</l>
<l>I shall be proud indeed (and no one prouder.</l>
<l>At swelling MOSES' <hi rend="italics">train</hi> by means of powder.</l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Men's Spring and Summer Wrappers, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> The Bulwer Pacha Paletot, and every description of light Over Coat. </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Cloth Over Coat, of a light texture, and handsomely trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Cloth Over Coat, lined with Silk </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Cloth Over Coat, superior quality </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Jean and Holland Blouses </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Fancy Victoria Blouses </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Tweed Victoria Blouses </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Dress Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Frock Coats </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Spring and Summer Trousers </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Doeskin and Buckskin Trousers </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Spring and Summer Vests, in every variety </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Black and Figured Satin Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Black, superior quality </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> White Marcella Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Black Cloth Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Boys' Hussar and Tunic Suits </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Boys' Spring and Summer Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Men's Fishing Coats, in every variety </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Paletots, made from a variety of material, fitted for Summer wear from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Paletots, in every style, elegantly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Superfine Cloth style, of a light texture </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Superfine Cloth style, lined with Silk </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Superfine Dress Coat </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Best Dress for </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Superfine Frock Dress </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Best Frock for </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Fancy Doeskin Trousers from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Black Doeskin Trousers </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Best Doeskin Trousers </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Black Cloth Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Best Cloth Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Splendid Satin Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Best Satin Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Hussar and Tunic Suits </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Superfine Suits </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Men's White Marcella Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Fishing Coats, in endless variety, from 10s. 6d. to </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes, in great variety, from 16s. to </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> &pound;1 10s.</p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Minion of the Million,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON,</head><p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aidgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p2b" n="2"/>
<head>YOUTH.&mdash;120, REGENT STREET.</head>
<p>PARENTS and GUARDIANS are respectfully invited to inspect the cost of the several garments here submitted, and considered necessary for the Universities, Public and Private Schools, &amp;c. In this branch clever and efficient persons are employed by Messrs. NICOLL, as in all other departments, the result being the production of a more graceful and elegant appearance in Youths' Clothing than has hitherto been approached; while, at the same time, their durability and general excellence will be as strongly characterised as in NICOLL'S PALETOT.</p>
<p>VIEW OF CALCUTTA, <lb/> Where Messrs. D. WILSON &amp; Co. are the Solo Agents for 11. J. and D. NICOLL, of 114, 116, 118, and 120, Regent Street, and 22, Cornhill, London, Merchant Clothiers, Paletot Patentees, and Cloth Manufacturers.</p>
<p>Many use the word &ldquo;PALETOT,&rdquo; but Messrs. NICOLL are the Sole Patentees of the design and material used in this graceful and inexpensive article of gentlemanly attire.</p>
<list>
<item>118, Regent Street, is a Department for Robes, College Gowns, &amp;c.</item>
<item>116, Regent Street, is a Department for Military and Diplomatic Uniforms, &amp;c.</item>
<item>114, Regent Street, is a Department for Paletot and Novelties in Costume.</item>
<item>22, Cornhill, is the City Depot for Specimens of each of the above Departments.</item>
</list><closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
