<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. IX:</emph>
 Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Ingrid Pohl</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.  250 K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> The Personal History, Adventures, Experience, &amp; Observation of David Copperfield the Younger, of Blunderstone Rookery. (Which He Never Meant to Be Published on any Account.) No. IX:</title>

<author>Charles  Dickens</author>


<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent> 71 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
<date>1850</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 20 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>
</p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl><taxonomy id="LCSH">
<bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy></classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="LCSH">
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>

<change>
<date>2002-11-13, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-10-03, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page verso image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>


<titlePage>


<docTitle><titlePart> No.  IX. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> JANUARY.
</docDate>
<docEdition>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s</hi>.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY, ADVENTURES, <lb/> EXPERIENCE, &amp; OBSERVATION <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD <lb/> THE YOUNGER <lb/> OF BLUNDERSTONE ROOKERY.<lb/>(Which He never meant to be Published on any Account.) </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, WHITEFRIARS.</publisher>
AGENTS:&mdash; J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; T. MURRAY, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>THE GREATEST LUXURY <lb/> FOR THE BED-ROOM IS <lb/> THE EIDER-DOWN QUILT.</head>
<p>EIDER-DOWN contains the most warmth, with the least weight, of any known substance; and this, combined with its freedom from Stem or Quill, renders it, either for a Bed covering, <lb/> OR AS A WRAPPER FOR THE COUCH OR CARRIAGE, <lb/> more agreeable, <lb/> AND ALSO MORE HEALTHFUL, <lb/> than any other covering.</p>
<p>The EIDER-DOWN QUILT is strongly recommended by the most eminent members of the faculty for the <lb/> AGED AND INFIRM, AS WELL AS FOR INVALIDS.</p>
<p>They are kept, in great variety of sizes and colours, and in Silk and Cotton cases.</p>
<p>LISTS OF PRICES <lb/> sent free by Post on application to <lb/> HEAL AND SON'S <lb/> BEDDING FACTORY, <lb/> 196 (opposite the Chapel), TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HEAL AND SON'S</head><p>LIST OF BEDDING, <lb/> Containing a full description of weights, sizes and prices, by which purchasers are enabled to judge the articles best suited to make a good set of Bedding, sent free by Post, on application at their Factory,</p><closer>196 (OPPOSITE THE CHAPEL), <lb/> TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, LONDON.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="1" id="p1"/><opener>No. IX.&mdash;JANUARY, 1850.</opener>
<head>COPPERFIELD ADVERTISER.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Sold at all Railway Stations, and by all Newsmen.</hi></p>
<div2>
<head>New Weekly Illustrated Periodical for Ladies.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Published Weekly, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d., Stamped,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d., or in Monthly Parts,</hi>
<lb/> THE LADIES' COMPANION <lb/> At Home and Abroad.</p>
<p>EDITED BY MRS. LOUDON.</p>
<p>ASSISTED BY THE MOST EMINENT WRITERS AND ARTISTS.</p>
<p>THE want of a First Class Periodical adapted to the Tastes and Pursuits of Women having been constantly urged upon me, I have projected, with an earnest desire for the Improvement and Elevation of the Female Character, and in conjunction with some of the best names in Literature and Art&mdash; <lb/> THE LADIES' COMPANION AT HOME AND ABROAD.</p>
<p>The first point will be to enforce the necessity of Mental Cultivation. In educating female children, we too often give an undue importance to accomplishments, forgetting that they are the adjuncts, and not the principal object; only the garnishing to the solid food; useful to make girls agreeable in society; but not enough to make them good wives and mothers, or, at any rate, valuable members of the community.</p>
<p>The Influence of Women in Society, and the necessity for their mental cultivation, are now generally acknowledged; and the old fancy, that learning must make women pedantic and disagreeable, is rapidly passing away. It is true that there are some pedantic women, who are exceedingly disagreeable; but are there not also pedantic men, who are just as much so? And yet no one, I believe, ever yet proposed to deny the benefit of mental cultivation to <hi rend="italics">all</hi> men, because the brains of some few are found too weak to bear it.</p>
<p>To make women agreeable social companions to their husbands and other male relations, it is necessary for them to be acquainted with many Matters of General Information, continually recurring in books and conversation, which are not usually taught in girls' schools; and it will be endeavoured, in the present work, to give young persons such a Knowledge of the Arts and Sciences, and of Ancient and Modern Literature, as will enable them to take an interest in subjects constantly spoken of, without penetrating into the depths of profound learning.</p>
<p>Next to mental cultivation we place those Household Duties and Useful and Elegant Occupations, in which women ought particularly to excel. It is not enough for a woman to be the companion of her husband; she must be his helpmate; the tutelary genius of his house: she must watch over his domestic comforts while he is engaged in the fatiguing duties of active life; and above all, she must make home comfortable to him, whether she does it merely by the careful performance of her household duties, or adds to them the graces of elegant accomplishments.</p>
<p>It is not only the poor man's wife who must attend to her Household Duties; every woman has household duties to perform, though they vary according to her rank in life; and in no one can we see the arduous duties of wife and mother more admirably carried out to their fullest extent than in the bright example held out to us by the Greatest, the Noblest, the most Honoured, and most Beloved Lady in the realm.</p>
<p>One important feature of this work will be to Advocate the Causes of those Females who are Compelled to Labour, either mentally or bodily, for their daily bread; and to suggest some Means of Employment for the Orphans of Clergymen, Artists, Officers, &amp;c., who are, perhaps, more to be pitied than any other class; as to them the privations and mortifications they undergo are doubly embittered by recollections of the delicacy with which they were reared, and by the refined tastes and sensitive feelings which are almost inseparable from the education they have received.</p>
<p>There are, of course, many minor points to be attended to, as, the Garden; the Poultry-yard; Designs for Furniture, Fashions, and Work; Reviews of Books; In-door Occupations and Amusements, and many other incidental topics arising from circumstances, or from the wants or wishes of our readers. The Illustrations will have frequent reference to the subjects just enumerated, but they will also include delineations of whatever may be considered distinguished for interest or beauty.</p>
<p>It must not, however, be supposed that the present publication is to take entirely a serious character; on the contrary, the aim will be to combine amusement with instruction, and to make the lighter parts as entertaining as the more important parts are solid and valuable.</p>
<closer>
<dateline>BAYSWATER, November 30th, 1849.</dateline>
<signed>J. W. LOUDON.</signed>
</closer><closer>LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET;</closer><trailer><hi rend="italics">Where Advertisements are received, and where all Communications for the Editor should be addressed.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<head>MR. DICKENS' CHRISTMAS BOOKS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo. Price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound in cloth, with gilt edges,</hi>
<lb/> THE ILLUSTRATIONS BY D. MACLISE, R.A., CLARKSON STANFIELD, R.A., FRANK STONE, JOHN LEEOH, <lb/> JOHN TENNIEL, AND RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<list>
<item>A Christmas Carol. In Prose.</item>
<item>The Chimes. A Goblin Story of some Bells that rang an Old Year Out, and a New Year In.</item>
<item>The Battle of Life. A Love Story.</item>
<item>The Cricket on the Hearth. A Fairy Tale of Home.</item>
<item>The Haunted Man and the Ghost's Bargain.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">This day is published, in a handsome quarto volume, price</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>MANNERS AND CVSTOMS <lb/> of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
<lb/> Englyshe in 1849.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">BY RICHARD DOYLE.</hi></p>
<p>TOGETHER WITH SOME EXTRACTS FROM <lb/> Mr. Pips his Diary.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Contributed by PERCIVAL LEIGH.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, in a Series of Etchings on Steel, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. coloured, or</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d plain.</hi></opener>
<head>&ldquo;YOUNG TROUBLESOME,&rdquo; <lb/> or<lb/>Master Jacky's Holidays.</head>
<p>From the blessed moment of his leaving school, to the identical moment of his going back again.</p>
<p>SHOWING, <lb/> HOW THERE NEVER WAS SUCH A BOY AS THAT BOY.</p>
<p>DESIGNED AND ETCHED BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<list>
<head>PERSONS REPRESENTED.</head>
<item>MR. PHOENIX, <hi rend="italics">a wealthy Merchant.</hi></item>
<item>MASTER JACKY, <hi rend="italics">his son, familiarly called</hi> YOUNG TROUBLESOME.</item>
<item>OLD BRADSHAW, <hi rend="italics">his friend and schoolfellow.</hi></item>
<item>CAITAIN CLARENCE, <hi rend="italics">betrothed to</hi> AMELIA.</item>
<item>MR. MAUDLIN GROOVES, M.A., <hi rend="italics">with his eye on</hi> LAURA.</item>
<item>MR. WORMWOOD SCRUBBS <hi rend="italics">An old gentleman of a peculiar temper, with a handsome independence, bequeathable by Will.</hi> Mr. SCRUBBS <hi rend="italics">has known</hi> Mr. PHOENIX <hi rend="italics">since the latter was a boy, and is Godfather to</hi> MASTER JACKY.</item>
<item>RUGGLES, <hi rend="italics">a devoted family domestic, loving</hi> MASTER JACKY <hi rend="italics">as his own son.</hi></item>
<item>MRS. PHOENIX, <hi rend="italics">wife to</hi> MR. PHOENIX.</item>
<item>AMELIA and LAURA, <hi rend="italics">their lovely and accomplished daughters.</hi></item>
<item>JANE, CARY, TOM, NED, FRANK, <hi rend="italics">the rising</hi> PHOENIX <hi rend="italics">generation.</hi></item>
<item>MASTER BROWN, <hi rend="italics">from next door.</hi></item>
<item>MASTER GREEN, <hi rend="italics">from over the way.</hi></item>
</list><list>
<head><hi rend="italics">Visitors, Servants, &amp;c.</hi></head>
<item>SCENE&mdash;<hi rend="italics">The House of</hi> MR. PHOENIX.</item><item>TIME&mdash;<hi rend="italics">The Christmas Holidays.</hi></item>
</list><p><hi rend="italics">An interval of half a year is supposed to have elapsed between the last Midsummer Holidays and the</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">rising of the Curtain.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, Bonverie Street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Now ready, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; Stamped,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head>PUNCH'S ALMANACK FOR 1850.</head>
<p>PROFUSELY ILLUSTRATED <lb/> BY JOHN LEECH AND RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p>PUNCH'S ALMANACKS <lb/> For the Eight preceding Years have been collected, and are published in a handsome volume, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<div3 type="section">
<opener><hi rend="italics">Price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., roan, gilt edges,</hi></opener><head>Punch's Pocket-Book for 1850.</head>
<p>WITH A COLOURED FRONTISPIECE ON STEEL, <lb/> AND MANY OTHER ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> BY JOHN LEECH, RICHARD DOYLE, AND H. K. BROWNE.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>WORKS BY MR. GILBERT A. A'BECKETT.</head>
<p>THE COMIC BLACKSTONE. Illustrated by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE QUIZZIOLOGY OF THE BRITISH DRAMA. Illustrated by JOHN LEECH. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE ALMANACK OF THE MONTH. Illustrated by RICHARD DOYLE. Two vols. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>WORKS BY MR. DOUGLAS JERROLD.</head>
<p>A MAN MADE OF MONEY. Illustrated by JOHN LEECH. Post 8vo. Price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
<p>MRS. CAUDLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES, as Suffered by the late JOB CAUDLE. Illustrated by JOHN LEECH. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>PUNCH'S COMPLETE LETTER-WRITER. Illustrated by KENNY MEADOWS. Price 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>PUNCH'S LETTERS TO HIS SON. Illustrated by KENNY MEADOWS. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE STORY OF A FEATHER. Illustrated by JOHN LEECH. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>DOUGLAS JERROLD'S SHILLING MAGAZINE. Complete in Seven Volumes, bound in cloth, price &pound;2 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Any Volume or Number may be had separately.</p>
<p>TIME WORKS WONDERS. A Comedy in Five Acts, as performed at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket. <hi rend="italics">Fifth Edition.</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>BUBBLES OF THE DAY. A Comedy in Five Acts, as performed at the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden. 1s.</p>
<closer>PUNCH OFFICE, 85, FLEET STREET.</closer>
</div3>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>WORKS BY MR. W. M. THACKERAY.</head>
<p>PENDENNIS: HIS FORTUNES AND MISFORTUNES, HIS FRIENDS AND GREATEST ENEMY. In course of publication in Shilling Numbers. Volume I., price 13s. cloth, is now ready.</p>
<p>VANITY FAIR. Illustrated with Forty Steel Engravings and numerous Woodcuts by the Author. In one large volume, 8vo, price 21s. cloth, or 24s. 6d. half-bound morocco.</p>
<p>THE BOOK OF SNOBS. A Selection of Amusing Papers for the first time collected into a Volume, containing upwards of Sixty Illustrations by the Author. In small 8vo, price 2s. 6d.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>Illustrated Works for Christmas Presents.</head>
<p>FORSTER'S LIFE OF GOLDSMITH.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In One Large Volume,</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s., with Forty Illustrations on Wood, from designs by</hi>
<lb/> STANFIELD, MACLISE, LEECH, DOYLE, <hi rend="italics">and</hi> HAMERTON, <lb/> THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF <lb/> OLIVER GOLDSMITH.</p>
<p>BY JOHN FORSTER, <lb/> Of the Inner Temple, Barrister, Author of &ldquo;Lives of Statesmen of the Commonwealth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A biography executed with a spirit, a feeling, a grace, and an eloquence, that leave nothing to be desired. Indeed, it would have been presumption in me to undertake the subject after it had been thus felicitously treated, did I not stand committed by my previous sketch.&rdquo;</p>
<p>WASHINGTON IRVING'S <hi rend="italics">Preface to his Life of Goldsmith.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head>THE ENCHANTED DOLL.</head>
<p>A Fairy Tale for Little People.</p>
<p>By MARK LEMON.</p>
<p>WITH NUMEROUS ILLUSTRATIONS BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This book is pretty in every sense of the word. It is a well-conducted legend, and one which children will like to hear many times.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In One volume, small</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s., with Ten Illustrations on Steel by the Author,</hi></opener><head>THE HISTORY OF SAMUEL TITMARSH <lb/> AND <lb/> THE GREAT HOGGARTY DIAMOND.</head>
<p>BY W. M. THACKERAY, Esq., <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Vanity Fair,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It may not be so caustic as &lsquo;Vanity Fair,&rsquo; or so funny as &lsquo;Pendennis,&rsquo; but it is nevertheless one of the most perfect of Mr. Thackeray's prose productions.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Observer.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In Two Volumes, handsomely bound in cloth, price</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi><lb/>ILLUSTRATED BY JOHN LEECH.<lb/>WITH TWO HUNDRED WOODCUTS, AND TWENTY LARGE COLOURED STEEL ENGRAVINGS.</opener>
<head>THE COMIC HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</head>
<p>BY GILBERT A. &agrave; BECKETT, Esq., <lb/> Author of the &ldquo;Comic Blackstone,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">In an Illustrated Cover, containing Twelve Prints, price</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., or</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. each, separately. Forming a</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">handsome and amusing Volume for the Drawing-room Table.</hi></opener>
<head>THE RISING GENERATION.</head>
<p>BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p>A SERIES OF DRAWINGS ON STONE, BEAUTIFULLY COLOURED.</p>
<p>&ldquo;John Leech is the English Gavarni; and if others surpass him in fancy, no one approaches him in genteel comedy. His pictures are bits of life.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Chronicle.</hi></p>
<closer>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<opener>Dedicated by Command to H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, &amp;c. &amp;c.</opener>
<head>THE ART-JOURNAL;</head><p>AN ILLUSTRATED MONTHLY JOURNAL OF THE FINE ARTS, THE ARTS OF <lb/> DESIGN AND MANUFACTURE, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>Price Half-a-Crown Monthly.</p>
<list>
<head>ENGRAVINGS FROM THE VERNON GALLERY.</head>
<item>1. Portrait of R. Vernon, Esq., after Pickersgill, R.A.</item>
<item>2. Highland Music after E. Landseer, R.A.</item>
<item>3. Wooden Bridge after Callcott, R.A.</item>
<item>4. Venice after Stanfield, R.A.</item>
<item>5. Sancho and the Duchesa after Leslie, R.A.</item>
<item>6. Brook by the Way after Gainsborough, R.A.</item>
<item>7. Chapeau de Brigand after Uwins, R.A.</item>
<item>8. The Scheldt&mdash;Texel Island after Stanfield, R.A.</item>
<item>9. The Fall of Clarendon after Ward, A R.A.</item>
<item>10. The Prawn Fisners after Collins, R.A.</item>
<item>11. The Valley Farm after Constable, R.A.</item>
<item>12. Waiting for the Boats after Callcott, R.A.</item>
<item>13. Cattle&mdash;Early Morning after Cooper, A.R.A.</item>
<item>14. Interior of Burgos Cathedral Roberts, R.A.</item>
<item>15. Dutch Boats in a Calm after E. W. Cooke.</item>
<item>16. Bathers Surprised by a Swan W. Etty, R.A.</item>
<item>17. The Penitent after W. Etty, R.A.</item>
<item>18. Venice&mdash;the Dogana after Turner, R.A.</item>
<item>19. The Way to Church after Creswick, A R.A.</item>
<item>20. The Truant after Webster, R.A.</item>
<item>21. Malvolio after Maclise, R.A.</item>
<item>22. The First Earing after Wilkie, R.A.</item>
<item>23. The Dutch Ferry after Callcott, R.A.</item>
<item>24. High Life after E. Landseer, R.A.</item>
<item>25. Low Life after E. Landseer, R.A.</item>
</list>
<p>The Volume, handsomely bound, of the ART-JOURNAL, for the year 1849. containing the above Twenty-five Line Engravings (on Steel) of the Vernon Gallery, Twelve Engravings (on Steel) of Works in Sculpture, above Eight Hundred Engravings on Wood, and near Four Hundred Pages of Letter-Press, may be purchased for the sum of Thirty-One Shillings and Sixpence.</p>
<p>The Proprietors have also to announce, that Twenty-four Engravings from the Vernon Gallery are in preparation for the year 1850. These are as follow:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>The Age of Innocence after Sir J. Reynolds, P.R.A.</item>
<item>The Village Festival after F. Goodall.</item>
<item>The Woodland Gate after W. Collins, R.A.</item>
<item>The Scanty Meal after J. F. Herring.</item>
<item>The Syrian Maid after H. W. Pickersgill, R.A.</item>
<item>The Last In after W. Mulready, R.A.</item>
<item>Reading the News after Sir D. Wilkie, R.A.</item>
<item>Venice: The Grand Canal J. M. W. Turner, R.A.</item>
<item>Sir Thomas More after J. R. Herbert, R.A.</item>
<item>Rustic Children after T. Gainsborough, R.A.</item>
<item>The Death of the Stag after E. Landseer, R.A.</item>
<item>Youth and Pleasure after W. Etty, R.A.</item>
<item>Rebecca at the Well after W. Hilton, R.A.</item>
<item>Storm Scene after J. Linnell.</item>
<item>The Battle of Borodino after G. Jones, R.A.</item>
<item>Country Cousins after R. Redgrave, A.R.A.</item>
<item>Crossing the Ford after Sir A. W. Callcott, R.A.</item>
<item>A Greek Girl after C. L. Eastlake, R.A.</item>
<item>The Church of St. Paul at Antwerp D. Roberts, R.A.</item>
<item>Lake of Como after C. Stanfield, R.A.</item>
<item>The Casement after G. S. Newton, R.A.</item>
<item>The Crown of Hops after W.F. Witherington, R.A.</item>
<item>Arabs Dividing Spoil after Sir W. Allan, R.A.</item>
<item>Cupid Bound after T. Stothard, R.A.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>AMONG THE WORKS OF SCULPTURE ARE THE FOLLOWING:&mdash;</head>
<item>THE TRIUMPH OF LOVE; by P. MacDowell, R.A.</item>
<item>THE GREEK SLAVE; by Hiram Power.</item>
<item>ST. GEORGE AND THE DRAGON; by W. Wyon, R.A.</item>
<item>THE GRACES; by E. H. Baily, R.A.</item>
<item>DANCING GIRL REPOSING; by W.C. Marshall, A.R.A.</item>
<item>DEATH AND SLEEP; by M. S. Watson.</item>
</list>
<p>Of these each Monthly Part, as heretofore, will contain Two, together with one work in Sculpture&mdash;original and from some famous British work&mdash;and, usually, about Fifty Engravings on Wood&mdash;comprising portraits of British Painters and Sculptors; Passages from the Poets, examples of genius and fancy of many eminent artists; Models of Antique Beauty; Original Designs for Manufacturers; Examples of Meritorious Objects in Manufactured Art, actually executed; and Selections from the most useful models or finest works produced in the principal cities of the Continent.</p>
<p>The Letterpress is contributed by many of the most eminent writers upon Art in England and of the Continent. The large circulation of the Journal enables the Editor to obtain the best assistance of the pen as of the pencil, so as to exhibit the results of knowledge and experience, and the practicability of improvements, in all matters essential to the Artist, instructive to the Amateur, profitable to the Manufacturer, and interesting to the Public.</p>
<closer>LONDON: GEORGE VIRTUE, 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW GIFT BOOKS FOR THE YOUNG.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Nearly Ready, in Super Royal</hi> 16<hi rend="italics">mo, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. Cloth, Gilt Edges,</hi>
<lb/> THE JUVENILE CALENDAR <lb/> And Zodiac of Flowers.</p>
<p>BY MRS. T. K. HERVEY.</p>
<p>WITH EMBLEMATIC ILLUSTRATIONS BY RICHARD DOYLE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Also, in Foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, Cloth Gilt, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s., with Numerous Engravings,</hi>
<lb/> THE ILLUSTRATED YEAR-BOOK OF WONDERS, <lb/> Events, and Discoveries.</p>
<p>EDITED BY A POPULAR WRITER.</p>
<closer>LONDON: ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; Co., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<opener>NEW MONTHLY WORK, BY MRS. ELLIS; <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;SOCIAL DISTINCTION; OR, HEARTS AND HOMES.&rdquo;<lb/><hi rend="italics">Now Ready, the First Number, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s., to be continued Monthly,</hi>
<lb/> MRS. ELLIS'S</opener><head>MORNING CALL;</head><p>A Cable Book of Literature and Art: <lb/>Being a new and original Miscellany, especially written and arranged for the instruction and entertainment of the Ladies of the British Empire. It will be conducted by MRS. ELLIS, and open with a new work of fiction, descriptive of domestic life, from her admired pen. Tales and Sketches by the ablest authors of the day will appear in its pages, which will be further illustrated with engravings from paintings by the most eminent modern artists, embracing everything that can interest the Mother, the Wife, and the Daughter; in connection with the Fine Arts and Elegant Literature.</p>
<closer>JOHN &amp; FREDERICK TALLIS, LONDON AND NEW YORK.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just Published, Second Edition, Enlarged, with Portrait of the Author; Cloth, Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>RUINS OF MANY LANDS.</head>
<p>A PILGRIMAGE. BY NICHOLAS MICHELL.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;Babylon&mdash;Nineveh&mdash;Petra&mdash;Egypt&mdash;Ruined Cities of America&mdash;Rock-Temples of India&mdash;Athens&mdash;Corinth&mdash;Rome&mdash;Pompeii&mdash;South of France&mdash;Ephesus&mdash;Baalbec&mdash;Palmyra&mdash;Persepolis&mdash;Jerusalem, &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Author opens to us new and delightful fields for contemplation and study, and whether we wander with him through Egypt's &lsquo;templed vale,&rsquo; to the ruined cities of Mexico, the rock-temples or India, or Athens, Patmyra, and Pompeii, we are always fascinated by his clear and fervid style, and the elevating character of his sentiments.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Most heartily do we rejoice to see a second and an enlarged edition of Mr. Michell's remarkable work.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">New Monthly Magazine.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Ideas more refined, poetic beauties more richly developed, and classic knowledge more extensive, we scarcely remember to have seen. The work is most valuable.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Cambridge Independent Press.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;This remarkable and interesting production must be deemed a standard composition wherever the English language is understood. It is an extraordinary volume.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser,</hi> 17th Nov.</p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM TEGG, and Co., Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SOWERBY'S ENGLISH BOTANY,</head><p>Re-Issue in Monthly Parts, at 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Part 30 of the above is now ready; as are also Vols. I. and II., containing, together, upwards of 420 Plates and Descriptions, at 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 19<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per Volume, boards. Copies of Vols. I. to VII., comprising the Flowering Plants, in neat Boards, well adapted for Presents, (this Work being the only complete Illustrated Flora of this or any country) at 14<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> the set.</p>
<closer>To be had of the Proprietor, JUDITH SOWERBY, 3, Mead Place, Lambeth, and of all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>LAUGH WHILE YOU CAN!</head>
<p>New Song for the Season.</p>
<p>DEDICATED TO ALL SUFFERERS IN MIND, BODY, AND POCKET.</p>
<p>BY HENRY FARE. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Better than champagne for raising the spirits of a dull party.&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;This author has the stuff in him.&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;We heartily welcome Mr. Fare&mdash;the Philosophy of his songs is undeniable.&rdquo; For other favourable notices, see <hi rend="italics">Herald, Daily News, Despatch,</hi> &amp;c.; also, <hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette,</hi> Oct. 26.&mdash;Posted free for 36 stamps.</p>
<closer>LIBRARY, 1, EDWARD'S TERRACE, KENSINGTON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">On the</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">rd January,</hi> 1850, <hi rend="italics">will be published, to be continued Weekly,</hi>
<lb/> No. I. OF</opener><head>THE DOMESTIC ECONOMIST; <lb/> AND <lb/> ADVISER IN EVERY BRANCH OF THE FAMILY ESTABLISHMENT.</head>
<p>CONDUCTED BY GEORGE W. JOHNSON, ESQ.</p>
<p>EDITOR OF &ldquo;THE COTTAGE GARDENER,&rdquo; ETC.</p>
<list>
<item>HOUSEHOLD MANAGEMENT, by the Authoress of &ldquo;My Flowers,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Our Village Walks,&rdquo; in THE COTTAGE GARDENER.</item>
<item>SANITARY ARRANGEMENT OF OUR DWELLINGS, by Cuthbert W. JOHNSON, Esq., F.R.S.</item>
<item>FAMILY COOKERY, by a well-known Authoress.</item>
<item>ECONOMICS OF TRAVELLING AND EMIGRATION, by S. Sidney, Esq., Editor of &ldquo;The Emigrant's Journal.&rdquo;</item>
<item>DOMESTIC MEDICINE, by a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh.</item>
<item>HOUSEHOLD FURNITURE AND DECORATION, by an Artist.</item>
<item>THE ECONOMY OF THE STABLE AND THE YARD, by Mr. W. C. Spooner, M.R.V.C., Author of &ldquo;The Foot of the Horse.&rdquo;</item>
<item>DAIRYING FOR A HOUSEHOLD, by a Lincolnshire Dairy Farmer.</item>
<item>THE ECONOMY OF THE WORK-TABLE AND TOILET, by Mrs. Savage, Authoress of &ldquo;The Fancy Needlework Instructor,&rdquo; &amp;c.</item>
<item>MANAGEMENT OF DOMESTIC ANIMALS, by Mr. Spooner; a Lincolnshire Farmer; and Mr. Sidney.</item>
<item>SCIENCE APPLIED TO EVERY-DAY LIFE, by C. F. GOWER, Esq., Author of &ldquo;The Scientific Phenomena of Domestic Life.&rdquo;</item>
<item>OUR SPORTS AND PASTIMES, by a Fellow of New College.</item>
</list><p>The above departments will comprise all subjects connected with Family Economy, Education, Travelling and Health; including Recipes relative to every household requirement.</p>
<p>WITHOUT entangling ourselves in political enquiries, as to the cause of the difficulties in which all classes are occasionally involved.&mdash;without grappling with questions of free trade and unequal taxation,&mdash;without pausing to enquire whether, or to what extent, our countrymen ought to seek aid from the Legislature,&mdash;it is our purpose to attend them along another path: that path which they hitherto have successfully trod, and which every Briton delights to pursue&mdash;the path of independence&mdash;with no other support, under the blessing of God, than their own clear head, and their own strong arm.</p>
<p>We are neither wise enough nor weak enough to attempt to teach them how to use those heads and arms in their respective avocations&mdash;here we should have to be pupils, not teachers; but we do intend to place before our readers such knowledge as, but for our pages, might remain unknown for years except to the discoverers and their immediate neighbours.</p>
<p>If we do not teach how to earn, we shall do that which is equally important&mdash;we shall show how to save. Not a class in all British Society but will find in our pages suggestions available either for the management of their establishments both within doors and without, the preparation for their food, or the cure of the bodily disarrangements both of themselves and of their domestic animals.</p>
<p>To aid us in our purpose, those who do not find in our pages the information they require in the several economic departments wherein we profess to be instructors, have only to furnish us with their queries, and we promise to them speedy and well advised replies.</p>
<p>Thus we hope to be useful in the field, the yard, and the stall&mdash;but our utility will not be restricted to these; we hope to have held out to us many kind and gentle hands to welcome us for what we may have to suggest for the kitchen, the dairy, the wardrobe, and the parlour. We hope to bring knowledge that may be acceptable to the daughters and wives of England&mdash;those, without whose aid man may labour, but not thrive&mdash;may have a house, and not a home; for where such helpmates are not, the quiet untiring pleasures of one's own fire-side&mdash;the real meaning of &ldquo;British comfort&rdquo;&mdash;are never known. We hope to be the means of reminding those helpmates of what may be done for the best beneath their roof-tree, both in health and in sickness&mdash;both for ornament and for use&mdash;and though, generally, they may be too well skilled in housewifery for us to impart to them great, as well as good suggestions, yet we shall not be unrewarded if we are useful in many trifles&mdash;for he has not had much experience of life who has not learned that small savings, small comforts, and small pleasures, make up the fulness and the overflowing of a successful and happy existence.</p>
<p>That we may achieve what we purpose, we have obtained the aid of those whose names appear arranged beneath our title&mdash;and we see in them, and in our good cause, an earnest of success. Our coadjutors are an assemblage of those who are not only sound in head, but sound at heart&mdash;those who, in their several departments, have carried out in the broad daylight what they have studied by the aid of the lamp; and, above all, we may add that they are those who have long been known as having never dipped their pens in gall, and who, though well loving the jewels of life, are not altogether &ldquo;of the earth&mdash;earthy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>THE DOMESTIC ECONOMIST will contain sixteen pages of the same size as THE COTTAGE GARDENER, and will be published every Thursday, price 2<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or 3<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> stamped for free transmission by Post. It will also be issued in Monthly Parts, All communications to be directed to &ldquo;THE EDITOR OF &lsquo;THE DOMESTIC ECONOMIST,&rsquo; at the Publishers', WILLIAM S. ORR &amp; CO.'S, 2, AMEN CORNER, LONDON.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>LONDON: WILLIAM S. ORR &amp; CO., AMEN CORNER, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<p><hi rend="italics">Will be published, early in January,</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">vols. imperial</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, with</hi> 50 <hi rend="italics">plates, handsomely bound in cloth</hi>
<lb/> &pound;2 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>WANDERINGS OF A PILGRIM, <lb/> IN SEARCH OF THE PICTURESQUE.</p>
<p>DURING FOUR-AND-TWENTY YEARS IN THE EAST; WITH REVELATIONS OF LIFE IN THE ZENANA.</p>
<p>BY <gap reason="Arabic characters"/></p>
<p>ILLUSTRATED WITH SKETCHES FROM NATURE.</p>
<closer>PELHAM RICHARDSON, 23, CORNHILL.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>This day, Second Edition, revised, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> cloth, <lb/> gilt edges.</opener>
<head>THE <lb/> ART OF CONVERSATION.</head>
<p>By CAPTAIN ORLANDO SABERTASH.</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Though conversation in its better part,</l>
<l>May be esteemed a gift and not an art,</l>
<l>Yet much depends, as in the tiller's toil,</l>
<l>On culture and the sowing of the soil.&rdquo;</l>
<signed><hi rend="italics">Cowper.</hi></signed>
</lg>
<closer>London: T. BOSWORTH, 215, Regent-street.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Seventh edition, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or with 30 maps on <lb/> steel, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head>A SCHOOL GEOGRAPHY.</head>
<p>BY JAMES CORNWELL, PH.D.</p>
<p>Also by the same, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> plain, or 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> coloured, <lb/> A SCHOOL ATLAS.</p>
<p>Consisting of 30 beautifully executed maps on steel, <lb/> in which is found every place mentioned in the <lb/> Author's &ldquo;School Geography.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>London: SIMPKIN, MARSHALL &amp; Co.; HAMILTON, <lb/> ADAMS &amp; Co.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW WORK BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;HOME <lb/> INFLUENCE.&rdquo;</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Nearly ready, in one vol., foolscap</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo,</hi> <lb/> WOMAN'S FRIENDSHIP; <lb/> A STORY OF DOMESTIC LIFE.</p>
<p>BY GRACE AGUILAR..</p>
<p>&ldquo;To show us how divine a thing A Woman may be made.&rdquo;</p>
<p>WORDSWORTH.</p>
<closer>London: GROOMBRIDGE &amp; SONS, Publishers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just published, in 1 vol. 8vo, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></opener>
<head>HOMOEOPATHY IN ACUTE DISEASES,</head><p>by STEPHEN YELDHAM M.R.C.S. &ldquo;A Book for the people.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Albion.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;The best that has appeared on Homoeopathy for a long time past.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Brit. Jour. Homoeopathy.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Scientifically interesting and <hi rend="italics">practically useful.&rdquo;&mdash;Weekly Times.</hi></p>
<closer>BAILLIERE, REGENT ST.; AYLOTT &amp; Co., 8, PATER-NOSTER ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>PRICE ONE FLORIN EACH.</head>
<p>The HAIR. Beware of Acids! All oils have a powerful acid in them. This truth may be rendered apparent by putting a drop upon copper, a green cankerous rust will soon appear. This acid is, of all things, the most injurious to the skin of the head, upon the healthiness of which mainly depends the existence of a fine head of Hair. MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT is not oil or grease, strictly, but is an exact resemblance of the peculiar matter with which nature supplies the Hair, and which will, if applied as directed in a Treatise on the Hair sold with each pot, restore the Hair from any injury it may have received from improper treatment, and speedily render it vigorous, abundant, and beautiful. In an elegant pot, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>MILTON'S HAIR LUBRICANT is sold in elegant Toilet pots, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each. Any Bookseller in the country can procure it in his weekly parcel.</p>
<p>The Wholesale Agents in London are Messrs. BARCLAY and Co., Farringdon-street.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="9" id="p9"/>
<head>WATERLOW AND SONS,</head><p>WHOLESALE AND RETAIL MANUFACTURING STATIONERS, <lb/> 65, 66, 67, &amp; 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</p>
<p>No man of business should write a letter, or transmit any document of importance, without keeping a copy of it. The additional labour of copying by hand, caused by the great increase in correspondence induced by cheap postage, may be entirely saved; as twenty letters may be copied in five minutes by WATERLOW &amp; SONS'</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="13">
<head>Improved Patent Copying Machines.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Lever Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Machine. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> 1st quality, Screw. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Screw Mach. wrt. iron beam. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Mahogany Tables. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> Damping Boxes. </cell>
<cell> Copying Books. 4to, Type-Paged. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> LARGE 4to </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 0s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;2 </cell>
<cell> 10s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 3s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;3 </cell>
<cell> 15s. </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> 11s. </cell>
<cell> 500 leaves, 8s. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> FOOLSCAP FOLIO </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 750 leaves, 10 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> POST FOLIO </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 1,000 leaves, 12 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The above Presses are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged if any fault is discovered.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>WRITING PAPERS.</head>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Commercial Letter, per Ream </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office Letter </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Large Blue Wove Office, superior </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Bath Letter </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">Very Best</hi> Cream Laid Letter </cell>
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> and 11 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">Very Best</hi> Cream, large </cell>
<cell> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Laid Foolscap </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine Laid Foolscap 36 lines </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">Note Paper Half the Price of Letter.</hi> </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="10">
<row role="label">
<cell> ENVELOPES. </cell>
<cell cols="4">Per 1000. </cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell cols="2">3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell cols="2">3 letter sizes. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream Laid, very best </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 11 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="7" cols="10">
<row role="label">
<cell> Adhesive Envelopes. Embossed with Iuitials or Devices. </cell>
<cell cols="4">Per 1000. </cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell><cell cols="2">3 note sizes. </cell>
<cell cols="2">3 letter sizes. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell><cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fine </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Extra Superfine </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Blue or Cream </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>SPECIAL DIES sunk for Coats of Arms, Crests and Devices of every description, from 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> up wards.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>Whatman's Original Turkey Mill Drawing Paper.</head>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial single quire at </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial 5 quires at </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Imperial per ream at </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant, single quire at </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant, 5 quires at </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Double Elephant, per ream at </cell>
<cell> 9 </cell>
<cell> 12 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Continuous Drawing Cartridge, 54 inches wide, 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per yard run. Retree English Tracing Paper, <lb/> 30 inches by 40 inches, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>LEON'S FRENCH TRACING PAPER.</head>
<p>The superior texture and transparency of this paper will be manifest to the Artist upon the first trial. It is highly esteemed on the Continent, and has already obtained the patronage of the first Engineers of this Country. It may be had in continuous lengths of 21&frac12; yards&mdash; 40 inches wide, at 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per piece, or 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per piece run, or 30 inches by 40 inches, 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per quire. Samples will be forwarded free upon application to Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, who are appointed sole Agents for England.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>IMPROVED PATENT ACCOUNT BOOKS,</head><p>Manufactured of the best material on the premises. Contracts taken for the supply of large establishments and exporters; or tenders given for any particular book or sets of books that may be required.</p>
<closer>WATERLOW AND SONS, <lb/> Wholesale and Retail Stationers, Account Book Manufacturers, <lb/> Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65, to 68, London Wall, and 49, Parliament Street, London.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="10" id="p10"/>
<head>Warren's Sketches of Character.</head>
<p>MR. WARREN, <lb/> Of 9, GREAT COLLEGE STREET, <lb/> WESTMINSTER, <lb/> Continues with immense success to delineate the <lb/> CHARACTER of Individuals from their HAND-WRITING.</p>
<p>Specimens of Writing, with the fee of Thirteen Postage-stamps, and a mention of the applicant's sex to be addressed as above.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR or INVISIBLE PERUKE.</head>
<p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. Browne, 47, FENCHURCH-ST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the head in the manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell>
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell>
<cell> Inches. </cell>
<cell> Eighths. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell>
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the head to where the Hair grows </cell>
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DEFORMITIES OF THE CHEST AND SPINE.</head>
<p>EAGLAND'S INVISIBLE SPINE SUPPORT, under the Patronage of Her Majesty's Surgeons, &amp;c.&mdash;Ladies suffering from spinal deviations and their injurious consequences are solicited to inspect Mr. EAGLAND'S newly-invented and inimitable SPINAL SUPPORTS. Their beautiful simplicity, extreme lightness, and their efficiency as a remedial agent, have proved them superior to any others; indeed, they have become eminently successful. They are also completely imperceptible, conceal the defects (without padding) from the most scrutinising observer, and never fail to confer immediate relief. Mr. E. has the pleasure to add that he is empowered to refer to ladies of the first respectability as to the value of his invention, in addition to which he holds testimonials of the highest order. Mrs. EAGLAND is in constant attendance from 12 till 5 daily.</p>
<closer>21, COVENTRY STREET, HAYMARKET.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>KIRBY, BEARD &amp; Co's <lb/> NE PLUS ULTRA NEEDLES, <lb/> WITH LARGE DRILLED EYES, <lb/> &amp; NE PLUS ULTRA PINS, <lb/> WITH PERFECT SOLID HEADS.</p>
<p>Sold by every Draper, &amp;c. in the United Kingdom.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="11" id="p11"/>
<head>For Purifying the Blood and Strengthening <lb/> the Digestive Organs.</head>
<p>FRENCH'S SARSAPARILLA AND CHAMOMILE, a concentrated Fluid Extract of these well known valuable Medicines. It is suited for either sex, and will prove a certain cure for Indigestion, Loss of Appetite, Dimness of Sight. Fainting Fits, Wasting of the Flesh, Languor, Skin Diseases, Rheumatic and Nervous Affections, and all Impurities of Blood caused by unhealthy climates, too sedentary a life, dissipation, and other causes. However debilitated the system, or deep-rooted the disease, by the diligent use of this purifying Medicine the energies of the whole nervous system will be augmented, a more powerful and healthy action of every faculty produced, and feebleness, and all the deplorable symptoms of disease will vanish, and strength and health be restored to the feeble and afflicted by its restorative properties.&mdash;Prepared only by W. A. FRENCH, 309, Holborn, two doors west of Chancerylane. Price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> and 22<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BEAUTY.&mdash;</head><p>The thorn that veils the primrose from our view is not more invidious in Nature than superfluous Hair on the Face, Neck, and Arms of Beauty. HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER is the most certain and elegant preparation for its removal&mdash;the <hi rend="italics">genuine</hi> is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. HOGARD&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor, by Mr. Hooper, Chemist, 24, Russell Street, Covent Garden, and by all respectable perfumers, in packets, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> Double ditto, 7<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> or by post, free for 50 or 88 Postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DIETETIC COCOA.&mdash;</head><p>Dyspeptics and persons of delicate constitution are strongly recommended to use TAYLOR BROTHERS' DIETETIC COCOA, as being very superior to any preparation of the Cocoa-nut hitherto introduced. This article is manufactured on a peculiar principle, by which the oily portions of the nut are neutralised, at the same time its flavour, purity, and nutritious properties are maintained. It is an essential article of diet for those under homoeopathic treatment, agrees with the most delicate digestive organs, is agreeable and soothing to the nervous system, and proves at the same time both invigorating and refreshing.&mdash;Sold retail, in 1lb., &frac12;lb., and &frac14;lb. tinfoil packets, at 1s. 4d. per lb., by most respectable Grocers and Tea-Dealers, and wholesale by TAYLOR BROTHERS, at their Mills, Brick-lane, and Wentworth-street, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE CONCERTINA easily ACQUIRED.&mdash;</head><p>SIMPSON'S COTTAGE CONCERTINA, with 20 keys, price 42<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi> has a deep rich melodious tone. With Simpson's Book of Instructions any lady or gentleman can teach themselves to play on this fashionable instrument, although they may be previously unacquainted with music. This book is forwarded post free on receipt of 36 postage stamps from Simpson's Concertina Manufactory, 266, Regentstreet. Concertinas lent on hire, repaired, and exchanged.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>KNOW THYSELF!&mdash;</head><p>Professor BLENKINSOP'S method of describing the CHARACTER Of persons from their HAND-WRITING never fails, being founded on Philosophical principles. A specimen of the ordinary Writing, stating Age, Sex, and Profession, enclosing 13 uncut Postage Stamps, will ensure an unerring description of the mental and moral qualities of the writer, pointing out gifts and defects hitherto unsuspected, with their probable influence on the future life.</p>
<closer>Address, DR. BLENKINSOP, 10, Lancaster Place, Waterloo Bridge, London.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>DECLARATION of a Dutch Soldier who fought at Waterloo cured by HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.&mdash;</head><p>&ldquo;I publicly state that Professor Holloway's Pills and Ointment have cured me of several ulcerous sores, which had their origin in imperfectly healed wounds received in the battle of Waterloo. The pain was of constant duration; and I was confined to my bed always during the harvest months. I have now for two years been enjoying the best of health, solely in consequence of using Holloway's Pills and Ointment, which cured me in a very short time: in gratitude for which I publish this testimony. (Signed) I. DE SWART, of Lent on the Vossepels, near Nymegen, Holland, 4th October, 1849.&rdquo;&mdash;Sold by all druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>INDIGESTION AVOIDED.</head>
<p>MESSRS. HARRIS AND SAUNDERS. Importers of the Everlent&aelig; Arabian Food, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> per lb., and sole manufacturers of the Arabian Digestive Biscuits, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> and 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per packet. W. Herapath, Esq. in his analysis says &ldquo;It is a nourishing food without giving any tendency to constipation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Wholesale Agents, DIETRICHSEN &amp; HANNAY, <lb/> 63, Oxford St., London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, AND PELISSES;</head><p>In all the New Materials and prevailing Styles, a large portion of which are expressly adapted for School Wear, at SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, LONDON (between the Bank and Finsbury Square).</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS constantly on view, from the useful dress at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> medium, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">t</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> handsome, 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 21<hi rend="italics">s</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> up to the richest goods made in Silk Velvets. Three, Four, and Five Guineas.</p>
<p>HOLLAND DRESSES of all kinds. Pinafores, 10&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Frocks, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi>; ditto, long sleeves, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> Blouses, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>MANTLES, PALETOTS, CLOAKS, JACKETS, and SPENCERS, in great variety, adapted for all ages, two years and upwards.</p>
<p>INFANTS' CLOAKS, HOODS, HATS, and BONNETS, LONG and SHORT ROBES, French Cambric Caps, Day and Night Gowns, Robe Blankets, and Squares, Lawn and Cambrie Night Caps, Open and Round Shirts, Trimmed Nursery Baskets, and Bassinets, with a general Stock of BABY LINEN, together with every article usually required for a YOUNG FAMILY: thus obviating the trouble and inconvenience (so long complained of) in going to various shops when JUVENILE CLOTHING is required.</p>
<p>An Illustrated Pamphlet, affording additional information, sent free on the receipt of a paid Letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="12" id="p12"/>
<head>ALPACA UMBRELLAS.</head>
<p>THE economy both in the cost and wear of this Umbrella has been fully borne out by the experience of these last 18 months, and which can be testified by some thousands of purchasers to whom they have given universal satisfaction. They may be obtained of most Umbrella Dealers in the United Kingdom, from 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Patentees, 140, Regent-street, <lb/> 94, Fleet-street, <lb/> 10, Royal Exchange.</p>
<p>Warehouse, 75, Cheapside.</p>
<p>CHEAP SILK UMBRELLAS, from 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each.</p>
<p>The houses licensed for the manufacture of the Alpaca Umbrella, wholesale, are</p>
<list>
<item>Messrs. J. &amp; W. RUTTER, 122, Cheapside.</item>
<item>Messrs. J. MORLAND &amp; SON, 50, Eastcheap.</item>
<item>Messrs. WADDINGTON &amp; SONS, 1, Coleman St.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Under Royal Patronage.<lb/>PERFECT FREEDOM FROM COUGHS IN TEN MINUTES, AND INSTANT RELIEF AND A RAPID CURE OF ASTHMA AND CONSUMPTION, COUGHS, <lb/> COLDS, AND ALL DISORDERS OF THE BREATH AND LUNGS, <lb/> ARE INSURED BY</opener><head>DR. LOCOCK'S PULMONIC WAFERS.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Small books, containing many hundreds of properly authenticated Testimonials, may be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">had from every Agent.</hi></p>
<div3>
<head>For Clearing the Voice, and Relieving <lb/> the Heart and Lungs.</head>
<p>Extract of a letter from Mr. N. W. Thomas, Fowey, <lb/> January 6, 1849.</p>
<p>Gentlemen.&mdash;I do not approve of Patent Medicines generally, but in respect to &ldquo;Dr. Locock's Pulmonic Wafers.&rdquo; I recommend them strongly, and from experience can vouch for their efficacy in clearing the voice, and easing the action of the Lungs, where respiration is impeded by an excess of mucus or inflammation.</p>
<p>Their sedative qualities in diseases of the heart are also great, without causing irritation or other symptoms incident to the use of opium and other usual remedies. (Signed) N. W. THOMAS, Chemist, Fowey.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>Another Cure of a long-standing <lb/> Asthmatic Cough.</head>
<p>Extract of a letter from Mr. W. Tomlinson, Bookseller, <lb/> Stodman-street. Newark.</p>
<p>Gentlemen.&mdash;I can fully prove the value of Locock's Wafers, as a near relative of mine was speedily cured of a most severe asthmatic cough of long duration by them, and many other cures equally astonishing constantly come under my notice, so that I can confidently recommend them, which I do with very great pleasure.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) <lb/> W. TOMLINSON.</signed>
</closer>
</div3><div3>
<p>TO SINGERS AND PUBLIC SPEAKERS they are invaluable, as in a few hours they remove all hoarseness, and wonderfully increase the power and flexibility of the voice.</p>
<p>They have a pleasant taste. Price 1s. 1&frac12;d., 2s. 9d., and 11s. per box.</p>
<p>AGENTS: DA SILVA &amp; CO., 1, Bride-lane, Fleet-street, London. Sold by all Medicine Vendors. <lb/> OF WHOM ALSO MAY BE HAD <lb/> DR. LOCOCK'S FEMALE WAFERS.</p>
<p>HAVE NO TASTE OF MEDICINE. The only Medicine recommended to be taken by Females!</p>
<p>Price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> per Box. Beware of Imitations.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="[i]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">I fall into captivity.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="[ii]"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">Uriah persists in hovering near us, at the dinner party.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pv" n="[iii]"/>
<opener>11, BOUVERIE STREET, <hi rend="italics">December</hi> 27, 1849.</opener>
<p>MESSRS. BRADBURY and EVANS beg to announce that in MARCH NEXT will be published, PRICE TWOPENCE, the First Number of a <lb/> NEW WEEKLY MISCELLANY <lb/> Of General Literature, <lb/> Conducted by Mr. CHARLES DICKENS; <lb/> Designed for the Entertainment and Instruction of all classes of readers, and to help in the discussion of the most important social questions of the time.</p>
</div1>


<div1 type="chapter">
<pb n="257" id="p257"/>
<head>[THE 
<lb/> PERSONAL HISTORY AND EXPERIENCE <lb/> OF <lb/> DAVID COPPERFIELD THE YOUNGER.]
</head>
<div2 type="chapter"><head>CHAPTER XXV. <lb/> GOOD AND BAD ANGELS.</head>
<p>I WAS going out at my door on the morning after that deplorable day of headache, sickness, and repentance, with an odd confusion in my mind relative to the date of my dinner-party, as if a body of Titans had taken an enormous lever and pushed the day before yesterday some months back, when I saw a ticket-porter coming up-stairs, with a letter in his hand. He was taking his time about his errand, then; but when he saw me on the top of the staircase, looking at him over the bannisters, he swung into a trot, and came up panting as if he had run himself into a state of exhaustion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;T. Copperfield, Esquire,&rdquo; said the ticket-porter, touching his hat with his little cane.</p>
<p>I could scarcely lay claim to the name: I was so disturbed by the conviction that the letter came from Agnes. However, I told him I was T. Copperfield, Esquire, and he believed it, and gave me the letter, which he said required an answer. I shut him out on the landing to wait for the answer, and went into my chambers again, in such a nervous state that I was fain to lay the letter down on my breakfast-table, and familiarise myself with the outside of it a little, before I could resolve to break the seal.</p>
<p>I found, when I did open it, that it was a very kind note, containing no reference to my condition at the theatre. All it said, was, &ldquo;My dear Trotwood. I am staying at the house of papa's agent, Mr. Waterbrook, in Ely-place, Holborn. Will you come and see me to-day, at any time you like to appoint? Ever yours affectionately, AGNES.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It took me such a long time to write an answer at all to my satisfaction, that I don't know what the ticket-porter can have thought, unless he thought I was learning to write. I must have written half a dozen answers at least. I began one, &ldquo;How can I ever hope, my dear Agnes, to efface from your remembrance the disgusting impression&rdquo;&mdash;there I didn't like it, and then I tore it up. I began another, &ldquo;Shakspeare has observed, my dear Agnes, how strange it is that a man should put an enemy into his mouth&rdquo;&mdash;that reminded me of Markham, and it got no farther. I even tried poetry. I began one note, in a six-syllable line, &ldquo;Oh do not remember&rdquo;&mdash;but that associated itself with the fifth of November, and became an absurdity. After many attempts, I wrote, &ldquo;My dear Agnes. Your letter is like you, and what could I say of it that would be higher praise than that? I will come at four o'clock. Affectionately and sorrowfully, T. C.&rdquo; With this missive (which I was in twenty minds at once about recalling, as soon as it was out of my hands), the ticket-porter at last departed.</p>
<p>If the day were half as tremendous to any other professional gentleman in Doctors' Commons as it was to me, I sincerely believe he made some
<pb n="258" id="p258"/>
expiation for his share in that rotten old ecclesiastical cheese. Although I left the office at half-past three, and was prowling about the place of appointment within a few minutes afterwards, the appointed time was exceeded by a full quarter of an hour, according to the clock of St. Andrew's, Holborn, before I could muster up sufficient desperation to pull the private bell-handle let into the left-hand door-post of Mr. Waterbrook's house.</p>
<p>The professional business of Mr. Waterbrook's establishment was done on the ground-floor, and the genteel business (of which there was a good deal) in the upper part of the building. I was shown into a pretty but rather close drawing-room, and there sat Agnes, netting a purse.</p>
<p>She looked so quiet and good, and reminded me so strongly of my airy fresh school days at Canterbury, and the sodden, smoky, stupid wretch I had been the other night, that, nobody being by, I yielded to my self-reproach and shame, and&mdash;in short, made a fool of myself. I cannot deny that I shed tears. To this hour I am undecided whether it was upon the whole the wisest thing I could have done, or the most ridiculous.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If it had been any one but you, Agnes,&rdquo; said I, turning away my head, &ldquo;I should not have minded it half so much. But that it should have been you who saw me! I almost wish I had been dead, first.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She put her hand&mdash;its touch was like no other hand&mdash;upon my arm for a moment; and felt so befriended and comforted, that I could not help moving it to my lips, and gratefully kissing it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sit down,&rdquo; said Agnes, cheerfully. &ldquo;Don't be unhappy, Trotwood. If you cannot confidently trust me, whom will you trust?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, Agnes!&rdquo; I returned. &ldquo;You are my good Angel!&rdquo;</p>
<p>She smiled rather sadly, I thought, and shook her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Agnes, my good Angel! Always my good Angel!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If I were, indeed, Trotwood,&rdquo; she returned, &ldquo;there is one thing that I should set my heart on very much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I looked at her inquiringly; but already with a foreknowledge of her meaning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;On warning you,&rdquo; said Agnes, with a steady glance, &ldquo;against your bad Angel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Agnes,&rdquo; I began, &ldquo;if you mean Steerforth&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do, Trotwood,&rdquo; she returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, Agnes, you wrong him very much. He my bad Angel, or anyone's! He, anything but a guide, a support, and a friend to me! My dear Agnes! Now, is it not unjust, and unlike you, to judge him from what you saw of me the other night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do not judge him from what I saw of you the other night,&rdquo; she quietly replied.</p>
<p>&ldquo;From what, then?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;From many things&mdash;trifles in themselves, but they do not seem to me to be so, when they are put together. I judge him, partly from your account of him, Trotwood, and your character, and the influence he has over you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was always something in her modest voice that seemed to touch a chord within me, answering to that sound alone. It was always earnest; but when it was very earnest, as it was now, there was a thrill
<pb n="259" id="p259"/>
in it that quite subdued me. I sat looking at her as she cast her eyes down on her work; I sat seeming still to listen to her; and Steerforth, in spite of all my attachment to him, darkened in that tone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is very bold in me,&rdquo; said Agnes, looking up again, &ldquo;who have lived in such seclusion, and can know so little of the world, to give you my advice so confidently, or even to have this strong opinion. But I know in what it is engendered, Trotwood,&mdash;in how true a remembrance of our having grown up together, and in how true an interest in all relating to you. It is that which makes me bold. I am certain that what I say is right. I am quite sure it is. I feel as if it were some one else speaking to you, and not I, when I caution you that you have made a dangerous friend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Again I looked at her, again I listened to her after she was silent, and again his image, though it was still fixed in my heart, darkened.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am not so unreasonable as to expect,&rdquo; said Agnes, resuming her usual tone, after a little while, &ldquo;that you will, or that you can, at once change any sentiment that has become a conviction to you; least of all a sentiment that is rooted in your trusting disposition. You ought not hastily to do that. I only ask you, Trotwood, if you ever think of me&mdash;I mean&rdquo; with a quiet smile, for I was going to interrupt her, and she knew why &ldquo;as often as you think of me&mdash;to think of what I have said Do you forgive me for all this?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I will forgive you, Agnes,&rdquo; I replied, &ldquo;when you come to do Steerforth justice, and to like him as well as I do.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not until then?&rdquo; said Agnes.</p>
<p>I saw a passing shadow on her face when I made this mention of him but she returned my smile, and we were again as unreserved in our mutual confidence as of old.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And when, Agnes,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;will you forgive me the other night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I recall it,&rdquo; said Agnes.</p>
<p>She would have dismissed the subject so, but I was too full of it to allow that, and insisted on telling her how it happened that I had disgraced myself, and what chain of accidental circumstances had had the theatre for its final link. It was a great relief to me to do this, and to enlarge on the obligation that I owed to Steerforth for his care of me when I was unable to take care of myself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You must not forget,&rdquo; said Agnes, calmly changing the conversation as soon as I had concluded, &ldquo;that you are always to tell me, not only when you fall into trouble, but when you fall in love. Who has succeeded to Miss Larkins, Trotwood?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No one, Agnes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some one, Trotwood,&rdquo; said Agnes, laughing, and holding up her finger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, Agnes, upon my word! There is a lady, certainly, at Mrs. Steerforth's house, who is very clever, and whom I like to talk to&mdash;Miss Dartle&mdash;but I don't adore her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Agnes laughed again at her own penetration, and told me that if I were faithful to her in my confidence she thought she should keep a little register of my violent attachments, with the date, duration, and termination of each, like the table of the reigns of the kings and queens, in the History of England. Then she asked me if I had seen Uriah.</p>
<pb n="260" id="p260"/>
<p>&ldquo;Uriah Heep?&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;No. Is he in London?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He comes to the office down-stairs, every day,&rdquo; returned Agnes. &ldquo;He was in London a week before me. I am afraid on disagreeable business, Trotwood.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;On some business that makes you uneasy, Agnes, I see,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;What can that be?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Agnes laid aside her work, and replied, folding her hands upon one another, and looking pensively at me out of those beautiful soft eyes of hers:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I believe he is going to enter into partnership with papa.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What? Uriah? That mean, fawning fellow, worm himself into such promotion?&rdquo; I cried, indignantly. &ldquo;Have you made no remonstrance about it, Agnes? Consider what a connexion it is likely to be. You must speak out. You must not allow your father to take such a mad step. You must prevent it, Agnes, while there's time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Still looking at me, Agnes shook her head while I was speaking, with a faint smile at my warmth: and then replied:</p>
<p>&ldquo;You remember our last conversation about papa? It was not long after that&mdash;not more than two or three days&mdash;when he gave me the first intimation of what I tell you. It was sad to see him struggling between his desire to represent it to me as a matter of choice on his part, and his inability to conceal that it was forced upon him. I felt very sorry.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Forced upon him, Agnes! Who forces it upon him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Uriah,&rdquo; she replied, after a moment's hesitation, &ldquo;has made himself indispensable to papa. He is subtle and watchful. He has mastered papa's weaknesses, fostered them, and taken advantage of them, until&mdash;to say all that I mean in a word, Trotwood, until papa is afraid of him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was more that she might have said; more that she knew, or that she suspected; I clearly saw. I could not give her pain by asking what it was, for I knew that she withheld it from me, to spare her father. It had long been going on to this, I was sensible: yes, I could not but feel, on the least reflection, that it had been going on to this for a long time. I remained silent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;His ascendancy over papa,&rdquo; said Agnes, &ldquo;is very great. He professes humility and gratitude&mdash;with truth, perhaps: I hope so&mdash;but his position is really one of power, and I fear he makes a hard use of his power.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said he was a hound, which, at the moment, was a great satisfaction to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At the time I speak of, as the time when papa spoke to me,&rdquo; pursued Agnes, &ldquo;he had told papa that he was going away; that he was very sorry, and unwilling to leave, but that he had better prospects. Papa was very much depressed then, and more bowed down by care than ever you or I have seen him; but he seemed relieved by this expedient of the partnership, though at the same time he seemed hurt by it and ashamed of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how did you receive it, Agnes?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I did, Trotwood,&rdquo; she replied, &ldquo;what I hope was right. Feeling sure that it was necessary for papa's peace that the sacrifice should be made, I entreated him to make it. I said it would lighten the load of his life&mdash;I hope it will!&mdash;and that it would give me increased opportunities of being his companion. Oh, Trotwood!&rdquo; cried Agnes, putting her hands before her face, as her tears started on it, &ldquo;I almost feel as if I
<pb n="261" id="p261"/>
had been papa's enemy, instead of his loving child. For I know how he has altered, in his devotion to me. I know how he has narrowed the circle of his sympathies and duties, in the concentration of his whole mind upon me. I know what a multitude of things he has shut out for my sake, and how his anxious thoughts of me have shadowed his life, and weakened his strength and energy, by turning them always upon one idea. If I could ever set this right! If I could ever work out his restoration, as I have so innocently been the cause of his decline!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I had never before seen Agnes cry. I had seen tears in her eyes when I had brought new honours home from school, and I had seen them there when we last spoke about her father, and I had seen her turn her gentle head aside when we took leave of one another; but I had never seen her grieve like this. It made me so sorry that I could only say, in a foolish, helpless manner, &ldquo;Pray, Agnes, don't! Don't, my dear sister!&rsquo;</p>
<p>But Agnes was too superior to me in character and purpose, as I know well now, whatever I might know or not know then, to be long in need of my entreaties. The beautiful, calm manner, which makes her so different in my remembrance from everybody else, came back again, as if a cloud had passed from a serene sky.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We are not likely to remain alone much longer,&rdquo; said Agnes, &ldquo;and while I have an opportunity, let me earnestly entreat you, Trotwood, to be friendly to Uriah. Don't repel him. Don't resent (as I think you have a general disposition to do) what may be uncongenial to you in him. He may not deserve it, for we know no certain ill of him. In any case, think first of papa and me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Agnes had no time to say more, for the room-door opened, and Mrs. Waterbrook, who was a large lady&mdash;or who wore a large dress: I don't exactly know which, for I don't know which was dress and which was lady&mdash;came sailing in. I had a dim recollection of having seen her at the theatre, as if I had seen her in a pale magic lantern; but she appeared to remember me perfectly, and still to suspect me of being in a state of intoxication.</p>
<p>Finding by degrees, however, that I was sober, and (I hope) that I was a modest young gentleman, Mrs. Waterbrook softened towards me considerably, and inquired, firstly, if I went much into the parks, and secondly, if I went much into society. On my replying to both these questions in the negative, it occurred to me that I fell again in her good opinion; but she concealed the fact gracefully, and invited me to dinner next day. I accepted the invitation, and took my leave; making a call on Uriah in the office as I went out, and leaving a card for him in his absence.</p>
<p>When I went to dinner next day, and, on the street-door being opened, plunged into a vapour-bath of haunch of mutton, I divined that I was not the only guest; for I immediately identified the ticket-porter in disguise, assisting the family servant, and waiting at the foot of the stairs to carry up my name. He looked, to the best of his ability, when he asked me for it confidentially, as if he had never seen me before; but well did I know him, and well did he know me. Conscience made cowards of us both.</p>
<p>I found Mr. Waterbrook to be a middle-aged gentleman, with a short throat, and a good deal of shirt-collar, who only wanted a black nose to
<pb n="262" id="p262"/>
be the portrait of a pug-dog. He told me he was happy to have the honour of making my acquaintance; and when I had paid my homage to Mrs. Waterbrook, presented me, with much ceremony, to a very awful lady in a black velvet dress, and a great black velvet hat, whom I remember as looking like a near relation of Hamlet's&mdash;say his aunt.</p>
<p>Mrs. Henry Spiker was this lady's name; and her husband was there too: so cold a man, that his head, instead of being grey, seemed to be sprinkled with hoar-frost. Immense deference was shown to the Henry Spikers, male and female; which Agnes told me was on account of Mr. Henry Spiker being solicitor to something or to somebody, I forget what or which, remotely connected with the Treasury.</p>
<p>I found Uriah Heep among the company, in a suit of black, and in deep humility. He told me, when I shook hands with him, that he was proud to be noticed by me, and that he really felt obliged to me for my condescension. I could have wished he had been less obliged to me, for he hovered about me in his gratitude all the rest of the evening; and whenever I said a word to Agnes, was sure, with his shadowless eyes and cadaverous face, to be looking gauntly down upon us from behind.</p>
<p>There were other guests&mdash;all iced for the occasion, as it struck me, like the wine. But, there was one who attracted my attention before he came in, on account of my hearing him announced as Mr. Traddles! My mind flew back to Salem House; and could it be Tommy, I thought, who used to draw the skeletons!</p>
<p>I looked for Mr. Traddles with unusual interest. He was a sober, steady-looking young man of retiring manners, with a comic head of hair, and eyes that were rather wide open; and he got into an obscure corner so soon, that I had some difficulty in making him out. At length I had a good view of him, and either my vision deceived me, or it was the old unfortunate Tommy.</p>
<p>I made my way to Mr. Waterbrook, and said, that I believe I had the pleasure of seeing an old schoolfellow there.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed?&rdquo; said Mr. Waterbrook, surprised. &ldquo;You are too young to have been at school with Mr. Henry Spiker?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, I don't mean him!&rdquo; I returned. &ldquo;I mean the gentleman named Traddles.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! Aye, aye! Indeed!&rdquo; said my host, with much diminished interest. &ldquo;Possibly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If it's really the same person,&rdquo; said I, glancing towards him, &ldquo;it was at a place called Salem House where we were together, and he was an excellent fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes. Traddles is a good fellow,&rdquo; returned my host, nodding his head with an air of toleration. &ldquo;Traddles is quite a good fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's a curious coincidence,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is really,&rdquo; returned my host, &ldquo;quite a coincidence, that Traddles should be here at all: as Traddles was only invited this morning, when the place at table, intended to be occupied by Mrs. Henry Spiker's brother, became vacant, in consequence of his indisposition. A very gentlemanly man, Mrs. Henry Spiker's brother, Mr. Copperfield.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I murmured an assent, which was full of feeling, considering that I knew nothing at all about him; and I inquired what Mr. Traddles was by profession.</p>
<pb n="263" id="p263"/>
<p>&ldquo;Traddles,&rdquo; returned Mr. Waterbrook, &ldquo;is a young man reading for the bar. Yes. He is quite a good fellow&mdash;nobody's enemy but his own.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is he his own enemy?&rdquo; said I, sorry to hear this.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; returned Mr. Waterbrook, pursing up his mouth, and playing with his watch-chain, in a comfortable, prosperous sort of way. &ldquo;I should say he was one of those men who stand in their own light. Yes, I should say he would never, for example, be worth five hundred pound. Traddles was recommended to me, by a professional friend. Oh yes. Yes. He has a kind of talent, for drawing briefs, and stating a case in writing, plainly. I am able to throw something in Traddles's way, in the course of the year; something&mdash;for him&mdash;considerable. Oh yes. Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was much impressed by the extremely comfortable and satisfied manner, in which Mr. Waterbrook delivered himself of this little word &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; every now and then. There was wonderful expression in it. It completely conveyed the idea of a man who had been born, not to say with a silver spoon, but with a scaling-ladder, and had gone on mounting all the heights of life one after another, until now he looked, from the top of the fortifications, with the eye of a philosopher and a patron, on the people down in the trenches.</p>
<p>My reflections on this theme were still in progress when dinner was announced. Mr. Waterbrook went down with Hamlet's aunt. Mr. Henry Spiker took Mrs. Waterbrook. Agnes, whom I should have liked to take myself, was given to a simpering fellow with weak legs. Uriah, Traddles, and I, as the junior part of the company, went down last, how we could. I was not so vexed at losing Agnes as I might have been since it gave me an opportunity of making myself known to Traddles on the stairs, who greeted me with great fervor: while Uriah writhed with such obtrusive satisfaction and self-abasement, that I could gladly have pitched him over the bannisters.</p>
<p>Traddles and I were separated at table, being billeted in two remote corners: he in the glare of a red velvet lady; I, in the gloom of Hamlet's aunt. The dinner was very long, and the conversation was about the Aristocracy&mdash;and Blood. Mrs. Waterbrook repeatedly told us, that if she had a weakness, it was Blood.</p>
<p>It occurred to me several times that we should have got on better, if we had not been quite so genteel. We were so exceedingly genteel, that our scope was very limited. A Mr. and Mrs. Gulpidge were of the party, who had something to do at second-hand (at least, Mr. Gulpidge had) with the law business of the Bank; and what with the Bank, and what with the Treasury, we were as exclusive as the Court Circular. To mend the matter, Hamlet's aunt had the family failing of indulging in soliloquy, and held forth in a desultory manner, by herself, on every topic that was introduced. These were few enough, to be sure; but as we always fell back upon Blood, she had as wide a field for abstract speculation as her nephew himself.</p>
<p>We might have been a party of Ogres, the conversation assumed such a sanguine complexion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I confess I am of Mrs. Waterbrook's opinion,&rdquo; said Mr. Waterbrook, with his wine-glass at his eye. &ldquo;Other things are all very well in their way, but give me Blood!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! There is nothing,&rdquo; observed Hamlet's aunt, &ldquo;so satisfactory to one! There is nothing that is so much one's <hi rend="italics">beau-ideal</hi> of&mdash;of all that sort
<pb n="264" id="p264"/>
of thing, speaking generally. There are some low minds (not many, I am happy to believe, but there are <hi rend="italics">some</hi>) that would prefer to do what <hi rend="italics">I</hi> should call bow down before idols. Positively Idols! Before services, intellect, and so on. But these are intangible points. Blood is not so. Wee see Blood in a nose, and we know it. We meet with it in a chin, and we say, &lsquo;There it is! That's Blood!&rsquo; It is an actual matter of fact. We point it out. It admits of no doubt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The simpering fellow with the weak legs, who had taken Agnes down, stated the question more decisively yet, I thought.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, you know, deuce take it,&rdquo; said this gentleman, looking round the board with an imbecile smile, &ldquo;we can't forego Blood, you know. We must have Blood, you know. Some young fellows, you know, may be a little behind their station, perhaps, in point of education and behaviour, and may go a little wrong, you know, and get themselves and other people into a variety of fixes&mdash;and all that&mdash;but deuce take it, it's delightful to reflect that they've got Blood in 'em! Myself, I'd rather at any time be knocked down by a man who had got Blood in him, than I'd be picked up by a man who hadn't!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This sentiment, as compressing the general question into a nutshell, gave the utmost satisfaction, and brought the gentleman into great notice until the ladies retired. After that, I observed that Mr. Gulpidge and Mr. Henry Spiker, who had hitherto been very distant, entered into a defensive alliance against us, the common enemy, and exchanged a mysterious dialogue across the table for our defeat and overthrow.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That affair of the first bond for four thousand five hundred pounds has not taken the course that was expected, Gulpidge,&rdquo; said Mr. Henry Spiker.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you mean the D. of A.'s?&rdquo; said Mr. Spiker.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The C. of B.'s?&rdquo; said Mr. Gulpidge.</p>
<p>Mr. Spiker raised his eye-brows, and looked much concerned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When the question was referred to Lord&mdash;I needn't name him,&rdquo; said Mr. Gulpidge, checking himself&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I understand,&rdquo; said Mr. Spiker, &ldquo;N.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Gulpidge darkly nodded&mdash;&ldquo;was referred to him, his answer was, &lsquo;Money, or no release.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lord bless my soul!&rdquo; cried Mr. Spiker.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Money, or no release,&rsquo; &rdquo; repeated Mr. Gulpidge firmly. &ldquo;The next in reversion&mdash;you understand me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;K.&rdquo; said Mr. Spiker, with an ominous look.</p>
<p>&ldquo;&mdash;K. then positively refused to sign. He was attended at New-market for that purpose, and he point-blank refused to do it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Spiker was so interested, that he became quite stony.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So the matter rests at this hour,&rdquo; said Mr. Gulpidge, throwing himself back in his chair. &ldquo;Our friend Waterbrook will excuse me if I forbear to explain myself generally, on account of the magnitude of the interests involved.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Waterbrook was only too happy, as it appeared to me, to have such interests, and such names, even hinted at, across his table. He assumed an expression of gloomy intelligence (though I am persuaded he knew no more about the discussion than I did), and highly approved of the discretion that had been observed. Mr. Spiker, after the receipt of such
<pb n="265" id="p265"/>
a confidence, naturally desired to favor his friend with a confidence of his own; therefore the foregoing dialogue was succeeded by another, in which it was Mr. Gulpidge's turn to be surprised, and that by another in which the surprise came round to Mr. Spiker's turn again, and so on, turn and turn about. All this time we, the outsiders, remained oppressed by the tremendous interests involved in the conversation; and our host regarded us with pride, as the victims of a salutary awe and astonishment.</p>
<p>I was very glad indeed to get up-stairs to Agnes, and to talk with her in a corner, and to introduce Traddles to her, who was shy, but agreeable, and the same good-natured creature still. As he was obliged to leave early, on account of going away next morning for a month, I had not nearly so much conversation with him as I could have wished; but we exchanged addresses, and promised ourselves the pleasure of another meeting when he should come back to town. He was greatly interested to hear that I knew Steerforth, and spoke of him with such warmth that I made him tell Agnes what he thought of him. But Agnes only looked at me the while, and very slightly shook her head when only I observed her.</p>
<p>As she was not among people with whom I believed she could be very much at home, I was almost glad to hear that she was going away within a few days, though I was sorry at the prospect of parting from her again so soon. This caused me to remain until all the company were gone. Conversing with her, and hearing her sing, was such a delightful reminder to me of my happy life in the grave old house she had made so beautiful, that I could have remained there half the night; but, having no excuse for staying any longer, when the lights of Mr. Waterbrook's society were all snuffed out, I took my leave very much against my inclination. I felt then, more than ever, that she was my better Angel; and if I thought of her sweet face and placid smile, as though they had shone on me from some removed being, like an Angel, I hope I thought no harm.</p>
<p>I have said that the company were all gone; but I ought to have excepted Uriah, whom I don't include in that denomination, and who had never ceased to hover near us. He was close behind me when I went down-stairs. He was close beside me, when I walked away from the house, slowly fitting his long skeleton fingers into the still longer fingers of a great Guy Fawkes pair of gloves.</p>
<p>It was in no disposition for Uriah's company, but in remembrance of the entreaty Agnes had made to me, that I asked him if he would come home to my rooms, and have some coffee.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, really, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he rejoined,&mdash;&ldquo;I beg your pardon, Mister Copperfield, but the other comes so natural,&mdash;I don't like that you should put a constraint upon yourself to ask a numble person like me to your ouse.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is no constraint in the case,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;Will you come?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should like to, very much,&rdquo; replied Uriah, with a writhe.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, then, come along!&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>I could not help being rather short with him, but he appeared not to mind it. We went the nearest way, without conversing much upon the road; and he was so humble in respect of those scarecrow gloves, that he was still putting them on, and seemed to have made no advance in that labour, when we got to my place.</p>
<p>I led him up the dark stairs, to prevent his knocking his head against
<pb n="266" id="p266"/>
anything, and really his damp cold hand felt so like a frog in mine, that I was tempted to drop it and run away. Agnes and hospitality prevailed, however, and I conducted him to my fireside. When I lighted my candles, he fell into meek transports with the room that was revealed to him; and when I heated the coffee in an unassuming block-tin vessel, in which Mrs. Crupp delighted to prepare it (chiefly, I believe, because it was not intended for the purpose, being a shaving-pot, and because there was a patent invention of great price mouldering away in the pantry), he professed so much emotion, that I could joyfully have scalded him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, really, Master Copperfield,&mdash;I mean Mister Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah, &ldquo;to see you waiting upon me is what I never could have expected! But, one way and another, so many things happen to me which I never could have expected, I am sure, in my umble station, that it seems to rain blessings on my ed. You have heard something, I des-say, of a change in my expectations, Master Copperfield,&mdash;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> should say, Mister Copperfield?&rdquo;</p>
<p>As he sat on my sofa, with his long knees drawn up under his coffee-cup, his hat and gloves upon the ground close to him, his spoon going softly round and round, his shadowless red eyes, which looked as if they had scorched their lashes off, turned towards me without looking at me, the disagreeable dints I have formerly described in his nostrils coming and going with his breath, and a snaky undulation pervading his frame from his chin to his boots, I decided in my own mind that I disliked him intensely. It made me very uncomfortable to have him for a guest, for I was young then, and unused to disguise what I so strongly felt.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have heard something, I des-say, of a change in my expectations, Master Copperfield,&mdash;I should say, Mister Copperfield?&rdquo; observed Uriah.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;something.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! I thought Miss Agnes would know of it!&rdquo; he quietly returned. &ldquo;I'm glad to find Miss Agnes knows of it. Oh, thank you, Master&mdash;Mister Copperfield!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I could have thrown my bootjack at him (it lay ready on the rug), for having entrapped me into the disclosure of anything concerning Agnes, however immaterial. But I only drank my coffee.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a prophet you have shown yourself, Mister Copperfield!&rdquo; pursued Uriah. &ldquo;Dear me, what a prophet you have proved yourself to be! Don't you remember saying to me once, that perhaps I should be a partner in Mr. Wickfield's business, and perhaps it might be Wickfield and Heep! <hi rend="italics">You</hi> may not recollect it; but when a person is umble, Master Copperfield, a person treasures such things up!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I recollect talking about it,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;though I certainly did not think it very likely then.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! who <hi rend="italics">would</hi> have thought it likely, Mister Copperfield!&rdquo; returned Uriah, enthusiastically, &ldquo;I am sure I didn't myself. I recollect saying with my own lips that I was much too umble. So I considered myself really and truly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He sat, with that carved grin on his face, looking at the fire, as I looked at him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But the umblest persons, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he presently resumed, &ldquo;may be the instruments of good. I am glad to think I have been the
<pb n="267" id="p267"/>
instrument of good to Mr. Wickfield, and that I may be more so. Oh what a worthy man he is, Mister Copperfield, but how imprudent he has been!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry to hear it,&rdquo; said I. I could not help adding, rather pointedly, &ldquo;on all accounts.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Decidedly so, Mister Copperfield,&rdquo; replied Uriah. &ldquo;On all accounts. Miss Agnes's above all! You don't remember your own eloquent expressions, Master Copperfield; but <hi rend="italics">I</hi> remember how you said one day that everybody must admire her, and how I thanked you for it! You have forgot that, I have no doubt, Master Copperfield?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said I, drily.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh how glad I am, you have not!&rdquo; exclaimed Uriah. &ldquo;To think that you should be the first to kindle the sparks of ambition in my umble breast, and that you've not forgot it! Oh!&mdash;Would you excuse me asking for a cup more coffee?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Something in the emphasis he laid upon the kindling of those sparks, and something in the glance he directed at me as he said it, had made me start as if I had seen him illuminated by a blaze of light. Recalled by his request, preferred in quite another tone of voice, I did the honors of the shaving-pot; but I did them with an unsteadiness of hand, a sudden sense of being no match for him, and a perplexed suspicious anxiety as to what he might be going to say next, which I felt could not escape his observation.</p>
<p>He said nothing at all. He stirred his coffee round and round, he sipped it, he felt his chin softly with his grisly hand, he looked at the fire, he looked about the room, he gasped rather than smiled at me, he writhed and undulated about, in his deferential servility, he stirred and sipped again, but he left the renewal of the conversation to me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So, Mr. Wickfield,&rdquo; said I, at last, &ldquo;who is worth five hundred of you&mdash;or me;&rdquo; for my life, I think I could not have helped dividing that part of the sentence with an awkward jerk; &ldquo;has been imprudent, has he, Mr. Heep?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh very imprudent indeed, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; returned Uriah, sighing modestly. &ldquo;Oh very much so! But I wish you'd call me Uriah, if you please. It's like old times.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well! Uriah,&rdquo; said I, bolting it out with some difficulty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you!&rdquo; he returned, with fervor. &ldquo;Thank you, Master Copperfield! It's like the blowing of old breezes or the ringing of old bellses to hear <hi rend="italics">you</hi> say Uriah. I beg your pardon. Was I making any observation?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;About Mr. Wickfield,&rdquo; I suggested.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! Yes, truly,&rdquo; said Uriah. &ldquo;Ah! Great imprudence, Master Copperfield. It's a topic that I wouldn't touch upon, to any soul but you. Even to you I can only touch upon it, and no more. If any one else had been in my place during the last few years, by this time he would have had Mr. Wickfield (oh, what a worthy man he is, Master Copperfield, too!) under his thumb. Un&mdash;der&mdash;his thumb,&rdquo; said Uriah, very slowly, as he stretched out his cruel-looking hand above my table, and pressed his own thumb down upon it, until it shook, and shook the room.</p>
<p>If I had been obliged to look at him with his splay foot on Mr. Wickfield's head, I think I could scarcely have hated him more.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear, yes, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he proceeded, in a soft voice, most
<pb n="268" id="p268"/>
remarkably contrasting with the action of his thumb, which did not diminish its hard pressure in the least degree, &ldquo;there's no doubt of it. There would have been loss, disgrace, I don't know what all. Mr. Wickfield knows it. I am the umble instrument of umbly serving him, and he puts me on an eminence I hardly could have hoped to reach. How thankful should I be!&rdquo; With his face turned towards me, as he finished, but without looking at me, he took his crooked thumb off the spot where he had planted it, and slowly and thoughtfully scraped his lank jaw with it, as if he were shaving himself.</p>
<p>I recollect well how indignantly my heart beat, as I saw his crafty face, with the appropriately red light of the fire upon it, preparing for something else.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he began&mdash;&ldquo;but am I keeping you up?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are not keeping me up. I generally go to bed late.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Master Copperfield! I have risen from my umble station since first you used to address me, it is true; but I am umble still. I hope I never shall be otherwise than umble. You will not think the worse of my umbleness, if I make a little confidence to you, Master Copperfield? Will you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, no,&rdquo; said I, with an effort.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you!&rdquo; He took out his pocket-handkerchief, and began wiping the palms of his hands. &ldquo;Miss Agnes, Master Copperfield&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Uriah?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, how pleasant to be called Uriah, spontaneously!&rdquo; he cried; and gave himself a jerk, like a convulsive fish. &ldquo;You thought her looking very beautiful to-night, Master Copperfield?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought her looking as she always does: superior, in all respects, to every one around her,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, thank you! It's so true!&rdquo; he cried. &ldquo;Oh, thank you very much for that!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all,&rdquo; I said, loftily. &ldquo;There is no reason why you should thank me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why that, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; said Uriah, &ldquo;is, in fact, the confidence that I am going to take the liberty of reposing. Umble as I am,&rdquo; he wiped his hands harder, and looked at them and at the fire by turns, &ldquo;umble as my mother is, and lowly as our poor but honest roof has ever been, the image of Miss Agnes (I don't mind trusting you with my secret, Master Copperfield, for I have always overflowed towards you since the first moment I had the pleasure of beholding you in a poney-shay) has been in my breast for years. Oh, Master Copperfield, with what a pure affection do I love the ground my Agnes walks on!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I believe I had a delirious idea of seizing the red-hot poker out of the fire, and running him through with it. It went from me with a shock, like a ball fired from a rifle: but the image of Agnes, outraged by so much as a thought of this red-headed animal's, remained in my mind when I looked at him, sitting all awry as if his mean soul griped his body, and made me giddy. He seemed to swell and grow before my eyes; the room seemed full of the echoes of his voice; and the strange feeling (to which, perhaps, no one is quite a stranger) that all this had occurred before, at some indefinite time, and that I knew what he was going to say next, took possession of me.</p>
<pb n="269" id="p269"/>
<p>A timely observation of the sense of power that there was in his face, did more to bring back to my remembrance the entreaty of Agnes, in its full force, than any effort I could have made. I asked him, with a better appearance of composure than I could have thought possible a minute before, whether he had made his feelings known to Agnes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, no, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; he returned; &ldquo;oh dear, no! Not to any one but you. You see I am only just emerging from my lowly station. I rest a good deal of hope on her observing how useful I am to her father (for I trust to be very useful to him, indeed, Master Copperfield), and how I smooth the way for him, and keep him straight. She's so much attached to her father, Master Copperfield (oh what a lovely thing it is in a daughter!), that I think she may come, on his account, to be kind to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I fathomed the depth of the rascal's whole scheme, and understood why he laid it bare.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you'll have the goodness to keep my secret, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; he pursued, &ldquo;and not, in general, to go against me, I shall take it as a particular favor. You wouldn't wish to make unpleasantness. I know what a friendly heart you've got; but having only known me on my umble footing (on my umblest, I should say, for I am very umble still), you might, unbeknown, go against me rather, with my Agnes. I call her mine, you see, Master Copperfield. There's a song that says, &lsquo;I'd crowns resign, to call her mine!&rsquo; I hope to do it, one of these days.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dear Agnes! So much too loving and too good for any one that I could think of, was it possible that she was reserved to be the wife of such a wretch as this!</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's no hurry at present, you know, Master Copperfield,&rdquo; Uriah proceeded, in his slimy way, as I sat gazing at him, with this thought in my mind. &ldquo;My Agnes is very young still; and mother and me will have to work our way upards, and make a good many new arrangements, before it would be quite convenient. So I shall have time gradually to make her familiar with my hopes, as opportunities offer. Oh, I'm so much obliged to you for this confidence! Oh, it's such a relief, you can't think, to know that you understand our situation, and are certain (as you wouldn't wish to make unpleasantness in the family) not to go against me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He took the hand which I dared not withhold, and having given it a damp squeeze, referred to his pale-faced watch.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;it's past one. The moments slip away so, in the confidence of old times, Master Copperfield, that it's almost half-past one!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I answered that I had thought it was later. Not that I had really thought so, but because my conversational powers were effectually scattered.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; he said, considering. &ldquo;The ouse that I am stopping at&mdash;a sort of a private hotel and boarding ouse, Master Copperfield, near the New River ed&mdash;will have gone to bed these two hours.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;that there is only one bed here, and that I&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, don't think of mentioning beds, Master Copperfield!&rdquo; he rejoined ecstatically, drawing up one leg. &ldquo;But <hi rend="italics">would</hi> you have any objections to my laying down before the fire?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If it comes to that,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;pray take my bed, and I'll lie down before the fire.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="270" id="p270"/>
<p>His repudiation of this offer was almost shrill enough, in the excess of its surprise and humility, to have penetrated to the ears of Mrs. Crupp; then sleeping, I suppose, in a distant chamber, situated at about the level of low water mark, soothed in her slumbers by the ticking of an incorrigible clock, to which she always referred me when we had any little difference on the score of punctuality, and which was never less than three quarters of an hour too slow, and had always been put right in the morning by the best authorities. As no arguments I could urge, in my bewildered condition, had the least effect upon his modesty in inducing him to accept my bed-room, I was obliged to make the best arrangements I could, for his repose before the fire. The mattress of the sofa (which was a great deal too short for his lank figure), the sofa pillows, a blanket, the table-cover, a clean breakfast-cloth, and a great coat, made him a bed and covering, for which he was more than thankful. Having lent him a nightcap, which he put on at once, and in which he made such an awful figure that I have never worn one since, I left him to his rest.</p>
<p>I never shall forget that night. I never shall forget how I turned and tumbled; how I wearied myself with thinking about Agnes and this creature; how I considered what could I do, and what ought I to do; how I could come to no other conclusion than that the best course for her peace, was to do nothing, and to keep to myself what I had heard. If I went to sleep for a few moments, the image of Agnes with her tender eyes, and of her father looking fondly on her, as I had so often seen him look, arose before me with appealing faces, and filled me with vague terrors. When I awoke, the recollection that Uriah was lying in the next room sat heavy on me like a waking night-mare; and oppressed me with a leaden dread, as if I had had some meaner quality of devil for a lodger.</p>
<p>The poker got into my dozing thoughts besides, and wouldn't come out. I thought, between sleeping and waking, that it was still red hot, and I had snatched it out of the fire, and run him through the body. I was so haunted at last by the idea, though I knew there was nothing in it, that I stole into the next room to look at him. There I saw him, lying on his back, with his legs extending to I don't know where, gurglings taking place in his throat, stoppages in his nose, and his mouth open like a postoffice. He was so much worse in reality than in my distempered fancy, that afterwards I was attracted to him in very repulsion, and could not help wandering in and out every half hour or so, and taking another look at him. Still, the long, long night seemed heavy and hopeless as ever, and no promise of day was in the murky sky.</p>
<p>When I saw him going down stairs early in the morning (for, thank Heaven! he would not stay to breakfast), it appeared to me as if the night was going away in his person. When I went out to the Commons, I charged Mrs. Crupp with particular directions to leave the windows open, that my sitting-room might be aired, and purged of his presence.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="271" id="p271"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXVI. <lb/> I FALL INTO CAPTIVITY.</head>
<p>I SAW no more of Uriah Heep, until the day when Agnes left town. I was at the coach-office to take leave of her and see her go; and there was he, returning to Canterbury by the same conveyance. It was some small satisfaction to me to observe his spare, short-waisted, high-shouldered, mulberry-coloured great-coat perched up, in company with an umbrella like a small tent, on the edge of the back seat on the roof, while Agnes was, of course, inside; but what I underwent in my efforts to be friendly with him, while Agnes looked on, perhaps deserved that little recompense. At the coach-window, as at the dinner-party, he hovered about us without a moment's intermission, like a great vulture: gorging himself on every syllable that I said to Agnes, or Agnes said to me.</p>
<p>In the state of trouble into which his disclosure by my fire had thrown me, I had thought very much of the words Agnes had used in reference to the partnership. &ldquo;I did what I hope was right. Feeling sure that it was necessary for papa's peace that the sacrifice should be made, I entreated him to make it.&rdquo; A miserable foreboding that she would yield to, and sustain herself by, the same feeling in reference to any sacrifice for his sake, had oppressed me ever since. I knew how she loved him. I knew what the devotion of her nature was. I knew from her own lips that she regarded herself as the innocent cause of his errors, and as owing him a great debt she ardently desired to pay. I had no consolation in seeing how different she was from this detestable Rufus with the mulberry-coloured great-coat, for I felt that in the very difference between them, in the self-denial of her pure soul and the sordid baseness of his, the greatest danger lay. All this, doubtless, he knew thoroughly, and had, in his cunning, considered well.</p>
<p>Yet, I was so certain that the prospect of such a sacrifice afar off, must destroy the happiness of Agnes; and I was so sure, from her manner, of its being unseen by her then, and having cast no shadow on her yet; that I could as soon have injured her, as given her any warning of what impended. Thus it was that we parted without explanation: she waving her hand and smiling farewell from the coach-window; her evil genius writhing on the roof, as if he had her in his clutches and triumphed.</p>
<p>I could not get over this farewell glimpse of them for a long time. When Agnes wrote to tell me of her safe arrival, I was as miserable as when I saw her going away. Whenever I fell into a thoughtful state, this subject was sure to present itself, and all my uneasiness was sure to be redoubled. Hardly a night passed without my dreaming of it. It became a part of my life, and as inseparable from my life as my own head.</p>
<p>I had ample leisure to refine upon my uneasiness: for Steerforth was at Oxford, as he wrote to me, and when I was not at the Commons, I was very much alone. I believe I had at this time some lurking distrust of
<pb n="272" id="p272"/>
Steerforth. I wrote to him most affectionately in reply to his, but I think I was glad, upon the whole, that he could not come to London just then. I suspect the truth to be, that the influence of Agnes was upon me, undisturbed by the sight of him; and that it was the more powerful with me, because she had so large a share in my thoughts and interest.</p>
<p>In the meantime, days and weeks slipped away. I was articled to Spenlow and Jorkins. I had ninety pounds a year (exclusive of my houserent and sundry collateral matters) from my aunt. My rooms were engaged for twelve months certain: and though I still found them dreary of an evening, and the evenings long, I could settle down into a state of equable low spirits, and resign myself to coffee; which I seem, on looking back, to have taken by the gallon at about this period of my existence. At about this time, too, I made three discoveries: first, that Mrs. Crupp was a martyr to a curious disorder called &ldquo;the spazzums,&rdquo; which was generally accompanied with inflammation of the nose, and required to be constantly treated with peppermint; secondly, that something peculiar in the temperature of my pantry, made the brandy-bottles burst; thirdly, that I was alone in the world, and much given to record that circumstance in fragments of English versification.</p>
<p>On the day when I was articled, no festivity took place, beyond my having sandwiches and sherry into the office for the clerks, and going alone to the theatre at night. I went to see &ldquo;The Stranger&rdquo; as a Doctors' Commons sort of play, and was so dreadfully cut up, that I hardly knew myself in my own glass when I got home. Mr. Spenlow remarked, on this occasion, when we concluded our business, that he should have been happy to have seen me at his house at Norwood to celebrate our becoming connected, but for his domestic arrangements being in some disorder, on account of the expected return of his daughter from finishing her education at Paris. But, he intimated that when she came home he should hope to have the pleasure of entertaining me. I knew that he was a widower with one daughter, and expressed my acknowledgments.</p>
<p>Mr. Spenlow was as good as his word. In a week or two, he referred to this engagement, and said, that if I would do him the favor to come down next Saturday, and stay till Monday, he would be extremely happy. Of course I said I <hi rend="italics">would</hi> do him the favor; and he was to drive me down in his phaeton, and to bring me back.</p>
<p>When the day arrived, my very carpet-bag was an object of veneration to the stipendiary clerks, to whom the house at Norwood was a sacred mystery. One of them informed me that he had heard that Mr. Spenlow ate entirely off plate and china; and another hinted at champagne being constantly on draught, after the usual custom of table beer. The old clerk with the wig, whose name was Mr. Tiffey, had been down on business several times in the course of his career, and had on each occasion penetrated to the breakfast-parlor. He described it as an apartment of the most sumptuous nature, and said that he had drunk brown East India sherry there, of a quality so precious as to make a man wink.</p>
<p>We had an adjourned cause in the Consistory that day&mdash;about excommunicating a baker who had been objecting in a vestry to a paving-rate&mdash;and as the evidence was just twice the length of Robinson Crusoe, according to a calculation I made, it was rather late in the day before we finished. However, we got him excommunicated for six weeks, and
<pb n="273" id="p273"/>
sentenced in no end of costs; and then the baker's proctor, and the judge, and the advocates on both sides (who were all nearly related), went out of town together, and Mr. Spenlow and I drove away in the phaeton.</p>
<p>The phaeton was a very handsome affair; the horses arched their necks and lifted up their legs as if they knew they belonged to Doctors' Commons. There was a good deal of competition in the Commons on all points of display, and it turned out some very choice equipages then; though I always have considered, and always shall consider, that in my time the great article of competition there was starch: which I think was worn among the proctors to as great an extent as it is in the nature of man to bear.</p>
<p>We were very pleasant, going down, and Mr. Spenlow gave me some hints in reference to my profession. He said it was the genteelest profession in the world, and must on no account be confounded with the profession of a solicitor: being quite another sort of thing, infinitely more exclusive, less mechanical, and more profitable. We took things much more easily in the Commons than they could be taken anywhere else, he observed, and that set us, as a privileged class, apart. He said it was impossible to conceal the disagreeable fact, that we were chiefly employed by solicitors; but he gave me to understand that they were an inferior race of men, universally looked down upon by all proctors of any pretensions.</p>
<p>I asked Mr. Spenlow what he considered the best sort of professional business? He replied, that a good case of a disputed will, where there was a neat little estate of thirty or forty thousand pounds, was, perhaps, the best of all. In such a case, he said, not only were there very pretty pickings in the way of arguments at every stage of the proceedings, and mountains upon mountains of evidence on interrogatory and counter-interrogatory (to say nothing of an appeal lying, first to the Delegates, and then to the Lords); but, the costs being pretty sure to come out of the estate at last, both sides went at it in a lively and spirited manner, and expense was no consideration. Then, he launched into a general eulogium on the Commons. What was to be particularly admired (he said) in the Commons, was its compactness. It was the most conveniently organised place in the world. It was the complete idea of snugness. It lay in a nut-shell. For example: You brought a divorce case, or a restitution case, into the Consistory. Very good. You tried it in the Consistory. You made a quiet little round game of it, among a family group, and you played it out at leisure. Suppose you were not satisfied with the Consistory, what did you do then? Why, you went into the Arches. What was the Arches? The same court, in the same room, with the same bar, and the same practitioners, but another judge, for there the Consistory judge could plead any court-day as an advocate. Well, you played your round game out again. Still you were not satisfied. Very good. What did you do then? Why, you went to the Delegates. Who were the Delegates? Why, the Ecclesiastical Delegates were the advocates without any business, who had looked on at the round game when it was playing in both courts, and had seen the cards shuffled, and cut, and played, and had talked to all the players about it, and now came fresh, as judges, to settle the matter to the satisfaction of everybody! Discontented people might talk of corruption in the Commons, closeness in the Commons, and the necessity of reforming the
<pb n="274" id="p274"/>
Commons, said Mr. Spenlow solemnly, in conclusion; but when the price of wheat per bushel had been highest, the Commons had been busiest; and a man might lay his hand upon his heart, and say this to the whole world,&mdash;&ldquo;Touch the Commons, and down comes the country!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I listened to all this with attention; and though, I must say, I had my doubts whether the country was quite as much obliged to the Commons as Mr. Spenlow made out, I respectfully deferred to his opinion. That about the price of wheat per bushel, I modestly felt was too much for my strength, and quite settled the question. I have never, to this hour, got the better of that bushel of wheat. It has re-appeared to annihilate me, all through my life, in connexion with all kinds of subjects. I don't know now, exactly, what it has to do with me, or what right it has to crush me, on an infinite variety of occasions; but whenever I see my old friend the bushel brought in by the head and shoulders (as he always is, I observe), I give up a subject for lost.</p>
<p>This is a digression. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was not the man to touch the Commons, and bring down the country. I submissively expressed, by my silence, my acquiescence in all I had heard from my superior in years and knowledge; and we talked about &ldquo;The Stranger&rdquo; and the Drama, and the pair of horses, until we came to Mr. Spenlow's gate.</p>
<p>There was a lovely garden to Mr. Spenlow's house; and though that was not the best time of the year for seeing a garden, it was so beautifully kept, that I was quite enchanted. There was a charming lawn, there were clusters of trees, and there were perspective walks that I could just distinguish in the dark, arched over with trellis-work, on which shrubs and flowers grew in the growing season. &ldquo;Here Miss Spenlow walks by herself,&rdquo; I thought. &ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We went into the house, which was cheerfully lighted up, and into a hall where there were all sorts of hats, caps, great-coats, plaids, gloves, whips, and walking-sticks. &ldquo;Where is Miss Dora?&rdquo; said Mr. Spenlow to the servant. &ldquo;Dora!&rdquo; I thought. &ldquo;What a beautiful name!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We turned into a room near at hand (I think it was the identical breakfast-room, made memorable by the brown East Indian Sherry), and I heard a voice say, &ldquo;Mr. Copperfield, my daughter Dora, and my daughter Dora's confidential friend!&rdquo; It was, no doubt, Mr. Spenlow's voice, but I didn't know it, and I didn't care whose it was. All was over in a moment. I had fulfilled my destiny. I was a captive and a slave. I loved Dora Spenlow to distraction!</p>
<p>She was more than human to me. She was a Fairy, a Sylph, I don't know what she was&mdash;any thing that no one ever saw, and every thing that every body ever wanted. I was swallowed up in an abyss of love in an instant. There was no pausing on the brink; no looking down, or looking back; I was gone, headlong, before I had sense to say a word to her.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">&ldquo;I,&rdquo;</hi> observed a well-remembered voice, when I had bowed and murmured something, &ldquo;have seen Mr. Copperfield before.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The speaker was not Dora. No; the confidential friend. Miss Murdstone!</p>
<p>I don't think I was much astonished. To the best of my judgment, no capacity of astonishment was left in me. There was nothing worth mentioning in the material world, but Dora Spenlow, to be astonished about. I said, &ldquo;How do you do, Miss Murdstone? I hope you are
<pb n="275" id="p275"/>
well.&rdquo; She answered, &ldquo;Very well.&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;How is Mr. Murdstone?&rdquo; She replied, &ldquo;My brother is robust, I am obliged to you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Spenlow, who, I suppose, had been surprised to see us recognise each other, then put in his word.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am glad to find,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;Copperfield, that you and Miss Murdstone are already acquainted.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfield and myself,&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, with severe composure, &ldquo;are connexions. We were once slightly acquainted. It was in his childish days. Circumstances have separated us since. I should not have known him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I replied that I should have known her, any where. Which was true enough.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Murdstone has had the goodness,&rdquo; said Mr. Spenlow to me, &ldquo;to accept the office&mdash;if I may so describe it&mdash;of my daughter Dora's confidential friend. My daughter Dora having, unhappily, no mother, Miss Murdstone is obliging enough to become her companion and protector.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A passing thought occurred to me that Miss Murdstone, like the pocket instrument called a life-preserver, was not so much designed for purposes of protection as of assault. But as I had none but passing thoughts for any subject save Dora, I glanced at her, directly afterwards, and was thinking that I saw, in her prettily pettish manner, that she was not very much inclined to be particularly confidential to her companion and protector, when a bell rang, which Mr. Spenlow said was the first dinnerbell, and so carried me off to dress.</p>
<p>The idea of dressing one's self, or doing any thing in the way of action, in that state of love, was a little too ridiculous. I could only sit down before my fire, biting the key of my carpet-bag, and think of the captivating, girlish, bright-eyed lovely Dora. What a form she had, what a face she had, what a graceful, variable, enchanting manner!</p>
<p>The bell rang again so soon that I made a mere scramble of my dressing, instead of the careful operation I could have wished under the circumstances, and went down-stairs. There was some company. Dora was talking to an old gentleman with a grey head. Grey as he was&mdash;and a great-grandfather into the bargain, for he said so&mdash;I was madly jealous of him.</p>
<p>What a state of mind I was in! I was jealous of everybody. I couldn't bear the idea of anybody knowing Mr. Spenlow better than I did. It was torturing to me to hear them talk of occurrences in which I had had no share. When a most amiable person, with a highly polished bald head, asked me across the dinner-table, if that were the first occasion of my seeing the grounds, I could have done anything to him that was savage and revengeful.</p>
<p>I don't remember who was there, except Dora. I have not the least idea what we had for dinner, besides Dora. My impression is, that I dined off Dora, entirely, and sent away half-a-dozen plates untouched. I sat next to her. I talked to her. She had the most delightful little voice, the gayest little laugh, the pleasantest and most fascinating little ways, that ever led a lost youth into hopeless slavery. She was rather diminutive altogether. So much the more precious, I thought.</p>
<p>When she went out of the room with Miss Murdstone (no other ladies were of the party), I fell into a reverie, only disturbed by the cruel apprehension
<pb n="276" id="p276"/>
that Miss Murdstone would disparage me to her. The amiable creature with the polished head told me a long story, which I think was about gardening. I think I heard him say, &ldquo;my gardener,&rdquo; several times. I seemed to pay the deepest attention to him, but I was wandering in a garden of Eden all the while, with Dora.</p>
<p>My apprehensions of being disparaged to the object of my engrossing affection were revived when we went into the drawing-room, by the grim and distant aspect of Miss Murdstone. But I was relieved of them in an unexpected manner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;David Copperfield,&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, beckoning me aside into a window. &ldquo;A word.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I confronted Miss Murdstone alone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;David Copperfield,&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, &ldquo;I need not enlarge upon family circumstances. They are not a tempting subject.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Far from it, ma'am,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Far from it,&rdquo; assented Miss Murdstone. &ldquo;I do not wish to revive the memory of past differences, or of past outrages. I have received outrages from a person&mdash;a female I am sorry to say, for the credit of my sex&mdash;who is not to be mentioned without scorn and disgust; and therefore I would rather not mention her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt very fiery on my aunt's account; but I said it would certainly be better, if Miss Murdstone pleased, <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to mention her. I could not hear her disrespectfully mentioned, I added, without expressing my opinion in a decided tone.</p>
<p>Miss Murdstone shut her eyes, and disdainfully inclined her head; then, slowly opening her eyes, resumed:</p>
<p>&ldquo;David Copperfield, I shall not attempt to disguise the fact, that I formed an unfavorable opinion of you in your childhood. It may have been a mistaken one, or you may have ceased to justify it. That is not in question between us now. I belong to a family remarkable, I believe, for some firmness; and I am not the creature of circumstance or change. I may have my opinion of you. You may have your opinion of me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I inclined my head, in my turn.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But it is not necessary,&rdquo; said Miss Murdstone, &ldquo;that these opinions should come into collision here. Under existing circumstances, it is as well on all accounts that they should not. As the chances of life have brought us together again, and may bring us together on other occasions, I would say let us meet here as distant acquaintances. Family circumstances are a sufficient reason for our only meeting on that footing, and it is quite unnecessary that either of us should make the other the subject of remark. Do you approve of this?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Murdstone,&rdquo; I returned, &ldquo;I think you and Mr. Murdstone used me very cruelly, and treated my mother with great unkindness. I shall always think so, as long as I live. But I quite agree in what you propose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Murdstone shut her eyes again, and bent her head. Then, just touching the back of my hand with the tips of her cold, stiff fingers, she walked away, arranging the little fetters on her wrists and round her neck: which seemed to be the same set, in exactly the same state, as when I had seen her last. These reminded me, in reference to Miss Murdstone's nature, of the fetters over a jail-door; suggesting on the outside, to all beholders, what was to be expected within.</p>
<pb n="277" id="p277"/>
<p>All I know of the rest of the evening is, that I heard the empress of my heart sing enchanted ballads in the French language, generally to the effect that, whatever was the matter, we ought always to dance, Ta ra la Ta ra la! accompanying herself on a glorified instrument, resembling a guitar. That I was lost in blissful delirium. That I refused refreshment. That my soul recoiled from punch particularly. That when Miss Murdstone took her into custody and led her away, she smiled and gave me her delicious hand. That I caught a view of myself in a mirror, looking perfectly imbecile and idiotic. That I retired to bed in a most maudlin state of mind, and got up in a crisis of feeble infatuation.</p>
<p>It was a fine morning, and early, and I thought I would go and take a stroll down one of those wire-arched walks, and indulge my passion by dwelling on her image. On my way through the hall, I encountered her little dog, who was called Jip&mdash;short for Gipsy. I approached him tenderly, for I loved even him; but he showed his whole set of teeth, got under a chair expressly to snarl, and wouldn't hear of the least familiarity.</p>
<p>The garden was cool and solitary. I walked about, wondering what my feelings of happiness would be, if I could ever become engaged to this dear wonder. As to marriage, and fortune, and all that, I believe I was almost as innocently undesigning then, as when I loved little Em'ly. To be allowed to call her &ldquo;Dora,&rdquo; to write to her, to dote upon and worship her, to have reason to think that when she was with other people she was yet mindful of me, seemed to me the summit of human ambition&mdash;I am sure it was the summit of mine. There is no doubt whatever that I was a lackadaisical young spooney; but there was a purity of heart in all this still, that prevents my having quite a contemptuous recollection of it, let me laugh as I may.</p>
<p>I had not been walking long, when I turned a corner, and met her. I tingle again from head to foot as my recollection turns that corner, and my pen shakes in my hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&mdash;are&mdash;out early, Miss Spenlow,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's so stupid at home,&rdquo; she replied, &ldquo;and Miss Murdstone is so absurd! She talks such nonsense about its being necessary for the day to be aired, before I come out. Aired!&rdquo; (She laughed, here, in the most melodious manner). &ldquo;On a Sunday morning, when I don't practise, I must do something. So I told papa last night I <hi rend="italics">must</hi> come out. Besides, it's the brightest time of the whole day. Don't you think so?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I hazarded a bold flight, and said (not without stammering) that it was very bright to me then, though it had been very dark to me a minute before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you mean a compliment?&rdquo; said Dora, &ldquo;or that the weather has really changed?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I stammered worse than before, in replying that I meant no compliment, but the plain truth; though I was not aware of any change having taken place in the weather. It was in the state of my own feelings, I added bashfully: to clench the explanation.</p>
<p>I never saw such curls&mdash;how could I, for there never were such curls!&mdash;as those she shook out to hide her blushes. As to the straw hat and blue ribbons which was on the top of the curls, if I could only have hung it up in my room in Buckingham Street, what a priceless possession it would have been!</p>
<pb n="278" id="p278"/>
<p>&ldquo;You have just come home from Paris,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said she. &ldquo;Have you ever been there?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! I hope you'll go soon. You would like it so much!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Traces of deep-seated anguish appeared in my countenance. That she should hope I would go, that she should think it possible I <hi rend="italics">could</hi> go, was insupportable. I depreciated Paris; I depreciated France. I said I wouldn't leave England, under existing circumstances, for any earthly consideration. Nothing should induce me. In short, she was shaking the curls again, when the little dog came running along the walk to our relief.</p>
<p>He was mortally jealous of me, and persisted in barking at me. She took him up in her arms&mdash;oh my goodness!&mdash;and caressed him, but he insisted upon barking still. He wouldn't let me touch him, when I tried; and then she beat him. It increased my sufferings greatly to see the pats she gave him for punishment on the bridge of his blunt nose, while he winked his eyes, and licked her hand, and still growled within himself like a little double-bass. At length he was quiet&mdash;well he might be with her dimpled chin upon his head!&mdash;and we walked away to look at a greenhouse.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are not very intimate with Miss Murdstone, are you?&rdquo; said Dora.&mdash;&ldquo;My pet!&rdquo;</p>
<p>(The two last words were to the dog. Oh if they had only been to me!)</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; I replied. &ldquo;Not at all so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is a tiresome creature,&rdquo; said Dora pouting. &ldquo;I can't think what papa can have been about, when he chose such a vexatious thing to be my companion. Who wants a protector! I am sure <hi rend="italics">I</hi> don't want a protector. Jip can protect me a great deal better than Miss Murdstone,&mdash;can't you, Jip dear?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He only winked lazily, when she kissed his ball of a head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Papa calls her my confidential friend, but I am sure she is no such thing&mdash;is she, Jip? We are not going to confide in any such cross people, Jip and I. We mean to bestow our confidence where we like, and to find out our own friends, instead of having them found out for us&mdash;don't we, Jip?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Jip made a comfortable noise, in answer, a little like a tea-kettle when it sings. As for me, every word was a new heap of fetters, rivetted above the last.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is very hard, because we have not a kind Mama, that we are to have, instead, a sulky, gloomy old thing like Miss Murdstone, always following us about&mdash;isn't it, Jip? Never mind, Jip. We won't be confidential, and we'll make ourselves as happy as we can in spite of her, and we'll teaze her, and not please her,&mdash;won't we, Jip?&rdquo;</p>
<p>If it had lasted any longer, I think I must have gone down on my knees on the gravel, with the probability before me of grazing them, and of being presently ejected from the premises besides. But, by good fortune the greenhouse was not far off, and these words brought us to it.</p>
<p>It contained quite a show of beautiful geraniums. We loitered along in front of them, and Dora often stopped to admire this one or that one, and I stopped to admire the same one, and Dora, laughing, held the dog up childishly, to smell the flowers; and if we were not all three in Fairyland,
<pb n="279" id="p279"/>
certainly <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was. The scent of a geranium leaf, at this day, strikes me with a half comical half serious wonder as to what change has come over me in a moment; and then I see a straw hat and blue ribbons, and a quantity of curls, and a little black dog being held up, in two slender arms, against a bank of blossoms and bright leaves.</p>
<p>Miss Murdstone had been looking for us. She found us here; and presented her uncongenial cheek, the little wrinkles in it filled with hair-powder, to Dora to be kissed. Then she took Dora's arm in hers, and marched us in to breakfast as if it were a soldier's funeral.</p>
<p>How many cups of tea I drank, because Dora made it, I don't know. But, I perfectly remember that I sat swilling tea until my whole nervous system, if I had had any in those days, must have gone by the board. By-and-by we went to church. Miss Murdstone was between Dora and me in the pew; but I heard her sing, and the congregation vanished. A sermon was delivered&mdash;about Dora, of course&mdash;and I am afraid that is all I know of the service.</p>
<p>We had a quiet day. No company, a walk, a family dinner of four, and an evening of looking over books and pictures; Miss Murdstone with a homily before her, and her eye upon us, keeping guard vigilantly. Ah! little did Mr. Spenlow imagine, when he sat opposite to me after dinner that day, with his pocket-handkerchief over his head, how fervently I was embracing him, in my fancy, as his son-in-law! Little did he think, when I took leave of him at night, that he had just given his full consent to my being engaged to Dora, and that I was invoking blessings on his head!</p>
<p>We departed early in the morning, for we had a Salvage case coming on in the Admiralty Court, requiring a rather accurate knowledge of the whole science of navigation, in which (as we couldn't be expected to know much about those matters in the Commons) the judge had entreated two old Trinity Masters, for charity's sake, to come and help him out. Dora was at the breakfast-table to make the tea again, however; and I had the melancholy pleasure of taking off my hat to her in the phaeton, as she stood on the door-step with Jip in her arms.</p>
<p>What the Admiralty was to me that day; what nonsense I made of our case in my mind, as I listened to it; how I saw &ldquo;DORA&rdquo; engraved upon the blade of the silver oar which they lay upon the table, as the emblem of that high jurisdiction; and how I felt, when Mr. Spenlow went home without me (I had had an insane hope that he might take me back again), as if I were a mariner myself, and the ship to which I belonged had sailed away and left me on a desert island; I shall make no fruitless effort to describe. If that sleepy old court could rouse itself, and present in any visible form the day dreams I have had in it about Dora, it would reveal my truth.</p>
<p>I don't mean the dreams that I dreamed on that day alone, but day after day, from week to week, and term to term. I went there, not to attend to what was going on, but to think about Dora. If I ever bestowed a thought upon the cases, as they dragged their slow length before me, it was only to wonder, in the matrimonial cases (remembering Dora), how it was that married people could ever be otherwise than happy; and, in the Prerogative cases, to consider, if the money in question had been left to me, what were the foremost steps I should immediately have taken in regard to Dora. Within the first week of my passion, I
<pb n="280" id="p280"/>
bought four sumptuous waistcoats &mdash;not for myself; <hi rend="italics">I</hi> had no pride in them; for Dora&mdash;and took to wearing straw-colored kid gloves in the streets, and laid the foundations of all the corns I have ever had. If the boots I wore at that period could only be produced and compared with the natural size of my feet, they would show what the state of my heart was, in a most affecting manner.</p>
<p>And yet, wretched cripple as I made myself by this act of homage to Dora, I walked miles upon miles daily in the hope of seeing her. Not only was I soon as well known on the Norwood Road as the postmen on that beat, but I pervaded London likewise. I walked about the streets where the best shops for ladies were, I haunted the Bazaar like an unquiet spirit, I fagged through the Park again and again, long after I was quite knocked up. Sometimes, at long intervals and on rare occasions, I saw her. Perhaps I saw her glove waved in a carriage window; perhaps I met her, walked with her and Miss Murdstone a little way, and spoke to her. In the latter case I was always very miserable afterwards, to think that I had said nothing to the purpose; or that she had no idea of the extent of my devotion, or that she cared nothing about me. I was always looking out, as may be supposed, for another invitation to Mr. Spenlow's house. I was always being disappointed, for I got none.</p>
<p>Mrs. Crupp must have been a woman of penetration; for when this attachment was but a few weeks old, and I had not had the courage to write more explicitly even to Agnes, than that I had been to Mr. Spenlow's house, &ldquo;whose family,&rdquo; I added, &ldquo;consists of one daughter;&rdquo;&mdash;I say Mrs. Crupp must have been a woman of penetration, for, even in that early stage, she found it out. She came up to me one evening, when I was very low, to ask (she being then afflicted with the disorder I have mentioned) if I could oblige her with a little tincture of cardamums mixed with rhubarb, and flavored with seven drops of the essence of cloves, which was the best remedy for her complaint;&mdash;or, if I had not such a thing by me, with a little brandy, which was the next best. It was not, she remarked, so palatable to her, but it was the next best. As I had never even heard of the first remedy, and always had the second in the closet, I gave Mrs. Crupp a glass of the second, which (that I might have no suspicion of its being devoted to any improper use) she began to take in my presence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cheer up, sir,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, &ldquo;I can't abear to see you so, sir, I'm a mother myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I did not quite perceive the application of this fact to <hi rend="italics">my</hi>self, but I smiled on Mrs. Crupp, as benignly as was in my power.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come, sir,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp. &ldquo;Excuse me. I know what it is, sir. There's a young lady in the case.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crupp?&rdquo; I returned, reddening.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, bless you! Keep a good heart, sir!&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, nodding encouragement. &ldquo;Never say die, sir! If She don't smile upon you, there's a many as will. You're a young gentleman to <hi rend="italics">be</hi> smiled on, Mr. Copperfull, and you must learn your walue, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Crupp always called me Mr. Copperfull: firstly, no doubt, because it was not my name; and secondly, I am inclined to think, in some indistinct association with a washing-day.</p>
<pb n="281" id="p281"/>
<p>&ldquo;What makes you suppose there is any young lady in the case, Mrs. Crupp?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfull,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, with a great deal of feeling, &ldquo;I'm a mother myself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>For some time Mrs. Crupp could only lay her hand upon her nankeen bosom, and fortify herself against returning pain with sips of her medicine. At length she spoke again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When the present set were took for you by your dear aunt, Mr. Copperfull,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, &ldquo;my remark were, I had now found summun I could care for. &lsquo;Thank Ev'in!&rsquo; were the expression, &lsquo;I have now found summun I can care for!&rsquo;&mdash;You don't eat enough, sir, nor yet drink.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is that what you found your supposition on, Mrs. Crupp?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, in a tone approaching to severity, &ldquo;I've laundressed other young gentlemen besides yourself. A young gentleman may be over-careful of himself, or he may be under-careful of himself. He may brush his hair too regular, or too unregular. He may wear his boots much too large for him, or much too small. That is according as the young gentleman has his original character formed. But let him go to which extreme he may, sir, there's a young lady in both of 'em.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Crupp shook her head in such a determined manner, that I had not an inch of 'vantage ground left.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was but the gentleman which died here before yourself,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, &ldquo;that fell in love&mdash;with a barmaid&mdash;and had his waistcoats took in directly, though much swelled by drinking.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crupp,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;I must beg you not to connect the young lady in my case with a barmaid, or anything of that sort, if you please.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Copperfull,&rdquo; returned Mrs. Crupp, &ldquo;I'm a mother myself, and not likely. I ask your pardon, sir, if I intrude. I should never wish to intrude where I were not welcome. But you are a young gentleman, Mr. Copperfull, and my adwice to you is, to cheer up, sir, to keep a good heart, and to know your own walue. If you was to take to something, sir,&rdquo; said Mrs. Crupp, &ldquo;if you was to take to skittles, now, which is healthy, you might find it divert your mind, and do you good.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With these words, Mrs. Crupp, affecting to be very careful of the brandy&mdash;which it was all gone&mdash;thanked me with a majestic curtsey, and retired. As her figure disappeared into the gloom of the entry, this counsel certainly presented itself to my mind in the light of a slight liberty on Mrs. Crupp's part; but, at the same time, I was content to receive it, in another point of view, as a word to the wise, and a warning in future to keep my secret better.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="282" id="p282"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXVII. <lb/> TOMMY TRADDLES.</head>
<p>IT may have been in consequence of Mrs. Crupp's advice, and, perhaps, for no better reason than because there was a certain similarity in the sound of the words skittles and Traddles, that it came into my head, next day, to go and look after Traddles. The time he had mentioned was more than out, and he lived in a little street near the Veterinary College at Camden Town, which was principally tenanted, as one of our clerks who lived in that direction informed me, by gentlemen students, who bought live donkeys, and made experiments on those quadrupeds in their private apartments. Having obtained from this clerk a direction to the academic grove in question, I set out, the same afternoon, to visit my old schoolfellow.</p>
<p>I found that the street was not as desirable a one as I could have wished it to be, for the sake of Traddles. The inhabitants appeared to have a propensity to throw any little trifles they were not in want of, into the road: which not only made it rank and sloppy, but untidy too, on account of the cabbage-leaves. The refuse was not wholly vegetable either, for I myself saw a shoe, a doubled-up saucepan, a black bonnet, and an umbrella, in various stages of decomposition, as I was looking out for the number I wanted.</p>
<p>The general air of the place reminded me forcibly of the days when I lived with Mr. and Mrs. Micawber. An indescribable character of faded gentility that attached to the house I sought, and made it unlike all the other houses in the street&mdash;though they were all built on one monotonous pattern, and looked like the early copies of a blundering boy who was learning to make houses, and had not yet got out of his cramped brick and mortar pothooks&mdash;reminded me still more of Mr. and Mrs. Micawber. Happening to arrive at the door as it was opened to the afternoon milkman, I was reminded of Mr. and Mrs. Micawber more forcibly yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now,&rdquo; said the milkman to a very youthful servant girl. &ldquo;Has that there little bill of mine been heerd on?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh master says he'll attend to it immediate,&rdquo; was the reply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because,&rdquo; said the milkman, going on as if he had received no answer, and speaking, as I judged from his tone, rather for the edification of somebody within the house, than of the youthful servant&mdash;an impression which was strengthened by his manner of glaring down the passage&mdash;&ldquo;Because that there little bill has been running so long, that I begin to believe it's run away altogether, and never won't be heerd of. Now, I'm not a going to stand it, you know!&rdquo; said the milkman, still throwing his voice into the house, and glaring down the passage.</p>
<p>As to his dealing in the mild article of milk, by-the-by, there never was a greater anomaly. His deportment would have been fierce in a butcher or a brandy merchant.</p>
<p>The voice of the youthful servant became faint, but she seemed to me,
<pb n="283" id="p283"/>
from the action of her lips, again to murmur that it would be attended to immediate.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I tell you what,&rdquo; said the milkman, looking hard at her for the first time, and taking her by the chin, &ldquo;are you fond of milk?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I likes it,&rdquo; she replied.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good,&rdquo; said the milkman. &ldquo;Then you won't have none to-morrow. D'ye hear? Not a fragment of milk you won't have to-morrow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I thought she seemed, upon the whole, relieved, by the prospect of having any to-day. The milkman, after shaking his head at her, darkly, released her chin, and with any thing rather than good will opened his can, and deposited the usual quantity in the family jug. This done, he went away, muttering, and uttered the cry of his trade next door, in a vindictive shriek.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does Mr. Traddles live here?&rdquo; I then enquired.</p>
<p>A mysterious voice from the end of the passage replied &ldquo;Yes.&rdquo; Upon which the youthful servant replied &ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is he at home?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>Again the mysterious voice replied in the affirmative, and again the servant echoed it. Upon this, I walked in, and in pursuance of the servant's directions walked up-stairs; conscious, as I passed the back parlor-door, that I was surveyed by a mysterious eye, probably belonging to the mysterious voice.</p>
<p>When I got to the top of the stairs&mdash;the house was only a story high above the ground floor&mdash;Traddles was on the landing to meet me. He was delighted to see me, and gave me welcome, with great heartiness, to his little room. It was in the front of the house, and extremely neat, though sparely furnished. It was his only room, I saw; for there was a sofa-bedstead in it, and his blacking-brushes and blacking were among his books&mdash;on the top shelf, behind a dictionary. His table was covered with papers, and he was hard at work in an old coat. I looked at nothing, that I know of, but I saw everything, even to the prospect of a church upon his china inkstand, as I sat down&mdash;and this, too, was a faculty confirmed in me in the old Micawber times. Various ingenious arrangements he had made, for the disguise of his chest of drawers, and the accommodation of his boots, his shaving-glass, and so forth, particularly impressed themselves upon me, as evidences of the same Traddles who used to make models of elephant's dens in writing paper to put flies in; and to comfort himself, under ill usage, with the memorable works of art I have so often mentioned.</p>
<p>In a corner of the room was something neatly covered up with a large white cloth. I could not make out what that was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Traddles,&rdquo; said I, shaking hands with him again, after I had sat down. &ldquo;I am delighted to see you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am delighted to see <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> Copperfield,&rdquo; he returned. &ldquo;I am very glad indeed to see you. It was because I was thoroughly glad to see you when we met in Ely Place, and was sure you were thoroughly glad to see me, that I gave you this address instead of my address at chambers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! You have chambers?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I have the fourth of a room and a passage, and the fourth of a clerk,&rdquo; returned Traddles. &ldquo;Three others and myself unite to have a set of chambers&mdash;to look business-like&mdash;and we quarter the clerk too. Half-a-crown a week he costs me.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="284" id="p284"/>
<p>His old simple character and good temper, and something of his old unlucky fortune also, I thought, smiled at me in the smile with which he made this explanation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's not because I have the least pride, Copperfield, you understand,&rdquo; said Traddles, &ldquo;that I don't usually give my address here. It's only on account of those who come to me, who might not like to come here. For myself, I am fighting my way on in the world against difficulties, and it would be ridiculous if I made a pretence of doing any thing else.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are reading for the bar, Mr. Waterbrook informed me?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, yes,&rdquo; said Traddles, rubbing his hands, slowly over one another, &ldquo;I am reading for the bar. The fact is, I have just begun to keep my terms, after rather a long delay. It's some time since I was articled, but the payment of that hundred pounds was a great pull. A great pull!&rdquo; said Traddles, with a wince, as if he had had a tooth out.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know what I can't help thinking of, Traddles, as I sit here looking at you?&rdquo; I asked him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said he.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That sky-blue suit you used to wear.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lord, to be sure!&rdquo; cried Traddles, laughing. &ldquo;Tight in the arms and legs, you know? Dear me! Well! Those were happy times, weren't they?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think our schoolmaster might have made them happier, without doing any harm to any of us, I acknowledge,&rdquo; I returned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps he might,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;But dear me, there was a good deal of fun going on. Do you remember the nights in the bed-room? When we used to have the suppers? And when you used to tell the stories? Ha, ha, ha! And do you remember when I got caned for crying about Mr. Mell? Old Creakle! I should like to see him again, too!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was a brute to you, Traddles,&rdquo; said I, indignantly; for his good humour made me feel as if I had seen him beaten but yesterday.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think so?&rdquo; returned Traddles. &ldquo;Really? Perhaps he was, rather. But it's all over, a long while. Old Creakle!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You were brought up by an uncle, then?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course I was!&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;The one I was always going to write to. And always didn't, eh! Ha, ha, ha! Yes, I had an uncle then. He died soon after I left school.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes. He was a retired&mdash;what do you call it!&mdash;draper&mdash;cloth-merchant&mdash;and had made me his heir. But he didn't like me when I grew up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you really mean that?&rdquo; said I. He was so composed, that I fancied he must have some other meaning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O dear yes, Copperfield! I mean it,&rdquo; replied Traddles. &ldquo;It was an unfortunate thing, but he didn't like me at all. He said I wasn't at all what he expected, and so he married his housekeeper.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what did you do?&rdquo; I asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I didn't do anything in particular,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;I lived with them, waiting to be put out in the world, until his gout unfortunately flew to his stomach&mdash;and so he died, and so she married a young man, and so I wasn't provided for.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="285" id="p285"/>
<p>&ldquo;Did you get nothing, Traddles, after all?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear yes!&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;I got fifty pounds. I had never been brought up to any profession, and at first I was at a loss what to do for myself. However, I began, with the assistance of the son of a professional man, who had been to Salem House&mdash;Yawler, with his nose on one side. Do you recollect him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>No. He had not been there with me; all the noses were straight, in my day.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It don't matter,&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;I began, by means of his assistance, to copy law writings. That didn't answer very well; and then I began to state cases for them, and make abstracts, and do that sort of work. For I am a plodding kind of fellow, Copperfield, and had learnt the way of doing such things pithily. Well! That put it in my head to enter myself as a law student; and that ran away with all that was left of the fifty pounds. Yawler recommended me to one or two other offices, however&mdash;Mr. Waterbrook's for one&mdash;and I got a good many jobs. I was fortunate enough, too, to become acquainted with a person in the publishing way, who was getting up an Encyclop&aelig;dia, and he set me to work; and, indeed&rdquo; (glancing at his table), &ldquo;I am at work for him at this minute. I am not a bad compiler, Copperfield,&rdquo; said Traddles, preserving the same air of cheerful confidence in all he said, &ldquo;but I have no invention at all; not a particle. I suppose there never was a young man with less originality than I have.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As Traddles seemed to expect that I should assent to this as a matter of course, I nodded; and he went on, with the same sprightly patience&mdash;I can find no better expression&mdash;as before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So, by little and little, and not living high, I managed to serape up the hundred pounds at last,&rdquo; said Traddles; &ldquo;and thank Heaven that's paid&mdash;though it was&mdash;though it certainly was,&rdquo; said Traddles, wincing again as if he had had another tooth out, &ldquo;a pull. I am living by the sort of work I have mentioned, still, and I hope, one of these days, to get connected with some newspaper: which would almost be the making of my fortune. Now, Copperfield, you are so exactly what you used to be, with that agreeable face, and it's so pleasant to see you, that I sha'n't conceal anything. Therefore you must know that I am engaged.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Engaged! Oh Dora!</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is a curate's daughter,&rdquo; said Traddles; &ldquo;one of ten, down in Devonshire. Yes!&rdquo; For he saw me glance, involuntarily, at the prospect on the inkstand. &ldquo;That's the church! You come round here, to the left, out of this gate,&rdquo; tracing his finger along the inkstand, &ldquo;and exactly where I hold this pen, there stands the house&mdash;facing, you understand, towards the church.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The delight with which he entered into these particulars, did not fully present itself to me until afterwards; for my selfish thoughts were making a ground-plan of Mr. Spenlow's house and garden at the same moment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is such a dear girl!&rdquo; said Traddles; &ldquo;a little older than me, but the dearest girl! I told you I was going out of town? I have been down there. I walked there, and I walked back, and I had the most delightful time! I dare say ours is likely to be a rather long engagement, but our motto is &lsquo;Wait and hope!&rsquo; We always say that. &lsquo;Wait and hope,&rsquo;
<pb n="286" id="p286"/>
we always say. And she would wait, Copperfield, till she was sixty&mdash;any age you can mention&mdash;for me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Traddles rose from his chair, and, with a triumphant smile, put his hand upon the white cloth I had observed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;However,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;it's not that we haven't made a beginning towards housekeeping. No, no; we have begun. We must get on by degrees, but we have begun. Here,&rdquo; drawing the cloth off with great pride and care, &ldquo;are two pieces of furniture to commence with. This flower-pot and stand, she bought herself. You put that in a parlor-window,&rdquo; said Traddles, falling a little back from it to survey it with the greater admiration, &ldquo;with a plant in it, and&mdash;and there you are! This little round table with the marble top (it's two feet ten in circumference), <hi rend="italics">I</hi> bought. You want to lay a book down, you know, or somebody comes to see you or your wife, and wants a place to stand a cup of tea upon, and&mdash;and there you are again!&rdquo; said Traddles. &ldquo;It's an admirable piece of workmanship&mdash;firm as a rock!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I praised them both, highly, and Traddles replaced the covering as carefully as he had removed it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's not a great deal towards the furnishing,&rdquo; said Traddles, &ldquo;but it's something. The table-cloths and pillow-cases, and articles of that kind, are what discourage me most, Copperfield. So does the ironmongery&mdash;candle-boxes, and gridirons, and that sort of necessaries&mdash;because those things tell, and mount up. However, &lsquo;wait and hope!&rsquo; And I assure you she's the dearest girl!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am quite certain of it,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the mean time,&rdquo; said Traddles, coming back to his chair; &ldquo;and this is the end of my prosing about myself, I get on as well as I can. I don't make much, but I don't spend much. In general, I board with the people down-stairs, who are very agreeable people indeed. Both Mr. and Mrs. Micawber have seen a good deal of life, and are excellent company.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Traddles!&rdquo; I quickly exclaimed. &ldquo;What are you talking about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Traddles looked at me, as if he wondered what <hi rend="italics">I</hi> was talking about.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. and Mrs. Micawber!&rdquo; I repeated. &ldquo;Why, I am intimately acquainted with them!&rdquo;</p>
<p>An opportune double knock at the door, which I knew well from old experience in Windsor Terrace, and which nobody but Mr. Micawber could ever have knocked at that door, resolved any doubt in my mind as to their being my old friends. I begged Traddles to ask his landlord to walk up. Traddles accordingly did so, over the bannister; and Mr. Micawber, not a bit changed&mdash;his tights, his stick, his shirt-collar, and his eye-glass, all the same as ever&mdash;came into the room with a genteel and youthful air.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, Mr. Traddles,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, with the old roll in his voice, as he checked himself in humming a soft tune. &ldquo;I was not aware that there was any individual, alien to this tenement, in your sanctum.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber slightly bowed to me, and pulled up his shirt-collar.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do you do, Mr. Micawber?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;you are exceedingly obliging. I am <hi rend="italics">in statu quo.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="287" id="p287"/>
<p>&ldquo;And Mrs. Micawber?&rdquo; I pursued.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;she is also, thank God, <hi rend="italics">in statu quo.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And the children, Mr. Micawber?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;I rejoice to reply that they are, likewise, in the enjoyment of salubrity.&rdquo;</p>
<p>All this time, Mr. Micawber had not known me in the least, though he had stood face to face with me. But, now, seeing me smile, he examined my features with more attention, fell back, cried, &ldquo;Is it possible! Have I the pleasure of again beholding Copperfield!&rdquo; and shook me by both hands with the utmost fervor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good Heaven, Mr. Traddles!&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;to think that I should find you acquainted with the friend of my youth, the companion of earlier days! My dear!&rdquo; calling over the bannisters to Mrs. Micawber, while Traddles looked (with reason) not a little amazed at this description of me. &ldquo;Here is a gentleman in Mr. Traddles's apartment, whom he wishes to have the pleasure of presenting to you, my love!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber immediately reappeared, and shook hands with me again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how is our good friend the Doctor, Copperfield?&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;and all the circle at Canterbury?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have none but good accounts of them,&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am most delighted to hear it,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber. &ldquo;It was at Canterbury where we last met. Within the shadow, I may figuratively say, of that religious edifice, immortalized by Chaucer, which was anciently the resort of Pilgrims from the remotest corners of&mdash;in short,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;in the immediate neighbourhood of the Cathedral.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I replied that it was. Mr. Micawber continued talking as volubly as he could; but not, I thought, without showing, by some marks of concern in his countenance, that he was sensible of sounds in the next room, as of Mrs. Micawber washing her hands, and hurriedly opening and shutting drawers that were uneasy in their action.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You find us, Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, with one eye on Traddles, &ldquo;at present established, on what may be designated as a small and unassuming scale; but, you are aware that I have, in the course of my career, surmounted difficulties, and conquered obstacles. You are no stranger to the fact, that there have been periods of my life, when it has been requisite that I should pause, until certain expected events should turn up; when it has been necessary that I should fall back, before making what I trust I shall not be accused of presumption in terming&mdash;a spring. The present is one of those momentous stages in the life of man. You find me, fallen back, <hi rend="italics">for</hi> a spring; and I have every reason to believe that a vigorous leap will shortly be the result.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was expressing my satisfaction, when Mrs. Micawber came in; a little more slatternly than she used to be, or so she seemed now, to my unaccustomed eyes, but still with some preparation of herself for company, and with a pair of brown gloves on.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, leading her towards me. &ldquo;Here is a gentleman of the name of Copperfield, who wishes to renew his acquaintance with you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It would have been better, as it turned out, to have led gently up to his announcement, for Mrs. Micawber, being in a delicate state of health,
<pb n="288" id="p288"/>
was overcome by it, and was taken so unwell, that Mr. Micawber was obliged, in great trepidation, to run down to the water-butt in the back yard, and draw a basinful to lave her brow with. She presently revived, however, and was really pleased to see me. We had half-an-hour's talk, all together; and I asked her about the twins, who, she said, were &ldquo;grown great creatures;&rdquo; and after Master and Miss Micawber, whom she described as &ldquo;absolute giants,&rdquo; but they were not produced on that occasion.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber was very anxious that I should stay to dinner. I should not have been averse to do so, but that I imagined I detected trouble, and calculation relative to the extent of the cold meat, in Mrs. Micawber's eye. I therefore pleaded another engagement; and observing that Mrs. Micawber's spirits were immediately lightened, I resisted all persuasion to forego it.</p>
<p>But I told Traddles, and Mr. and Mrs. Micawber, that before I could think of leaving, they must appoint a day when they would come and dine with me. The occupations to which Traddles stood pledged, rendered it necessary to fix a somewhat distant one; but an appointment was made for the purpose, that suited us all, and then I took my leave.</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber, under pretence of showing me a nearer way than that by which I had come, accompanied me to the corner of the street; being anxious (he explained to me) to say a few words to an old friend, in confidence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Copperfield,&rdquo; said Mr. Micawber, &ldquo;I need hardly tell you that to have beneath our roof, under existing circumstances, a mind like that which gleams&mdash;if I may be allowed the expression&mdash;which gleams&mdash;in your friend Traddles, is an unspeakable comfort. With a washerwoman, who exposes hard-bake for sale in her parlor-window, dwelling next door, and a Bow-street officer residing over the way, you may imagine that his society is a source of consolation to myself and to Mrs. Micawber. I am at present, my dear Copperfield, engaged in the sale of corn upon commission. It is not an avocation of a remunerative description&mdash;in other words it does <hi rend="italics">not</hi> pay&mdash;and some temporary embarrassments of a pecuniary nature have been the consequence. I am, however, delighted to add that I have now an immediate prospect of something turning up (I am not at liberty to say in what direction), which I trust will enable me to provide, permanently, both for myself and for your friend Traddles, in whom I have an unaffected interest. You may, perhaps, be prepared to hear that Mrs. Micawber is in a state of health which renders it not wholly improbable that an addition may be ultimately made to those pledges of affection which&mdash;in short, to the infantine group. Mrs. Micawber's family have been so good as to express their dissatisfaction with this state of things. I have merely to observe, that I am not aware it is any business of theirs, and that I repel that exhibition of feeling with scorn, and with defiance!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Micawber then shook hands with me again, and left me.</p>
</div2></div1>




</body>
<back>
<div1>
<pb id="p1a" n="1"/>
<head>WORKS <lb/> PUBLISHED BY A. HALL, VIRTUE &amp; CO.</head>
<p>25, PATERNOSTER ROW, LONDON.</p>
<div2>
<head>Elegant Gift Book for the Season.</head>
<p>In a handsome super-royal octavo volume, price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt; morocco gilt, 28<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE NILE BOAT; <lb/> OR, <lb/> GLIMPSES OF THE LAND OF EGYPT.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Illustrated by Thirty-five Steel Engravings and Maps, with numerous Cuts,</hi></p>
<p>BY W. H. BARTLETT, <lb/> AUTHOR OF &ldquo;FORTY DAYS IN THE DESERT,&rdquo; &ldquo;WALKS ABOUT JERUSALEM,&rdquo; ETC.</p>
<p>EGYPT&mdash;the seat of the most ancient civilization known to us, the birth-place of art and science&mdash;has ever been regarded with peculiar interest, alike by the artist, the historian, the philosopher, and the student of sacred history. Accordingly, from the time of Herodotus to the present day, descriptions of the aspect of this singular country, the manners and customs of its population, and, above all, the wonderful monuments which attest its past magnificence, have ever been sought for and perused with avidity.</p>
<p>The recent recovery by Champollion and others, of the key of hieroglyphic writing, constitutes a new era in the study of Egyptian antiquities. Conjecture as to their origin and purpose has given place to solid and well-grounded fact. Their dates, and the names of their builders, are now revealed to us: a new light has been thrown, not only upon the history of this great people, but also upon that of contemporaneous nations, especially the Jews.</p>
<p>Very numerous, it must be confessed, are the publications that have been recently devoted to the subject; from the magnificent folios of Denon, Champolliou, and others, to the small duodecimo compiled for the information of the million. The province of the volume announced is so far peculiar that it aims at affording a few distinct and lively impressions, by the combination of the pencil and the pen, of the more interesting objects existing on the banks of the Nile, accompanied by such a measure of historical and archaeological explanation as may inform the mind of the reader, without confusing him with redundant or unintelligible details. Exaggeration has been studiously avoided, and accuracy particularly studied. The Illustrations have been copied from original Sketches taken on the spot, and engraved with conscientious fidelity.</p>
<p>To those whose information about Egypt is as yet but slight, this volume, by pointing out the prominent objects, may serve as an agreeable introduction to more serious researches; while to others, who have neither time nor inclination to go deeply into the subject, it may supply, in a brief and popular shape, those general results which could only be obtained from the perusal of voluminous and costly publications.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p2a" n="2"/>
<opener>BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;THE NILE BOAT.&rdquo;<lb/>FOURTH EDITION, <lb/> In One Super-Royal Octavo Volume, price 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, or 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco gilt, <lb/> ILLUSTRATED WITH TWENTY-SEVEN ENGRAVINGS ON STEEL, A MAP, AND <lb/> NUMEROUS WOODCUTS,</opener><head>FORTY DAYS IN THE DESERT, <lb/> On the Track of the Israelites <lb/> on, <lb/> A JOURNEY FROM CAIRO BY WADY FEIRAN TO MOUNT SINAI <lb/> AND PETRA.</head>
<p>The object of this volume is to give distinct and graphic pen and pencil sketches of the Route of the Israelites from Egypt to Mount Sinai, dwelling particularly upon the beautiful oasis of</p>
<p>WADY FEIRAN, AND THE NEIGHBOURING MOUNTAIN, THE SERBAL, <lb/> pronounced by Lepsius and other <hi rend="italics">savans</hi> to be the real Sinai. The work also embraces notices of the Convent of St. Catherine, Mount Hor, and the extraordinary city of Petra.</p>
<p>The Illustrations have all been drawn upon the spot, with every attention to accuracy. The interest of the subject, though much has been written upon it, is, perhaps, on the increase, fresh light having been obtained by recent researches. In a pictorial point of view, it is full of interesting materials. The halting-places of the Israelites, the mountain of the law-giving, the coasts of the Red Sea, the wonderful rock scenery and excavated temples and tombs of Petra, combine to present a wild and singular variety of illustration.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener><hi rend="italics">By the Author of &ldquo;The Nile Boat.&rdquo;</hi><lb/>FOURTH EDITION.&mdash;Complete in One handsome Volume, Super-royal Octavo, price <lb/> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> morocco gilt, <lb/> WITH TWENTY-FOUR STEEL ENGRAVINGS, <lb/> TWO MAPS, AND MANY SUPERIOR WOODCUTS,</opener><head>WALKS IN AND ABOUT <lb/> THE CITY AND ENVIRONS OF JERUSALEM,</head><p>BY W. H. BARTLETT.</p>
<p>The Engravings from Sketches taken on the Spot, and expressly <lb/> for the Work.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Now ready, in post 8vo. price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt,</opener><head>SCRIPTURE SITES AND SCENES,</head><p>FROM ACTUAL SURVEY, <lb/> In Egypt, Arabia, and Palestine, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Mustrated with Seventeen Steel Engravings, Three Maps, and Thirty-seven</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Woodcuts.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p3a" n="3"/>
<head>UNIFORM SERIES OF <lb/> SPLENDIDLY ILLUSTRATED WORKS,</head><p>Specially adapted to adorn the Drawing-room Table, and at the same time enrich <lb/> the Library.</p>
<p>The Christian in Palestine;</p>
<p>Or, SCENES OF SACRED HISTORY. Illustrated from Sketches taken by Mr. W. H. BARTLETT, during his recent Journey in the Holy Land, and comprising 80 highly-finished Engravings on Steel, by COUSEN, BENTLEY, and BRANDARD, and others. With Explanatory Descriptions, by HENRY STEBBING, D.D. F.R.S. One Vol. quarto, cloth gilt, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Danube Illustrated;</p>
<p>A Series of 80 Plates, tastefully executed in the highest style, with Historical Text from the Pen of DR. BEATTIE. One Volume, cloth gilt, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Switzerland;</p>
<p>A Series of 108 fine Steel Plates, from Drawings by W. H. BARTLETT, with original letter-press by W. BEATTIE, ESQ. M.D. In Two Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
<p>The Waldenses;</p>
<p>A Series of 72 Engravings of the Scenery of the Valleys of the Alps, after Drawings by W. H. BARTLETT, and others. The Text by W. BEATTIE, M.D. In One Volume, cloth gilt, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
<p>Scotland;</p>
<p>Comprising 120 Plates, from Drawings by T. ALLOM, ESQ. and others. With Historical and Descriptive Text by DR. BEATTIE. In Two Vols. cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Beauties of the Bosphorus.</p>
<p>By MISS PARDOE. With 80 elaborate Plates, after W. H. BARTLETT, ESQ. In One Volume, cloth gilt, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>American Scenery;</p>
<p>Comprising 120 highly-finished Plates, after Sketches by W. H. BARTLETT. The accompanying Descriptions by N. P. WILLIS. In Two handsome Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Canadian Scenery;</p>
<p>A Companion Work to the former, and forming a fine Series of 120 Plates. In Two Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Scenery of Ireland.</p>
<p>By J. STIRLING COYNE. In 120 superior Plates, by W. H. BARTLETT, illustrative of the Country, and combining striking peculiarities of the National Costumes, Habits, and Traditions. In Two Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The Ports, Harbours, and Watering Places of Great Britain.</p>
<p>A complete Series of 125 Views of all the points of interest round the entire Coast, executed in the Messrs. FINDEN'S best style. In Two Volumes, cloth gilt, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>Views in Wales;</p>
<p>Comprising the most Picturesque Scenery of the Principality, with Historical and Topographical Notices. In Two Volumes, 4to. half-roan, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p4a" n="4"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">A New Illustrated Work, uniform with the &ldquo;Royal Gems from the Galleries</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">of Europe,&rdquo; in one vol. price</hi> 50<hi rend="italics">s. cloth gilt,</hi></opener><head>THE WILKIE GALLERY, <lb/> WITH NOTICES BIOGRAPHICAL AND CRITICAL.</head>
<p>The Engravings are accompanied by original critical notices from the pen of an artist whose abilities peculiarly qualify him to explain and illustrate those numerous points of excellence with which the compositions of WILKIE abound. The work will also comprise a Biography of the Painter, written expressly for the WILKIE GALLERY.</p>
<p>A PORTRAIT OF WILKIE AND A VIEW OF HIS BIRTHPLACE <lb/> FORM PART OF THE ILLUSTRATIONS.</p>
<p>The volume contains Forty-four beautiful Engravings in line; average size, 6&frac12; by <lb/> 9&frac12; inches.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GEMS OF BEAUTY;</head><p>Displayed in a Series of Forty-two highly-finished Steel Engravings of <lb/> various subjects.</p>
<p>From Designs by E. T. PARIS, G. CATTERMOLE, R. HERBERT, and E. CORBOULD.</p>
<p>Engraved under the superintendence of Mr. CHARLES HEATH.</p>
<p>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS IN VERSE, BY THE COUNTESS OF BLESSINGTON.</p>
<p>In folio, cloth gilt, 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing can surpass the exquisite finish of the plates.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;One of the most splendid works of the kind ever produced.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Messenger.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Undoubtedly the most exquisite book of the season.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Metropolitan Conservative Journal.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RYALL'S PORTRAITS OF <lb/> EMINENT CONSERVATIVES AND STATESMEN.</head>
<p>DEDICATED, BY PERMISSION, TO THE CARLTON CLUB.</p>
<p>This magnificent work forms two splendid volumes, folio, in superb morocco bindings, comprising Seventy-two highly-finished Engravings, by first-rate Artists, after Portraits by SIR THOMAS LAWRENCE, P.R.A., SIR G. HAYTER, R.A., H. W. PICKERSGILL, R.A., A. F. CHALON, R.A., T. PHILLIPS, R.A., H. P. BRIGGS, R.A., and other eminent Painters. Average size of the Engravings, 9&frac12; inches by 7&frac58; inches.</p>
<p>The Portraits are accompanied by Biographical Memoirs, which have been written expressly for this work, by members of the Senate, the Bar, and authors of high reputation.</p>
<p>Two vols. morocco elegant, gilt leaves, 8<hi rend="italics">l.;</hi> ditto, large paper, India proofs, gilt leaves, 12<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE DRAWING-ROOM TABLE BOOK.</head>
<p>EDITED BY MRS. S. C. HALL.</p>
<p>This volume comprises Original Tales by the Editor, and Poetry by popular living Authors. It is embellished with Twenty-four splendid Engravings by FINDEN, RYALL, ROLLS, and others, from Paintings by WARREN, LANISEER, LESLIE, DANIELL, &amp;c. The Work is beautifully printed, enriched with ornamental devices, and elegantly bound and gilt, 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p5a" n="5"/>
<head>WORKS BY MR. AND MRS. S. C. HALL.</head>
<div3>
<opener>New Edition, in three vols. super-royal octavo, price 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt,</opener><head>IRELAND: <lb/> ITS SCENERY, CHARACTER, &amp;c.</head>
<p>Illustrated with Forty-eight Steel Engravings, <lb/> AFTER DRAWINGS BY T. CRESWICK, A.R.A. AND OTHERS.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Five Hundred exquisite Wood Engravings, and Eighteen Maps of the Counties.</hi></p>
<p>The Authors have laboured with zeal and industry to obtain such topographical and statistical information as may be useful to those who visit Ireland, or who desire the means of judging correctly as to its capabilities and condition. But their especial duty has been to associate with more important details such incidents, descriptions, legends, traditions, and personal sketches, as may excite interest in those who might be deterred from the perusal of mere facts, if communicated in a less popular form. Independently of their own actual observation and experience, they have had the aid of many who have continually employed the pen or pencil&mdash;or both&mdash;in collecting and preserving records that serve to throw light on the state of the country and the character of its people; and they have obtained the co-operation of others who are interested, with them, in making Ireland more advantageously known to England, and who have confidence in the Authors' competency for the due discharge of their important task.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<opener>NEW EDITION, printed in imperial octavo, in two volumes, price 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each,</opener><head>THE BOOK OF BRITISH BALLADS,</head><p>EDITED BY S. C. HALL, ESQ. F.S.A.</p>
<p>WITH FOUR HUNDRED ILLUSTRATIONS ON WOOD.</p>
<p>This publication includes the choicest of those reliques that have been gathered with so much industry and labour, by PERCY, EVANS, RITSON, ELLIS, SCOTT, JAMESON, PILKINGTON, MOTHERWELL, and others; the majority of which, although they rank among the most popular compositions in the language, have never yet been brought together. The Engravings are on Wood, from Drawings by the most eminent of our British Artists; and, as an illustration is introduced upon every page, the volume contains about Four Hundred Embellishments.</p>
<p>The Illustrations have been engraved by the most eminent British Wood Engravers, from Drawings by</p>
<list>
<item>HERBERT, A.R.A.</item>
<item>REDGRAVE, A.R.A.</item>
<item>CRESWICK, A.R.A.</item>
<item>FRANKLIN.</item>
<item>CORBOULD.</item>
<item>KENNY MEADOWS.</item>
<item>PATON.</item>
<item>TOWNSEND.</item>
<item>SIMPSON.</item>
<item>FANNY M'IAN.</item>
<item>H. WARREN.</item>
<item>A. CROWQUILL, &amp;c. &amp;c.</item>
</list>
<p>Each Ballad is preceded by two pages giving its history, and supplying such information concerning it as the Editor has been able to obtain. In these pages are introduced, generally, the airs to which the Ballads were sung, and any Pictorial Illustration that may explain the text.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>ROYAL GEMS from the GALLERIES of EUROPE,</head><p>ENGRAVED AFTER PICTURES OF THE GREAT MASTERS.</p>
<p>With Notices, Biographical, Historical, &amp; Descriptive, <lb/> BY S. C. HALL, F.S.A.</p>
<p>Containing Ninety highly-finished Plates, engraved in the first style of art, by <lb/> W. GREATBACH, C. ROLLS, L. STOCKS, COUSEN, and others.</p>
<p>Size of the Engravings, 6&frac12; inches by 9&frac12; inches. Complete in two handsome <lb/> vols. cloth gilt, 5<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;They (the plates) are very well engraved, transmitting the beauty of the painting to the engraved resemblance, and conveying a good idea of the brilliancy and clearness of the painters. That this work is a help to good taste, and will do good for the Arts, nobody will deny.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p6a" n="6"/>
<head>New And Popular Musical Works.</head>
<div3>
<opener>In one handsome volume, folio music size, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt,</opener><head>THE ILLUSTRATED BOOK OF BRITISH SONG,</head><p>WITH PIANO-FORTE ACCOMPANIMENTS, AND BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL NOTES, <lb/> BY GEORGE HOGARTH, ESQ.</p>
<p>This Work contains upwards of Sixty Popular Songs, from the Works of PURCELL, ARNE, SHIELD, HANDEL, JACKSON, STORACE, and others. Each Song illustrated by an eminent Artist.</p>
<p>The Drawings by MEADOWS, PROKERSGILL, FRANKLIN, WARREN, TOPHAM, HOOK, &amp;c. The Engravings by DALZIEL, LANDELLS, LINTON, MEASOM, NICHOLLS, and others.</p>
<p>A Second Series of this work is now in course of publication.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Price Two Shillings, sewed,</opener><head>ONE HUNDRED ROUNDS, <lb/> FOR TWO, THREE, FOUR, FIVE, AND SIX VOICES.</head>
<p>COMPILED, ADAPTED, AND PARTLY COMPOSED, <lb/> BY CHARLES H. PURDAY.</p>
<p>Most of these Rounds are new to the British Public in their present shape; some have had new words adapted to them; and others are original, both in words and music.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Complete in three volumes, super-royal 8vo. price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth,</opener><head>THE PEOPLE'S MUSIC BOOK.</head>
<p>PRINCIPALLY ARRANGED FOR FOUR VOICES, AND AN ACCOMPANIMENT FOR THE <lb/> ORGAN OR PIANO-FORTE.</p>
<p>By JAMES TURLE, Esq. Organist of Westminster Abbey; and EDWARD <lb/> TAYLOR, Esq. Gresham Professor of Music.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<head>THE VOLUMES MAY BE HAD SEPARATELY.</head>
<row>
<cell> I.&mdash;PSALM TUNES </cell>
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> II.&mdash;SACRED MUSIC, CHANTS, &amp;c. </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> III.&mdash;SONGS, DUETTS, TRIOS, GLEES, MADRIGALS, &amp;c. </cell>
<cell> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In oblong royal quarto, price Six Shillings, sewed,</opener><head>MOZART'S REQUIEM,</head><p>His last and greatest Work, adapted to English Words, selected chiefly from the <lb/> Scriptures, and approved by Ecclesiastical Dignitaries.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2>
<pb id="p7a" n="7"/>
<head>Library Editions of Standard Historical Works.</head>
<div3>
<opener>Now ready, two vols. super-royal 8vo. with upwards of Fifty Illustrations,</opener><head>THE DECLINE &amp; FALL OF THE ROMAN EMPIRE.</head>
<p>BY EDWARD GIBBON.</p>
<p>Illustrated Edition, with a Memoir of the Author, and Additional Notes, principally referring to Christianity, from the French of M. Gurzor.</p>
<p>The Illustrations comprise&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>1. Maps of the Roman Empire, and of the Cities of Rome and Constantinople.</item>
<item>2. <hi rend="italics">Architectural Monuments,</hi> from the Augustan period to the time of Leo X.</item>
<item>3. Views of celebrated Cities and Sites, with topographical references.</item>
<item>4. A series of Coins and Portraits.</item>
</list>
</div3><div3>
<head>HUME AND SMOLLETT'S HISTORY OF ENGLAND,</head><p>Embellished with numerous Portraits, and Scenes of the principal events <lb/> in English History, engraved on Steel.</p>
<p>Also an ESSAY on the STUDY of HISTORY, by the Rev. H. STEBBING, D.D.; <lb/> WITH A CONTINUATION TO THE YEAR 1846, <lb/> By E. FARR, ESQ.</p>
<p>In three vols. imperial 8vo. Price 2<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth gilt. The Continuation <lb/> may be had separately, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>ROLLIN'S ANCIENT HISTORY</head><p>OF THE <lb/> MEDES, PERSIANS, EGYPTIANS, CARTHAGINIANS, GREEKS, MACEDONIANS, BABYLONIANS, AND <lb/> ASSYRIANS, ALEXANDER THE GREAT AND HIS SUCCESSORS.</p>
<p>Illustrated by many fine Plates, and a series of Maps, specially engraved for the Work.</p>
<p>The whole corrected and revised by a Clergyman.</p>
<p>In two vols. 8vo. cloth, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE HISTORY OF AMERICA.</head>
<p>BY J. ROBERTSON, D.D. F.R.S.</p>
<p>From the earliest period: comprising the Progress of Navigation&mdash;Life of Columbus&mdash;his Discoveries&mdash;War with the Indians&mdash;Conquest of Cuba&mdash;Conquest of New Spain by Cort&eacute;s&mdash;Conquest of Peru&mdash;Civil Wars of the Spaniards&mdash;Manners, Public Works, and Buildings, of the Mexicans&mdash;Government of the Spanish Colonies&mdash;Trade between Spain and the Philippines&mdash;History of Virginia and New England. With a Continuation of</p>
<p>THE HISTORY OF THE UNITED STATES TO THE PRESENT TIME.</p>
<p>Illustrated by Twelve fine Views of the most interesting Scenery in the country, and <lb/> a Portrait of Dr. Robertson. In royal 8vo. Price 20<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>A FAMILY HISTORY OF CHRIST'S UNIVERSAL <lb/> CHURCH.</head>
<p>BY THE REV. HENRY STEBBING, D.D.</p>
<p>The intention of this History is to furnish the heads of Families with the means of instructing those around them in the most important branch of knowledge that can engage their attention.</p>
<p>Demy 8vo. Two vols. cloth. Price 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p8a" n="8"/>
<head>Works by the Ren. Alernuder Fletcher, D.D.</head>
<p>OF FINSBURY CHAPEL, LONDON.</p>
<div3>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Thirtieth Edition of One Thousand each.</hi><lb/>Revised and Corrected by the Author.&mdash;In one volume 4to. cloth gilt, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>A GUIDE TO FAMILY DEVOTION.</head>
<p>BY THE <lb/> REV. ALEXANDER FLETCHER, D.D.</p>
<p>Containing 730 Hymns, 730 Prayers, and 730 Passages of Scripture, with appropriate Reflections. Also, an Appendix, comprising a great variety of Hymns and Prayers, to suit particular Days, Seasons, and Events of Providence. The whole so arranged as to form the most complete and distinct Family Service for every Morning and Evening in the Year, ever published. It is embellished with many fine Engravings on Steel, after the Old Masters, and a Portrait of the Author.</p>
<p>The following few are selected from the extensive list of eminent Ministers who <lb/> concur in strongly recommending the Work:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>Rev. H. STEBBING, D.D. F.R.S. Hampstead-road</item>
<item>J. HARRIS, D.D. Cheshunt</item>
<item>J. SHERMAN, SurreyChapel</item>
<item>J. A. JAMES, Birmingham</item>
<item>J. PYE SMITH, Homerton</item>
<item>W.B. COLLYER, D.D. Peckham</item>
<item>Rev. F. A. Cox, D.D. Hackney</item>
<item>G. COLLISON, D.D. Hackney</item>
<item>T. RAFFLES, D.D. LL.D. Liverpool</item>
<item>T. BINNEY, Weigh-house</item>
<item>JAMES PARSONS, York</item>
<item>W. JAY, Bath</item>
<item>J. CLAYTON, Poultry</item>
<item>Rev. JOHN ELY, Leeds</item>
<item>R. PHILIP, Maberley Chapel</item>
<item>J. DAVIS, Bristol</item>
<item>J. YOUNG, Albion Chapel</item>
<item>G. LAWSON, Selkirk</item>
<item>H. CALDERWOOD, Kendal.</item>
</list>
</div3><div3>
<opener>DR. FLETCHER'S DEVOTIONAL BIBLE.<lb/>In two vols. 4to. and uniform with the &ldquo;Family Devotion,&rdquo; price 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth,</opener><head>THE DEVOTIONAL FAMILY BIBLE,</head><p>With Practical and Experimental Reflections on each Verse of the Old and New <lb/> Testament, and rich Marginal References.</p>
<p>Embellished with 130 beautiful Steel Engravings, being copies of Paintings by <lb/> celebrated Masters, and Views of the Scenery of the Holy Land.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>SCRIPTURE HISTORY.</head>
<p>Designed for the Improvement of Youth. Embellished with 241 Engravings and <lb/> an elegant Frontispiece. In two volumes, 16mo. cloth gilt, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3>
<head>SCRIPTURE NATURAL HISTORY.</head>
<p>Illustrated by upwards of 256 beautiful Woodcuts. Two vols. cloth gilt, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>SERMONS TO YOUNG PEOPLE.</head>
<p>Three vols. 18mo. cloth gilt, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
<list>
<item>FIRST SERIES:&mdash;THE WISDOM AND GLORY OF GOD.</item>
<item>SECOND SERIES:&mdash;A COURSE OF SERMONS ON OBEDIENCE TO PARENTS.</item>
<item>THIRD SERIES:&mdash;ON THE SEASONS AND EVENTS OF PROVIDENCE.</item>
</list>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>THE HOFLAND LIBRARY: <lb/> FOR <lb/> THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF YOUTH.</head>
<p>Illustrated with Plates.</p>
<p>EACH VOLUME HANDSOMELY BOUND IN EMBOSSED SCARLET <lb/> CLOTH, WITH GILT EDGES, ETC.</p>
<list>
<head>FIRST CLASS, in 12mo. Price 2s. 6d.</head>
<item>1. ALFRED CAMPBELL; or, Travels of a Young Pilgrim.</item>
<item>2. DECISION; a Tale.</item>
<item>3. ENERGY.</item>
<item>4. FAREWELL TALES.</item>
<item>5. FORTITUDE.</item>
<item>6. HUMILITY.</item>
<item>7. INTEGRITY.</item>
<item>8. MODERATION.</item>
<item>9. PATIENCE.</item>
<item>10. REFLECTION.</item>
<item>11. SELF-DENIAL.</item>
<item>12. YOUNG CADET; or, Travels in Hindostan.</item>
<item>13. YOUNG PILGRIM; or, Alfred Campbell's Return.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>SECOND CLASS, in 18mo. Price 1s. 6d.</head>
<item>1. ADELAIDE; or, Massacre of St. Bartholomew.</item>
<item>2. AFFECTIONATE BROTHERS.</item>
<item>3. ALICIA AND HER AUNT; or, Think before you Speak.</item>
<item>4. BARBADOS GIRL.</item>
<item>5. BLIND FARMER AND HIS CHILDREN.</item>
<item>6. CLERGYMAN'S WIDOW AND HER YOUNG FAMILY.</item>
<item>7. DAUGHTER-IN-LAW, HER FATHER AND FAMILY.</item>
<item>8. ELIZABETH AND HER THREE BEGGAR BOYS.</item>
<item>9. GODMOTHER'S TALES.</item>
<item>10. GOOD GRANDMOTHER AND HER OFFSPRING.</item>
<item>11. MERCHANT'S WIDOW AND HER YOUNG FAMILY.</item>
<item>12. RICH BOYS AND POOR BOYS, and other Tales.</item>
<item>13. THE SISTERS; a Domestic Tale.</item>
<item>14. STOLEN BOY; an Indian Tale.</item>
<item>15. WILLIAM AND HIS UNCLE BEN.</item>
<item>16. YOUNG NORTHERN TRAVELLER.</item>
<item>17. YOUNG CRUSOE; or, Shipwrecked Boy.</item>
</list>
<closer>LONDON: <lb/> PUBLISHED (BY ASSIGNMENT OF A. H. NEWMAN AND CO.) BY <lb/> A. HALL, VIRTUE &amp; CO. 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p10a" n="10"/>
<opener>Twenty-fifth Edition. A new and beautiful Reprint, revised and enlarged, with <lb/> additional Minor Poems, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi><lb/>ILLUSTRATED BY CORBOULD,</opener>
<head>THE OMNIPRESENCE OF THE DEITY,</head><p>And other Poems, <lb/> BY ROBERT MONTGOMERY, M.A.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He has displayed a depth of thought which would do honour to any writer of the present day. A glowing spirit of devotion distinguished the whole work. On every page we find &lsquo;Thoughts that breathe and words that burn&rsquo; A truer body of ethics we have never read: and he who can peruse it without emotion, clothed as it is in the graceful garb of poetry, must have a very cold and insensible heart.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Times.</hi></p>
<div3>
<head>A NEW TREATISE ON THE GAME OF CHESS.</head>
<p>BY GEORGE WALKER, ESQ.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Ninth Edition.</hi> 12mo. cloth lettered, reduced to 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Second Edition, in 12mo cloth, price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>STUDIES IN ENGLISH POETRY.</head>
<p>EDITED BY JOSEPH PAYNE.</p>
<p>With short Biographical Sketches and Notes, intended as a Text-book for the higher classes in Schools, and as an Introduction to the Study of English Literature.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In preparation, uniform with the above, by the same Editor,</opener><head>STUDIES IN ENGLISH PROSE.</head>
<p></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Second Edition, revised and corrected, with an INDEX,</opener><head>CHEMISTRY NO MYSTERY:</head><p>Being the subject-matter of a Course of Lectures by Dr. SCOFFERN, <lb/> ILLUSTRATED THROUGHOUT WITH DIAGRAMS AND WOODCUTS.</p>
<p>In 12mo. cloth lettered, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Third Edition, revised and corrected,</opener><head>BAKEWELL'S <lb/> PHILOSOPHICAL CONVERSATIONS.</head>
<p>ILLUSTRATED WITH DIAGRAMS AND WOODCUTS.</p>
<p>In 12mo. cloth, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>New Edition. price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>THE MANUAL OF HERALDRY.</head>
<p>ILLUSTRATED BY FOUR HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Also, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> uniform with the above,</opener><head>A NEW MANUAL OF PERSPECTIVE.</head>
<p>ILLUSTRATED BY NUMEROUS ENGRAVINGS.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p11a" n="11"/>
<head>New Illustrated Works for the Young.</head>
<div3>
<opener>Uniformly printed in square 16mo. handsomely bound in cloth, price 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</opener>
<head>STRATAGEMS.</head>
<p>By MRS. NEWTON CROSLAND, (late CAMILLA TOULMIN.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;A sweet tale, penned in a fair mood, and such as will make a rare gift for a child.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Sun.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>&ldquo;THE ADVENTURES OF A DANCING DOG;&rdquo;</opener><head>PIPPIE'S WARNING; or, Mind your Temper.</head>
<p>By CATHERINE CROWE, Author of &ldquo;Susan Hopley,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A capital story.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi> &ldquo;This is a capital child's book.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Scotsman.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>MY OLD PUPILS.</head>
<p>The former work of this Author, &ldquo;MY SCHOOLBOY DAYS,&rdquo; has attained great popularity, upwards of ten thousand copies having been circulated in this country <hi rend="italics">alone.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Third Edition, with gilt edges,</opener><head>STORIES FROM THE GOSPELS.</head>
<p>By MRS. LYNCH, Author of &ldquo;Maude Effingham,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>With Plates on Steel, price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener>
<head>HOW TO WIN LOVE;</head><p>OR, RHODA'S LESSON.</p>
<p>BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;MICHAEL THE MINER,&rdquo; ETC.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A very captivating story.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Post.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Truthfulness, descriptive talent, and pure morality in every line.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Just what a story for children ought to be.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Douglas Jerrold's Newspaper.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In the Press,</hi></opener><head>PLEASANT PASTIME;</head><p>Or, DRAWING ROOM DRAMAS, for Private Representation by the Young.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In fcap. 8vo. price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt, illustrated by FRANKLIN,</opener><head>COLA MONTI;</head><p>OR, THE STORY OF A GENIUS. A TALE FOR BOYS.</p>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;How to Win Love,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We heartily commend it as delightful holiday reading.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Critic.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A lively narrative of school-boy adventures.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A very charming and admirably written volume. It is adapted to make boys <hi rend="italics">better.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A simple and pleasing story of school-boy life.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In 18mo. price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> cloth, with Frontispiece,</opener><head>MY YOUNG COMPANIONS.</head>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;My School-boy Days,&rdquo; &ldquo;My Old Pupils.&rdquo;</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p12a" n="12"/>
<opener>Now ready, in one volume, in a neat cloth binding, price 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi><lb/>THREE TALES BY MARTIN F. TUPPER, ESQ. D.C.L. F.R.S.<lb/>Author of &ldquo;Proverbial Philosophy,&rdquo; &amp;c.</opener>
<head>THE CROCK OF GOLD, <lb/> THE TWINS, AND HEART.</head>
<p>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Extracts from Recent Notices of &ldquo;The Crock of Gold.&rdquo;</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;This charming tale has won its way to the well-merited distinction of a &lsquo;Popular Edition,&rsquo; embellished with a characteristic frontispiece from the telling pencil of John Leech. We can read it again and again with fresh pleasure.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We have rarely had occasion to speak more highly of any work than of this.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Weekly Messenger.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We are glad to see such tales within the reach of the people. Mechanics' Institutes, and libraries of a popular character, should avail themselves of this edition.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Plymouth Herald.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A tale powerfully told, and with a good moral strongly enforced.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Kentish Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;This is one of the most original, peculiar, racy, and interesting books we have ever read.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Cincinnati Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;It is the fervour of style, the freshness of illustration, the depth of true feeling present in every page, that gives these tales a charm peculiar to themselves.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">New York Evening Post,</hi> Edited by W. C. Bryant.</p>
<div3>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In the Press,</hi></opener><head>A POPULAR EDITION OF MR. TUPPER'S POEMS,</head><p>Uniform with &ldquo;Proverbial Philosophy,&rdquo; <lb/> With Steel Frontispiece, and Vignette View of the Author's <lb/> Residence at Albury.</p>
<p>CONTENTS.</p>
<p>BALLADS FOR THE TIMES, now first collected; GERALDINE; <lb/> HACTENUS; A THOUSAND LINES; and other Poems.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In post 8vo.<lb/>BARON WILLIAM VON HUMBOLDTS</opener><head>LETTERS TO A LADY.</head>
<p>FROM THE GERMAN.</p>
<p>With Introduction by DR. STEBBING.</p>
<p>&ldquo;These Letters are interesting and delightful compositions.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Chronicle.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Sustained and animated throughout with a spirit of religion and philosophy . . . The Letters before us evince a spirit of the purest kind, invigorated by thought and refined by literature.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Standard of Freedom.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A most delightful book.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bristol Mercury.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>In one volume, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth lettered, with Frontispieces by LEECH and WEIR.</opener>
<head>TOIL AND TRIAL, <lb/> A STORY of LONDON LIFE. By MRS. NEWTON CROSLAND.<lb/>AND <lb/> THE DOUBLE CLAIM, A TALE of REAL LIFE. By MRS. T. K. HERVEY.</head>
<p>NOTICES OF &ldquo;TOIL AND TRIAL.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The book is well calculated to help an important movement.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athenoeum.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;She is a moralist, who draws truth from sorrow with the hand of a master, and depicts the miseries of mankind only that she may improve their condition.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Weekly Messenger.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crosland's purpose is good.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Globe.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Second Edition, in two vols. fcap. 8vo. price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth,</opener><head>THE STORY OF LILLY DAWSON.</head>
<p>By CATHERINE CROWE, Author of &ldquo;Susan Hopley,&rdquo; <lb/> &ldquo;Pippie's Warning,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crowe has exhibited much skill and ability in the construction and development of her story.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Literary Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A novel of very rare merit.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Messenger.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Crowe's style possesses a charm which renders her work irresistible.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Dispatch.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A narrative of stirring interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Jerrold's Paper.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;A delightful tale, related with vigour, full of striking and original scenes, and an endless series of adventures, and displaying considerable acquaintance with human nature.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Sunday Times.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Lilly Dawson&rsquo; is a creation worthy of Scott. The work will place Mrs. Crowe high among the living writers of fiction.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p13a" n="13"/>
<head>WORKS BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D.</head>
<div3>
<opener>A TENTH EDITION of the First Series is now ready.&mdash;In two handsome volumes, <lb/> foolscap 8vo. cloth gilt, 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each,</opener><head>APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES; <lb/> OR, <lb/> LECTURES ON THE BOOK OF REVELATION.</head>
<p>DELIVERED AT EXETER HALL AND AT CROWN COURT CHURCH.</p>
<p>These Lectures show the application of Prophecy to the present startling times and events, and have excited a very great interest. The present edition has been carefully revised by the Author, who has added a new Preface, a comprehensive Index, and made numerous corrections and improvements.</p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>Now ready, price 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in fcap. 8vo. cloth, full gilt,</opener><head>LECTURES ON THE SEVEN CHURCHES,</head><p>Being a Third Volume of APOCALYPTIC SKETCHES.</p>
<p>This Series is illustrated by beautiful Wood Engravings, representing the present <lb/> state of the Apostolic Churches.</p>
</div3><div3><p>THE CELEBRATED PROTESTANT DISCUSSION between the Rev. JOHN CUMMING, D.D. and DANIEL FRENCH, Esq. Barrister-at-Law; held at Hammersmith, in 1839. Crown 8vo. cloth, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>INFANT SALVATION; or, All Saved who Die in Infancy. Specially addressed to Mothers mourning the Loss of Infants and Children. Second Edition, fcap. 8vo. cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE BAPTISMAL FONT. An Exposition of the Nature and Obligations of Christian Baptism, with an Appendix. Uniform with the above, cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>A MESSAGE FROM GOD; or, Thoughts on Religion for Thinking Men. Second Edition, fcap. 8vo. cloth, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>THE TRUE SUCCESSION. A Sermon. Fourth Edition, fcap. 8vo. sewed, 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>LIBERTY&mdash;EQUALITY&mdash;FRATERNITY. Three Discourses, 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;IS CHRISTIANITY FROM GOD?&rdquo; A Manual of Christian Evidences for Sunday School Teachers, City Missionaries, and Young Persons. Fifth Edition, fcap. 8vo. cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;OUR FATHER.&rdquo; A Manual of Family Prayer, for General and Special Occasions; with Short Prayers for Spare Minutes, and Passages for Reflection. New Edition, in fcap. 8vo. price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> in cloth.</p>
<p>THE COMMUNION TABLE. A Manual for Communicants, containing a Plain and Practical Exposition of the Lord's Supper. In fcap. 8vo. price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>LECTURES FOR THE TIMES. An Exposition of Tridentine and Tractarian Popery. One thick 8vo. volume, cloth, price 7<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> or in 12mo. small paper, cloth, 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>CHRISTIAN PATRIOTISM; or, the Claims of Home and Country to Christian Consideration. An Essay. 8vo. sewed, 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>ALSO, JUST PUBLISHED, EDITED BY THE SAME AUTHOR, <lb/> THE PULPIT PSALM BOOK. The Psalms and Paraphrases according to the version of the Church of Scotland, with the names of suitable Tunes, Explanations of each Psalm, and a Supplement of Hymns and Doxologies for Special and Missionary occasions; to which are prefixed, Prayers and Services from John Knox's Book of Common Order, as at the Reformation; also, the Confession of Faith and Shorter Catechism. Peculiarly suitable for Presents to Clergymen, and forming a valuable Manual for the Pew and the Family. In cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.;</hi> morocco, 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p14a" n="14"/>
<head>THE ONLY EDITION CONTAINING DR. SYMINGTON'S IMPROVEMENTS.</head>
<div3>
<opener>Complete in three vols. royal 4to. price 4<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth, embellished with numerous <lb/> highly-finished Steel Engravings,</opener><head>THE REV. T. SCOTT'S COMMENTARY ON THE <lb/> HOLY BIBLE,</head><p>CONTAINING THE OLD AND NEW TESTAMENTS, ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORIZED VERSION, <lb/> Illustrated by Original Views of the Scenery and Remarkable <lb/> Places in and around Jerusalem and the Holy Land, <lb/> INCLUDING <lb/> Accurate representations of the Scenes of the most important Events in Sacred History, the Life and Labours of the Saviour, and the Journeys of his Apostles.</p>
<p>With an Introductory Essay, and numerous Practical, Explanatory, &amp; Critical Notes, by the Rev. W. SYMINGTON, D.D. Glasgow.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE PRACTICAL WORKS OF RICHARD BAXTER.</head>
<p>The only complete Edition. Reprinted, without abridgment, from the Original <lb/> collected Edition.</p>
<p>With an Introductory Essay on the Genius and Writings of Baxter, by ROBERT PHILIP, <lb/> and a fine Portrait of BAXTER.</p>
<p>In four volumes, imperial 8vo. cloth, 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;To every religious family able to afford a trifle for the purchase of books, these volumes are recommended as containing a complete library of practical divinity. No minister of Christian truth ought to be without them.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Nonconformist.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE WORKS OF THE REV. JOHN NEWTON,</head><p>Late Rector of the united Parishes of St. Mary Woolnoth and St. Mary Woolchurch-Haw, <lb/> London. With a Portrait.</p>
<p>Also, a LIFE OF THE AUTHOR, by the Rev. RICHARD CECIL; and an INTRODUCTION, <lb/> by the Rev. FRANCIS CUNNINGHAM, Vicar of Lowestoft.</p>
<p>In one vol. super-royal 8vo. cloth, 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE WORKS OF THE REV. ANDREW FULLER.</head>
<p>With a MEMOIR OF HIS LIFE, by ANDREW GUNTON FULLER.</p>
<p>Super-royal 8vo. With Engravings. Cloth, 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Coming on to modern theological writers, I recommend you to familiarize yourselves with the works of the acute, the philosophical, the profound, the pious, Jonathan Edwards, and those of Andrew Fuller. I know nothing like the latter for a beautiful combination of doctrinal, practical, and experimental religion.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Counsels to Students of Theology on leaving College, by John Angell James.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>CONSOLATION FOR CHRISTIAN MOURNERS;</head><p>A SERIES OF DISCOURSES OCCASIONED BY THE DEATH OF FRIENDS, AND OTHER AFFLICTIVE <lb/> DISPENSATIONS.</p>
<p>By the Rev. ADAM THOMSON, D.D. of Coldstream.</p>
<p>12mo. Price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p15a" n="15"/>
<head>Pictorial Editions of Standard Works.</head>
<p>UNIFORM IN SIZE AND STYLE OF BINDING.</p>
<div3>
<head>BUNYAN'S PILGRIM'S PROGRESS.</head>
<p>A splendidly Illustrated Edition, in super-royal 8vo. comprising <lb/> ONE HUNDRED AND TWENTY FINE ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD, <lb/> By the Messrs. WHIMPER, from Designs made expressly for the purpose.</p>
<p>Also, Nine elegant Engravings on Steel, a Portrait, and a Fac-simile of <lb/> John Bunyan's Will.</p>
<p>Complete in one handsome volume, cloth, price 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE HOLY WAR.</head>
<p>Uniform in size and style, and forming an appropriate companion to the &ldquo;Pictorial <lb/> Pilgrim's Progress.&rdquo; Containing <lb/> SIXTY-SIX SPLENDID ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> Designed expressly for this Edition. Cloth gilt, 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>FOXE'S ACTS &amp; MONUMENTS OF THE CHURCH,</head><p>WITH AN INTRODUCTORY ESSAY.</p>
<p>The whole carefully Revised and Edited by the Rev. JOHN CUMMING, D.D. Author of &ldquo;Apocalyptic Sketches,&rdquo; &amp;c. Illustrated with numerous Wood Engravings, a series of highly-finished Portraits of the leading characters connected with the Reformation, and other Illustrative Plates.</p>
<p>In three large vols. super-royal 8vo. cloth gilt, price 3<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 13<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE WORKS OF JOSEPHUS.</head>
<p>With an Introductory Essay, by the Rev. HENRY STEBBING, D.D.</p>
<p>Illustrated by Eighty fine Woodcuts, from Designs by Melville.</p>
<p>Also, Eleven Engravings on Steel, and a Portrait of the Author.</p>
<p>In one vol. super-royal 8vo. cloth, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>SHAKSPERE ILLUSTRATED.</head>
<p>EDITED BY THE REV. HENRY STEBBING, F.R.S.</p>
<p>A New Edition, comprising the whole of his Dramatic Works. Also, a BIOGRAPHY OF SHAKSPERE, and an Inquiry into the Authenticity of his Portraits, by A. WIVELL, Esq.</p>
<p>The Embellishments consist in a series of Fifty Engravings of Scenes in the various Plays, Landscape Illustrations of remarkable places, and Portraits of distinguished characters. Super-royal 8vo. cloth, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE WORKS OF BURNS.</head>
<p>Embellished with Thirty-three Plates (after Wright and other artists), illustrative of the principal subjects of his Poems. With a New LIFE OF BURNS, and Explanatory Notes preceding each poem, by ALLAN CUNNINGHAM.</p>
<p>One vol. super-royal 8vo. cloth extra, price 18<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> An Edition with 61 Plates, <lb/> price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>This will be found the most complete and best Edition of the Works of Burns yet offered to the public, and the only one edited by and published under the immediate superintendence of Mr. Cunningham.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p16a" n="16"/>
<head>Illustrated Handbooks for the Tourist.</head>
<div3>
<head>THE CASTLES AND ABBEYS OF ENGLAND.</head>
<p>A SUPERBLY ILLUSTRATED WORK, <lb/> By W. BEATTIE, M.D. Member of the Institute of France, and Author of <lb/> &ldquo;Switzerland Illustrated,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c. In one vol. imperial 8vo. price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>This work presents Engravings of whatever is most interesting or least known in the Scenery, Style, or Decoration of each subject, and is embellished with Vignette specimens of the Castles, Abbeys, Cathedrals, Chapels, Tombs, Altars, Halls, Galleries, Armouries, Portraits and Medallions, Sculptures, Arches, Gateways, Antique Furniture and Inscriptions, Statues and fragments of Art, Festive, Military, and Rural Scenes, Battle-fields, Banquet Halls, National Sports and Athletic Games, and whatever illustrates most forcibly the minds, habits, and pursuits of our baronial ancestors; the whole so distributed throughout the work, that the engravings and the literary matter mutually illustrate each other, and bring the edifices and their inhabitants once more before the eyes of the reader.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE RHINE BOOK:</head><p>Embracing the Scenery of the River, and its Historical and Legendary <lb/> Associations.</p>
<p>By FRED. KNIGHT HUNT.</p>
<p>THE RHINE BOOK, by an arrangement entirely novel, seeks to separate the romance of travel from its common-place. Numerous illustrations from original sketches, and all the attractions of the finest printing, render the volume worthy of the library, the drawing-room, or the boudoir, whilst it unites with its claims to elegance those points of practical usefulness necessary in a Guide Book. Dates, distances, times, and prices, are fully and exactly stated, to enable the Tourist to know and regulate his expenses at pleasure, and to avoid those extortions to which, when destitute of such information, he would most certainly be subject.</p>
<p>With One Hundred Engravings, square royal, cloth, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>WANDERINGS OF A PEN AND PENCIL;</head><p>Being the Results of an Antiquarian and Picturesque Tour through the Midland <lb/> Counties of England, by F. P. PALMER and ALFRED CROWQUILL.</p>
<p>The Illustrations are drawn by the latter, and engraved by our best Artists.</p>
<p>The book presents something of interest for those readers who cherish the affection for antiquity, or an appreciation of manners, customs, and legends, which abound in the nooks of &ldquo;Merry England.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Super-royal 8vo. with One Hundred and Twenty Engravings, Maps, &amp;c. cloth 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<opener>AN HISTORICAL AND PICTURESQUE GUIDE TO</opener><head>THE BLACKWATER RIVER, IN MUNSTER.</head>
<p>BY J. R. O'FLANAGAN, ESQ.</p>
<p>With Fifty-five Engravings. Small 4to. cloth, 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;From Mullen, famed for its mineral springs, to the bay of Youghal, flows the Blackwater&mdash;a river which, in point of varied and beautiful scenery, may stand comparison with almost any on the Continent. It is the course of this noble stream&mdash;the picturesque and luxuriant soil through which it glides&mdash;a soil teeming with the richest treasures, but less fostered by art than any other within the British Islands&mdash;that Mr. O'Flanagan has made the subject of the present very elegant work.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Dublin Evening Post.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>OLD FOREST RANGER;</head><p>Or, Wild Sports of India, on the Neilgherry Hills, in the Jungles, and on the Plains. By CAPTAIN WALTER CAMPBELL, of Skipness, late of the Seventh Royal Fusileers. The Second Edition, revised; with Eight Lithotint Plates and several Woodcuts. Square royal, price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2>
<pb id="p17a" n="17"/><head>Works for the Young.</head><div3>
<opener>Sixth Edition of Five Thousand, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth,</opener>
<head>STEILL'S PICTORIAL SPELLING-BOOK;</head>
<p>OR,<lb/>A SERIES OF EASY AND PROGRESSIVE LESSONS ON FACTS AND OBJECTS.</p><p>Embellished with 130 graphic and pleasing Illustrations, calculated to excite in the minds of the young a desire to learn to read sooner than by the usual methods. Five editions of five thousand have been rapidly disposed of, and the sixth edition, revised and corrected, with many valuable additions and improvements, both as regards the letter-press and illustrations, is now before the public. </p>
</div3>
<div3>
<head>SELECT POETRY FOR CHILDREN,</head><p>With brief Explanatory Notes by JOSEPH PAYNE, Author of &ldquo;Studies in English Poetry.&rdquo;</p><p>Fifth Edition, corrected and enlarged for the Use of Schools. In 18mo. price 3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> extra cloth.</p>
</div3>
<div3>
<head>THE NEW PROGRESSIVE DRAWING BOOK.</head><p>A Series of easy and comprehensive Lessons for Drawing Landscape, Architecture, the Human Figure, Shipping, Animals, &amp;c. without the aid of a Master.</p><p>With a complete Treatise on Perspective.</p><p>Illustrated by upwards of THREE HUNDRED ENGRAVINGS. PRICE 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3>
<opener>On the FIRST OF EVERY MONTH, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></opener><head>SHARPE'S LONDON MAGAZINE.</head><p>A Journal of Entertainment and Instruction for General Reading, consisting of Original Essays, Tales, &amp;c. by Miss AGNES STRICKLAND, Mrs. POSTANS, Mrs. COWDEN CLARKE, the author of &ldquo;Frank Fairlegh,&rdquo; MARTIN TUPPER, Esq., W. Beattie, Esq. M. D., W. H. BARTLETT, Esq. J. TIMBS, Esq. and other popular Writers.</p><p>This Magazine is printed in super-royal octavo, in a new and elegant type; each Part contains Two fine Engravings on Steel, from Designs by the best Artists.</p><p>Nine Volumes of the Magazine have already appeared, and may be had, elegantly bound in scarlet cloth, price 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each. They are recommended as particularly valuable for Lending Libraries.</p>
</div3>
<div3>
<opener>On the FIRST OF EVERY MONTH, in Parts, price 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> each containing</opener><head>TWO ENGRAVINGS BY GEORGE CRUIKSHANK,<lb/>FRANK FAIRLEGH;<lb/>OR<lb/>SCENES FROM THE LIFE OF A PRIVATE PUPIL.</head><p>This, though not exactly a work of deep and thrilling interest, or quite calculated to harrow the reader's feelings and plough up the inmost recesses of his soul, yet has its good points, as all who love real honest harmless fun have acknowledged.</p>
</div3>
</div2><div2>
<pb id="p18a" n="18"/>
<head>THE PHILOSOPHICAL WORKS OF JOHN LOCKE;</head><p>COMPRISING<lb/>The Conduct of the Understanding&mdash;Essay on the Human Understanding&mdash;Examination of P. Malebranche's Opinion of seeing all things in God&mdash;Remarks upon some of Mr. Norris's Books&mdash;Elements of Natural Philosophy&mdash;Some Thoughts concerning Reading and Study for a Gentleman. With a Preliminary Discourse and Notes, by J. A. ST. JOHN, Esq. Super-royal 8vo. price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth lettered.</p>
<div3>
<opener>Dedicated to the Queen, by Her Majesty's express Command.</opener><head>HOUSEHOLD VERSES,</head><p>BY THE LATE BERNARD BARTON.</p><p>Embellished with a Vignette Title and Frontispiece, engraved by BENTLEY, from Drawings by CHURCHYARD. Foolscap 8vo. cloth extra, price 6<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3>
<head>LAYS AND LEGENDS,<lb/>ILLUSTRATIVE OF ENGLISH LIFE.</head><p>BY CAMILLA TOULMIN.</p><p>In demy quarto, tastefully bound and gilt, 21 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3>
<head>THE BOOK OF ART;</head><p>Or, Cartoons, Frescoes, Sculpture, and Decorative Art, as applied to the New Houses of Parliament, as also to Building in general.</p>
<p>The volume contains above One Hundred Engravings, price 14<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth gilt.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>WISE SAWS AND MODERN INSTANCES.</head><p>BY THOMAS COOPER,<lb/>Author of &ldquo;The Purgatory of Suicides.&rdquo; Two volumes, small 8vo. 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
<div3>
<opener>By the Author, foolscap 8vo. price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> cloth,</opener><head>THE BARON'S YULE FEAST;</head><p>A Christmas Ryme.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>THE PALFREY;<lb/>A LOVE STORY OF OLDEN TIME.</head><p>BY LEIGH HUNT.</p><p>With Six Illustrations by MEADOWS, FRANKLIN, and SCOTT. Post 8vo. 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p19a" n="19"/>
<opener>DEDICATED, BY COMMAND, TO H.R.H. PRINCE ALBERT, ETC. ETC.</opener>
<head>THE ART-JOURNAL:</head><p>An Illustrated Monthly Journal <lb/> OF <lb/> THE FINE ARTS, THE ARTS OF DESIGN AND MANUFACTURE, <lb/> ETC. ETC.</p>
<p>PRICE HALF-A-CROWN MONTHLY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">An occasion favourable for New Subscribers to the</hi> ART-JOURNAL <hi rend="italics">is presented by</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">the commencement of a New Volume with the New Year.</hi></p>
<p>To the atelier of the ARTIST; to the library of the AMATEUR; to the desk of the STUDENT; to the workshop of the MANUFACTURER; and to the drawing-room table of the ADMIRER OF BEAUTIFUL ENGRAVINGS, the ART-JOURNAL is recommended as &ldquo;a companion and counsellor, at once agreeable and instructive;&rdquo; as &ldquo;ably and impartially conducted;&rdquo; as &ldquo;stimulating the manufacturer to the production of excellence, and the public to appreciate his improved works;&rdquo; and as having worked out with &ldquo;industry, integrity, and ability,&rdquo; its high purpose of &ldquo;supplying to Artists, Amateurs, and Connoisseurs, accurate and useful information upon all subjects in which they are interested, and to the public the means of justly ascertaining and estimating the progress of Art both at home and abroad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With the year 1849 commenced the issue in the ART-JOURNAL of a series of Prints of the highest order of merit, engraved in the Line manner by the most eminent British Engravers. These consist of THE VERNON GALLERY (each Monthly Part containing two examples), the permission to engrave which was accorded to the Editor by the late ROBERT VERNON, Esq. previous to his &ldquo;proffer&rdquo; of the collection to the Nation&mdash;a permission graciously sanctioned and confirmed by the Trustees of the National Gallery. &ldquo;To the British School of Art the publication has been a boon of magnitude;&rdquo; &ldquo;Mr. VERNON's gift is thus made doubly the property of the people;&rdquo; &ldquo;rendering ample justice to the best works of the best Artists of our country,&rdquo; and &ldquo;aiding the progress of national improvement, by rendering accessible to all classes a source of enjoyment and instruction.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To these testimonials may be added that of Mr. VERXON, who characterised the Engravings as &ldquo;most beautifully executed,&rdquo; and &ldquo;trusted that when published in the ART-JOURNAL they would be appreciated by the Public, and, by their diffusion at so moderate a cost, improve and increase the taste for the productions of our Native Artists.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is not therefore too much to assume that the ART-JOURNAL is a National Work, aiding the great cause of National Improvement.</p>
<p>The Volume, handsomely bound, of the ART-JOURNAL for the year 1849, containing Twenty-five Line Engravings (on Steel) of the Vernon Gallery, Twelve Engravings (on Steel) of Works in Sculpture, above Eight Hundred Engravings on Wood, and Four Hundred Pages of Letter-press, may be purchased for the sum of THIRTY-ONE SHILLINGS and SIXPENCE. A few years ago Ten Shillings was the charge for a single print of the size and character issued in this Journal for as many pence.</p>
<pb id="p20a" n="20"/>
<p>Twenty-four Engravings from the Vernon Gallery are in preparation for the year 1850. These are as follow:&mdash;</p>
<p>
<table rows="25" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> PAINTED BY </cell>
<cell> ENGRAVED BY </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Age of Innocence </cell>
<cell> Sir J. Reynolds, P.R.A. </cell>
<cell> Joubert. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Village Festival </cell>
<cell> F. Goodall </cell>
<cell> Carter. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Woodland Gate </cell>
<cell> W. Collins, R.A. </cell>
<cell> C. Cousen. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Seanty Meal </cell>
<cell> J. F. Herring </cell>
<cell> Hacker. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Syrian Maid </cell>
<cell> H. W. Pickersgill, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Sangster. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Last In </cell>
<cell> W. Mulready, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Smyth. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Reading the News </cell>
<cell> Sir D. Wilkie, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Taylor. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Venice: The Grand Canal </cell>
<cell> J. M. W. Turner, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Prior. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Sir Thomas More </cell>
<cell> J. R. Herbert, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Outrim. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Rustic Children </cell>
<cell> T. Gainsborough, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Shaw. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Death of the Stag </cell>
<cell> E. Landseer, R.A. </cell>
<cell> J. Cousen. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Youth and Pleasure </cell>
<cell> W. Etty, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Sharpe. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Rebecca at the Well </cell>
<cell> W. Hilton, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Rolls. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Storm Scene </cell>
<cell> J. Linnell </cell>
<cell> Bentley. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Battle of Borodino </cell>
<cell> G. Jones, R.A </cell>
<cell> Allen. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Country Cousins </cell>
<cell> R. Redgrave, A.R.A. </cell>
<cell> Shenton. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Crossing the Ford </cell>
<cell> Sir A. W. Callcott, R.A. </cell>
<cell> J. Cousen. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> A Greek Girl </cell>
<cell> C. L. Eastlake, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Graves. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Church of St. Paul, at Antwerp </cell>
<cell> D. Roberts, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Challis. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lake of Como </cell>
<cell> C. Stanfield, R.A. </cell>
<cell> J. Cousen. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Casement </cell>
<cell> G. S. Newton, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Sangster. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Crown of Hops </cell>
<cell> W. F. Witherington, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Bourne. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Arabs dividing Spoil </cell>
<cell> Sir W. Allan, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Smyth. </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cupid Bound </cell>
<cell> T. Stothard, R.A. </cell>
<cell> Whitfield. </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>Among the Works of Sculpture are the following:&mdash;</head>
<list>
<item>The Triumph of Love; by P. MacDowell, R.A.</item>
<item>The Greek Slave; by Hiram Power.</item>
<item>St. George and the Dragon; by W. Wyon, R.A.</item>
<item>The Graces; by E. II. Baily, R.A.</item>
<item>Dancing Girl Reposing; by W.C. Marshall, A.R.A.</item>
<item>Death and Sleep; by M.S. Watson.</item>
</list><p>Of these each Monthly Part, as heretofore, will contain TWO, together with one work in Sculpture,&mdash;original and from some famous British work,&mdash;and, usually, about Fifty Engravings on Wood,&mdash;comprising portraits of British Painters and Sculptors; Passages from the Poets, examples of the genius and fancy of many eminent artists; models of antique beauty; original designs for manufactures; examples of meritorious objects in manufactured Art, actually executed; and selections from the most useful models or finest works produced in the principal cities of the Continent.</p>
<p>The letter-press is contributed by many of the most eminent writers upon Art in England and of the Continent. The large circulation of the Journal enables the Editor to obtain the best assistance of the pen as of the pencil, so as to exhibit the results of knowledge and experience, and the practicability of improvements, in all matters essential to the Artist, instructive to the Amateur, profitable to the Manufacturer, and interesting to the Public.</p>
<p>In order to meet the wishes of those who require copies of the Engravings, for the portfolio or for framing, it has been resolved to issue A LIMITED NUMBER OF PROOFS, AND IMPRESSIONS on large paper; for these early application will be necessary, as they will be taken <hi rend="italics">only for Subscribers.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>ARTISTS' PROOFS, Two Guineas (of which only 150 will be printed). These will be <lb/> signed by the Engraver.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> THE PART. </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> PROOFS, before letters, India paper (Of which only 200 will be printed). </cell>
<cell> &pound;1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> LETTERED PROOFS, India paper (Of which only 200 will be printed). </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<closer>PUBLISHER, GEORGE VIRTUE, 25, PATERNOSTER ROW, <lb/> AND 26, JOHN STREET, NEW YORK.<lb/>COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE EDITOR MUST BE ADDRESSED TO MARLBOROUGH CHAMBERS, <lb/> 49, PALL MALL, LONDON.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p21a" n="21"/>
<head>JANUARY.</head>
<p>THERE is no month in the year when Winter has such entire sway as January. It is termed by some &ldquo;the very hole of winter,&rdquo; and justly so, too. It is then that the fanciful fret-work is seen to deaden and decorate the window-panes, while Jack Frost, with his icy fingers, pencils his sketches. It is in January that all around is sad, gloomy and lifeless. Not a crocus is seen to show its early blossom, and not a primrose sparkles in the eye. The very hyacinths in the windows seem fearful of showing anything but their pendant roots.</p>
<p>The evenings are cold, long and dreary; and but for the prevailing festivities, there would be nothing to comfort&mdash;nothing to cheer. The balls and evening parties, however, with other rational entertainments, do much to alleviate and enliven in this month.</p>
<p>E. MOSES AND SON have taken occasion to touch upon this month, in order to call attention to those Winter articles, so essential for various purposes at this season of the year. For the inclemency of the month E. MOSES &amp; SON have warm and elegant Paletots in every variety.</p>
<p>For the entertainments of the month the proprietors have fancy vests, coats, trousers, &amp;c., as various and numerous as a purchaser could wish to select from. E. MOSES &amp; SON are confident that an inspection will convince the reader of the immense superiority of their Winter articles over those of any other House in the Trade; and, consequently, they earnestly solicit the same at the earliest opportunity.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Ready Made.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield, handsomely </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Albert Wrapper, a very handsome style of Overcoats </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Shooting Coat </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Lounging and Morning Cost </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 4 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vest </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 17 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frock </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 19 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Youths' and Boys' Overcoats in every style, from </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 7 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hussar and Tunit Suit </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 14 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Boys' Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="17" cols="4">
<head>Made to Measure.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell>
<cell> &pound; </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell>
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Autumn and Winter Overcoats, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Chesterfield Wrapper, in a warm material, lined </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Paletot, handsomely and warmly trimmed </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 16 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Eglinton Wrapper, a very elegant Style of Overcoat </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Strathmore Winter Overcoat, newest Style, lined throughout </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Trousers in Tweed and Doeskin </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 10 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cassimere Trousers </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Autumn and Winter Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 8 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Black Cloth </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 13 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Silk Velvet Vests </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 18 </cell>
<cell> 6 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Dress Coats, from 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 2 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Brock 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 0<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 3 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> H. and T. Suit, from </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine </cell>
<cell> 1 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Men's Shooting Coats </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 15 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elegant Dressing Robes in great variety from 16<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to </cell>
<cell> 5 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
<cell> 0 </cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A large Stock of Fur Coats in every Shape, from &pound;3 to &pound;20.</p>
<p>NAVAL AND MILITARY UNIFORMS, LIVERIES, &amp;c.</p>
<p>MOURNING TO ANY EXTENT AT FIVE MINUTES' NOTICE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A Suit of Mourning complete for</hi> &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>The New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Minion of the Million,&rdquo; with full Directions for Self-measurement, can be had on application, or forwarded, post free, to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Shawl and For Departments are now replete with every novelty of the Season.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any Article purchased, either Ready-made or Made to Measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON</head>
<p>TAILORS, WOOLLEN DRAPERS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, <lb/> BOOT AND SHOE MAKERS, AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS, <lb/> 154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; and 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, City, London.</p>
<p>ALL COMMUNICATING WITH EACH OTHER, AND FORMING ONE VAST ESTABLISHMENT.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the public against imposition, but having heard that the untradesmanlike falsehood of being connected with them, or, it is the same concern, has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons, they beg to state they have no connexion with any other House in or out of London, except their branch Establishments, 36, Fargate, Sheffield, and 19, Thornton's Buildings, Bradford, Yorkshire; and those who desire genuine and cheap Clothing, &amp;c., should call at or send to Minories and Aldgate, City, London; or to the Branch Establishments as above.</p>
<p>TAKE NOTICE.&mdash;This Establishment is closed from sunset Friday, till sunset Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p22a" n="22"/>
<opener>The NOVELTY most recently introduced by Messrs. NICOLL is called</opener>
<head>NICOLL'S <lb/> EIDER DOWN PALETOT,</head><p>such novelty consisting in the adaptation of Eider Down in the formation of NICOLL'S PALETOT, the original elegance and utility of which is, however, faithfully preserved.</p>
<p>Eiders are found in greatest numbers in Iceland and the Fern Islands, where their beautiful and delicate down is well known to be proof against the most severe cold, and even the small quantity which can be compressed and concealed between the two hands will serve in the formation of a Paletot, which, while it has most extraordinary lightness, has, nevertheless, more warmth than the finest and thickest blanket, the great desideratum for a winter garment being thus accomplished, namely, personal warmth without fatigue.</p>
<p>Public inspection is invited at Messrs. NICOLL'S wholesale and retail warerooms.</p>
<p>114, 116, &amp; 120, REGENT-STREET, <lb/> and 22, CORNBILL, <lb/> London.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
