<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>A Tale of Two Cities, No. II:
Electronic Edition.
</emph></title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882.</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Andrew Leiter</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 175K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">A Tale of Two Cities</title>
<author>Charles Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent> 56 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Chapman and Hall</publisher>
<date>1859</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number Dickens 23 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2002-09-30, </date><respStmt><name> Jill Kuhn Sexton </name><resp></resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-12, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<pb id="pi" n="i"/>
<titlePage>

<titlePart> No. II. </titlePart>
<docDate>JULY.</docDate>
<docEdition>PRICE 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition><docTitle><titlePart>A TALE <lb/> OF <lb/> TWO CITIES </titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH <lb/> ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN AND HALL 193, PICCADILLY; <lb/> AND &ldquo;ALL THE YEAR ROUND&rdquo; OFFICE, 11, WELLINGTON-STREET NORTH, STRAND.</publisher>
<lb/>
The Author reserves the right of Translation.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="ii"/>
<head>FAMILY MOURNING.</head>
<p>MESSRS. JAY'S MOURNING WAREHOUSE <lb/> IS THE LARGEST IN EUROPE.</p>
<p>MOURNING COSTUME <lb/> of every description is kept READY-MADE.</p>
<p>SILKS <lb/> are advancing in price, but as Messrs. JAY'S have a large stock of <lb/> BLACK GLACE SILKS, <lb/> they are enabled to sell them much below their present value at Lyons. Though Messrs. <lb/> JAY professedly keep the best articles for <lb/> MOURNING AND HALF MOURNING, <lb/> and their assortment of <lb/> GERMAN BAREGES AND GRENADINES <lb/> is unequalled, they are also selling <lb/> FRENCH FOULARD SILKS at 2s. 3d. per yard; and <lb/> PRINTED MUSLINS at 6d. per yard.</p>
<p>THE <lb/> LONDON GENERAL MOURNING WAREHOUSE, <lb/> 247, 249, &amp; 251, REGENT STREET.</p>
<p>JAY'S.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>MILLINERY.</head>
<p>The MANAGER of the MILLINERY DEPARTMENT of the LONDON GENERAL MOURNING WAREHOUSE has just returned from Paris with the latest French Novelties, and Messrs. JAY respectfully solicit their customers to inspect this last importation of fashions.</p>
<p>THE <lb/> LONDON GENERAL MOURNING WAREHOUSE, <lb/> 247, 249, &amp; 251, REGENT STREET.</p>
<p>JAY'S.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb id="p1" n="1"/>
<opener>No. II&mdash;JULY, 1859.</opener>
<head>TALE OF TWO CITIES ADVERTISER.</head>
<p>HEAL AND SON'S <lb/> NEW <lb/> ILLUSTRATED CATALOGUE <lb/> CONTAINS DESIGNS AND PRICES OF 160 DIFFERENT ARTICLES <lb/> OF BED-ROOM FURNITURE AS WELL AS OF 100 <lb/> BEDSTEADS AND PRICES OF EVERY <lb/> DESCRIPTION OF BEDDING <lb/> SENT FREE BY POST <lb/> HEAL AND SON <lb/> BEDSTEAD BEDDING AND BED-ROOM <lb/> FURNITURE MANUFACTURERS <lb/> 196 TOTTENHAM COURT RD. <lb/> LONDON</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>POPULAR TALES BY F. E. SMEDLEY, ESQ.</head>
<p>I. <lb/> FRANK FARLEIGH; <lb/> OR, SCENES FROM THE LIFE OF A PRIVATE PUPIL.</p>
<p>2s. 6d. boards; 3s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>II. <lb/> LEWIS ARUNDEL; <lb/> OR, THE RAILROAD OF LIFE.</p>
<p>3s. boards; 4s. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>III. <lb/> HARRY COVERDALE'S COURTSHIP, AND WHAT CAME <lb/> OF IT.</p>
<p>2s. 6d. boards; 3s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>IV. <lb/> THE FORTUNES OF THE COLVILLE FAMILY.</p>
<p>Cuts by PHIZ. 1s. 6d. boards; 2s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>Arthur Hall, Virtue and Co., 25, Paternoster-row.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p2" n="2"/>
<head>MR. CHARLES DICKENS'S WORKS.</head>
<p>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p>
<p>NEW AND COMPLETE LIBRARY EDITION, <lb/> Beautifully printed in Post Octavo, and carefully revised by the Author, <lb/> WITH PORTRAIT AND VICNETTES.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">To be completed in Twenty-two Volumes.</hi></p>
<list>
<head>Already published.</head>
<item>PICKWICK PAPERS. 2 Vols. 12s.</item>
<item>NICHOLAS NICKLEBY. 2 Vols. 12s.</item>
<item>MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT. 2 Vols. 12s.</item>
<item>OLD CURIOSITY SHOP and REPRINTED PIECES. 2 Vols. 12s.</item>
<item>BARNABY RUDGE and HARD TIMES. 2 Vols. 12s.</item>
<item>SKETCHES BY BOZ. 1 Vol. 6s.</item>
</list>
<p><hi rend="italics">The remaining Eleven Volumes are now in course of publication by</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Messrs.</hi> BRADBURY <hi rend="italics">and</hi> EVANS.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>ORIGINAL EDITIONS.</head>
<p>THE PICKWICK PAPERS. With Forty-three Illustrations by SEYMOUR and &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo; 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1s.</p>
<p>NICHOLAS NICKLEBY. With Forty Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo; 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1s.</p>
<p>SKETCHES BY BOZ. With Forty Illustrations by GEO. CRUIKSHANK. 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1s.</p>
<p>MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT. With Forty Illustrations by &ldquo;PHIZ.&rdquo; 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1s.</p>
<p>THE OLD CURIOSITY SHOP. With Seventy-five Illustrations by GEORGE CATTERMOLE and H. K. BROWNE. Imperial 8vo. 13s.</p>
<p>BARNABY RUDGE. A TALE OF THE RIOTS OF 'EIGHTY. With Seventy-eight Illustrations by G. CATTERMOLE and H. K. BROWNE. Imperial 8vo. 13s.</p>
<p>AMERICAN NOTES, FOR GENERAL CIRCULATION. Fourth Edition. 2 Vols. post 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1s.</p>
<p>OLIVER TWIST; OR, THE PARISH BOY'S PROGRESS. Illustrated by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK. Third Edition. 3 Vols. 8vo. 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5s.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>CHEAP AND UNIFORM EDITION.</head>
<p>Handsomely printed in Crown Octavo, cloth, with Frontispieces.</p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>THE PICKWICK PAPERS</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>NICHOLAS NICKLEBY</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>BARNABY RUDGE</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>OLD CURIOSITY SHOP</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>OLIVER TWIST</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>SKETCHES BY BOZ</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>CHRISTMAS BOOKS</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>AMERICAN NOTES</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p3" n="7"/>
<opener>SIXTY YEARS OF SUCCESS <lb/> HAVE PROVED BEYOND QUESTION THAT</opener><head>ROWLANDS' MACASSAR OIL</head><p>POSSESSES EXTRAORDINARY PROPERTIES FOR PROMOTING THE <lb/> GROWTH AND IMPROVING AND BEAUTIFYING THE <lb/> HUMAN HAIR.</p>
<p>It prevents Hair from falling off or turning grey, strengthens weak HAIR, cleanses it from Scurf and Dandriff, and makes it BEAUTIFULLY SOFT, PLIABLE, and GLOSSY. In the growth of <lb/> THE BEARD, WHISKERS, AND MUSTACHIOS, <lb/> it is unfailing in its stimulative operation. For CHILDREN it is especially recommended as forming the basis of A BEAUTIFUL HEAD OF HAIR, while its introduction into the Nursery of ROYALTY, and the numerous Testimonials constantly received of its efficacy, afford the best and surest proofs of its merits.&mdash;Price 3s. 6d. and 7s.; Family Bottles (equal to four small), 10s. 6d.; and double that size, 21s.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;On the Wrapper of each Bottle are the words, &ldquo;ROWLANDS' MACASSAR OIL,&rdquo; &amp;c., in white letters, and their signature, &ldquo;A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS,&rdquo; in red ink.</p>
<p>Sold at 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>ALLEN'S PATENT PORTMANTEAUS <lb/> AND TRAVELLING BAGS,</head><p>WITH SQUARE OPENING; <lb/> LADIES' DRESS TRUNKS, DRESSING BAGS, <lb/> WITH SILVER FITTINGS; <lb/> DESPATCH BOXES, WRITING AND <lb/> DRESSING CASES; <lb/> And Five Hundred other Articles for Home or Continental Travelling, illustrated in their New Catalogue for 1859. By post for two stamps.</p>
<p>J. W. and T. ALLEN, Manufacturers of Officers' Barrack Furniture and Military Outfitters (<hi rend="italics">see separate Catalogue</hi>), 18 and 22, STRAND.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>In one thick volume, a New Edition, the Twelfth, greatly improved, price 16s.,</opener>
<head>MODERN DOMESTIC MEDICINE.</head><p>Forming a Comprehensive Medical Guide for the Clergy, Families, and Emigrants. By T. J. GRAHAM, M.D., Member of the Royal College of Surgeons of England.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of all the Medical Guides that have come to our hands, this is by far the best. For fulness and completeness they all yield the palm to Dr. Graham's.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Banner.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Undoubtedly the best medical work for private families in the English language. It is invaluable.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Literary Times.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We always rejoice in an opportunity of calling public attention to Dr. Graham's &lsquo;Domestic Medicine,&rsquo; which we have long considered as far excelling every publication of its class.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">British Standard, February,</hi> 1859.</p>
<p>Published by Simpkin and Co., Paternoster-row; and Hatchards, 187, Piccadilly. Sold by all booksellers.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just published. SECOND EDITION.<lb/>Crown 8vo, 12s.</opener>
<head>HEALTH AND DISEASE-THEIR LAWS.</head>
<p>With Plain Practical Prescriptions. By BENJAMIN RIDGE, M.D., F.R.C.S., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Written expressly for the information of the Million; free from Professional Technicalities, with many new Observations for Domestic Use, with which every one should be acquainted.</p>
<p>Chapman and Hall, 193, Piccadilly.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p4" n="8"/>
<opener>REMOVAL TO 5, CHARING CROSS (late 69, Strand).</opener>
<head>EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT,</head><p>Price 40s. All Silk throughout, 50s. to 60s.</p>
<p>PORTABLE INDIA RUBBER BOATS, <lb/> &pound;7 10s. to &pound;10 10s. and &pound;18 18s.</p>
<p>KNAPSACKS FOR TOURISTS, 18s. 6d.</p>
<p>THE SIPHONIA DEPOT, EDMISTON, 5, CHARING CROSS.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>PARASOLS.</head>
<p>THE style and fashion of Parasols having undergone a complete change during the last few years, W. and J. SANGSTER have manufactured for the present season an unusual variety, comprising, among others, the following:</p>
<list>
<item>The Empress&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
<item>The Sultana&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
<item>The Persian&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
<item>The Irish Lace&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
<item>The China Crape&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
<item>The Brocaded Lyons&mdash;for the carriage or f&ecirc;te.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>SILKS:</head>
<item>The Moire Antique&mdash;for walking.</item>
<item>The Glac&eacute; Antique&mdash;for walking.</item>
</list>
<p>Sun Shades, in silk as well as alpaca, of various colours.</p>
<p>W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, <list> <item>140, REGENT-STREET,</item>
<item> 94, FLEET-STREET,</item>
<item>10, ROYAL EXCHANGE,</item>
<item>75, CHEAPSIDE.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p5" n="3"/>
<head>NEW WORKS.</head>
<p>MR. WALTER WHITE'S NEW BOOK OF HOME TRAVEL.</p>
<p>NORTHUMBERLAND AND THE BORDER.</p>
<p>By WALTER WHITE, Author of &ldquo;A Month in Yorkshire,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>1 vol. post 8vo. <hi rend="italics">July</hi>1.</p>
<p>TOBACCO: ITS HISTORY AND ASSOCIATIONS.</p>
<p>Including an Account of the Plant and its Manufacture, Snuff and Snuff-Takers, Tobacco <lb/> Pipes, and all the Concomitants of Smoking in all Ages and Countries.</p>
<p>By F. W. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A.</p>
<p>With One Hundred Illustrations by the Author.</p>
<p>1 vol. post 8vo. <hi rend="italics">July</hi> 1.</p>
<p>MEMOIRS OF ROBERT-HOUDIN, <lb/> AMBASSADOR, AUTHOR, AND CONJUROR.</p>
<p>Written by HIMSELF.</p>
<p>2 vols. post 8vo, 21s.</p>
<p>AURORA LEIGH: <lb/> A POEM.</p>
<p>By ELIZABETH BARRETT BROWNING.</p>
<p>With Portrait. FOURTH AND CHEAPER EDITION. Fcap. 8vo, 7s.</p>
<p>NORTH AND SOUTH.</p>
<p>By the AUTHOR of &ldquo;MARY BARTON,&rdquo; &ldquo;RUTH,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>THIRD AND CHEAPER EDITION. Post 8vo, 5s.</p>
<p>THE THREE GATES:</p>
<p>A POEM.</p>
<p>By CHAUNCY HARE TOWNSHEND. <hi rend="italics">July</hi> 1.</p>
<p>FOURTH EDITION IN A FEW DAYS.</p>
<p>OUR FARM OF FOUR ACRES, AND THE MONEY <lb/> WE MADE BY IT.</p>
<p>Post 8vo, price 2s.</p>
<p>MR. LEVER'S NEW WORK.</p>
<p>DAVENPORT DUNN: A MAN OF OUR DAY.</p>
<p>By CHARLES LEVER, Author of &ldquo;Harry Lorrequer,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>In 1 8vo volume, price 23s. With 44 Illustrations by H. K. Browne.</p>
<p>ROBERT MORNAY: A NOVEL.</p>
<p>By MAX FERRER.</p>
<p>Post 8vo, 9s.</p>
<p>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p6" n="4"/>
<head>IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT.</head>
<p>METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN, <lb/> BY ROYAL COMMAND.</p>
<p>JOSEPH GILLOTT</p>
<p>BEGS most respectfully to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic Institutions, and the public generally, that, by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and, in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times, he has introduced a NEW SERIES of his useful productions, which for EXCELLENCE OF TEMPER, QUALITY OF MATERIAL, and, above all, CHEAPNESS IN PRICE, he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition.</p>
<p>Each Pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of boxes, containing one gross each, with label outside, and the fac-simile of his signature.</p>
<p>At the request of persons extensively engaged in tuition, J. G. has introduced his WARRANTED SCHOOL AND PUBLIC PENS, which are especially adapted to their use, being of different degrees of flexibility, and with fine, medium, and broad points, suitable for the various kinds of Writing taught in Schools.</p>
<p>Sold Retail by all Stationers, Booksellers, and other respectable Dealers in Steel Pens.&mdash;Merchants and wholesale Dealers can be supplied at the Works, Graham-street; 96, New-street, Birmingham;</p>
<p>No. 91, JOHN STREET, NEW YORK; and at <lb/> 37, GRACECHURCH STREET, LONDON.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>KEATING'S PALE NEWFOUNDLAND COD LIVER OIL,</head><p>perfectly pure, nearly tasteless, and free from adulteration of any kind, has been analysed, reported on, and recommended by Professors TAYLOR and THOMSON, of Guy's and St. Thomas's Hospitals, who, in the words of the late Dr. PEREIRA, say, that &ldquo;the finest oil is that most devoid of <hi rend="italics">colour, odour,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">flavour,</hi>&rdquo; characters this will be found to possess in a high degree. Half-pints 1s. 6d., Pints 2s. 6d., Quarts 4s. 6d., and Five-pint Bottles 10s. 6d., Imperial Measure.</p>
<p>79, St. Paul's Churchyard, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>A CLEAR COMPLEXION <lb/> is produced by <lb/> GOWLAND'S LOTION.</head>
<p>LADIES visiting the Sea-side or exposed to the heat of the sun and dust will immediately on the application of this celebrated preparation (established 101 years) experience its extraordinary genial qualities. It produces and sustains <lb/> GREAT PURITY AND DELICACY OF <lb/> COMPLEXION, <lb/> It removes freckles, tan, redness, and pimples, and promotes healthy action, softness and elasticity of the skin, and is recommended in preference to any other preparation by the Medical Profession.</p>
<p>Sold by all Druggists and Perfumers. Half-pints, 2s. 9d.; Quarts, 8s. 6d.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p>is celebrated over the whole world for its sanitary and invigorating properties, and its delightful aroma. Price 1s., 2s. 6d., and 5s.&mdash;Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. Rimmel, 96, Strand, 24, Cornhill, and Crystal Palace.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NOTICE OF DIVIDEND.</head>
<p>BANK OF DEPOSIT, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Established A.D.</hi> 1844.</p>
<p>3, PALL MALL EAST, LONDON.</p>
<p>THE WARRANTS for the HALF-YEARLY Interest, at the rate of 5 per Cent. per Annum, on Deposit Accounts, to the 30th instant, will be ready for delivery on and after the 11th of July, and payable daily between the hours of 10 and 4.</p>
<p>PETER MORRISON, <hi rend="italics">Managing Director.</hi> June, 1859.</p>
<p>Forms for opening accounts sent free on application.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>PELICAN <lb/> LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY.</head>
<p>ESTABLISHED IN 1797.</p>
<p>70, Lombard-street, City, and 57, Charing-cross, <lb/> Westminster.</p>
<p>BONUS OF 1861.</p>
<p>ALL POLICIES effected prior to the 1st July, 1861, on the Bonus Scale of Premiums, will participate in the next Division of Profits.</p>
<p>For Prospectuses and Forms of Proposal apply at the Offices as above, or to any of the Company's Agents.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>In a handsome demy 8vo vol., price 21s.,</opener><head>MEMOIRS of BARTHOLOMEW FAIR,</head><p>By HENRY MORLEY. With 80 fac-simile Drawings.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A very pretty and life-like picture, exhibiting Mr. Morley's power of presenting, in a fashion far different from that of Dryasdust, correct antiquarian details. It is just in this that his strength seems mainly to lie.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Saturday Review.</hi></p>
<p>Chapman and Hall, 193, Piccadilly.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>2 vols. post 8vo, 21s.,</opener><head>LIFE in VICTORIA;</head><p>or, Victoria in 1853, and Victoria in 1858; showing the march of improvement made by the Colony within those Periods in Town and Country, Cities and Diggings. By WILLIAM KELLY.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never has there been any fact in history so utterly and simply practical in its details, and rude in its actual expression, that appeals so forcibly to the imagination, as the story of &lsquo;Victoria.&rsquo; Mr. Kelly is the proper man to tell it well, for through him it can tell itself. When there he is not only in the scene, but of the scene. The adventurous spirit of the men who made the colony is his own spirit. He has been at home in California, at home in Australia; and he is now on the way to British Columbia. &lsquo;Victoria&rsquo; speaks through him with its own natural voice.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>Chapman and Hall, 193. Piccadilly.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p7" n="5"/>
<opener>This day is published, price 6s., No. XVII. of</opener><head>THE NATIONAL REVIEW.</head>
<list>
<head>CONTENTS:</head>
<item>I. Glaciers and Glacier Theories.</item>
<item>II. Peasant Life in Hungary.</item>
<item>III. The People of the Arabian Nights.</item>
<item>IV. The Settlement of New England.</item>
<item>V. Utopian Banquets.</item>
<item>VI. The Apostolic Age.</item>
<item>VII. John Milton.</item>
<item>VIII. The Bertrams.</item>
<item>IX. Revelation: What it is not, and what it is.</item>
<item>X. Italy: its Prospects and Capacities.</item>
<item>XI. Books of the Quarter.</item>
</list>
<p>Chapman and Hall, 193, Piccadilly.</p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>MR. ANTHONY TROLLOPE'S NEW NOVELS.</head>
<p>&ldquo;To those who are in the habit of reading Novels, it is unnecessary to say that Mr. Trollope is one of the most amusing of authors.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Times,</hi> May 23.</p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<opener>THE SECOND EDITION OF</opener><head>THE BERTRAMS: A NOVEL.</head>
<p>By ANTHONY TROLLOPE, Author of &ldquo;Doctor Thorne,&rdquo; &ldquo;Barchester Towers,&rdquo; &amp;c. <hi rend="italics">To be had at all the Libraries.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;We recommend &lsquo;The Bertrams&rsquo; to our readers; they will appreciate our delicacy in not forestalling their interest by giving them any hint of the story that awaits them, and which, they may accept our word for it, they will find deeply interesting.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Athen&oelig;um.</hi></p>
</div3><div3 type="advertisement">
<head>DOCTOR THORNE: A NOVEL.</head>
<p>By ANTHONY TROLLOPE.</p>
<p>THIRD AND CHEAPER EDITION, price Five Shillings.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>A DECADE OF ITALIAN WOMEN.</head>
<list>
<item>ST. CATHERINE OF SIENA.</item>
<item>CATERINA SFORZA.</item>
<item>VITTORIA COLONNA.</item>
<item>TULLIA D'ARAGONA.</item>
<item>OLYMPIA MORATA.</item>
<item>ISABELLA ANDREINI.</item>
<item>BIANCA CAPPELLO.</item>
<item>OLYMPIA PAMFILI.</item>
<item>ELIZABETTA SIRANI.</item>
<item>LA CORILLA.</item>
</list><p>By THOMAS ADOLPHUS TROLLOPE.</p>
<p>In two vols. post 8vo, with Portraits, price 22s.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<opener>SECOND EDITION, fcap 8vo, 9s. 6d.,</opener><head>THE WANDERER.</head>
<p>By OWEN MEREDITH, Author of &ldquo;Clytemnestra,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<opener>MR. CARLYLE'S NEW WORK. Demy 8vo, with Portraits and Maps,</opener><head>HISTORY OF FRIEDRICH THE SECOND, <lb/> CALLED <lb/> FREDERICK THE GREAT.</head>
<p>By THOMAS CARLYLE.</p>
<p>THIRD EDITION. Vols. I. and II., demy 8vo, 40s.</p>
<p>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p8" n="6"/>
<head>MR. CARLYLE'S WORKS.</head>
<p>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Completion of the New and uniform Edition in Sixteen Volumes.</hi></p>
<p>THE FRENCH REVOLUTION: A HISTORY. 2 vols. crown 8vo. 12s.</p>
<p>OLIVER CROMWELL'S LETTERS AND SPEECHES: <lb/> WITH ELUCIDATIONS AND CONNECTING NARRATIVE</p>
<p>3 vols. crown 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>LIFE OF JOHN STERLING.&mdash;LIFE OF SCHILLER. 1 vol. crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>CRITICAL AND MISCELLANEOUS ESSAYS. 4 vols. crown 8vo. 24s.</p>
<p>SARTOR RESARTUS. LECTURES ON HEROES AND HERO-WORSHIP.</p>
<p>1 vol. crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>LATTER-DAY PAMPHLETS. 1 vol. crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>CHARTISM.&mdash;PAST AND PRESENT. 1 vol. crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>TRANSLATIONS FROM THE GERMAN: <lb/> MUS&AElig;US, TIECK, RICHTER.</p>
<p>1 vol. crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>TRANSLATIONS FROM THE GERMAN <lb/> WILHELM MEISTER'S APPRENTICESHIP AND TRAVELS.</p>
<p>2 vols. crown 8vo. 12s.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>The Saturday Review.</head>
<p>&ldquo;Few of the cheap reprints of the books of popular authors which have of late become so common will attract more attention or enjoy greater popularity than the collected edition of Mr. Carlyle's writings. With those who admire him most, he enjoys a reputation which is almost mystical. To numberless young and ardent readers, his writings have come as the announcement of a new gospel; nor can any one read them without a very deep interest in the books, and a very sincere feeling of respect for the author. Perhaps all books may be ranged under two heads,&mdash;those which assume, and those which seek to establish, principles; and if the former are both more interesting and more practically important than the latter after a certain early period of life, it cannot be denied that the influence of the latter, acting at the most susceptible and impressible age, is both wider and deeper. It is the great peculiarity of Mr. Carlyle's books that, from first to last, they are all principle. There is hardly any detail in them, or, if there is any, it is comparatively unimportant. It is his ambition in every case to go to the heart of the matter&mdash;to set before his reader what is vital and essential, and to leave on one side all the mere husks and shells of history, biography, politics, theology, or criticism. The object is a common one with men of any real artistic power, but we doubt whether any one ever effected it so completely. Mr. Carlyle has hardly ever written a page, however insignificant the subject of it may be, which does not bear upon it the stamp of his own character in a manner almost unexampled. He has spent his life in a protest against the Dryasdusts both of politics and of literature. If people want information about matters of fact, they must go elsewhere. If they want a vivid picture of the fact as Mr. Carlyle saw it, or a vehement set of consequences drawn therefrom, they will nowhere else find anything so vivid. Mr. Carlyle's whole career and present position appear to us to embody more fully than those of any other man the especial advantages and disadvantages of the literary temperament,&mdash;the turn of mind which leads its possessors to sit on a hill retired and make remarks upon men and things instead of taking part in the common affairs of life. We do not mean to say that he has not&mdash;for we think he has&mdash;a very warm sympathy for, and interest in, the race to which he belongs in all the phases of its existence; but he is emphatically a preacher, and not an actor,&mdash;amongst certain classes of society, far the most popular preacher to which this generation has listened.&rdquo;</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="iii"/>
<p><figure id="ill6"><p>The Likeness.</p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="iv"/>
<p><figure id="ill7"><p>Congratulations.</p></figure></p>
</div1>

<div1 type="tale">
<pb n="33" id="p33"/>

<head>[A TALE OF TWO CITIES]</head>

<div2 type="section">

<head>BOOK THE SECOND.
<lb/>
THE GOLDEN THREAD.</head>

<div3 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER I. <lb/> FIVE YEARS LATER.</head>
<p>TELLSON'S Bank by Temple Bar was an old-fashioned place, even in the year one thousand seven hundred and eighty. It was very small, very dark, very ugly, very incommodious. It was an old-fashioned place moreover, in the moral attribute that the partners in the House were proud of its smallness, proud of its darkness, proud of its ugliness, proud of its incommodiousness. They were even boastful of its eminence in those particulars, and were fired by an express conviction that, if it were less objectionable, it would be less respectable. This was no passive belief, but an active weapon which they flashed at more convenient places of business. Tellson's (they said) wanted no elbow-room, Tellson's wanted no light, Tellson's wanted no embellishment. Noakes and Co.'s might, or Snooks Brothers' might; but Tellson's, thank Heaven!&mdash;</p>
<p>Any one of these partners would have disinherited his son on the question of rebuilding Tellson's. In this respect the House was much on a par with the Country; which did very often disinherit its sons for suggesting improvements in laws and customs that had long been highly objectionable, but were only the more respectable.</p>
<p>Thus it had come to pass, that Tellson's was the triumphant perfection of inconvenience. After bursting open a door of idiotic obstinacy with a weak rattle in its throat, you fell into Tellson's down two steps, and came to your senses in a miserable little shop, with two little counters, where the oldest of men made your cheque shake as if the wind rustled it, while they examined the signature by the dingiest of windows, which were always under a shower-bath of mud from Fleet-street, and which were made the dingier by their own iron bars proper, and the heavy shadow of Temple Bar. If your business necessitated your seeing &ldquo;the House,&rdquo; you were put into a species of Condemned Hold at the back, where you meditated on a misspent life, until the House came with its hands in its pockets, and you could hardly blink at it in the dismal twilight. Your money came out of, or went into, wormy old wooden drawers, particles of which flew up your nose and down your throat when they were opened and shut. Your bank-notes had a musty odour, as if they were fast decomposing into rags again. Your plate was stowed away among the neighbouring cesspools, and evil communications
<pb n="34" id="p34"/>
corrupted its good polish in a day or two. Your deeds got into extemporised strong-rooms made of kitchens and sculleries, and fretted all the fat out of their parchments into the banking-house air. Your lighter boxes of family papers went up-stairs into a Barmecide room, that always had a great dining-table in it and never had a dinner, and where, even in the year one thousand seven hundred and eighty, the first letters written to you by your old love, or by your little children, were but newly released from the horror of being ogled through the windows, by the heads exposed on Temple Bar with an insensate brutality and ferocity worthy of Abyssinia or Ashantee.</p>
<p>But indeed, at that time, putting to Death was a recipe much in vogue with all trades and professions, and not least of all with Tellson's. Death is Nature's remedy for all things, and why not Legislation's? Accordingly, the forger was put to Death; the utterer of a bad note was put to Death; the unlawful opener of a letter was put to Death; the purloiner of forty shillings and sixpence was put to Death; the holder of a horse at Tellson's door, who made off with it, was put to Death; the coiner of a bad shilling was put to Death; the sounders of three-fourths of the notes in the whole gamut of Crime, were put to Death. Not that it did the least good in the way of prevention&mdash;it might almost have been worth remarking that the fact was exactly the reverse&mdash;but, it cleared off (as to this world) the trouble of each particular case, and left nothing else connected with it to be looked after. Thus, Tellson's, in its day, like greater places of business, its contemporaries, had taken so many lives, that, if the heads laid low before it had been ranged on Temple Bar instead of being privately disposed of, they would probably have excluded what little light the ground floor had, in a rather significant manner.</p>
<p>Cramped in all kinds of dim cupboards and hutches at Tellson's, the oldest of men carried on the business gravely. When they took a young man into Tellson's London house, they hid him somewhere till he was old. They kept him in a dark place, like a cheese, until he had the full Tellson flavour and blue-mould upon him. Then only was he permitted to be seen, spectacularly poring over large books, and casting his breeches and gaiters into the general weight of the establishment.</p>
<p>Outside Tellson's&mdash;never by any means in it, unless called in&mdash;was an odd-job-man, an occasional porter and messenger, who served as the live sign of the house. He was never absent during business hours, unless upon an errand, and then he was represented by his son: a grisly urchin of twelve, who was his express image. People understood that Tellson's, in a stately way, tolerated the odd-job-man. The House had always tolerated some person in that capacity, and time and tide had drifted this person to the post. His surname was Cruncher, and on the youthful occasion of his renouncing by proxy the works of darkness, in the easterly parish church of Houndsditch, he had received the added appellation of Jerry.</p>
<p>The scene, was Mr. Cruncher's private lodging in Hanging-swordalley, Whitefriars; the time, half-past seven of the clock on a windy March morning, Anno Domini seventeen hundred and eighty. (Mr. Cruncher himself always spoke of the year of our Lord as Anna
<pb n="35" id="p35"/>
Dominoes: apparently under the impression that the Christian era dated from the invention of a popular game, by a lady who had bestowed her name upon it.)</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher's apartments were not in a savoury neighbourhood, and were but two in number, even if a closet with a single pane of glass in it might be counted as one. But, they were very decently kept. Early as it was, on the windy March morning, the room in which he lay a-bed was already scrubbed throughout; and between the cups and saucers arranged for breakfast, and the lumbering deal table, a very clean white cloth was spread.</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher reposed under a patchwork counterpane, like a Harlequin at home. At first, he slept heavily, but, by degrees, began to roll and surge in bed, until he rose above the surface, with his spiky hair looking as if it must tear the sheets to ribbons. At which juncture, he exclaimed, in a voice of dire exasperation:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bust me, if she ain't at it agin!&rdquo;</p>
<p>A woman of orderly and industrious appearance rose from her knees in a corner, with sufficient haste and trepidation to show that she was the person referred to.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What!&rdquo; said Mr. Cruncher, looking out of bed for a boot. &ldquo;You're at it agin, are you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>After hailing the morn with this second salutation, he threw a boot at the woman as a third. It was a very muddy boot, and may introduce the odd circumstance connected with Mr. Cruncher's domestic economy, that, whereas he often came home after banking hours with clean boots, he often got up next morning to find the same boots covered with clay.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What,&rdquo; said Mr. Cruncher, varying his apostrophe after missing his mark&mdash;&ldquo;what are you up to, Aggerawayter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was only saying my prayers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Saying your prayers. You're a nice woman! What do you mean by flopping yourself down and praying agin me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was not praying against you; I was praying for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You weren't. And if you were, I won't be took the liberty with. Here! your mother's a nice woman, young Jerry, going a praying agin your father's prosperity. You've got a dutiful mother, you have, my son. You've got a religious mother, you have, my boy: going and flopping herself down, and praying that the bread-and-butter may be snatched out of the mouth of her only child!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Master Cruncher (who was in his shirt) took this very ill, and, turning to his mother, strongly deprecated any praying away of his personal board.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what do you suppose, you conceited female,&rdquo; said Mr. Cruncher, with unconscious inconsistency, &ldquo;that the worth of <hi rend="italics">your</hi> prayers may be? Name the price that you put <hi rend="italics">your</hi> prayers at!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They only come from the heart, Jerry. They are worth no more than that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Worth no more than that,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Cruncher. &ldquo;They ain't worth much, then. Whether or no, I won't be prayed agin, I tell you. I can't afford it. I'm not a going to be made unlucky by <hi rend="italics">your</hi> sneaking. If you must go flopping yourself down, flop in favour of your husband and child, and not in opposition to 'em. If I had had any but a unnat'ral wife, and this poor boy had had any but a unnat'ral
<pb n="36" id="p36"/>
mother, I might have made some money last week, instead of being counterprayed and countermined and religiously circumwented into the worst of luck. Bu-u-ust me!&rdquo; said Mr. Cruncher, who all this time had been putting on his clothes, &ldquo;if I ain't, what with piety and one blowed thing and another, been choused this last week into as bad luck as ever a poor devil of a honest tradesman met with! Young Jerry, dress yourself, my boy, and while I clean my boots keep a eye upon your mother now and then, and if you see any signs of more flopping, give me a call. For, I tell you,&rdquo; here he addressed his wife once more, &ldquo;I won't be gone agin, in this manner. I am as rickety as a hackney-coach, I'm as sleepy as laudanum, my lines is strained to that degree that I shouldn't know, if it wasn't for the pain in 'em, which was me and which somebody else, yet I'm none the better for it in pocket; and it's my suspicion that you've been at it from morning to night to prevent me from being the better for it in pocket, and I won't put up with it, Aggerawayter, and what do you say now!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Growling, in addition, such phrases as &ldquo;Ah! yes! You're religious, too. You wouldn't put yourself in opposition to the interests of your husband and child, would you? Not you!&rdquo; and throwing off other sarcastic sparks from the whirling grindstone of his indignation, Mr. Cruncher betook himself to his boot-cleaning and his general preparations for business. In the mean time, his son, whose head was garnished with tenderer spikes, and whose young eyes stood close by one another, as his father's did, kept the required watch upon his mother. He greatly disturbed that poor woman at intervals, by darting out of his sleeping closet, where he made his toilet, with a suppressed cry of &ldquo;You are going to flop, mother.&mdash;Halloa, father!&rdquo; and, after raising this fictitious alarm, darting in again with an undutiful grin.</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher's temper was not at all improved when he came to his breakfast. He resented Mrs. Cruncher's saying Grace with particular animosity.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, Aggerawayter! What are you up to? At it agin?&rdquo;</p>
<p>His wife explained that she had merely &ldquo;asked a blessing.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't do it!&rdquo; said Mr. Cruncher, looking about, as if he rather expected to see the loaf disappear under the efficacy of his wife's petitions. &ldquo;I ain't a going to be blest out of house and home. I won't have my wittles blest off my table. Keep still!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Exceedingly red-eyed and grim, as if he had been up all night at a party which had taken anything but a convivial turn, Jerry Cruncher worried his breakfast rather than ate it, growling over it like any four-footed inmate of a menagerie. Towards nine o'clock he smoothed his ruffled aspect, and, presenting as respectable and business-like an exterior as he could overlay his natural self with, issued forth to the occupation of the day.</p>
<p>It could scarcely be called a trade, in spite of his favourite description of himself as &ldquo;a honest tradesman.&rdquo; His stock consisted of a wooden stool, made out of a broken-backed chair cut down, which stool young Jerry, walking at his father's side, carried every morning to beneath the banking-house window that was nearest Temple Bar: where, with the addition of the first handful of straw that could be gleaned from any passing vehicle to keep the
<pb n="37" id="p37"/>
cold and wet from the odd-job-man's feet, it formed the encampment for the day. On this post of his, Mr. Cruncher was as well known to Fleet-street and the Temple, as the Bar itself&mdash;and was almost as ill-looking.</p>
<p>Encamped at a quarter before nine, in good time to touch his three-cornered hat to the oldest of men as they passed in to Tellson's, Jerry took up his station on this windy March morning, with Young Jerry standing by him, when not engaged in making forays through the Bar, to inflict bodily and mental injuries of an acute description on passing boys who were small enough for his amiable purpose. Father and son, extremely like each other, looking silently on at the morning traffic in Fleet-street, with their two heads as near to one another as the two eyes of each were, bore a considerable resemblance to a pair of monkeys. The resemblance was not lessened by the accidental circumstance, that the mature Jerry bit and spat out straw, while the twinkling eyes of the youthful Jerry were as restlessly watchful of him as of everything else in Fleet-street.</p>
<p>The head of one of the regular in-door messengers attached to Tellson's establishment was put through the door, and the word was given:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Porter wanted!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hooray, father! Here's an early job to begin with!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having thus given his parent God speed, Young Jerry seated himself on the stool, entered on his reversionary interest in the straw his father had been chewing, and cogitated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Al-ways rusty! His fingers is al-ways rusty!&rdquo; muttered Young Jerry. &ldquo;Where does my father get all that iron rust from? He don't get no iron rust here!&rdquo;</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER II. <lb/> A SIGHT.</head>
<p>&ldquo;You know the Old Bailey well, no doubt?&rdquo; said one of the oldest of clerks to Jerry the messenger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ye-es, sir,&rdquo; returned Jerry, in something of a dogged manner. &ldquo;I <hi rend="italics">do</hi> know the Bailey.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just so. And you know Mr. Lorry.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know Mr. Lorry, sir, much better than I know the Bailey. Much better,&rdquo; said Jerry, not unlike a reluctant witness at the establishment in question, &ldquo;than I, as a honest tradesman, wish to know the Bailey.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very well. Find the door where the witnesses go in, and show the doorkeeper this note for Mr. Lorry. He will then let you in.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Into the court, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Into the court.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher's eyes seemed to get a little closer to one another, and to interchange the inquiry, &ldquo;What do you think of this?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="38" id="p38"/>
<p>&ldquo;Am I to wait in the court, sir?&rdquo; he asked, as the result of that conference.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am going to tell you. The doorkeeper will pass the note to Mr. Lorry, and do you make any gesture that will attract Mr. Lorry's attention, and show him where you stand. Then what you have to do, is, to remain there until he wants you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is that all, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's all. He wishes to have a messenger at hand. This is to tell him you are there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the ancient clerk deliberately folded and superscribed the note, Mr. Cruncher, after surveying him in silence until he came to the blotting-paper stage, remarked:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose they'll be trying Forgeries this morning?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Treason!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's quartering,&rdquo; said Jerry. &ldquo;Barbarous!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is the law,&rdquo; remarked the ancient clerk, turning his surprised spectacles upon him. &ldquo;It is the law.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's hard in the law to spile a man, I think. It's hard enough to kill him, but it's wery hard to spile him, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all,&rdquo; returned the ancient clerk. &ldquo;Speak well of the law. Take care of your chest and voice, my good friend, and leave the law to take care of itself. I give you that advice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's the damp, sir, what settles on my chest and voice,&rdquo; said Jerry. &ldquo;I leave you to judge what a damp way of earning a living mine is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, well,&rdquo; said the old clerk; &ldquo;we all have our various ways of gaining a livelihood. Some of us have damp ways, and some of us have dry ways. Here is the letter. Go along.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Jerry took the letter, and, remarking to himself with less internal deference than he made an outward show of, &ldquo;You are a lean old one, too,&rdquo; made his bow, informed his son, in passing, of his destination, and went his way.</p>
<p>They hanged at Tyburn, in those days, so the street outside Newgate had not obtained one infamous notoriety that has since attached to it. But, the gaol was a vile place, in which most kinds of debauchery and villany were practised, and where dire diseases were bred, that came into court with the prisoners, and sometimes rushed straight from the dock at my Lord Chief Justice himself, and pulled him off the bench. It had more than once happened, that the judge in the black cap pronounced his own doom as certainly as the prisoner's, and even died before him. For the rest, the Old Bailey was famous as a kind of deadly inn-yard, from which pale travellers set out continually, in carts and coaches, on a violent passage into the other world: traversing some two miles and a half of public street and road, and shaming few good citizens, if any. So powerful is use, and so desirable to be good use in the beginning. It was famous, too, for the pillory, a wise old institution, that inflicted a punishment of which no one could foresee the extent; also, for the whipping-post, another dear old institution, very humanising and softening to behold in action; also, for extensive transactions in blood-money, another fragment of ancestral wisdom, systematically leading to the most frightful mercenary crimes that could be committed under Heaven. Altogether, the Old Bailey, at that date,
<pb n="39" id="p39"/>
was a choice illustration of the precept, that &ldquo;Whatever is is right;&rdquo; an aphorism that would be as final as it is lazy, did it not include the troublesome consequence, that nothing that ever was, was wrong.</p>
<p>Making his way through the tainted crowd, dispersed up and down this hideous scene of action, with the skill of a man accustomed to make his way quietly, the messenger found out the door he sought, and handed in his letter through a trap in it. For, people then paid to see the play at the Old Bailey, just as they paid to see the play in Bedlam&mdash;only the former entertainment was much the dearer. Therefore, all the Old Bailey doors were well guarded&mdash;except, indeed, the social doors by which the criminals got there, and they were always left wide open.</p>
<p>After some delay and demur, the door grudgingly turned on its hinges a very little way, and allowed Mr. Jerry Cruncher to squeeze himself into court.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's on?&rdquo; he asked, in a whisper, of the man he found himself next to.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's coming on?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Treason case.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The quartering one, eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; returned the man, with a relish; &ldquo;he'll be drawn on a hurdle to be half hanged, and then he'll be taken down and sliced before his own face, and then his inside will be taken out and burnt while he looks on, and then his head will be chopped off, and he'll be cut into quarters. That's the sentence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If he's found Guilty, you mean to say?&rdquo; Jerry added, by way of proviso.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! they'll find him Guilty,&rdquo; said the other. &ldquo;Don't you be afraid of that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher's attention was here diverted to the doorkeeper, whom he saw making his way to Mr. Lorry, with the note in his hand. Mr. Lorry sat at a table, among the gentlemen in wigs: not far from a wigged gentleman, the prisoner's counsel, who had a great bundle of papers before him: and nearly opposite another wigged gentleman with his hands in his pockets, whose whole attention, when Mr. Cruncher looked at him then or afterwards, seemed to be concentrated on the ceiling of the court. After some gruff coughing and rubbing of his chin and signing with his hand, Jerry attracted the notice of Mr. Lorry, who had stood up to look for him, and who quietly nodded, and sat down again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's <hi rend="italics">he</hi> got to do with the case?&rdquo; asked the man he had spoken with.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Blest if I know,&rdquo; said Jerry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What have <hi rend="italics">you</hi> got to do with it, then, if a person may inquire?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Blest if I know that either,&rdquo; said Jerry.</p>
<p>The entrance of the Judge, and a consequent great stir and settling-down in the court, stopped the dialogue. Presently, the dock became the central point of interest. Two gaolers, who had been standing there, went out, and the prisoner was brought in, and put to the bar.</p>
<pb n="40" id="p40"/>
<p>Everybody present, except the one wigged gentleman who looked at the ceiling, started at him. All the human breath in the place, rolled at him, like a sea, or a wind, or a fire. Eager faces strained round pillars and corners, to get a sight of him; spectators in back rows stood up, not to miss a hair of him; people on the floor of the court, laid their hands on the shoulders of the people before them, to help themselves, at anybody's cost, to a view of him &mdash; stood a-tiptoe, got upon ledges, stood upon next to nothing, to see every inch of him. Conspicuous among these latter, like an animated bit of the spiked wall of Newgate, Jerry stood: aiming at the prisoner the beery breath of a whet he had taken as he came along, and discharging it to mingle with the waves of other beer, and gin, and tea, and coffee, and what not, that flowed at him, and already broke upon the great windows behind him in an impure mist and rain.</p>
<p>The object of all this staring and blaring, was a young man of about five-and-twenty, well-grown and well-looking, with a sunburnt cheek and a dark eye. His condition was that of a young gentleman. He was plainly dressed in black, or very dark grey, and his hair, which was long and dark, was gathered in a ribbon at the back of his neck: more to be out of his way than for ornament. As an emotion of the mind will express itself through any covering of the body, so the paleness which his situation engendered came through the brown upon his cheek, showing the soul to be stronger than the sun. He was otherwise quite self-possessed, bowed to the Judge, and stood quiet.</p>
<p>The sort of interest with which this man was stared and breathed at, was not a sort that elevated humanity. Had he stood in peril of a less horrible sentence&mdash;had there been a chance of any one of its savage details being spared&mdash;by just so much would he have lost in his fascination. The form that was to be doomed to be so shamefully mangled, was the sight; the immortal creature that was to be so butchered and torn asunder, yielded the sensation. Whatever gloss the various spectators put upon the interest, according to their several arts and powers of self-deceit, the interest was, at the root of it, Ogreish.</p>
<p>Silence in the court! Charles Darnay had yesterday pleaded Not Guilty to an indictment denouncing him (with infinite jingle and jangle) for that he was a false traitor to our serene, illustrious, excellent, and so forth, prince, our Lord the King, by reason of his having, on divers occasions, and by divers means and ways, assisted Lewis, the French King, in his wars against our said serene, illustrious, excellent, and so forth; that was to say, by coming and going between the dominions of our said serene, illustrious, excellent, and so forth, and those of the said French Lewis, and wickedly, falsely, traitorously, and otherwise evil-adverbiously, revealing to the said French Lewis what forces our said serene, illustrious, excellent, and so forth, had in preparation to send to Canada and North America. This much, Jerry, with his head becoming more and more spiky as the law terms bristled it, made out with huge satisfaction, and so arrived circuitously at the understanding that the aforesaid, and over and over again aforesaid, Charles Darnay, stood there before him upon his trial; that the jury were swearing in; and that Mr. Attorney-General was making ready to speak.</p>
<pb n="41" id="p41"/>
<p>The accused, who was (and who knew he was) being mentally hanged, beheaded, and quartered, by everybody there, neither flinched from the situation, nor assumed any theatrical air in it. He was quiet and attentive; watched the opening proceedings with a grave interest; and stood with his hands resting on the slab of wood before him, so composedly, that they had not displaced a leaf of the herbs with which it was strewn. The court was all bestrewn with herbs and sprinkled with vinegar, as a precaution against gaol air and gaol fever.</p>
<p>Over the prisoner's head, there was a mirror, to throw the light down upon him. Crowds of the wicked and the wretched had been reflected in it, and had passed from its surface and this earth's together. Haunted in a most ghastly manner that abominable place would have been, if the glass could ever have rendered back its reflexions, as the ocean is one day to give up its dead. Some passing thought of the infamy and disgrace for which it had been reserved, may have struck the prisoner's mind. Be that as it may, a change in his position making him conscious of a bar of light across his face, he looked up; and when he saw the glass his face flushed, and his right hand pushed the herbs away.</p>
<p>It happened, that the action turned his face to that side of the court which was on his left. About on a level with his eyes, there sat, in that corner of the Judge's bench, two persons upon whom his look immediately rested; so immediately, and so much to the changing of his aspect, that all the eyes that were turned upon him, turned to them.</p>
<p>The spectators saw in the two figures, a young lady of little more than twenty, and a gentleman who was evidently her father; a man of a very remarkable appearance in respect of the absolute whiteness of his hair, and a certain indescribable intensity of face: not of an active kind, but pondering and self-communing. When this expression was upon him, he looked as if he were old; but, when it was stirred and broken up&mdash;as it was now, in a moment, on his speaking to his daughter&mdash;he became a handsome man, not past the prime of life.</p>
<p>His daughter had one of her hands drawn through his arm, as she sat by him, and the other pressed upon it. She had drawn close to him, in her dread of the scene, and in her pity for the prisoner. Her forehead had been strikingly expressive of an engrossing terror and compassion that saw nothing but the peril of the accused. This had been so very noticeable, so very powerfully and naturally shown, that starers who had had no pity for him were touched by her; and the whisper went about, &ldquo;Who are they?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Jerry the messenger, who had made his own observations in his own manner, and who had been sucking the rust off his fingers in his absorption, stretched his neck to hear who they were. The crowd about him had pressed and passed the inquiry on to the nearest attendant, and from him it had been more slowly pressed and passed back: at last it got to Jerry:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Witnesses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For which side?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Against.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Against what side?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="42" id="p42"/>
<p>&ldquo;The prisoner's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Judge, whose eyes had gone in the general direction, recalled them, leaned back in his seat, and looked steadily at the man whose life was in his hand, as Mr. Attorney-General rose to spin the rope, grind the axe, and hammer the nails into the scaffold.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER III. <lb/> A DISAPPOINTMENT.</head>
<p>MR. ATTORNEY-GENERAL had to inform the jury, that the prisoner before them, though young in years, was old in the treasonable practices which claimed the forfeit of his life. That this correspondence with the public enemy was not a correspondence of to-day, or of yesterday, or even of last year, or of the year before. That, it was certain the prisoner had, for longer than that, been in the habit of passing and repassing between France and England, on secret business of which he could give no honest account. That, if it were in the nature of traitorous ways to thrive (which, happily, it never was), the real wickedness and guilt of his business might have remained undiscovered. That, Providence, however, had put it into the heart of a person who was beyond fear and beyond reproach, to ferret out the nature of the prisoner's schemes, and, struck with horror, to disclose them to his Majesty's Chief Secretary of State and most honourable Privy Council. That, this patriot would be produced before them. That, his position and attitude were, on the whole, sublime. That, he had been the prisoner's friend, but, at once in an auspicious and an evil hour detecting his infamy, had resolved to immolate the traitor he could no longer cherish in his bosom, on the sacred altar of his country. That, if statues were decreed in Britain, as in ancient Greece and Rome, to public benefactors, this shining citizen would assuredly have had one. That, as they were not so decreed, he probably would not have one. That, Virtue, as had been observed by the poets (in many passages which he well knew the jury would have, word for word, at the tips of their tongues; whereat the jury's countenances displayed a guilty consciousness that they knew nothing about the passages), was in a manner contagious; more especially the bright virtue known as patriotism, or love of country. That, the lofty example of this immaculate and unimpeachable witness for the Crown, to refer to whom however unworthily was an honour, had communicated itself to the prisoner's servant, and had engendered in him a holy determination to examine his master's table-drawers and pockets, and secrete his papers. That, he (Mr. Attorney-General) was prepared to hear some disparagement attempted of this admirable servant; but that, in a general way, he preferred him to his (Mr. Attorney-General's) brothers and sisters, and honoured him more than his (Mr. Attorney General's) father and mother. That, he called with confidence on the jury to come and do likewise. That, the evidence of these two witnesses, coupled with the documents of their discovering that would
<pb n="43" id="p43"/>
be produced, would show the prisoner to have been furnished with lists of his Majesty's forces, and of their disposition and preparation, both by sea and land, and would leave no doubt that he had habitually conveyed such information to a hostile power. That, these lists could not be proved to be in the prisoner's handwriting; but that it was all the same; that, indeed, it was rather the better for the prosecution, as showing the prisoner to be artful in his precautions. That, the proof would go back five years, and would show the prisoner already engaged in these pernicious missions, within a few weeks before the date of the very first action fought between the British troops and the Americans. That, for these reasons, the jury, being a loyal jury (as he knew they were), and being a responsible jury (as <hi rend="italics">they</hi> knew they were), must positively find the prisoner Guilty, and make an end of him, whether they liked it or not. That, they never could lay their heads upon their pillows; that, they never could tolerate the idea of their wives laying their heads upon their pillows; that, they never could endure the notion of their children laying their heads upon their pillows; in short, that there never more could be, for them or theirs, any laying of heads upon pillows at all, unless the prisoner's head was taken off. That head Mr. Attorney-General concluded by demanding of them, in the name of everything he could think of with a round turn in it, and on the faith of his solemn asseveration that he already considered the prisoner as good as dead and gone.</p>
<p>When the Attorney-General ceased, a buzz arose in the court as if a cloud of great blue-flies were swarming about the prisoner, in anticipation of what he was soon to become. When it toned down again, the unimpeachable patriot appeared in the witness-box.</p>
<p>Mr. Solicitor-General then, following his leader's lead, examined the patriot: John Barsad, gentleman, by name. The story of his pure soul was exactly what Mr. Attorney-General had described it to be&mdash;perhaps, if it had a fault, a little too exactly. Having released his noble bosom of its burden, he would have modestly withdrawn himself, but that the wigged gentleman with the papers before him, sitting not far from Mr. Lorry, begged to ask him a few questions. The wigged gentleman sitting opposite, still looked at the ceiling of the court.</p>
<p>Had he ever been a spy himself? No, he scorned the base insinuation. What did he live upon? His property. Where was his property? He didn't precisely remember where it was. What was it? No business of anybody's. Had he inherited it? Yes, he had. From whom? Distant relation. Very distant? Rather. Ever been in prison? Certainly not. Never in a debtors' prison? Didn't see what that had to do with it. Never in a debtors' prison?&mdash;Come, once again. Never? Yes. How many times? Two or three times. Not five or six? Perhaps. Of what profession? Gentleman. Ever been kicked? Might have been. Frequently? No. Ever kicked down stairs? Decidedly not; once received a kick on the top of a staircase, and fell down stairs of his own accord. Kicked on that occasion for cheating at dice? Something to that effect was said by the intoxicated liar who committed the assault, but it was not true. Swear it was not true? Positively. Ever live by cheating at play? Never. Ever live by play? Not more than other gentlemen do. Ever borrow money of the prisoner? Yes. Ever pay him? No.
<pb n="44" id="p44"/>
Was not this intimacy with the prisoner, in reality a very slight one, forced upon the prisoner in coaches, inns, and packets? No. Sure he saw the prisoner with these lists? Certain. Knew no more about the lists? No. Had not procured them himself, for instance? No. Expect to get anything by this evidence? No. Not in regular government pay and employment, to lay traps? Oh dear no. Or to do anything? Oh dear no. Swear that? Over and over again. No motives but motives of sheer patriotism? None whatever.</p>
<p>The virtuous servant, Roger Cly, swore his way through the case at a great rate. He had taken service with the prisoner, in good faith and simplicity, four years ago. He had asked the prisoner, aboard the Calais packet, if he wanted a handy fellow, and the prisoner had engaged him. He had not asked the prisoner to take the handy fellow as an act of charity&mdash;never thought of such a thing. He began to have suspicions of the prisoner, and to keep an eye upon him, soon afterwards. In arranging his clothes, while travelling, he had seen similar lists to these in the prisoner's pockets, over and over again. He had taken these lists from the drawer of the prisoner's desk. He had not put them there first. He had seen the prisoner show these identical lists to French gentlemen at Calais, and similar lists to French gentlemen, both at Calais and Boulogne. He loved his country, and couldn't bear it, and had given information. He had never been suspected of stealing a silver teapot; he had been maligned respecting a mustard-pot, but it turned out to be only a plated one. He had known the last witness seven or eight years; that was merely a coincidence. He didn't call it a particularly curious coincidence; most coincidences were curious. Neither did he call it a curious coincidence that true patriotism was <hi rend="italics">his</hi> only motive too. He was a true Briton, and hoped there were many like him.</p>
<p>The blue-flies buzzed again, and Mr. Attorney-General called Mr. Jarvis Lorry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Jarvis Lorry, are you a clerk in Tellson's bank?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;On a certain Friday night in November one thousand seven hundred and seventy-five, did business occasion you to travel between London and Dover by the mail?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It did.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Were there any other passengers in the mail?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Two.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did they alight on the road in the course of the night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They did.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Lorry, look upon the prisoner. Was he one of those two passengers?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I cannot undertake to say that he was.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does he resemble either of those two passengers?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Both were so wrapped up, and the night was so dark, and we were all so reserved, that I cannot undertake to say even that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Lorry, look again upon the prisoner. Supposing him wrapped up as those two passengers were, is there anything in his bulk and stature to render it unlikely that he was one of them?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will not swear, Mr. Lorry, that he was not one of them?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="45" id="p45"/>
<p>&ldquo;So at least you say he may have been one of them?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes. Except that I remember them both to have been&mdash;like myself&mdash;timorous of highwaymen, and the prisoner has not a timorous air.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you ever see a counterfeit of timidity, Mr. Lorry?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I certainly have seen that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Lorry, look once more upon the prisoner. Have you seen him, to your certain knowledge, before?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was returning from France a few days afterwards, and, at Calais, the prisoner came on board the packet-ship in which I returned, and made the voyage with me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At what hour did he come on board?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At a little after midnight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the dead of the night. Was he the only passenger who came on board at that untimely hour?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He happened to be the only one.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never mind about &lsquo;happening,&rsquo; Mr. Lorry. He was the only passenger who came on board in the dead of the night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Were you travelling alone, Mr. Lorry, or with any companion?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With two companions. A gentleman and lady. They are here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They are here. Had you any conversation with the prisoner?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hardly any. The weather was stormy, and the passage long and rough, and I lay on a sofa, almost from shore to shore.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The young lady, to whom all eyes had been turned before, and were now turned again, stood up where she had sat. Her father rose with her, and kept her hand drawn through his arm.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, look upon the prisoner.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To be confronted with such pity, and such earnest youth and beauty, was far more trying to the accused than to be confronted with all the crowd. Standing, as it were, apart with her on the edge of his grave, not all the staring curiosity that looked on, could, for the moment, nerve him to remain quite still. His hurried right hand parcelled out the herbs before him into imaginary beds of flowers in a garden; and his efforts to control and steady his breathing, shook the lips from which the colour rushed to his heart. The buzz of the great flies was loud again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, have you seen the prisoner before?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;On board of the packet-ship just now referred to, sir, and on the same occasion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are the young lady just now referred to?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O! most unhappily, I am!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The plaintive tone of her compassion merged into the less musical voice of the Judge, as he said, something fiercely: &ldquo;Answer the questions put to you, and make no remark upon them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, had you any conversation with the prisoner on that passage across the Channel?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="46" id="p46"/>
<p>&ldquo;Recal it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the midst of a profound stillness, she faintly began:</p>
<p>&ldquo;When the gentleman came on board&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you mean the prisoner?&rdquo; inquired the Judge, knitting his brows.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my Lord.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then say the prisoner.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When the prisoner came on board, he noticed that my father,&rdquo; turning her eyes lovingly to him as he stood beside her, &ldquo;was much fatigued and in a very weak state of health. My father was so reduced, that I was afraid to take him out of the air, and I had made a bed for him on the deck near the cabin steps, and I sat on the deck at his side to take care of him. There were no other passengers that night, but we four. The prisoner was so good as to beg permission to advise me how I could shelter my father from the wind and weather, better than I had done. I had not known how to do it well, not understanding how the wind would set when we were out of the harbour. He did it for me. He expressed great gentleness and kindness for my father's state, and I am sure he felt it. That was the manner of our beginning to speak together.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let me interrupt you for a moment. Had he come on board alone?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How many were with him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Two French gentlemen.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Had they conferred together?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They had conferred together until the last moment, when it was necessary for the French gentlemen to be landed in their boat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Had any papers been handed about among them, similar to these lists?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some papers had been handed about among them, but I don't know what papers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Like these in shape and size?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Possibly, but indeed I don't know, although they stood whispering very near to me: because they stood at the top of the cabin stops to have the light of the lamp that was hanging there; it was a dull lamp, and they spoke very low, and I did not hear what they said, and saw only that they looked at papers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, to the prisoner's conversation, Miss Manette.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The prisoner was as open in his confidence with me&mdash;which arose out of my helpless situation&mdash;as he was kind, and good, and useful to my father. I hope,&rdquo; bursting into tears, &ldquo;I may not repay him by doing him harm to-day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Buzzing from the blue-flies.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, if the prisoner does not perfectly understand that you give the evidence which it is your duty to give&mdash;which you must give&mdash;and which you cannot escape from giving&mdash;with great unwillingness, he is the only person present in that condition. Please to go on.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He told me that he was travelling on business of a delicate and difficult nature, which might get people into trouble, and that he was therefore travelling under an assumed name. He said that this business had, within a few days, taken him to France, and might,
<pb n="47" id="p47"/>
at intervals, take him backwards and forwards between France and England for a long time to come.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did he say anything about America, Miss Manette? Be particular.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He tried to explain to me how that quarrel had arisen, and he said that, so far as he could judge, it was a wrong and foolish one on England's part. He added, in a jesting way, that perhaps George Washington might gain almost as great a name in history as George the Third. But there was no harm in his way of saying this: it was said laughingly, and to beguile the time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Any strongly marked expression of face on the part of a chief actor in a scene of great interest to whom many eyes are directed, will be unconsciously imitated by the spectators. Her forehead was painfully anxious and intent as she gave this evidence, and, in the pauses when she stopped for the Judge to write it down, watched its effect upon the Counsel for and against. Among the lookers-on there was the same expression in all quarters of the court; insomuch, that a great majority of the foreheads there, might have been mirrors reflecting the witness, when the Judge looked up from his notes to glare at that tremendous heresy about George Washington.</p>
<p>Mr. Attorney-General now signified to my Lord, that he deemed it necessary, as a matter of precaution and form, to call the young lady's father, Doctor Manette. Who was called accordingly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Manette, look upon the prisoner. Have you ever seen him before?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Once. When he called at my lodgings in London. Some three years, or three years and a half, ago.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can you identify him as your fellow-passenger on board the packet, or speak to his conversation with your daughter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir, I can do neither.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is there any particular and special reason for your being unable to do either.?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He answered, in a low voice, &ldquo;There is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Has it been your misfortune to undergo a long imprisonment, without trial, or even accusation, in your native country, Doctor Manette?&rdquo;</p>
<p>He answered, in a tone that went to every heart, &ldquo;A long imprisonment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Were you newly released on the occasion in question?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They tell me so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you no remembrance of the occasion?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;None. My mind is a blank, from some time&mdash;I cannot even say what time&mdash;when I employed myself, in my captivity, in making shoes, to the time when I found myself living in London with my dear daughter here. She had become familiar to me, when a gracious God restored my faculties; but, I am quite unable even to say how she had become familiar. I have no remembrance of the process.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Attorney-General sat down, and the father and daughter sat down together.</p>
<p>A singular circumstance then arose in the case. The object in hand, being, to show that the prisoner went down, with some fellow-plotter untracked, in the Dover mail on that Friday night in November five years ago, and got out of the mail in the night, as a
<pb n="48" id="p48"/>
blind, at a place where he did not remain, but from which he travelled back some dozen miles or more, to a garrison and dockyard, and there collected information; a witness was called to identify him as having been at the precise time required, in the coffee-room of an hotel in that garrison-and-dockyard town, waiting for another person. The prisoner's counsel was cross-examining this witness with no result, except that he had never seen the prisoner on any other occasion, when the wigged gentleman who had all this time been looking at the ceiling of the court, wrote a word or two on a little piece of paper, screwed it up, and tossed it to him. Opening this piece of paper in the next pause, the counsel looked with great attention and curiosity at the prisoner.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You say again you are quite sure that it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> the prisoner?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The witness was quite sure.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you ever see anybody very like the prisoner?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Not so like (the witness said), as that he could be mistaken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Look well upon that gentleman, my learned friend there,&rdquo; pointing to him who had tossed the paper over, &ldquo;and then look well upon the prisoner. How say you? Are they very like each other?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Allowing for my learned friend's appearance being careless and slovenly, if not debauched, they were sufficiently like each other to surprise, not only the witness, but everybody present, when they were thus brought into comparison. My Lord being prayed to bid my learned friend lay aside his wig, and giving no very gracious consent, the likeness became much more remarkable. My Lord inquired of Mr. Stryver (the prisoner's counsel), whether they were next to try Mr. Carton (name of my learned friend) for treason? But, Mr. Stryver replied to my Lord, no; but he would ask the witness to tell him whether what happened once, might happen twice; whether he would have been so confident if he had seen this illustration of his rashness sooner; whether he would be so confident, having seen it; and more. The upshot of which, was, to smash this witness like a crockery vessel, and shiver his part of the case to useless lumber.</p>
<p>Mr. Cruncher had by this time taken quite a lunch of rust off his fingers, in his following of the evidence. He had now to attend while Mr. Stryver fitted the prisoner's case on the jury, like a compact suit of clothes; showing them how the patriot, Barsad, was a hired spy and traitor, an unblushing trafficker in blood, and one of the greatest scoundrels upon earth since accursed Judas&mdash;which he certainly did look rather like. How the virtuous servant, Cly, was his friend and partner, and was worthy to be; how the watchful eyes of those forgers and false swearers had rested on the prisoner as a victim, because some family affairs in France, he being of French extraction, did require his making those passages across the Channel&mdash;though what those affairs were, a consideration for others who were near and dear to him, forbad him, even for his life, to disclose. How the evidence that had been warped and wrested from the young lady, whose anguish in giving it they had witnessed, came to nothing, involving the mere little innocent gallantries and politenesses likely to pass between any young gentleman and young lady so thrown together:&mdash;with the exception of that reference to George Washington, which was altogether too extravagant and impossible, to be regarded in any other light than as a monstrous joke. How it would
<pb n="49" id="p49"/>
be a weakness in the government to break down in this attempt to practise for popularity on the lowest national antipathies and fears, and therefore Mr. Attorney-General had made the most of it; how, nevertheless, it rested upon nothing, save that vile and infamous character of evidence too often disfiguring such cases, and of which the State Trials of this country were full. But, there My Lord interposed (with as grave a face as if it had not been true), saying that he could not sit upon that Bench and suffer those allusions.</p>
<p>Mr. Stryver then called his few witnesses, and Mr. Cruncher had next to attend while Mr. Attorney-General turned the whole suit of clothes Mr. Stryver had fitted on the jury, inside out; showing how Barsad and Cly were even a hundred times better than he had thought them, and the prisoner a hundred times worse. Lastly, came My Lord himself, turning the suit of clothes, now inside out, now outside in, but on the whole decidedly trimming and shaping them into grave-clothes for the prisoner.</p>
<p>And now, the jury turned to consider, and the great flies swarmed again.</p>
<p>Mr. Carton, who had so long sat looking at the ceiling of the court, changed neither his place nor his attitude, even in this excitement. While his learned friend, Mr. Stryver, massing his papers before him, whispered with those who sat near, and from time to time glanced anxiously at the jury; while all the spectators moved more or less, and grouped themselves anew; while even My Lord himself arose from his seat, and slowly paced up and down his platform, not unattended by a suspicion in the minds of the audience that his state was feverish; this one man sat leaning back, with his torn gown half off him, his untidy wig put on just as it had happened to light on his head after its removal, his hands in his pockets, and his eyes on the ceiling as they had been all day. Something especially reckless in his demeanour, not only gave him a disreputable look, but so diminished the strong resemblance he undoubtedly bore to the prisoner (which his momentary earnestness, when they were compared together, had strengthened), that many of the lookers-on, taking note of him now, said to one another they would hardly have thought the two were so alike. Mr. Cruncher made the observation to his next neighbour, and added, &ldquo;I'd hold half a guinea that <hi rend="italics">he</hi> don't get no law-work to do. Don't look like the sort of one to get any, do he?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Yet, this Mr. Carton took in more of the details of the scene than he appeared to take in; for now, when Miss Manette's head dropped upon her father's breast, he was the first to see it, and to say audibly: &ldquo;Officer! look to that young lady. Help the gentleman to take her out. Don't you see she will fall!&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was much commiseration for her as she was removed, and much sympathy with her father. It had evidently been a great distress to him, to have the days of his imprisonment recalled. He had shown strong internal agitation when he was questioned, and that pondering or brooding look which made him old, had been upon him, loke a heavy cloud, ever since. As he passed out, the jury, who had turned back and paused a moment, spoke, through their foreman.</p>
<p>They were not agreed, and wished to retire. My Lord (perhaps
<pb n="50" id="p50"/>
with George Washington on his mind) showed some surprise that they were not agreed, but signified his pleasure that they should retire under watch and ward, and retired himself. The trial had lasted all day, and the lamps in the court were now being lighted. It began to be rumoured that the jury would be out a long while. The spectators dropped off to get refreshment, and the prisoner withdrew to the back of the dock, and sat down.</p>
<p>Mr. Lorry, who had gone out when the young lady and her father went out, now reappeared, and beckoned to Jerry: who, in the slackened interest, could easily get near him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Jerry, if you wish to take something to eat, you can. But, keep in the way. You will be sure to hear when the jury come in. Don't be a moment behind them, for I want you to take the verdict back to the bank. You are the quickest messenger I know, and will get to Temple Bar long before I can.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Jerry had just enough forehead to knuckle, and he knuckled it in acknowledgment of this communication and a shilling. Mr. Carton came up at the moment, and touched Mr. Lorry on the arm.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How is the young lady?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is greatly distressed; but her father is comforting her, and she feels the better for being out of court.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll tell the prisoner so. It won't do for a respectable bankgentleman like you, to be seen speaking to him publicly, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Lorry reddened, as if he were conscious of having debated the point in his mind, and Mr. Carton made his way to the outside of the bar. The way out of court lay in that direction, and Jerry followed him, all eyes, ears, and spikes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Darnay!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The prisoner came forward directly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will naturally be anxious to hear of the witness, Miss Manette. She will do very well. You have seen the worst of her agitation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am deeply sorry to have been the cause of it. Could you tell her so for me, with my fervent acknowledgments?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I could. I will, if you ask it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Carton's manner was so careless as to be almost insolent. He stood, half turned from the prisoner, lounging with his elbow against the bar.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do ask it. Accept my cordial thanks.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What,&rdquo; said Carton, still only half turned towards him, &ldquo;do you expect, Mr. Darnay?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The worst.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's the wisest thing to expect, and the likeliest. But I think their withdrawing is in your favour.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Loitering on the way out of court not being allowed, Jerry heard no more; but left them&mdash;so like each other in feature, so unlike each other in manner&mdash;standing side by side, both reflected in the glass above them.</p>
<p>An hour and a half himped heavily away in the thief-and-rascal-crowded passages below, even though assisted off with mutton pies and ale. The hoarse messenger, uncomfortably seated on a form after taking that refection, had dropped into a doze, when a loud murmur
<pb n="51" id="p51"/>
and a rapid tide of people setting up the stairs that led to the court, carried him along with them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Jerry! Jerry!&rdquo; Mr. Lorry was already calling at the door when he got there.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here, sir! It's a fight to get back again. Here I am, sir!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Lorry handed him a paper through the throng. &ldquo;Quick! Have you got it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Hastily written on the paper was the word &ldquo;ACQUITTED.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you had sent the message, &lsquo;Recalled to Life,&rsquo; again,&rdquo; muttered Jerry, as he turned, &ldquo;I should have known what you meant, this time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had no opportunity of saying, or so much as thinking, anything else, until he was clear of the Old Bailey; for, the crowd came pouring out with a vehemence that nearly took him off his legs, and a loud buzz swept into the street as if the baffled blue-flies were dispersing in search of other carrion.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER IV. <lb/> CONGRATULATORY.</head>
<p>FROM the dimly-lighted passages of the court, the last sediment of the human stew that had been boiling there all day, was straining off, when Doctor Manette, Lucie Manette his daughter, Mr. Lorry, the solicitor for the defence, and its counsel Mr. Stryver, stood gathered around Mr. Charles Darnay&mdash;just released&mdash;congratulating him on his escape from death.</p>
<p>It would have been difficult by a far brighter light, to recognise in Doctor Manette, intellectual of face and upright of bearing, the shoemaker of the garret in Paris. Yet, no one could have looked at him twice, without looking again: even though the opportunity of observation had not extended to the mournful cadence of his low grave voice, and to the abstraction that overclouded him fitfully, without any apparent reason. While one external cause, and that a reference to his long lingering agony, would always&mdash;as on the trial&mdash;evoke this condition from the depths of his soul, it was also in its nature to arise of itself, and to draw a gloom over him, as incomprehensible to those unacquainted with his story as if they had seen the shadow of the actual Bastille thrown upon him by a summer sun, when the substance was three hundred miles away.</p>
<p>Only his daughter had the power of charming this black brooding from his mind. She was the golden thread that united him to a Past beyond his misery, and to a Present beyond his misery: and the sound of her voice, the light of her face, the touch of her hand, had a strong beneficial influence with him almost always. Not absolutely always, for she could recal some occasions on which her power
<pb n="52" id="p52"/>
had failed; but, they were few and slight, and she believed them over.</p>
<p>Mr. Darnay had kissed her hand fervently and gratefully, and had turned to Mr. Stryver, whom he warmly thanked. Mr. Stryver, a man of little more than thirty, but looking twenty years older than he was, stout, loud, red, bluff, and free from any drawback of delicacy, had a pushing way of shouldering himself (morally and physically) into companies and conversations, that argued well for his shouldering his way up in life.</p>
<p>He still had his wig and gown on, and he said, squaring himself at his late client to that degree that he squeezed the innocent Mr. Lorry clean out of the group: &ldquo;I am glad to have brought you off with honour, Mr. Darnay. It was an infamous prosecution, grossly infamous; but not the less likely to succeed, on that account.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have laid me under an obligation to you for life&mdash;in two senses,&rdquo; said his late client, taking his hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have done my best for you, Mr. Darnay; and my best is as good as another man's, I believe.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It clearly being incumbent on somebody to say, &ldquo;Much better,&rdquo; Mr. Lorry said it; perhaps not quite disinterestedly, but with the interested object of squeezing himself back again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You think so?&rdquo; said Mr. Stryver. &ldquo;Well! you have been present all day, and you ought to know. You are a man of business, too.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And as such,&rdquo; quoth Mr. Lorry, whom the counsel learned in the law had now shouldered back into the group, just as he had previously shouldered him out of it&mdash;&ldquo;as such, I will appeal to Doctor Manette, to break up this conference and order us all to our homes. Miss Lucie looks ill, Mr. Darnay has had a terrible day, we are worn out.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Speak for yourself, Mr. Lorry,&rdquo; said Stryver; &ldquo;I have a night's work to do yet. Speak for yourself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I speak for myself,&rdquo; answered Mr. Lorry, &ldquo;and for Mr. Darnay, and for Miss Lucie, and&mdash;Miss Lucie, do you not think I may speak for us all?&rdquo; He asked her the question pointedly, and with a glance at her father.</p>
<p>His face had become frozen, as it were, in a very curious look at Darnay: an intent look, deepening into a frown of dislike and distrust, not even unmixed with fear. With this strange expression on him his thoughts had wandered away.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My father,&rdquo; said Lucie, softly laying her hand on his.</p>
<p>He slowly shook the shadow off, and turned to her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Shall we go home, my father?&rdquo;</p>
<p>With a long breath, he answered, &ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The friends of the acquitted prisoner had dispersed, under the impression&mdash;which he himself had originated&mdash;that he would not be released that night. The lights were nearly all extinguished in the passages, the iron gates were being closed with a jar and a rattle, and the dismal place was deserted until to-morrow morning's interest of gallows, pillory, whipping-post, and branding-iron, should repeople it. Walking between her father and Mr. Darnay, Lucie Manette passed into the open air. A hackney-coach was called, and the father and daughter departed in it.</p>
<pb n="53" id="p53"/>
<p>Mr. Stryver had left them in the passages, to shoulder his way back to the robing-room. Another person who had not joined the group, or interchanged a word with any one of them, but who had been leaning against the wall where its shadow was darkest, had silently strolled out after the rest, and had looked on until the coach drove away. He now stepped up to where Mr. Lorry and Mr. Darnay stood upon the pavement.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So, Mr. Lorry! Men of business may speak to Mr. Darnay now?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Nobody had made any acknowledgment of Mr. Carton's part in the day's proceedings; nobody had known of it. He was unrobed, and was none the better for it in appearance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you knew what a conflict goes on in the business mind, when the business mind is divided between good-natured impulse and business appearances, you would be amused, Mr. Darnay.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Lorry reddened, and said, warmly, &ldquo;You have mentioned that before, sir. We men of business, who serve a House, are not our own masters. We have to think of the House more than ourselves.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> know, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> know,&rdquo; rejoined Mr. Carton, carelessly. &ldquo;Don't be nettled, Mr. Lorry. You are as good as another, I have no doubt; better, I dare say.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And indeed, sir,&rdquo; pursued Mr. Lorry, not minding him, &ldquo;I really don't know what you have to do with the matter. If you'll excuse me, as very much your elder, for saying so, I really don't know that it is your business.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Business! Bless you, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> have no business,&rdquo; said Mr. Carton.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is a pity you have not, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think so too.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you had,&rdquo; pursued Mr. Lorry, &ldquo;perhaps you would attend to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lord love you, no!&mdash;I shouldn't,&rdquo; said Mr. Carton.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir!&rdquo; cried Mr. Lorry, thoroughly heated by his indifference, &ldquo;business is a very good thing, and a very respectable thing. And, sir, if business imposes its restraints and its silences and impediments, Mr. Darnay as a young gentleman of generosity knows how to make allowance for that circumstance. Mr. Darnay, good night, God bless you, sir! I hope you have been this day preserved for a prosperous and happy life.&mdash;Chair there!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Perhaps a little angry with himself, as well as with the barrister, Mr. Lorry bustled into the chair, and was carried off to Tellson's. Carton, who smelt of port wine, and did not appear to be quite sober, laughed then, and turned to Darnay:</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a strange chance that throws you and me together. This must be a strange night to you, standing alone here with your counterpart on these street-stones?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hardly seem yet,&rdquo; returned Charles Darnay, &ldquo;to belong to this world again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't wonder at it; it's not so long since you were pretty far advanced on your way to another. You speak faintly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I begin to think I <hi rend="italics">am</hi> faint.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then why the devil don't you dine? I dined, myself, while those numskulls were deliberating which world you should belong to
<pb n="54" id="p54"/>
&mdash;this, or some other. Let me show you the nearest tavern to dine well at.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Drawing his arm through his own, he took him down Ludgate-hill to Fleet-street, and so, up a covered way, into a tavern. Here, they were shown into a little room, where Charles Darnay was soon recruiting his strength with a good plain dinner and good wine: while Carton sat opposite to him at the same table, with his separate bottle of port before him, and his fully half-insolent manner upon him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you feel, yet, that you belong to this terrestrial scheme again, Mr. Darnay?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am frightfully confused regarding time and place; but I am so far mended as to feel that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It must be an immense satisfaction!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He said it bitterly, and filled up his glass again: which was a large one.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As to me, the greatest desire I have, is to forget that I belong to it. It has no good in it for me&mdash;except wine like this&mdash;nor I for it. So we are not much alike in that particular. Indeed, I begin to think we are not much alike in any particular, you and I.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Confused by the emotion of the day, and feeling his being there with this Double of coarse deportment, to be like a dream, Charles Darnay was at a loss how to answer; finally, answered not at all.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now your dinner is done,&rdquo; Carton presently said, &ldquo;why don't you call a health, Mr. Darnay; why don't you give your toast?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What health? What toast?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, it's on the tip of your tongue. It ought to be, it must be, I'll swear it's there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, then!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Manette, then!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Looking his companion full in the face while he drank the toast, Carton flung his glass over his shoulder against the wall, where it shivered to pieces; then, rang the bell, and ordered in another.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a fair young lady to hand to a coach in the dark, Mr. Darnay!&rdquo; he said, filling his new goblet.</p>
<p>A slight frown and a laconic &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; were the answer.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a fair young lady to be pitied by and wept for by!. How does it feel? Is it worth being tried for one's life, to be the object of such sympathy and compassion, Mr. Darnay?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Again Darnay answered not a word.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She was mightily pleased to have your message, when I gave it her. Not that she showed she was pleased, but I suppose she was.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The allusion served as a timely reminder to Darnay that this disagreeable companion had, of his own free will, assisted him in the strait of the day. He turned the dialogue to that point, and thanked him for it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I neither want any thanks, nor merit any,&rdquo; was the careless rejoinder. &ldquo;It was nothing to do, in the first place; and I don't know why I did it, in the second. Mr. Darnay, let me ask you a question.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Willingly, and a small return for your good offices.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think I particularly like you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really, Mr. Carton,&rdquo; returned the other, oddly disconcerted, &ldquo;I have not asked myself the question.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="55" id="p55"/>
<p>&ldquo;But ask yourself the question now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have acted as if you do; but I don't think you do.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> don't think I do,&rdquo; said Carton. &ldquo;I begin to have a very good opinion of your understanding.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nevertheless,&rdquo; pursued Darnay, rising to ring the bell, &ldquo;there is nothing in that, I hope, to prevent my calling the reckoning, and our parting without ill-blood on either side.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Carton rejoining, &ldquo;Nothing in life!&rdquo; Darnay rang. &ldquo;Do you call the whole reckoning?&rdquo; said Carton. On his answering in the affirmative, &ldquo;Then bring me another pint of this same wine, drawer, and come and wake me at ten.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The bill being paid, Charles Darnay rose and wished him good night. Without returning the wish, Carton rose too, with something of a threat or defiance in his manner, and said, &ldquo;A last word, Mr. Darnay: you think I am drunk?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think you have been drinking, Mr. Carton.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Think? You know I have been drinking.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Since I must say so, I know it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then you shall likewise know why. I am a disappointed drudge, sir. I care for no man on earth, and no man on earth cares for me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Much to be regretted. You might have used your talents better.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;May be so, Mr. Darnay; may be not. Don't let your sober face elate you, however; you don't know what it may come to. Good night!&rdquo;</p>
<p>When he was left alone, this strange being took up a candle, went to a glass that hung against the wall, and surveyed himself minutely in it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you particularly like the man?&rdquo; he muttered, at his own image; &ldquo;why should you particularly like a man who resembles you? There is nothing in you to like; you know that. Ah, confound you! What a change you have made in yourself! A good reason for taking to a man, that he shows you what you have fallen away from, and what you might have been! Change places with him, and would you have been looked at by those blue eyes as he was, and commiserated by that agitated face as he was? Come on, and have it out in plain words! You hate the fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He resorted to his pint of wine for consolation, drank it all in a few minutes, and fell asleep on his arms, with his hair straggling over the table, and a long winding-sheet in the candle dripping down upon him.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="chapter">
<pb n="56" id="p56"/>
<head>CHAPTER V. <lb/> THE JACKAL.</head>
<p>THOSE were drinking days, and most men drank hard. So very great is the improvement Time has brought about in such habits, that a moderate statement of the quantity of wine and punch which one man would swallow in the course of a night, without any detriment to his reputation as a perfect gentleman, would seem, in these days, a ridiculous exaggeration. The learned profession of the Law was certainly not behind any other learned profession in its Bacchanalian propensities; neither was Mr. Stryver, already fast shouldering his way to a large and lucrative practice, behind his compeers in this particular, any more than in the drier parts of the legal race.</p>
<p>A favourite at the Old Bailey, and eke at the Sessions, Mr. Stryver had begun cautiously to hew away the lower staves of the ladder on which he mounted. Sessions and Old Bailey had now to summon their favourite, specially, to their longing arms; and shouldering itself towards the visage of the Lord Chief Justice in the Court of King's Bench, the florid countenance of Mr. Stryver might be daily seen, bursting out of the bed of wigs, like a great sunflower pushing its way at the sun from among a rank garden-full of flaring companions.</p>
<p>It had once been noted at the Bar, that while Mr. Stryver was a glib man, and an unscrupulous, and a ready, and a bold, he had not that faculty of extracting the essence from a heap of statements, which is among the most striking and necessary of the advocate's accomplishments. But, a remarkable improvement came upon him as to this. The more business he got, the greater his power seemed to grow of getting at its pith and marrow; and however late at night he sat carousing with Sydney Carton, he always had his points at his fingers' ends in the morning.</p>
<p>Sydney Carton, idlest and most unpromising of men, was Stryver's great ally. What the two drank together, between Hilary Term and Michaelmas, might have floated a king's ship. Stryver never had a case in hand, anywhere, but Carton was there, with his hands in his pockets, staring at the ceiling of the court; they went the same Circuit, and even there they prolonged their usual orgies late into the night, and Carton was rumoured to be seen at broad day, going home stealthily and unsteadily to his lodgings, like a dissipated cat. At last, it began to get about, among such as were interested in the matter, that although Sydney Carton would never be a lion, he was an amazingly good jackal, and that he rendered suit and service to Stryver in that humble capacity.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ten o'clock, sir,&rdquo; said the man at the tavern, whom he had charged to wake him&mdash;&ldquo;ten o'clock, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">What's</hi> the matter?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="57" id="p57"/>
<p>&ldquo;Ten o'clock, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you mean? Ten o'clock at night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir. Your honour told me to call you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! I remember. Very well, very well.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After a few dull efforts to get to sleep again, which the man dexterously combated by stirring the fire continuously for five minutes, he got up, tossed his hat on, and walked out. He turned into the Temple, and, having revived himself by twice pacing the pavements of King's Bench Walk and Paper Buildings, turned into the Stryver chambers.</p>
<p>The Stryver clerk, who never assisted at these conferences, had gone home, and the Stryver principal opened the door. He had his slippers on, and a loose bedgown, and his throat was bare for his greater ease. He had that rather wild, strained, seared marking about the eyes, which may be observed in all free livers of his class, from the portrait of Jeffries downward, and which can be traced, under various disguises of Art, through the portraits of every Drinking Age.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are a little late, Memory,&rdquo; said Stryver.</p>
<p>&ldquo;About the usual time; it may be a quarter of an hour later.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They went into a dingy room lined with books and littered with papers, where there was a blazing fire. A kettle steamed upon the hob, and in the midst of the wreck of papers a table shone, with plenty of wine upon it, and brandy, and rum, and sugar, and lemons.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have had your bottle, I perceive, Sydney.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Two to-night, I think. I have been dining with the day's client; or seeing him dine&mdash;it's all one!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That was a rare point, Sydney, that you brought to bear upon the identification. How did you come by it? When did it strike you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought he was rather a handsome fellow, and I thought I should have been much the same sort of fellow, if I had had any luck.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Stryver laughed, till he shook his precocious paunch. &ldquo;You and your luck, Sydney! Get to work, get to work.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sullenly enough, the jackal loosened his dress, went into an adjoining room, and came back with a large jug of cold water, a basin, and a towel or two. Steeping the towels in the water, and partially wringing them out, he folded them on his head in a manner hideous to behold, sat down at the table, and said, &ldquo;Now I am ready!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not much boiling down to be done to-night, Memory,&rdquo; said Mr. Stryver, gaily, as he looked among his papers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How much?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Only two sets of them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Give me the worst first.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There they are, Sydney. Fire away!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The lion then composed himself on his back on a sofa on one side of the drinking-table, while the jackal sat at his own paper-bestrewn table proper, on the other side of it, with the bottles and glasses ready to his hand. Both resorted to the drinking-table without stint, but each in a different way; the lion for the most part reclining with his hands in his waistband, looking at the fire, or occasionally flirting with some lighter document; the jackal, with knitted brows and intent
<pb n="58" id="p58"/>
face, so deep in his task, that his eyes did not even follow the hand he stretched out for his glass &mdash; which often groped about, for a minute or more, before it found the glass for his lips. Two or three times, the matter in hand became so knotty, that the jackal found it imperative on him to get up, and steep his towels anew. From these pilgrimages to the jug and basin, he returned with such eccentricities of damp head-gear as no words can describe; which were made the more ludicrous by his anxious gravity.</p>
<p>At length the jackal had got together a compact repast for the lion, and proceeded to offer it to him. The lion took it with care and caution, made his selections from it, and his remarks upon it, and the jackal assisted both. When the repast was fully discussed, the lion put his hands in his waistband again, and lay down to meditate. The jackal then invigorated himself with a bumper for his throttle, and a fresh application to his head, and applied himself to the collection of a second meal; this was administered to the lion in the same manner, and was not disposed of until the clocks struck three in the morning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And now we have done, Sydney, fill a bumper of punch,&rdquo; said Mr. Stryver.</p>
<p>The jackal removed the towels from his head, which had been steaming again, shook himself, yearned, shivered, and complied.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You were very sound, Sydney, in the matter of those Crown witnesses to-day. Every question told.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I always am sound; am I not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't gainsay it. What has roughened your temper? Put some punch to it and smooth it again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With a deprecatory grunt, the jackal again complied.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The old Sydney Carton of old Shrewsbury School,&rdquo; said Stryver, nodding his head over him as he reviewed him in the present and the past, &ldquo;the old seesaw Sydney. Up one minute and down the next; now in spirits and now in despondency!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; returned the other sighing: &ldquo;yes! The same Sydney, with the same luck. Even then, I did exercises for other boys, and seldom did my own.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And why not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;God knows. It was my way, I suppose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He sat, with his hands in his pockets and his legs stretched out before him, looking at the fire.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Carton,&rdquo; said his friend, squaring himself at him with a bullying air, as if the fire-grate had been the furnace in which sustained endeavour was forged, and the one delicate thing to be done for the old Sydney Carton of old Shrewsbury School was to shoulder him into it, &ldquo;your way is, and always was, a lame one. You summon no energy and purpose. Look at me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, botheration!&rdquo; returned Sydney, with a lighter and more good-humoured laugh, &ldquo;don't <hi rend="italics">you</hi> be moral!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How have I done what I have done?&rdquo; said Stryver; &ldquo;how do I do what I do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Partly through paying me to help you, I suppose. But it's not worth your while to apostrophise me, or the air, about it; what you want to do, you do. You were always in the front rank, and I was always behind.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="59" id="p59"/>
<p>&ldquo;I had to get into the front rank; I was not born there, was I?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was not present at the ceremony; but my opinion is you were,&rdquo; said Carton. At this, he laughed again, and they both laughed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Before Shrewsbury, and at Shrewsbury, and ever since Shrewsbury,&rdquo; pursued Carton, &ldquo;you have fallen into your rank, and I have fallen into mine. Even when we were fellow-students in the Quartier Latin, picking up French, and French law, and other French crumbs that we didn't get much good of, you were always somewhere, and I was always&mdash;nowhere.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And whose fault was that?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Upon my soul, I am not sure that it was not yours. You were always driving and riving and shouldering and pressing, to that restless degree that I had no chance for my life but in rust and repose. It's a gloomy thing, however, to talk about one's own past, with the day breaking. Turn me in some other direction before I go.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well then! Pledge me to the pretty witness,&rdquo; said Stryver, holding up his glass. &ldquo;Are you turned in a pleasant direction?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Apparently not, for he became gloomy again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pretty witness,&rdquo; he muttered, looking down into his glass. &ldquo;I have had enough of witnesses to-day and to-night; who's your pretty witness?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The picturesque doctor's daughter, Miss Manette.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">She</hi> pretty!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is she not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, man alive, she was the admiration of the whole Court!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rot the admiration of the whole Court! Who made the Old Bailey a judge of beauty? She was a golden-haired doll?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know, Sydney,&rdquo; said Mr. Stryver, looking at him with sharp eyes, and slowly drawing a hand across his florid face: &ldquo;do you know, I rather thought, at the time, that you sympathised with the golden-haired doll, and were quick to see what happened to the golden-haired doll?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quick to see what happened! If a girl, doll or no doll, swoons within a yard or two of a man's nose, he can see it without a perspective-glass. I pledge you, but I deny the beauty. And now I'll have no more drink; I'll get to bed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When his host followed him out on the staircase with a candle, to light him down the stairs, the day was coldly looking in through its grimy windows. When he got out of the house, the air was cold and sad, the dull sky overcast, the river dark and dim, the whole scene like a lifeless desert. And wreaths of dust were spinning round and round before the morning blast, as if the desert-sand had risen far away, and the first spray of it in its advance had begun to overwhelm the city.</p>
<p>Waste forces within him, and a desert all around, this man stood still on his way across a silent terrace, and saw for a moment, lying in the wilderness before him, a mirage of honourable ambition, self-denial, and perseverance. In the fair city of this vision, there were airy galleries from which the loves and graces looked upon him, gardens in which the fruits of life hung ripening, waters of Hope
<pb n="60" id="p60"/>
that sparkled in his sight. A moment, and it was gone. Climbing to a high chamber in a well of houses, he threw himself down in his clothes on a neglected bed, and its pillow was wet with wasted tears.</p>
<p>Sadly, sadly, the sun rose; it rose upon no sadder sight than the man of good abilities and good emotions, incapable of their directed exercise, incapable of his own help and his own happiness, sensible of the blight on him, and resigning himself to let it eat him away.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER VI. <lb/> HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE.</head>
<p>THE quiet lodgings of Doctor Manette were in a quiet street-corner not far from Soho-square. On the afternoon of a certain fine Sunday when the waves of four months had rolled over the trial for treason, and carried it, as to the public interest and memory, far out to sea, Mr. Jarvis Lorry walked along the sunny streets from Clerken-well where he lived, on his way to dine with the Doctor. After several relapses into business-absorption, Mr. Lorry had become the Doctor's friend, and the quiet street-corner was the sunny part of his life.</p>
<p>On this certain fine Sunday, Mr. Lorry walked towards Soho, early in the afternoon, for three reasons of habit. Firstly, because, on fine Sundays, he often walked out, before dinner, with the Doctor and Lucie; secondly, because, on unfavourable Sundays, he was accustomed to be with them as the family friend, talking, reading, looking out of window, and generally getting through the day; thirdly, because he happened to have his own little shrewd doubts to solve, and knew how the ways of the Doctor's household pointed to that time as a likely time for solving them.</p>
<p>A quainter corner than the corner where the Doctor lived, was not to be found in London. There was no way through it, and the front windows of the Doctor's lodgings commanded a pleasant little vista of street that had a congenial air of retirement on it. There were few buildings then, north of the Oxford-road, and forest-trees flourished, and wild flowers grew, and the hawthorn blossomed, in the now vanished fields. As a consequence, country airs circulated in Soho with vigorous freedom, instead of languishing into the parish like stray paupers without a settlement; and there was many a good south wall, not far off, on which the peaches ripened in their season.</p>
<p>The summer light struck into the corner brilliantly in the earlier part of the day; but, when the streets grew hot, the corner was in shadow, though not in shadow so remote but that you could see beyond it into a glare of brightness. It was a cool spot, staid but cheerful, a wonderful place for echoes, and a very harbour from the raging streets.</p>
<pb n="61" id="p61"/>
<p>There ought to have been a tranquil bark in such an anchorage, and there was. The Doctor occupied two floors of a large still house, where several callings purported to be pursued by day, but whereof little was audible any day, and which was shunned by all of them at night. In a building at the back, attainable by a court-yard where a plane-tree rustled its green leaves, church-organs claimed to be made, and silver to be chased, and likewise gold to be beaten by some mysterious giant who had a golden arm starting out of the wall of the front hall&mdash;as if he had beaten himself precious, and menaced a similar conversion of all visitors. Very little of these trades, or of a lonely lodger rumoured to live up-stairs, or of a dim coach-trimming maker asserted to have a counting-house below, was ever heard or seen. Occasionally, a stray workman putting his coat on, traversed the hall, or a stranger peered about there, or a distant clink was heard across the court-yard, or a thump from the golden giant. These, however, were only the exceptions required to prove the rule that the sparrows in the plane-tree behind the house, and the echoes in the corner before it, had their own way from Sunday morning unto Saturday night.</p>
<p>Doctor Manette received such patients here as his old reputation, and its revival in the floating whispers of his story, brought him. His scientific knowledge, and his vigilance and skill in conducting ingenious experiments, brought him otherwise into moderate request, and he earned as much as he wanted.</p>
<p>These things were within Mr. Jarvis Lorry's knowledge, thoughts, and notice, when he rang the door-bell of the tranquil house in the corner, on the fine Sunday afternoon.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Manette at home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Expected home.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Lucie at home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Expected home.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Miss Pross at home?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Possibly at home, but of a certainty impossible for handmaid to anticipate intentions of Miss Pross, as to admission or denial of the fact.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As I am at home myself,&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry, &ldquo;I'll go up-stairs.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Although the Doctor's daughter had known nothing of the country of her birth, she appeared to have innately derived from it that ability to make much of little means, which is one of its most useful and most agreeable characteristics. Simple as the furniture was, it was set off by so many little adornments, of no value but for their taste and fancy, that its effect was delightful. The disposition of everything in the rooms, from the largest object to the least; the arrangement of colours, the elegant variety and contrast obtained by thrift in trifles, by delicate hands, clear eyes, and good sense; were at once so pleasant in themselves, and so expressive of their originator, that, as Mr. Lorry stood looking about him, the very chairs and tables seemed to ask him, with something of that peculiar expression which he knew so well by this time, whether he approved?</p>
<p>There were three rooms on a floor, and, the doors by which they communicated being put open that the air might pass freely through them all, Mr. Lorry, smilingly observant of that fanciful resemblance
<pb n="62" id="p62"/>
which he detected all around him, walked from one to another. The first was the best room, and in it were Lucie's birds, and flowers, and books, and desk, and work-table, and box of water-colours; the second was the Doctor's consulting-room, used also as the dining-room; the third, changingly speckled by the rustle of the plane-tree in the yard, was the Doctor's bedroom&mdash;and there, in a corner, stood the disused shoemaker's bench and tray of tools, much as it had stood on the fifth floor of the dismal house by the wine-shop, in the suburb of Saint Antoine in Paris.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wonder,&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry, pausing in his looking about, &ldquo;that he keeps that reminder of his sufferings by him!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And why wonder at that?&rdquo; was the abrupt inquiry that made him start.</p>
<p>It proceeded from Miss Pross, the wild red woman, strong of hand, whose acquaintance he had first made at the Royal George Hotel at Dover, and had since improved.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should have thought&mdash;&rdquo; Mr. Lorry began.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pooh! You'd have thought!&rdquo; said Miss Pross; and Mr. Lorry left off.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do you do?&rdquo; inquired that lady then&mdash;sharply, and yet as if to express that she bore him no malice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am pretty well, I thank you,&rdquo; answered Mr. Lorry, with meekness, &ldquo;how are you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing to boast of,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! indeed!&rdquo; said Miss Pross. &ldquo;I am very much put out about my Ladybird.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For gracious sake say something else besides &lsquo;indeed,&rsquo; or you'll fidget me to death,&rdquo; said Miss Pross: whose character (dissociated from stature) was shortness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really, then?&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry as an amendment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Really, is bad enough,&rdquo; returned Miss Pross, &ldquo;but better. Yes, I am very much put out.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;May I ask the cause?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't want dozens of people who are not at all worthy of Ladybird, to come here looking after her,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Do</hi> dozens come for that purpose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hundreds,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>It was characteristic of this lady (as of some other people before her time and since) that whenever her original proposition was questioned, she exaggerated it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry, as the safest remark he could think of.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have lived with the darling&mdash;or the darling has lived with me, and paid me for it; which she certainly should never have done, you may take your affidavit, if I could have afforded to keep either myself or her for nothing&mdash;since she was ten years old. And it's really very hard,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>Not seeing with precision what was very hard, Mr. Lorry shook his head; using that important part of himself as a sort of fairy cloak that would fit anything.</p>
<pb n="63" id="p63"/>
<p>&ldquo;All sorts of people who are not in the least degree worthy of the pet, are always turning up,&rdquo; said Miss Pross. &ldquo;When you began it&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> began it, Miss Pross?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Didn't you? Who brought her father to life?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! If <hi rend="italics">that</hi> was beginning it&mdash;&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It wasn't ending it, I suppose? I say, when you began it, it was hard enough; not that I have any fault to find with Doctor Manette, except that he is not worthy of such a daughter, which is no imputation on him, for it was not to be expected that anybody should be, under any circumstances. But it really is doubly and trebly hard to have crowds and multitudes of people turning up after him (I could have forgiven him), to take Ladybird's affections away from me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Lorry knew Miss Pross to be very jealous, but he also knew her by this time to be, beneath the surface of her eccentricity, one of those unselfish creatures&mdash;found only among women&mdash;who will, for pure love and admiration, bind themselves willing slaves, to youth when they have lost it, to beauty that they never had, to accomplishments that they were never fortunate enough to gain, to bright hopes that never shone upon their own sombre lives. He knew enough of the world to know that there is nothing in it better than the faithful service of the heart; so rendered and so free from any mercenary taint, he had such an exalted respect for it, that, in the retributive arrangements made by his own mind&mdash;we all make such arrangements, more or less&mdash;he stationed Miss Pross much nearer to the lower Angels than many ladies immeasurably better got up both by Nature and Art, who had balances at Tellson's.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There never was, nor will be, but one man worthy of Ladybird,&rdquo; said Miss Pross; &ldquo;and that was my brother Solomon, if he hadn't made a mistake in life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here again: Mr. Lorry's inquiries into Miss Pross's personal history, had established the fact that her brother Solomon was a heartless scoundrel who had stripped her of everything she possessed, as a stake to speculate with, and had abandoned her in her poverty for evermore, with no touch of compunction. Miss Pross's fidelity of belief in Solomon (deducting a mere trifle for this slight mistake) was quite a serious matter with Mr. Lorry, and had its weight in his good opinion of her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As we happen to be alone for the moment, and are both people of business,&rdquo; he said, when they had got back to the drawing-room, and had sat down there in friendly relations, &ldquo;let me ask you&mdash;does the Doctor, in talking with Lucie, never refer to the shoemaking time, yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And yet keeps that bench and those tools beside him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; returned Miss Pross, shaking her head. &ldquo;But I don't say he don't refer to it within himself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you believe that he thinks of it much?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you imagine&mdash;&rdquo; Mr. Lorry had begun, when Miss Pross took him up short with:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never imagine anything. Have no imagination at all.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="64" id="p64"/>
<p>&ldquo;I stand corrected; do you suppose&mdash;you go so far as to suppose, sometimes?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now and then,&rdquo; said Miss Pross.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you suppose,&rdquo; Mr. Lorry went on, with a laughing twinkle in his bright eye, as it looked kindly at her, &ldquo;that Doctor Manette has any theory of his own, preserved through all those years, relative to the cause of his being so oppressed; perhaps, even to the name of his oppressor?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't suppose anything about it but what Ladybird tells me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And that is&mdash;?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That she thinks he has.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now don't be angry at my asking all these questions; because I am a mere dull man of business, and you are a woman of business.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dull?&rdquo; Miss Pross inquired, with placidity.</p>
<p>Rather wishing his modest adjective away, Mr. Lorry replied, &ldquo;No, no, no. Surely not. To return to business:&mdash;Is it not remarkable that Doctor Manette, unquestionably innocent of any crime as we are well assured he is, should never touch upon that question? I will not say with me, though he had business relations with me many years ago, and we are now intimate; I will say with the fair daughter to whom he is so devotedly attached, and who is so devotedly attached to him? Believe me, Miss Pross, I don't approach the topic with you, out of curiosity, but out of zealous interest.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well! To the best of my understanding, and bad's the best you'll tell me,&rdquo; said Miss Pross, softened by the tone of the apology, &ldquo;he is afraid of the whole subject.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Afraid?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's plain enough, I should think, why he may be. It's a dreadful remembrance. Besides that, his loss of himself grew out of it. Not knowing how he lost himself, or how he recovered himself, he may never feel certain of not losing himself again. That alone wouldn't make the subject pleasant, I should think.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was a profounder remark than Mr. Lorry had looked for. &ldquo;True,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;and fearful to reflect upon. Yet, a doubt lurks in my mind, Miss Pross, whether it is good for Doctor Manette to have that suppression always shut up within him. Indeed, it is this doubt and the uneasiness it sometimes causes me that has led me to our present confidence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can't be helped,&rdquo; said Miss Pross, shaking her head. &ldquo;Touch that string, and he instantly changes for the worse. Better leave it alone. In short, must leave it alone, like or no like. Sometimes, he gets up in the dead of the night, and will be heard, by us overhead there, walking up and down, walking up and down, in his room. Ladybird has learnt to know then, that his mind is walking up and down, walking up and down, in his old prison. She hurries to him, and they go on together, walking up and down, walking up and down, until he is composed. But he never says a word of the true reason of his restlessness, to her, and she finds it best not to hint at it to him. In silence they go walking up and down together, walking up and down together, till her love and company have brought him to himself.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="65" id="p65"/>
<p>Notwithstanding Miss Pross's denial of her own imagination, there was a perception of the pain of being monotonously haunted by one sad idea, in her repetition of the phrase, walking up and down, which testified to her possessing such a thing.</p>
<p>The corner has been mentioned as a wonderful corner for echoes; it had begun to echo so resoundingly to the tread of coming feet, that it seemed as though the very mention of that weary pacing to and fro had set it going.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here they are!&rdquo; said Miss Pross, rising to break up the conference; &ldquo;and now we shall have hundreds of people pretty soon!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was such a curious corner in its acoustical properties, such a peculiar Ear of a place, that as Mr. Lorry stood at the open window, looking for the father and daughter whose steps he heard, he fancied they would never approach. Not only would the echoes die away, as though the steps had gone; but, echoes of other steps that never came, would be heard in their stead, and would die away for good when they seemed close at hand. However, father and daughter did at last appear, and Miss Pross was ready at the street door to receive them.</p>
<p>Miss Pross was a pleasant sight, albeit wild, and red, and grim, taking off her darling's bonnet when she came up-stairs, and touching it up with the ends of her handkerchief, and blowing the dust off it, and folding her mantle ready for laying by, and smoothing her rich hair with as much pride as she could possibly have taken in her own hair if she had been the vainest and handsomest of women. Her darling was a pleasant sight too, embracing her and thanking her, and protesting against her taking so much trouble for her&mdash;which last she only dared to do playfully, or Miss Pross, sorely hurt, would have retired to her own chamber and cried. The Doctor was a pleasant sight too, looking on at them, and telling Miss Pross how she spoilt Lucie, in accents and with eyes that had as much spoiling in them as Miss Pross had, and would have had more if it were possible. Mr. Lorry was a pleasant sight too, beaming at all this in his little wig, and thanking his bachelor stars for having lighted him in his declining years to a Home. But, no Hundreds of people came to see the sights, and Mr. Lorry looked in vain for the fulfilment of Miss Pross's prediction.</p>
<p>Dinner-time, and still no Hundreds of people. In the arrangements of the little household, Miss Pross took charge of the lower regions, and always acquitted herself marvellously. Her dinners, of a very modest quality, were so well cooked and so well served, and so neat in their contrivances, half English and half French, that nothing could be better. Miss Pross's friendship being of the thoroughly practical kind, she had ravaged Soho and the adjacent provinces, in search of impoverished French, who, tempted by shillings and half-crowns, would impart culinary mysteries to her. From these decayed sons and daughters of Gaul, she had acquired such wonderful arts, that the woman and girl who formed the staff of domestics regarded her as quite a Sorceress, or Cinderella's Godmother: who would send out for a fowl, a rabbit, a vegetable or two from the garden, and change them into anything she pleased.</p>
<p>On Sundays, Miss Pross dined at the Doctor's table, but on other
<pb n="66" id="p66"/>
days persisted in taking her meals, at unknown periods, either in the lower regions, or in her own room on the second floor&mdash;a blue chamber, to which no one but her Ladybird ever gained admittance. On this occasion Miss Pross, responding to Ladybird's pleasant face and pleasant efforts to please her, unbent exceedingly; so the dinner was very pleasant, too.</p>
<p>It was an oppressive day, and, after dinner, Lucie proposed that the wine should be carried out under the plane-tree, and they should sit there in the air. As everything turned upon her and revolved about her, they went out under the plane-tree, and she carried the wine down for the special benefit of Mr. Lorry. She had installed herself, some time before, as Mr. Lorry's cup-bearer; and while they sat under the plane-tree, talking, she kept his glass replenished. Mysterious backs and ends of houses peeped at them as they talked, and the plane-tree whispered to them in its own way above their heads.</p>
<p>Still, the Hundreds of people did not present themselves. Mr. Darnay presented himself while they were sitting under the plane-tree, but he was only One.</p>
<p>Doctor Manette received him kindly, and so did Lucie. But, Miss Pross suddenly became afflicted with a twitching in the head and body, and retired into the house. She was not unfrequently the victim of this disorder, and she called it, in familiar conversation, &ldquo;a fit of the jerks.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Doctor was in his best condition, and looked specially young. The resemblance between him and Lucie was very strong at such times, and, as they sat side by side, she leaning on his shoulder, and he resting his arm on the back of her chair, it was very agreeable to trace the likeness.</p>
<p>He had been talking, all day, on many subjects and with unusual vivacity. &ldquo;Pray, Doctor Manette,&rdquo; said Mr. Darnay, as they sat under the plane-tree&mdash;and he said it in the natural pursuit of the topic in hand, which happened to be the old buildings of London&mdash;&ldquo;have you seen much of the Tower?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lucie and I have been there; but only casually. We have seen enough of it, to know that it teems with interest; little more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> have been there, as you remember,&rdquo; said Darnay, with a smile, though reddening a little angrily, &ldquo;in another character, and not in a character that gives facilities for seeing much of it. They told me a curious thing when I was there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What was that?&rdquo; Lucie asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In making some alterations, the workmen came upon an old dungeon, which had been, for many years, built up and forgotten. Every stone of its inner wall was covered with inscriptions which had been carved by prisoners&mdash;dates, names, complaints, and prayers. Upon a corner stone in an angle of the wall, one prisoner who seemed to have gone to execution, had cut, as his last work, three letters. They were done with some very poor instrument, and hurriedly, with an unsteady hand. At first, they were read as D. I. C.; but, on being more carefully examined, the last letter was found to be G. There was no record or legend of any prisoner with those initials, and many fruitless guesses were made what the name could have
<pb n="67" id="p67"/>
been. At length, it was suggested that the letters were not initials, but the complete word, DIG. The floor was examined very carefully under the inscription, and, in the earth beneath a stone, or tile, or some fragment of paving, were found the ashes of a paper, mingled with the ashes of a small leathern case or bag. What the unknown prisoner had written will never be read, but he had written something, and hidden it away to keep it from the gaoler.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My father!&rdquo; exclaimed Lucie, &ldquo;you are ill!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had suddenly started up, with his hand to his head. His manner and his look quite terrified them all.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my dear, not ill. There are large drops of rain falling, and they made me start. We had better go in.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He recovered himself almost instantly. Rain was really falling in large drops, and he showed the back of his hand with rain-drops on it. But, he said not a single word in reference to the discovery that had been told of, and, as they went into the house, the business eye of Mr. Lorry either detected, or fancied it detected, on his face, as it turned towards Charles Darnay, the same singular look that had been upon it when it turned towards him in the passages of the Court House.</p>
<p>He recovered himself so quickly, however, that Mr. Lorry had doubts of his business eye. The arm of the golden giant in the hall was not more steady than he was, when he stopped under it to remark to them that he was not yet proof against slight surprises (if he ever would be), and that the rain had startled him.</p>
<p>Tea-time, and Miss Pross making tea, with another fit of the jerks upon her, and yet no Hundreds of people. Mr. Carton had lounged in, but he made only Two.</p>
<p>The night was so very sultry, that although they sat with doors and windows open, they were overpowered by heat. When the tea-table was done with, they all moved to one of the windows, and looked out into the heavy twilight. Lucie sat by her father; Darnay sat beside her; Carton leaned against a window. The curtains were long and white, and some of the thunder-gusts that whirled into the corner, caught them up to the ceiling, and waved them like spectral wings.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The rain-drops are still falling, large, heavy, and few,&rdquo; said Doctor Manette. &ldquo;It comes slowly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It comes surely,&rdquo; said Carton.</p>
<p>They spoke low, as people watching and waiting mostly do; as people in a dark room, watching and waiting for Lightning, always do.</p>
<p>There was a great hurry in the streets, of people speeding away to get shelter before the storm broke; the wonderful corner for echoes resounded with the echoes of footsteps coming and going, yet not a footstep was there.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A multitude of people, and yet a solitude!&rdquo; said Darnay, when they had listened for a while.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is it not impressive, Mr. Darnay?&rdquo; asked Lucie. &ldquo;Sometimes, I have sat here of an evening, until I have fancied&mdash;but even the shade of a foolish fancy makes me shudder to-night, when all is so black and solemn&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let us shudder too. We may know what it is?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It will seem nothing to you. Such whims are only impressive as
<pb n="68" id="p68"/>
we originate them, I think; they are not to be communicated. I have sometimes sat alone here of an evening, listening, until I have made the echoes out to be the echoes of all the footsteps that are coming by-and-by into our lives.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is a great crowd coming one day into our lives, if that be so,&rdquo; Sydney Carton struck in, in his moody way.</p>
<p>The footsteps were incessant, and the hurry of them became more and more rapid. The corner echoed and re-echoed with the tread of feet; some, as it seemed, under the windows; some, as it seemed, in the room; some coming, some going, some breaking off, some stopping altogether; all in the distant streets, and not one within sight.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are all these footsteps destined to come to all of us, Miss Manette, or are we to divide them among us?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know, Mr. Darnay; I told you it was a foolish fancy, but you asked for it. When I have yielded myself to it, I have been alone, and then I have imagined them the footsteps of the people who are to come into my life, and my father's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I take them into mine!&rdquo; said Carton. &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> ask no questions and make no stipulations. There is a great crowd bearing down upon us, Miss Manette, and I see them!&mdash;by the Lightning.&rdquo; He added the last words, after there had been a vivid flash which had shown him lounging in the window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I hear them!&rdquo; he added again, after a peal of thunder. &ldquo;Here they come, fast, fierce, and furious!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was the rush and roar of rain that he typified, and it stopped him, for no voice could be heard in it. A memorable storm of thunder and lightning broke with that sweep of water, and there was not a moment's interval in crash, and fire, and rain, until after the moon rose at midnight.</p>
<p>The great bell of Saint Paul's was striking One in the cleared air, when Mr. Lorry, escorted by Jerry, high-booted and bearing a lantern, set forth on his return-passage to Clerkenwell. There were solitary patches of road on the way between Soho and Clerkenwell, and Mr. Lorry, mindful of footpads, always retained Jerry for this service: though it was usually performed a good two hours earlier.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a night it has been! Almost a night, Jerry,&rdquo; said Mr. Lorry, &ldquo;to bring the dead out of their graves.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never see the night myself, master&mdash;nor yet I don't expect to it&mdash;what would do that,&rdquo; answered Jerry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good night, Mr. Carton,&rdquo; said the man of business. &ldquo;Good night, Mr. Darnay. Shall we ever see such a night again, together!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Perhaps. Perhaps, see the great crowd of people with its rush and roar, bearing down upon them, too.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1a" n="1"/>
<head>IMPORTANT FAMILY MEDICINE.</head>
<p>NORTON'S CAMOMILE PILLS, <lb/> THE <lb/> MOST CERTAIN PRESERVER OF HEALTH, <lb/> A MILD, YET SPEEDY, SAFE, AND <lb/> EFFECTUAL AID IN CASES OF INDIGESTION, <lb/> AND ALL STOMACH COMPLAINTS, <lb/> AND, AS A NATURAL CONSEQUENCE, <lb/> A PURIFIER OF THE BLOOD, AND A SWEETENER OF THE WHOLE SYSTEM.</p>
<p>INDIGESTION is a weakness or want of power of the digestive juices in the stomach to convert what we eat and drink into healthy matter, for the proper nourishment of the whole system. It is caused by everything which weakens the system in general, or the stomach in particular. From it proceed nearly all the diseases to which we are liable; for it is very certain, that if we could always keep the stomach right we should only die by old age or accident. Indigestion produces a great variety of unpleasant sensations: amongst the most prominent of its miserable effects are a want of, or an inordinate, appetite, sometimes attended with a constant craving for drink, a distension or feeling of enlargement of the stomach, flatulency, heartburn, pains in the stomach, acidity, unpleasant taste in the mouth, perhaps sickness, rumbling noise in the bowels: in some cases of depraved digestion there is nearly a complete disrelish for food, but still the appetite is not greatly impaired, as at the state period of meals persons so afflicted can eat heartily, although without much gratification; a long train of nervous symptoms are also frequent attendants, general debility, great languidness, and incapacity for exertion. The minds of persons so afflicted frequently become irritable and desponding, and great anxiety is observable in the countenance; they appear thoughtful, melancholy, and dejected, under great apprehension of some imaginary danger, will start at any unexpected noise or occurrence, and become so agitated that they require some time to calm and collect themselves: yet for all this the mind is exhilarated without much difficulty; pleasing events, society, will for a time dissipate all appearance of disease; but the excitement produced by an agreeable change vanishes soon after the cause has gone by. Other symptoms are, violent palpitations, restlessness, the sleep disturbed by frightful dreams and startings, and affording little or no refreshment; occasionally there is much moaning, with a sense of weight and oppression upon the chest, nightmare, &amp;c.</p>
<p>It is almost impossible to enumerate all the symptoms of this first invader upon the constitution, as in a hundred cases of <hi rend="italics">Indigestion</hi> there will probably be something peculiar to each; but, be they what they may, they are all occasioned by the food becoming a burden rather than a support to the stomach; and in all its stages the medicine most wanted is that which will afford speedy and effectual assistance to the digestive organs, and give energy to the nervous and muscular systems,&mdash;nothing can more speedily or with more certainty effect so desirable an object than <hi rend="italics">Norton's Extract of Camomile Flowers.</hi> The herb has from time immemorial been highly esteemed in England as a grateful anodyne, imparting an aromatic bitter to the taste, and a pleasing degree of warmth and strength to the stomach, and in all cases of indigestion, gout in the stomach, windy colic, and general weakness, it has for ages been strongly recommended by the most eminent practitioners as very useful and beneficial. The great, indeed only, objection to its use has been the large quantity of water which it takes to dissolve a small part of the flowers, and which must be taken with it into the
<pb id="p2a" n="2"/>
stomach. It requires a quarter of a pint of boiling water to dissolve the soluble portion of one drachm of Camomile Flowers; and, when one or even two ounces may be taken with advantage, it must at once be seen how impossible it is to take a proper dose of this wholesome herd in the form of tea; and the only reason why it has not long since been placed the very first in rank of all restorative medicines is, that in taking it the stomach has always been loaded with water, which tends in a great measure to counteract, and very frequently wholly to destroy the effect. It must be evident that loading a weak stomach with a large quantity of water, merely for the purpose of conveying into it a small quantity of medicine must be injurious; and that the medicine must possess powerful renovating properties only to counteract the bad effects likely to be produced by the water. Generally speaking, this has been the <sic corr="case with">casewith</sic> Camomile Flowers, a herb possessing the highest restorative qualities, and when properly taken, decidedly the most speedy restorer, and the most certain preserver of health.</p>
<p>These PILLS are wholly CAMOMILE, prepared by a peculiar process, accidentally discovered, and known only to the proprietor, and which he firmly believes to be one of the most valuable modern discoveries in medicine, by which all the essential and extractive matter of more than an ounce of the flowers is concentrated in four moderate sized pills. Experience has afforded the most ample proof that they possess all the fine aromatic and stomachic properties for which the herb has been esteemed; and, as they are taken into the stomach unencumbered by any diluting or indigestible substance, in the same degree has their benefit been more immediate and decided. Mild in their operation and pleasant in their effect, they may be taken at any age, and under any circumstance, without danger or inconvenience. A person exposed to cold and wet a whole day or night could not possibly receive any injury from taking them, but on the contrary, they would effectually prevent a cold being taken. After a long acquaintance with and strict observance of the medicinal properties of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> it is only doing them justice to say, that they are really the most valuable of all TONIC MEDICINES. By the word tonic is meant a medicine which gives strength to the stomach sufficient to digest in proper quantities all wholesome food, which increases the power of every nerve and muscle of the human body, or, in other words, invigorates the nervous and muscular systems. The solidity or firmness of the whole tissue of the body which so quickly follows the use of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> their certain and speedy effects in repairing the partial dilapidations from time or intemperance, and their lasting salutary influence on the whole frame, is most convincing, that in the smallest compass is contained the largest quantity of the tonic principle, of so peculiar a nature as to pervade the whole system, through which it diffuses health and strength sufficient to resist the formation of disease, and also to fortify the constitution against contagion; as such, their general use is strongly recommended as a preventative during the prevalence or malignant fever or other infectious diseases, and to persons attending sick rooms they are invaluable as in no one instance have they ever failed in preventing the taking of illness, even under the most trying circumstances.</p>
<p>As <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills</hi> are particularly recommended for all stomach complaints or indigestion, it will probably be expected that some advice should be given respecting diet, though after all that has been written upon the subject, after the publication of volume upon volume, after the country has, as it were, been inundated with practical essays on diet, as a means of prolonging life, it would be unnecessary to say more, did we not feel it our duty to make the humble endeavour of inducing the public to regard them not, but to adopt that course which is dictated by nature, by reason, and by common sense. Those persons who study the wholesomes, and are governed by the opinions of writers on diet, are uniformly both unhealthy in body and weak in mind. There can be no doubt that the palate is designed to inform us what is proper for the stomach, and of course that must best instruct us what food to take and what to avoid: we want no other adviser. Nothing can be more clear than that those articles which are agreeable to the taste, were by nature intended for our food and sustenance, whether liquid or solid, foreign or of native production: if they are pure and unadulterated, no harm need be dreaded by their
<pb id="p3a" n="3"/>
use; they will only injure by abuse. Consequently, whatever the palate approves, eat and drink always in moderation, but never in excess; keeping in mind that the first process of digestion is performed in the mouth, the second in the stomach; and that, in order that the stomach may be able to do its work properly, it is requisite the first process should be well performed; this consists in masticating or chewing the solid food, so as to break down and separate the fibres and small substances of meat and vegetables, mixing them well, and blending the whole together before they are swallowed; and it is particularly urged upon all to take plenty of time to their meals and never eat in haste. If you conform to this short and simple, but comprehensive advice, and find that there are various things which others eat and drink with pleasure and without inconvenience, and which would be pleasant to yourself only that they disagree, you may at once conclude that the fault is in the stomach, that it does not possess the power which it ought to do, that it wants assistance, and the sooner that assistance is afforded the better. A very short trial of this medicine will best prove how soon it will put the stomach in a condition to perform with ease all the work which nature intended for it. By its use you will soon be able to enjoy, in moderation, whatever is agreeable to the taste, and unable to name one individual article of food which disagrees with or sits unpleasantly on the stomach. Never forget that a small meal well digested affords more nourishment to the system than a large one, even of the same food, when digested imperfectly. Let the dish be ever so delicious, ever so enticing a variety offered, the bottle ever so enchanting, never forget that temperance tends to preserve health, and that health is the soul of enjoyment. But should an impropriety be at any time, or ever so often committed, by which the stomach becomes overloaded or disordered, render it immediate aid by taking a dose of <hi rend="italics">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi> which will so promptly assist in carrying off the burden thus imposed upon it that all will soon be right again.</p>
<p>It is most certainly true that every person in his lifetime consumes a quantity of noxious matter, which if taken at one meal would be fatal: it is these small quantities of noxious matter, which are introduced into our food, either by accident or wilful adulteration, which we find so often upset the stomach, and not unfrequently lay the foundation of illness, and perhaps final ruination to health. To preserve the constitution, it should be our constant care, if possible, to counteract the effect of these small quantities of unwholesome matter; and whenever, in that way, an enemy to the constitution finds its way into the stomach, a friend should be immediately sent after it, which would prevent its mischievous effects, and expel it altogether; no better friend can be found, nor one which will perform the task with greater certainty than NORTON'S CAMOMILE PILLS. And let it be observed that the longer this medicine is taken the less it will be wanted; it can in no case become habitual, as its entire action is to give energy and force to the stomach, which is the spring of life, the source from which the whole frame draws its succour and support. After an excess of eating or drinking, and upon every occasion of the general health being at all disturbed, these PILLS should be immediately taken, as they will stop and eradicate disease at its commencement. Indeed, it is most confidently asserted, that by the timely use of this medicine only, and a common degree of caution, any person may enjoy all the comforts within his reach, may pass through life without an illness, and with the certainty of attaining a healthy OLD AGE.</p>
<p>On account of their volatile properties, they must be kept in bottles; and if closely corked their qualities are neither impaired by time nor injured by any change of climate whatever. Price 13&frac12;d. and 2s. 9d. each, with full directions. The large bottle contains the quantity of three small ones, or PILLS equal to fourteen ounces of CAMOMILE FLOWERS.</p>
<p>Sold by nearly all respectable Medicine Vendors.</p>
<p>Be particular to ask for &ldquo;NORTON'S PILLS,&rdquo; and <lb/> do not be persuaded to purchase an imitation.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p4a" n="4"/>
<head>A CLEAR COMPLEXION!!!</head>
<p>GODFREY'S <lb/> EXTRACT OF ELDER FLOWERS <lb/> Is strongly recommended for Softening, Improving, Beautifying and Preserving the SKIN, and giving it a blooming and charming appearance. It will completely remove Tan, Sunburn, Redness, &amp;c., and by its Balsamic and Healing qualities render the skin soft, pliable, and free from dryness, &amp;c., clear it from every humour, pimple, or eruption; and by continuing its use only a short time, the skin will become and continue soft and smooth, and the complexion perfectly clear and beautiful.</p>
<p>Sold in Bottles, price 2s. 9d., by all Medicine Vendors and <lb/> Perfumers.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>FOR GOUT, RHEUMATISM AND RHEUMATIC GOUT.</head>
<p>SIMCO'S GOUT AND RHEUMATIC PILLS <lb/> are a certain and safe remedy. They restore tranquillity to the nerves, give tone to the stomach, and strength to the whole system. No other medicine can be compared to these excellent Pills, as they prevent the disorder from attacking the stomach or head, and have restored thousands from pain and misery to health and comfort.</p>
<p>Sold by all Medicine Vendors, at 1s. 1&frac12;d. or 2s. 9d. per box.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>INFLUENZA, COUGHS, AND COLDS.</head>
<p>SIMCO'S ESSENCE OF LINSEED <lb/> is the most efficacious remedy ever discovered for the relief of persons suffering from Influenza; the first two doses generally arrest the progress of this distressing complaint, and a little perseverance completely removes it. Children's Coughs, as well as recent ones in Adults, will be removed by a few doses (frequently by the first); and Asthmatic persons, who previously had not been able to lie down in bed, have received the utmost benefit from the use of <lb/> SIMCO'S ESSENCE OF LINSEED.</p>
<p>Sold in Bottles at 1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi> and 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p5a" n="5"/>
<opener>BRITISH COLLEGE OF HEALTH, <lb/> EUSTON (late NEW) ROAD, LONDON, <lb/> WHERE MORISON'S MEDICINES <lb/> ARE COMPOUNDED. </opener>
<head>REPORT OF P. A. AVEILH&Eacute;, <lb/> GENERAL AGENT TO THE BRITISH COLLEGE OF HEALTH, <lb/> FOR THE SALE OF <lb/> MORISON'S VEGETABLE UNIVERSAL MEDICINES, <lb/> AT <lb/> CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">UNITED STATES.</hi></head>
<opener>
<dateline>Messrs. MORISON, <lb/> BRITISH COLLEGE OF HEALTH, <lb/> LONDON.</dateline>
<dateline>Charleston, 28th February, 1859.</dateline>
<salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
</opener><p>[Mr. Aveilh&eacute;, after giving an order for Medicine to be sent out to him, proceeds as follows]:&mdash;</p>
<p>In soliciting your attention to the prompt and faithful execution of this order, I beg to conclude with the following remarks, which will interest and perhaps be serviceable to you:&mdash;During the last thirty years the Vegetable Universal Medicine has been my great specific. For the last fifteen years, I have used it with unbounded success on my Plantation in Cuba, and in my family, and among my friends, neighbours, and acquaintances here, description of whose many varied and virulent cases, would fill a tolerable-sized volume. Were it not through that unaccountable fastidiousness which prevails in all ranks of society, I might give publicity to many names of those who have proved the virtues of your great medicine, under my treatment; yet, I can give scores of references from parties of the first respectability, cured by your Pills, and who are sounding your praise in every direction. In 1854, during the prevalence of yellow fever in epidemic form (I have always considered it endemic), I had my two sons very sick, and treated them with your Pills with complete success. At the same period, the small pox virus raged with much fury and disaster, attacking several of my servants and children, all of whom I cured with your Pills alone, and on none of whom could be seen any such life-time lasting consequences, as had been and still are patent upon cases saved usually by physicians. My many cures of yellow-fever, small-pox, pleurisy, rheumatism, &amp;c., &amp;c., soon obtained such publicity, that had I wished to attend and lend my assistance in the administration of Pills to only one half of the applicants, I should have been obliged to neglect my other more important duties. There are occasions, however, when we cannot resist the appeals of misery and disease, even at some considerable prejudice and loss to ourselves. It is with grateful feelings, therefore, and duly impressed with a sense of the obligation you have imposed upon your fellow-men through the virtues of your great Hygeian principle, that I apprize you of the complete success which attended my agency in the following extraordinary case. I was called upon and consulted for a young lady of about 18 years of age (an acquaintance), who had been prostrated on her bed for over eight months, having had the attention of two of our ablest physicians and surgeons; indeed, men whose names are synonymous with learning and successful practice. Imagine my consternation at the announcement&mdash;&ldquo;that she was incurable&rdquo;&mdash;in such able hands! Imagine my surprise on being solicited to undertake the case with your Vegetable Universal Medicine! Charity, humanity, caused to disappear from before my eyes the responsibility that clothed the
<pb id="p6a" n="6"/>
trust, I would, under ordinary circumstances, have shrunk to undertake. It was especially a delicate affair, from the fact, that the physicians were permitted to continue their customary visits, a toleration dictated by friendship and prudence, to which I could not object. I therefore entered upon my duties with firmness, and every confidence in the efficacy of your medicine, convinced that if any relief could be given, it could only be by this great specific. This young lady, as I said before, had been suffering for over eight long months from an abscess on the upper back part of the thigh, near the seat; during eight months of which time she was compelled to keep her bed, unable to stir, much less rise of her own strength, or walk. The physicians had applied poultices of all descriptions, administered a few powders now and then, but to no purpose, until they finally, after mature and wise consultation, determined to probe the sore. A very short time after this operation, another similar sore made its appearance at the end where the probe had reached. The same conduct, however, continued to be observed by the physicians in treating this one, as had been done with the other, when the extreme weakness of the patient, from loss of apetite, and produced by the incongruous and absurd mode of treatment, became so alarming, as to create a necessity for another consultation. The torments and sufferings of this unfortunate young lady are beyond description. The council was held, and an incision recommended! The operation was performed, while the patient slept unconscious under the influence of chloroform. Did I say incision! My heart revolts at the expression! It was a butchery! Had the physicians confined themselves to a single instance of cutting, there might be found some reason for condemning this language; but these acts were repeated, and with poultices, a few insignificant and helpless powders, now and then constituted their whole treatment, during all this time. Stretched on her bed, obliged to keep the leg crooked upwards, to avoid friction on the inflamed and sore part, she became insensible to the influences of sleep, and could obtain no rest, either by day or by night; she had long lost her appetite, her sinking condition became terribly apparent, and premonition of death was observable in her waning form. Her periods had undoubtedly been disturbed, since in these eight months there had been no natural course; and she was extraordinarily costive, conclusive evidence to me, that the former, together with the f&oelig;cal matter, found egress therethrough, from the almost insupportable stench emitted by the afflicted parts. Her case at this juncture was considered hopeless, and so declared, unless amputation be submitted to. But the glaring truths of your Morisonian principle reached her ears, and she resolved to succumb by that means, rather than be again subjected to their butchery. In this condition, then, did I receive her, not however without considerable anxiety and apprehension, because to her entreaties for some purgatives (of which she felt the necessity) her physicians objected, alleging that it would contribute to more immediate dissolution. I had as my guide your invaluable book, containing the multiplicity of your cures, and the method of treatment to be adopted in the different cases, besides many years' of personal experience. I commenced by giving her 6 Pills No 1 and 6 No. 2 alternately every day, and continued this treatment for a month, during which time the physician visited her twice&mdash;on the last of which occasions he remarked, that &ldquo;her complexion had improved&rdquo;&mdash;that &ldquo;the flesh in the wound had assumed a healthier tone and color,&rdquo;&mdash;the patient felt her appetite returning, and avowed it to him.&mdash;&ldquo;Nature is now acting&rdquo; said he! Indeed he was correct there, even while ignoring the true cause of this wonderful change to improvement This was, of all the moments of my life, the most joyful! I continued administering the Pills in doses of seven, eight and so on, increasing one Pill as recommended by you for another month. After the second month (during the latter part of which she could on occasions gradually extend the leg I applied a drying salve to the sores, which began to heal. Her appetite grown good again, induced me to permit her to gratify her palate to a moderate extent, and when she had not yet completed her third month of this treatment, I had removed all restraints to her diet. I persuaded her to attempt to get out of bed, to perambulate her room with the aid of crutches, and thus to extend and exercise the limb so long inactive. She did so; and to her amazement and delight, soon experienced the return of strength, vigour and elasticity to the limb. In the course of the fifth month she walked without assistance, and she walks now (exhibiting no signs of contraction or limping); a married woman now, with a fine child, (both in perfect health); a living witness of the substantial virtues of your great panacea. In her you have another worthy disciple, for by her agency too many hopeless cases have been restored to health.</p>
<p>Throughout the past summer, when the yellow fever (of an African type, as pronounced by the faculty) again made its appearance, scourged our fair city, and desolated many a household, when physicians themselves acknowledged that the disease baffled their science, and consequently in order to preserve the reputation of ability plucked from nature's own industry, were compelled to deny to the afflicted their pretended capabilities! I again had recourse to your Vegetable Universal Pills, with increased success, permanently curing some sixteen cases of the most malignant nature. The appeals of humanity were attended to by me with prodigality, and soon reduced me to the necessity of applying to your New York Agents for a supply of the Pills. Hence my order above, and my solicitations for the agency here, which I am convinced will redound to your advantage, and through my knowledge and experience in its administration, must wreathe new laurels on the brow of a public benefactor.</p>
<p>If necessary I can furnish you with the best references as to every qualification required for an agent. Hoping soon to hear from you,</p><closer>
<salute>I remain, yours respectfully,</salute>
<lb/><signed> P. A. AVEILH&Eacute;</signed>.</closer>
<trailer><hi rend="italics">Morison's Universal Medicine may be had of all the Hygeian Agents throughout the world; a list of whom may be obtained at the British College of Health, Euston-road, London.</hi></trailer>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p7a" n="7"/>
<head>FENDERS, FIRE-IRONS, AND FURNISHING <lb/> IRONMONGERY.</head>
<p>Families Furnishing will find it advantageous to inspect the Stock and compare Prices, which will be found lower than other Houses where quality is considered.</p>
<p>SLACK<lb/>LONDON</p><p>
<table rows="32" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>Iron Fenders</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Bronzed Fenders 3s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Bright Steel</cell>
<cell>65</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fire Irons 2s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Parlour Irons 6s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Drawing-room 9s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coal Boxes</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coal Scoops 2s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tea Trays 3s. 0d. to</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Set of 3 Trays</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Papier Mach&eacute; Trays</cell>
<cell>25</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Dish Covers, set</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Queen's pattern</cell>
<cell>23</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Meat Screen</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Roasting Jack</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fish Kettle</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory Knives, per doz</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory, full size</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Dessert full size</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>White Bone full size</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Black pinned full size</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Black Horn, to balance</cell>
<cell>14</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Teapots 5s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Water Cans 3s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Foot Tubs 4s. 6d. to</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1 Quart Saucepan</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>2 Quart Saucepan</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>3 Quart Saucepan</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>3 Gallon iron pot</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Saucepan and steamer</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Moderator Lamps from</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Copper Teakettles 7s. 0d. to</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GREATEST VARIETY OF DISH COVERS IN LONDON.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">Every article in Furnishing Ironmongery at equally low prices. All marked in plain Figures</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">and Warranted. The money returned for any article not approved of.</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Orders above</hi> 21., <hi rend="italics">carriage free, per rail.</hi></p>
<p>ESTABLISHED FIFTY YEARS.</p>
<p>Slack's Catalogue with 350 Engravings Gratis, or Post Free.</p>
<p>RICHARD &amp; JOHN SLACK <lb/> 336, STRAND. <lb/> OPPOSITE SOMERSET HOUSE.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">

<pb id="p8a" n="8"/>
<head>THE WAR.</head>
<p>OUR present poet laureate, Alfred Tennyson, a year or two ago surprised and vexed many peace-loving readers by his advocacy or defence of war, just as his predecessor. William Wordsworth, had done by his sonnets in favour of the punishment of death and his <sic
corr="description">decription</sic> of &ldquo;Slaughter&rdquo; as &ldquo;God's daughter.&rdquo; But to use the language of Cowper,</p>
<lg type="section">
<l>&ldquo;War is a game which, were their subjects wise,</l>
<l>Kings would not play at.&rdquo;</l>
</lg><p>And certainly the British people, as they have advanced in general intelligence, have set a higher value on human life, and have exhibited an increasing horror of all unnecessary bloodshed. The poorer classes have found that even remote foreign wars have a tendency to raise the price of the necessaries of life at home. We are glad to learn that with respect to articles of apparel and all items included in the term &ldquo;outfit,&rdquo; the great merchant tailors in the Minories, E. MOSES and SON, are prepared&mdash;having extraordinary facilities for the purpose&mdash;to accommodate their extensive circle of customers of all ranks as economically in the calamitous days of warfare as when Peace and Commerce walk hand in hand together.</p>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES AND SON</head><p>are now offering at unprecedentedly low prices an immense and choice assortment of every <lb/> description of <lb/> SPRING AND SUMMER CLOTHING <lb/> for adults and juveniles of all classes.&mdash;Their <lb/> BESPOKE CLOTHING DEPARTMENT <lb/> contains an extensive and carefully-selected stock of fabrics of all kinds and qualities The <hi rend="italics">latest styles</hi> are combined with the <hi rend="italics">best workmanship,</hi> and A <sic
corr="PERFECT">PERTECT</sic> FIT IS GUARANTEED.</p>
<p>OUTFITS FOR EVERY VOYAGE AND CLIMATE <lb/> A large and well-assorted stock of <lb/> HOSIERY AND UNDERCLOTHING <lb/> for both sexes.&mdash;MANTLES, UMBRELLAS, <sic
corr="PARASOLS">PAPASOLS</sic>, DRESSING CASES, WRITING DESKS, <lb/> PERFUMERY, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>An unrivalled stock of BOOTS and SHOES for ladies, gentlemen, and children.</p>
<p>HATS and CAPS of all kinds and in every style.</p>
<p>N.B.&mdash;All goods are marked in plain figures&mdash;the lowest price. Should any article not give satisfaction, it will be exchanged, or the money returned.</p>
<p>Lists of Prices, with rules for self-measurement, gratis on application, or post free.</p>
<p>E MOSES and SON'S Establishments are as follow:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<head>LONDON.</head>
<item>154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories.</item>
<item>83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate.</item>
</list><list>
<head>WEST-END BRANCH.</head>
<item>506, 507, and 508, New Oxford-street.</item>
<item>1, 2, and 8, Hart-street.</item>
</list><list>
<head>COUNTRY BRANCHES.</head>
<item>36, Fargate, Sheffield.</item>
<item>19 and 20, Bridge-street, Bradford, Yorkshire.</item>
</list><p>C. WHITING, BEAUPORT HOUSE, STRAND.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
