<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Bleak House, No. IV:
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882.</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Maura McKee</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 250K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">BLEAK HOUSE</title>

<author>Charles Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>  69 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Bradbury &amp; Evans</publisher>
<date>1852</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 21 c. 2 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2002-09-19, </date><respStmt><name> Jill Kuhn Sexton </name><resp></resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-08-29, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>

<titlePage>
<titlePart> No. IV. </titlePart>

<docDate> JUNE.</docDate>

<docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>
BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE 
</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>
<docImprint>
WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE.
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
<lb/>AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M`GLASHAN, DUBLIN.<lb/>
NOTICE is hereby given that the Author of &ldquo;BLEAK HOUSE&rdquo; reserves to <lb/> himself the right of publishing a Translation in France.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="ii"/>
<head>TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</head>
<p>EDMISTON'S POCKET SIPHONIA, <lb/> OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT.</p>
<p>WEIGHT 10 oz.</p>
<p>Sole Manufacturers of the celebrated Pocket Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on Saddle; the most <hi rend="italics">important</hi> feature in this <hi rend="italics">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.&mdash;Price according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p>
<p>EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, <lb/> Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head>
<p>WATERPROOF&mdash;&ldquo;The lightest and most effectual, is the SIPHONIA, made by EDMISTON &amp; SON, of 69, Strand; they can be carried in the hat or pocket.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life, April</hi> 20<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable weather of the season, has been manufactured by EDMISTON &amp; SON. It is remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome umbrella.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Home News, May</hi> 24<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1851.</p>
<list>
<item>Leggings or Overalls.</item>
<item>Yacht Jackets.</item>
<item>Fishing and Shooting Hats or Caps.</item>
<item>Driving Gloves.</item>
<item>Cricketing Gloves.</item>
<item>Gun Covers.</item>
<item>Gig Aprons.</item>
<item>Son-Westers.</item>
<item>Goloshes.</item>
<item>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods.</item>
<item>Ladies' Capes, with Paletots.</item>
<item>Air Cushions.</item>
<item>Air Pillows.</item>
<item>Air Beds.</item>
<item>India Rubber Portable Folding Baths.</item>
<item>Nursing Aprons.</item>
<item>Crib Sheets.</item>
<item>The newly invented Swimming Gloves, <lb/> Of great propelling power.</item>
</list>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<head>EDMISTON'S LIFE-BELTS NONE SHOULD BE WITHOUT.</head>
<p>FISHING AND SHOOTING BOOTS, soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every description of India Rubber and Gutta Percha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c.</p>
<p>BELFAST&mdash;ALBION CLOTH COMPANY. EDINBURGH&mdash;GRIEVE &amp; OLIVER, Princes-street. LIVERPOOL&mdash;J. H. SMITH, 22, Lord-street. SHAFTESBURY&mdash;JAS. WHITE. GUISBORO'&mdash;ROBINSON. HANLEY&mdash;TRED SMITH. LERWICK&mdash;HICKS. PORTSMOUTH&mdash;SEAGROVE, BROTHERS. SOUTHAMPTON&mdash;BATTEN &amp; LUKIS.</p>
<p>LONDON: EDMISTON &amp; SON, 416 &amp; 69, STRAND, near the Adelphi.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="1" id="p1"/>
<opener>No. IV.&mdash;JUNE, 1852.</opener><head>BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head>
<p>AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF WILLIAM JERDAN; with his Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences and Correspondence, during the last Forty Years, as Editor of the &ldquo;Sun&rdquo; Newspaper, 1812-17, and of the &ldquo;Literary Gazette,&rdquo; 1817-50, in connection with most of the eminent persons who have been distinguished in the past half-century as Statesmen, Poets, Authors, Men of Science, Artists, &amp;c. Vol. I., with PORTRAIT, and View of KELSO, after TURNER, in post 8vo, price 5s. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>THE CELT, THE ROMAN, AND THE SAXON. A History of the Early Inhabitants of Britain down to the Conversion of the Anglo-Saxons to Christianity. Illustrated by the Ancient Remains brought to light by recent Research. By THOMAS WRIGHT, Esq., F.S.A. With numerous Illustrations. <hi rend="italics">Shortly.</hi></p>
<p>NINEVEH AND PERSEPOLIS: an Historical Sketch of Ancient Assyria and Persia, with an Account of the recent Researches in those Countries. By W. S. W. VAUX, M.A., of the British Museum. Third Edition, revised and enlarged, in post 8vo, with numerous Illustrations. Price 8s. bound in cloth; or 17s. morocco antique.</p>
<p>SPECIMENS OF OLD INDIAN POETRY. Translated from the Original Sanskrit into English Verse. By RALPH T. H. GRIFFITH, M.A., M.R.A.S., and Boden Sanskrit Scholar in the University of Oxford. Price 5s., post 8vo, cloth.</p>
<p>OLD FOREST RANGER; or, Wild Sports of India in the Neilgherry Hills, in the Jungles, and on the Plains. By MAJOR WALTER CAMPBELL, of Skipness. With Illustrations on Steel. New Edition, in post 8vo. <hi rend="italics">In Preparation.</hi></p>
<p>A WEEK AT KILLARNEY. By Mr. and Mrs. S. C. Hall. Being a Guide to Tourists to the Lakes of Killarney. Illustrated by Twenty Engravings on Steel, from Drawings by T. CRESWICK, A.R.A., and W. H. BARTLETT. Also, 110 Engravings on Wood by various Artists, describing the most picturesque of the Beauties, the most remarkable of the Natural Features, and the most interesting of the ancient Ruins of the Killarney Lakes, and the several Routes through Ireland which conduct to them; with Maps of the Lakes and the adjacent Districts. New Edition, revised by a recent visit. Price 10s. 6d. cloth gilt.</p>
<p>FOOTSTEPS OF OUR LORD AND HIS APOSTLES, in Syria, Greece, and Italy. A Succession of Visits to the Scenes of New Testament Narrative. By W. H. BARTLETT. Third Edition, with Twenty-three Engravings on Steel, price 14s. cloth, gilt edges; or 26s. morocco elegant.</p>
<p>BALLADS FOR THE TIMES, and Other Poems. By Martin FARQUHAR TUPPER, Esq., D.C.L., F.R.S., &amp;c. &amp;c. Second Complete Edition, price 7s. 6d., with Vignette and Frontispiece, uniform with &ldquo;PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.&rdquo;</p>
<p>THE CANADIAN CRUSOES: a Tale of the Rice Lake Plains. By Mrs. TRAILL (late Catherine Parr Strickland), Author of &ldquo;The Backwoods of Canada.&rdquo; In fcap., with numerous Illustrations. <hi rend="italics">Shortly.</hi></p>
<p>LOVE A REALITY, NOT ROMANCE. By Mrs. Thomas Geldart, Author of &ldquo;Truth is Everything,&rdquo; &amp;c. With Illustrations by GILBERT. Price 3s. 6d., fcap. cloth, gilt edges.</p>
<p>YE MAIDEN AND MARRIED LIFE OF MARY POWELL. Afterwards MISTRESS MILTON. New Edition, in post 8vo, with Portrait. Price 7s. 6d., antique.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a charming little book; and whether we regard its subject, cleverness, or delicacy of sentiment and expression&mdash;to say nothing of its type and orthography&mdash;it is likely to be a most acceptable present to young or old, be their peculiar taste for religion, morals, poetry, history, or romance.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Christian Observer.</hi></p>
<p>QUEENE PHILIPPA'S GOLDEN BOOKE. Handsomely bound and gilt, with Illuminations.</p>
<p>YE HOUSEHOLD OF SIR THOMAS MORE. Libellus a Margareta More, quindecim annos nata, Chelsel&aelig; inceptus. Uniform with &ldquo;MARY POWELL.&rdquo;</p>
<p>ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="2" id="p2"/>
<head>New Works.</head>
<p>New Sporting Publication, Illustrated by JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Monthly Parts, to be completed in Twelve, price</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">s. each,</hi>
<lb/> MR. SPONGE'S SPORTING TOUR.</p>
<p>By the Author of &ldquo;Handley Cross,&rdquo; &ldquo;Jorrocks's Jaunts,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>EACH NUMBER CONTAINS ONE COLOURED ENGRAVING AND NUMEROUS WOODCUTS, BY JOHN LEECH.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Six Parts are ready, and may be had by order of any Bookseller or Newsvender.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This day is published, in crown octavo, price</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">s.,</hi>
<lb/> THE STORY OF NELL GWYN <lb/> AND THE SAYINGS OF KING CHARLES II.</p>
<p>Related and Collected by PETER CUNNINGHAM, F.S.A.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Complete in One Volume, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d., bound in cloth,</hi>
<lb/> HOW TO SEE THE BRITISH MUSEUM.</p>
<p>IN FOUR VISITS.</p>
<p>BY WILLIAM BLANCHARD JERROLD.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As a Guide-book through that vast collection it will be prized for the simplicity of its arrangement, and the clearness of its style.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Leader.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italics">In One Volume</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s., illustrated with Ten large Coloured Engravings and</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">numerous Woodcuts by</hi> JOHN LEECH, <lb/> THE COMIC HISTORY OF ROME.</p>
<p>BY G. A. A'BECKETT, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;THE COMIC HISTORY OF ENGLAND,&rdquo; in Two Volumes.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Now Publishing, in Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d. each, in Monthly Parts, price</hi> 7<hi rend="italics">d., and in Volumes,</hi>
<lb/> THE WRITINGS OF DOUGLAS JERROLD.</p>
<p>NOW FIRST COLLECTED.</p>
<p>THREE VOLUMES ARE COMPLETED, PRICE 4S. EACH, VIZ:&mdash;</p>
<p>VOL. 1.&mdash;MEN OF CHARACTER.</p>
<p>2.&mdash;ST. GILES AND ST. JAMES.</p>
<p>3.&mdash;MRS. CAUDLE'S CURTAIN LECTURES; THE STORY OF A FEATHER; AND THE SICK GIANT AND THE DOCTOR DWARF.</p>
<p>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p>
<p>New Pictorial Work.&mdash;&ldquo;THE PEOPLE'S ILLUSTRATED JOURNAL,&rdquo; of Arts, Manufactures, Practical Science, and Social Economy.</p>
<p>The First Monthly Part, embellished with NEARLY ONE HUNDRED BEAUTIFUL ENGRAVINGS, is now ready, price Elevenpence!</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Also Publishing in Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<p>OFFICE, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="3" id="p3"/>
<head>PAXTON'S FLOWER-GARDEN.</head>
<p>Edited by DR. LINDLEY and SIR JOSEPH PAXTON.</p>
<p>EACH VOLUME IS ILLUSTRATED BY THIRTY-SIX HIGHLY-FINISHED PLATES AND MORE THAN TWO <lb/> HUNDRED BEAUTIFUL ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD.</p>
<p>Volumes I. and II. are published. Price 33s. each, elegantly bound in cloth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">This work is also publishing in Monthly Parts, of which</hi> 27 <hi rend="italics">are published, and may be procured by order of any</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Bookseller. Price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d. each.</hi></p>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<head>PAXTON'S BOTANICAL DICTIONARY.</head>
<p>Comprising the Names, History, and Culture of all Plants known in Britain; with a full Explanation of <lb/> Technical Terms. Crown 8vo, 16s.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Supplement, containing all the New Plants since the First Edition, may be had separately, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</opener>
<head>Colburn &amp; Co.'s New Publications.</head>
<p>THE LIFE of MARIE DE' MEDICIS, Queen of France, Consort of Henry IV., and Regent under Louis XIII. By Miss PARDOE. 3 vols. 8vo, with Portraits, &amp;c., 42s. bound.</p>
<p>NEPAUL.&mdash;The Narrative of Two Years' Residence at NEPAUL. By Capt. THOMAS SMITH, Assistant Political Resident at Nepaul from 1841 to 1845. 2 vols., 21s.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This will henceforth be the standard work on Nepaul. Capt. Smith's narrative of his personal adventures is most exciting.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">United Service Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>HISTORY OF THE BRITISH CONQUESTS IN INDIA. By HORACE ST. JOHN. 2 vols., 21s.</p>
<p>FIVE YEARS IN THE WEST INDIES. By Charles W. DAY, Esq. 2 vols., 21s.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We recommend these interesting volumes to every one wishing to become acquainted with the condition of our West Indian Colonies.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">John Bull.</hi></p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>The New Novels.</head>
<p>ADAM GRAEME, OF MOSSGRAY. By the Author of &ldquo;Margaret Maitland.&rdquo; Second Edition.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Adam Graeme&rsquo; will enhance the reputation of its popular author. In this varied and deeply interesting story, Scottish manners and habits are depicted with the utmost fidelity. It is a work as replete with moral instruction as it is full of dramatic interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Britannia.</hi></p>
<p>MARY SEAHAM. By Mrs. Grey, Author of &ldquo;The Gambler's Wife,&rdquo; &amp;c. 3 vols.</p>
<p>CONFESSIONS OF AN ETONIAN. By Charles ROWCROFT, Esq., Author of &ldquo;Tales of the Colonies,&rdquo; &amp;c. 3 vols.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The life of an Etonian is here amusingly drawn and happily coloured by an accomplished artist. The work is full of anecdote and lively painting of men and manners.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Globe.</hi></p>
<p>AURELIA; or, A BEAUTY'S LIFE IN ITALY, 3 vols.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A story of that entrancing sort which cannot be laid aside till the whole is told. Lively sketches of society in Italy, piquant passages of love, jealousy, revenge, are offered in profusion.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Globe.</hi></p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>NEW, REVISED, AND CHEAPER EDITION.<lb/>EMBELLISHED WITH PORTRAITS OF EVERY QUEEN.<lb/><hi rend="italics">Now complete in</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">vols.</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, price</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">s. each, bound, any of which may be purchased separately.</hi></opener>
<head>LIVES OF THE QUEENS OF ENGLAND.</head>
<p>By AGNES STRICKLAND.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We congratulate the public upon the appearance of this new and cheaper edition of the &lsquo;Lives of the Queens of England.&rsquo; No one can be said to possess an accurate knowledge of the history of this country who has not studied this truly national work, which in this new edition, has received all the aids that further research on the part of the author, and of embellishments on the part of the publishers, could tend to make it still more valuable, and still more attractive, than it had been in its original form.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p>
<p>COLBURN &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS, 13, GREAT MARLBOROUGH STREET.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>Works by Dr. Lindley.</head>
<p>THE ELEMENTS OF BOTANY;<lb/>STRUCTURAL AND PHYSIOLOGICAL.</p>
<p>With a Glossary of Technical Terms, and numerous Illustrations. By DR. LINDLEY. 12s. cloth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Glossary may be had separately, price</hi> 5<hi rend="italics">s. cloth.</hi></p>
<p>THE ELEMENTS OF MEDICAL AND ECONOMICAL <lb/> BOTANY.</p>
<p>By DR. LINDLEY. With numerous Illustrations. 8vo, price 14s. cloth.</p>
<p>SCHOOL BOTANY;</p><p>OR, THE RUDIMENTS OF BOTANICAL SCIENCE.</p>
<p>BY DR. LINDLEY.</p>
<p>With nearly 400 Illustrations. 8vo, price 5s. 6d. half-bound.</p>
<p>ORCHIDACE&AElig; LINDENIAN&AElig;;</p><p>OR, NOTES UPON A COLLECTION OF ORCHIDS FORMED IN COLOMBIA AND CUBA.</p>
<p>By MR. J. LINDEN. 8vo, price 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CARPENTER'S (T.) ARITHMETIC.</head>
<p>NEW EDITION, BY W. RUTHERFORD, ESQ.</p>
<p>Price, bound in cloth, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>CARPENTER'S ARITHMETIC: designed for the use of Schools, by THOMAS CARPENTER, Author of &ldquo;The Scholar's Spelling Assistant;&rdquo; New Edition, carefully corrected and considerably enlarged. By W. RUTHERFORD, LL.D., F.R.A.S., Royal Military Academy, Woolwich.</p>
<p>London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co., 85, Queen-street, Cheapside.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>EVERY EMPLOYER&mdash;EVERY SERVANT</head><p>should read A PLEA FOR A GENERAL HALF-HOLIDAY, once in every week; being an Appeal on behalf of the Labouring Classes. Price 2d.</p>
<p>London: JOHN KING, 120, Fleet-street, and by all Booksellers.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>MESSRS. ROBERT COCKS'S NEW <lb/> MUSICAL PUBLICATIONS.</head>
<p>HAMILTON'S MODERN INSTRUCTIONS FOR THE PIANOFORTE, fingered by CZERNY, 29th Edition, 4s. &ldquo;The instructions are clear and simple, the size full music folio, the plates of extra boldness, and more than 140 popular and modern airs, preludes, exercises, &amp;c., twelve chants, and four songs, with the fingering marks, fill up this complete grammar for the piano student.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser,</hi> Feb. 14.</p>
<p>TO MUSICAL SOCIETIES, AMATEURS, AND OTHERS. &mdash; All gratis, and postage free.&mdash;1. A Catalogue of scarce Music, vocal and instrumental, and rare and valuable Musical Works, embracing more than a thousand items.&mdash;2. A complete Catalogue of Beethoven's Works.&mdash;3. A Descriptive Catalogue of Classical Music.&mdash;4. Monthly List of New Publications.&mdash;5. Lists of 500 Rare Old Violins, Tenors, Violoncellos, Double Basses, Harps, Flutes, Pianos, &amp;c.</p>
<p>To be had on application, by writing or otherwise, to ROBERT COCKS &amp; Co., New Burlington-street, London, Publishers to the Queen.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>MANGNALL'S QUESTIONS, BY GUY <lb/> AND WRIGHT.</head>
<p>With an Historical Frontispiece and Engravings. A New Edition, corrected to the Present Time, by JOSEPH GUY, Jun., of Magdalen Hall, Oxford, Author of the &ldquo;Juvenile Letter Writer,&rdquo; &amp;c. 12mo, roan. Price 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>HISTORICAL AND MISCELLANEOUS QUESTIONS for the Use of Young People, with a Selection of British and General Biography, &amp;c., by R. MANGNALL. Adapted for the Use of Schools, by the Rev. G. N. WRIGHT. A New Edition, corrected to the Present Time, by JOSEPH GUY, Jun. Illustrated with a New Historical Frontispiece, and many <hi rend="italics">New Engravings.</hi></p>
<p>London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co, 85, Queen-street, Cheapside.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CORNS, BUNIONS, DISEASES OF THE NAILS, <lb/> ETC.</head>
<p>Lately published, price 2s. 6d., by post 3s.</p>
<p>THE FOOT, its Pains and Penalties. Being concise Instructions for the Management of the Feet, with Remarks on the Quackery of Pulling out the Roots (so called) of Corns.</p>
<p>By L. DURLACHER, Surgeon-Chiropodist to Her Majesty.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He omits all technical terms, and writes clearly and intelligibly, vindicating his rational views and sober claims from the preposterous exaggeration of the empirics and daily advertiser.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Examiner.</hi></p>
<p>London: A. DURLACHER, 16, Old Bond-street, and all Booksellers; and may be had of the author, 15, Old Burlington-street.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NEW DISCOVERY IN CROCHET.</head>
<p>MISS LAMBERT has just discovered a New Mode of working Crochet, superior to any yet adopted; full <hi rend="italics">Instructions</hi> with <hi rend="italics">Engravings</hi> of which she is now prepared to forward free by return of post, upon receipt of Two Shillings and Two Stamps. 9, Craven-street, Strand.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<head>THE LADIES' COMPANION TO THE FLOWER-GARDEN.</head>
<p>BEING AN ALPHABETICAL ARRANGEMENT OF ALL THE ORNAMENTAL PLANTS GROWN IN GARDENS <lb/> AND SHRUBBERIES, WITH FULL DIRECTIONS FOR THEIR CULTURE.</p>
<p>BY MRS. LOUDON.</p>
<p>The Fifth Edition. Price 7s. cloth, with numerous Woodcuts representing the processes of Grafting, <lb/> Budding, Layering, &amp;c.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>HOW TO LAY OUT A SMALL GARDEN.</head>
<p>Intended as a Guide to Amateurs in Choosing, Forming, or Improving a Place (from a Quarter of an Acre to Thirty <lb/> Acres in extent), with reference to both design and execution.</p>
<p>BY EDWARD KEMP, Landscape Gardener, Birkenhead Park.</p>
<p>Price 3s. 6d., bound in cloth.</p>
</div3><div3 type="section">
<opener>BY THE SAME AUTHOR, price 2s.,</opener><head>THE HAND-BOOK OF GARDENING.</head>
<p>For the use of all persons who possess a Garden of limited extent. The Tenth Edition, enlarged and improved.</p>
<p>BRADBURY AND EVANS, 11, BOUVERIE STREET.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>LADIES' BONNETS, DUNSTABLE, RICE, CHIP.</head>
<p>ENGLISH AND FOREIGN FANCY BONNETS, IN EVERY SHAPE, EVERY SIZE, AND EVERY QUALITY.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">A large and superior assortment of Leghorn Bonnets, and Children's Hats. Millinery Bonnets, in all colours, of</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">the Newest Designs in Shape and Material. Morning Bonnets. Wedding Bonnets. Also a variety of</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">the choicest Bonnets, direct from the first houses in Paris.</hi></p>
<p>ALL AT THE LOWEST POSSIBLE PRICES, FOR CASH ONLY.</p>
<p>BETHEL WARE, 217, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>A SOVEREIGN REMEDY FOR BAD TEA.</head>
<p>A LEADEN PACKAGE, containing FIVE POUNDS of FINE, TRUE, RICH, RIPE, RARE SOUCHONG TEA (which will please everybody), sent, CARRIAGE FREE, to any part of England, on receipt of a Post-office Order for ONE SOVEREIGN, by</p>
<p>PHILLIPS AND COMPANY, TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> No. 8, KING WILLIAM-STREET, CITY, LONDON.</p>
<p>And will prove indeed a Sovereign Remedy for Bad Tea.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p>(as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Disinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous, useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p>
<p>Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p>
<div3>
<head>RIMMEL'S HAIR DYE</head><p>imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.&mdash;Price 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended.&mdash;Beware of counterfeits.</p>
<p>Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39. Gerard-street, Soho, London.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SOYER'S RELISH.</head>
<p>&ldquo;To describe the Sauce would be to make our readers hungry,&mdash;rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poured.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p>
<p>THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents,</p>
<p>CROSSE AND BLACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen.</p>
<p>GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>THE GORGET, <lb/> A SELF-ADJUSTING SHIRT.</head>
<p>Registered in London and Patented in Paris, <lb/> September, 1851.</p>
<p>THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR AND WRISTBAND, Registered January, 1852. The most perfect and easy fitting shirt yet produced, and by a simple invention of the patentee, adjusts itself to all movements of the body, either walking, sitting, and riding. The Patentee invites inspection, and is confident no other Shirt will be worn after the Gorget. The price, including the ELLIPTIC WRISTBAND, 42s, the half dozen. The ELLIPTIC COLLAR (quite unique), in all sizes and shapes, with Patent Elastic Fastening, 12s, the dozen. Price List, with directions for Self-measurement, forwarded on application. The PATENT ELASTIC COLLAR FASTENING can be attached to any collar opening back or front. Six sent by post on receipt of thirteen postage stamps. Patentee:&mdash;G. P. COOPER, Tailor to Her Majesty, Prince Albert, and the Prince of Wales, 6, SUFFOLK STREET, PALL MALL EAST.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>GERARD'S CELEBRATED <lb/> POMADE FOR THE HAIR.</head>
<p>Superior to all nominally-styled restoratives, as <hi rend="italics">Bears' Grease, Creams, Oils, Extracts, &amp;c., &amp;c.;</hi> eradicates scurf and dandriff; thoroughly cleanses and renders the hair peculiarly soft and luxuriant, without the greasy clamminess so greatly complained of in similar articles. In cases of premature baldness, from whatever cause, it will be found a complete restorative. The inventor does not assert that it will reproduce hair after falling off from declining years, but guarantees that it will greatly prevent it. It is particularly recommended to sufferers from an Eastern climate. To be procured only at 390, Strand, London, in Pots, 2s. each.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRT.</head>
<p>No. 84.</p>
<p>31s. 6d. &amp; 37a. 6d. the Half-dozen.</p>
<p>THE most comfortable and perfect-fitting Shirts extant, combining the highest degree of excellence at the smallest cost. Satisfaction (as usual) guaranteed. or the money returned.</p>
<p>Superb Dress Shirts for evening wear, 6s. 6d., 7s, 6d., and 8s. 6d. each. Also, Fashionable Coloured Shirts, ready made, or made to order, 20s. 26s., and 31s. 6d. the half-dozen. A choice of 200 New Patterns.</p>
<p>The general Ready-made Stock is the best, the cheapest, and the largest assortment of Shirts in London, and embraces all the recent improvements in the art.</p>
<p>Illustrated Priced Lists, with directions for self-measurement, and full particulars, gratis and post-free.</p>
<p>Patterns of the new and elegant designs for Coloured Shirts sent post-paid on receipt of Four Stamps.</p>
<p>RODGERS &amp; CO., Shirt Makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing Cross, and No. 29, at the Corner of New-street, Covent-garden, London. Established Sixty Years.&mdash;N.B. Boys' Shirts in all Sizes.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TEN GUINEA HARMONIUM</head><p>has the full compass of Five Octaves, powerful, rich tone, and <hi rend="italics">never requires tuning,</hi> is particularly suited for Churches, Chapels, Schools, &amp;c., producing a sustained tone, susceptible of the utmost expression. An extensive variety of HARMONIUMS, with the Patent Pianoforte Hammer-action from 16 to 100 Guineas. Warren's Tutor for the above, 4s.&mdash;WHEATSTONE &amp; CO., Inventors and Patentees of the Concertina, 20, Conduit-street, Regent-street, London, Messrs. W. &amp; Co., were awarded the only Exhibition PRIZE MEDAL for Harmoniums.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>PAPERHANGINGS.</head>
<p>COTTERELL, BROTHERS, 500, New Oxford-street, offer to the public a selection from all the best patterns manufactured in London and Paris. The prices range from 5d. per piece of 12 yards. Samples forwarded by post on receipt of six stamps. The trade supplied on very liberal terms.&mdash;500, New Oxford-street; also at Bristol and Bath.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>REGISTERED RAILWAY TRUNKS.</head>
<p>B. BARRETT, BROTHERS, 184, OXFORD STREET, between Duke-street, and Orchard-street, Inventors and Manufacturers of the Travelling Wardrobe, Ladies Railway Dress Imperials, with the patent fittings to divide Bonnets from the Dresses; Overland and Bullock Trunks for India; Light Trunks of every description for Continental and Home Service; Real Solid Leather Portmanteaux of the newest construction; a large assortment of Carpet and Enamelled Leather Bags; Packing and Tin Cases for India and the Colonies.</p>
<p>B. BARRETT, BROTHERS, 184, Oxford-street.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<p>SCHWEPPE'S SODA, POTASS, and MAGNESIA WATERS and AERATED LEMONADE continue to be manufactured upon the largest scale at their several Establishments in London, Liverpool, Bristol, and Derby. The celebrity of these well-known waters, and the preference they universally command, are evidences that their original superior quality over all others is well sustained. Every bottle is protected by a label with the name of their firm, without which none is genuine, and it may be had of nearly all respectable chemists throughout the kingdom. Importers of the German Selters Water direct from the springs, as for the last twenty years.</p>
<p>51, BERNERS STREET, LONDON.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p>furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned. &ldquo;Robert Shaw, London,&rdquo; is in white letters on the Government stamp of the genuine. Prices, 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d.; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HOLLOWAY'S PILLS, A MOST EFFICIENT REMEDY FOR BILE, INDIGESTION, AND DEBILITATED CONSTITUTIONS.&mdash;</head><p>The extraordinary powers of this medicine in curing disorders of the stomach, bile, indigestion, and liver complaints are wonderful. Thousands whose lives were a burden to them whilst suffering from these complaints are now enjoying the best of health by taking these invaluable pills, and now strongly recommend their use to others similarly afflicted. A few doses give relief, and a continuance of them for a short time effects a perfect cure. Persons whose constitutions have been weakened by long residence in hot climates cannot have a more certain remedy to restore them to robust health than Holloway's Pills.&mdash;Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>PULVERMACHER'S PATENT PORTABLE<lb/>HYDRO-ELECTRIC CHAIN,</head>
<p>FOR PERSONAL USE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Records</hi> of this Latest Discovery in Electricity, containing upwards of <lb/> FOUR HUNDRED Communications of Cures, effected within the last Six Months.</p>
<p>From Physicians of the highest standing, Noblemen, Clergymen, Magistrates, in short, persons in all classes of Society, and from all parts of the country, may now be had at MR. MEINIG'S HEAD OFFICES, and from all the Agents in Town or Country. Being. however, mostly Chance Communications, <hi rend="italics">even this great number does not probably represent</hi> ONE-FIFTIETH PART <hi rend="italics">of the Cures actually effected within Six Months,</hi> in the most variegated forms of Nervous and functional Disease, by this truly Miraculous Agent.&mdash;The Discovery, that mild, but continuous Electric Currents, as evolved from these Portable Chains, exercise the most <hi rend="italics">decisive alterative influence</hi> on the whole System, will, when generally known, range among the greatest blessings that we owe to Science, and will prove even more conducive to <hi rend="italics">individual happiness</hi> than that other Marvel of the Day, the <hi rend="italics">Electric Telegraph.</hi> The Chains may, as hitherto, be fully tested beforehand; FULL DESCRIPTIONS, with the highest References, Reports of numbers of INSTANTANEOUS CURES, &amp;c., may be had (by Post for Two Stamps), of CH. MEINIG, Head Depots, 103, <hi rend="italics">Leadenhall Street,</hi> and 71, <hi rend="italics">Regent Street, London,</hi> and from all Agents in Town and Country, and the Colonies.&mdash;&ldquo;I can scarcely recommend this ingenious invention too strongly to the notice of my medical brethren.&rdquo;&mdash;From that eminent Physician of Guy's Hospital, <lb/> Dr. GOLDING BIRD, M.D., F.R.S., &amp;c.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>AGENTS IN</head>
<p>Aberdeen, Williamson.&mdash;Ashford, T. Brothers.&mdash;Ashton-under-Lyne, Waterhouse.&mdash;Bakewell, Mills, &amp; Greaves.&mdash;Banbury, J. B. Austin.&mdash;Bangor, Robert Pritchard.&mdash;Bath, Bell &amp; Moody, and Geo. Braham.&mdash;Bedford, Thomas Ward.&mdash;Belfast, Gratton &amp; Co.&mdash;Belper, James Calvert.&mdash;Birmingham, T. W. Holdsworth, and Mary Salt &amp; Sons.&mdash;Berwick, J. Davidson.&mdash;Bideford, Thomas Hogg.&mdash;Bolton, Scowcroft.&mdash;Bridgewater, J. Hurman.&mdash;Brighton, Kemp, Glazier, &amp; Kemp.&mdash;Bristol, Ferris &amp; Score.&mdash;Bury, Warhurst.&mdash;Burnley, J. W. Anningson.&mdash;Cambridge, F. H. Jones.&mdash;Canterbury, Wilson.&mdash;Chatham, Hollick.&mdash;Cheltenham, D. Gibbon.&mdash;Chester, Samuel Davies.&mdash;Clifton, G. F. Schacht.&mdash;Colchester, Alfred Hagg.&mdash;Cork, Harrington &amp; Sons.&mdash;Dartmouth, Rees.&mdash;Derby, Joseph Bloor.&mdash;Dereham, Abrams.&mdash;Devonport, W. Heath.&mdash;Douglas, Isle of Man, W. Casey.&mdash;Dover, J. D. Squier.&mdash;Driffield, W. Turner.&mdash;Dublin, Pring &amp; Co., and Bewley &amp; Evans.&mdash;Dunstable, Dr. Laurie.&mdash;Edinburgh, Duncan, Flockhart, &amp; Co., J. Mackay, and J. Robertson.&mdash;Ely, Lincolne.&mdash;Exeter, J. Palk.&mdash;Folkestone, J. N. Davis.&mdash;Glasgow, Glasgow Apothecaries' Company.&mdash;Gloucester, Fouracre.&mdash;Grantham, Thomas Ekin.&mdash;Gravesend, Philemon Rolfe.&mdash;Halifax, William Dyer, and J. Thompson.&mdash;Hastings, W. Mason.&mdash;Horncastle, W. Kemp.&mdash;Hull, Chris. Bell.&mdash;Huntingdon, J. Provost.&mdash;Ipswich, Ransom.&mdash;Leamington, J. M. Herring.&mdash;Leicester, Joseph Goddard.&mdash;Lincoln, C. K. Tomlinson.&mdash;Liverpool, Abraham &amp; Co., J. B. Edwards, and C. H. Chadburn.&mdash;Lynn, Bayes.&mdash;Macclesfield, I. Brooks.&mdash;Maiden head, Highs &amp; Walker.&mdash;Maids tone, Taylor &amp; Jul.&mdash;Manchester, Gibbons, T. &amp; W. Wood, and J. B. Dancer.&mdash;Margate, W. Inch.&mdash;Market Dayton, J. Good all. &mdash; Melton Mowbray, W. Clark.&mdash;Monmouth, G. Crook. &mdash; Newbury. Thomas Fidler. &mdash; Newcastle-on-Tyne, James Gilpin &amp; Son.&mdash;Newport, E. V. Jenkins. &mdash; Northampton, Rowden.&mdash;Norwich, H. R. Priest.&mdash;Nottingham, J. Shepperley.&mdash;Oldham, Hargraves.&mdash;Ormskirk, Kershaw.&mdash;Oswestry, Edwards.&mdash;Oxford, Telfer.&mdash;Petworth, John A. Cocher.&mdash;Piymouth, Ch. Fox Hinton, and Balkwill &amp; Co.&mdash;Preston, George Sharples.&mdash;Prescot, J.Kershaw.&mdash;Ramsgate, Morton.&mdash;Reading, W. H. Staveley.&mdash;Reigate, W. Forbes.&mdash;Richmond, Hopwood &amp; Son.&mdash;Richmond. Yorkshire, James Ward.&mdash;Rochdale, Jas. Booth.&mdash;Rochester, T. S. King.&mdash;Salisbury, E. Whitlock.&mdash;Scarborough, John Jackson.&mdash;Sheffield, Chadburn Bros.&mdash;Shrewsbury, Witney &amp; Sons.&mdash;Sittingbourne, W. G. Gordelier.&mdash;Southampton, Randall &amp; Son.&mdash;Southport, Robert Johnson.&mdash;Stamford, George Patterson.&mdash;St. Heliers, Jersey, Thomas Beard.&mdash;Stockport, A. H. Shaw.&mdash;Stockton-on-Tees, W. Adamson.&mdash;Stroud, Geo. Gay.&mdash;Stratford, Essex, F. J. Alexander, Surgeon.&mdash;Stourbridge, Samuel Hughes.&mdash;Sudbury, Hagg &amp; Co.&mdash;Sunderland, J. Ritson &amp; Son, and J. Dixon.&mdash;Swaffham, Finch.&mdash;Taunton, F. &amp; C. Lake.&mdash;Tavistock, S. Perry.&mdash;Tewkesbury, May.&mdash;Shrapston, Samuel Stanton.&mdash;Tunbridge Wells, E. May.&mdash;Torquay, Fisher Brothers.&mdash;Truro, R. O. Job.&mdash;Walsal, Henry Highway.&mdash;Warrington, Samuel Webster.&mdash;Wellington, W. Edwards.&mdash;Whitchurch, J. H. Morris.&mdash;Wigan, Kellett.&mdash;Wolverhampton, W. Fleeming. &mdash; Woodbridge, J. W. Issett.&mdash;Woolwich, David Rodgers.&mdash;Worcester, W. Woods.&mdash;Wymondham, James Fison.&mdash;Yarmouth, Mabsou.&mdash;York, J. Wood.</p>
<p>Bombay, Thacker &amp; Co.&mdash;Calcutta, Thacker, Spink, &amp; Co.&mdash;Gibraltar, N. C. Mathiasen.&mdash;Kingston, Jamaica, S. Belinfante &amp; Co.&mdash;Umballah, N. W. India, Peake, Allen, &amp; Co.</p>
<p>Powerful Batteries of 120 Plates on the same principle, the Size of a Pocket-book.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMEN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.&mdash;</head><p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so Superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell>Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose</cell>
<cell>As dotted 1 to 1.</cell>
<cell>Inches.</cell>
<cell>Eighths.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required</cell>
<cell>As dotted 2 to 2.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows</cell>
<cell>As marked 3 to 3.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>70 BARKER &amp; COMPY. 70</head><pb n="8" id="p8"/><p>The Anthropos.<lb/>&pound;2 2 0</p>
<p>The Omega Shirts.<lb/>6 for &pound;1 18 6</p><p>
<table rows="10" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>THE ANTHROPOS OVER COAT</cell>
<cell>&pound;2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>BLACK SAXONY DRESS COAT, SILK LININGS</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>BLACK SAXONY FROCK COAT, SILK LININGS</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>BLACK DRESS TROWSERS</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>SHRUNK SUMMER ANGOLA TROWSERS</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>NEW MORNING COAT</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>MORNING CASHMERE VEST</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>DERBY OVER COAT</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>DRESSING GOWNS</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>11</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>OMEGA SHIRTS SIX FOR &pound;1 18s. 6d.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Barker &amp; Company, Clothiers and Shirt Makers, 70, Cornhill, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>PRIZE MEDAL.</head>
<p>WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN, Manufacturing Goldsmiths, Established A.D. 1798, beg to announce to the Nobility, Gentry, and Public in general, that in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them since the Great Exhibition, they have resolved to throw open their Manufactory to the public at <hi rend="italics">Manufactures' Prices,</hi> a closer connexion than has hitherto existed between the real worker in the precious metals and the Public, being obviously an advantage to both parties.</p>
<p>WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S dealings will be principally to establish confidence in the gold employed in the manufacture of chains, where at present the greatest uncertainty exists, owing to the prevalence of electro-gilt articles, and weighing chains, frequently as low as 11 carats fine=38s. 11&frac14;d., against sovereigns of 22 carats fine=77s. 10&frac12;. per oz., when there is no analogy between one and the other; a chain weighing 5 sovereigns being intrinsically worth only 50s. The object of the vendor is wholly to conceal the remaining 50s.</p>
<p>Gold is capable of being alloyed to any extent, and in order to protect the public, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN will make the Mint-price of 77s. 10&frac12;d. per oz. for British standard, the basis of all their operations, and making their profit on the workmanship alone, will charge the bullion in their chains at its intrinsic value, undertaking to repurchase it at any time at the same price: thus&mdash;</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>per oz.</cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>15 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell>
<cell>53s.</cell>
<cell>1d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>18 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell>
<cell>63s.</cell>
<cell>8&frac18;.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>22 Carat Gold will be charged and will realise</cell>
<cell>77s.</cell>
<cell>10&frac12;d.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The price for workmanship will be charged according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern. For example&mdash;</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>A Chain weighing 2 oz. of 15 Carat Gold is worth, at 53s. 1d. per oz.</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>2 intrinsic value.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Supposing the Workmanship to be</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell>
<cell>&pound;7</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>By this arrangement the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">bullion</hi> in a gold chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p>
<p>WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S Stock consists of Gold Guard Chains, Albert Chains, Seals, Keys, Rings, Brooches, Bracelets, Diamond Setting, and every description of Goldsmiths' and Jewellers' Work, all made on the premises.</p>
<p>MANUFACTORY, No. 16, Henrietta-street, Covent-garden, London; where the processes of manipulation may be seen by those who are interested in the subject.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="9" id="p9"/>
<head>FRENCH ORGANDIE MUSLINS.</head>
<p>THE FRENCH MUSLIN COMPANY <lb/> have taken the centrally situated Premises, No. 16, Oxford Street, for the exclusive <lb/> SALE OF MUSLINS, <lb/> and have on show some thousands, many of the designs of which are surpassingly beautiful, and all of that lady-like character so peculiar to the French.</p>
<p>A Pattern Dress sent to any part of the Kingdom on receipt of thirty-six postage-stamps.</p>
<p>Address, REID, Manager, 16, Oxford Street, near Tottenham Court Road. For Colonies to ROSSEAU, Rue St. Honore, Paris.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES,</head><p>of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p>
<p>IN FULL DRESS.</p>
<p>WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p>
<p>INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS.</p>
<p>BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p>
<p>BABY LINEN, IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p>
<p>TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p>
<p>An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information, sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>MECHI, <lb/> 4, Leadenhall Street, <lb/> LONDON.</head>
<p>THE BEST &amp; CHEAPEST <lb/> CUTLERY, DESKS, DRESSING CASES <lb/> WORK BOXES, TEA TRAYS <lb/> &amp; PAPIER MACH&Eacute; ELEGANCIES.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Bagatelle &amp; Backgammon Boards.</hi></p>
<p>EVERY THING FOR THE TOILET &amp; WORK TABLE.</p>
<p>Pocket Books, Card Cases Portfolios &amp; Inkstands.</p>
<p>TRY MECHI'S MAGIC STROP</p>
<p>Mechi's Patent Castellated Silver Wire <lb/> Tooth Brushes, 9d. each.</p>
<p>LADIES IVORY HANDLED PENKNIVES IS. EACH</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="10" id="p10"/>
<opener>LADIES TRAVELLING, <lb/> OR DURING THE DRIVE, AQUATIC EXCURSION, <lb/> or while otherwise exposed to the scorching rays of the Sun, and heated particles of Dust, will find</opener><head>ROWLAND'S <lb/> KALYDOR</head><p>a most refreshing preparation for the Complexion, dispelling the cloud of languor and relaxation, allaying all heat and irritability, and immediately affording the pleasing sensation attending restored elasticity and healthful state of the skin. Composed of choice exotics of balsamic nature, utterly free from all mineral admixture, and pleasing and delightful in its effects, ROWLANDS' KALYDOR, tends to neutralise the effects of atmosphere upon the Skin, and to promote that healthy action of the microscopic vessels, by which its general well-being and the beauty of its appearance are so essentially promoted. Freckles, Tan, Spots, Pimples, Flushes, and Discolorations fly before its application, and give place to delicate clearness with the glow of beauty and of bloom. In cases of Sunburn, or Stings of Insects, its virtues have long been <sic
corr="acknowledged">ackowledged</sic>.</p>
<p>Its <hi rend="italics">purifying and refreshing properties</hi> have obtained its selection by Royalty, and the several Courts throughout Europe, together with the <hi rend="italics">&eacute;lite</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">Aristocracy.</hi>&mdash;Price 4s. 6d. and 8s. 6d. per bottle.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;The words ROWLANDS' KALYDOR are on the wrapper of each bottle.</p>
<p>Sold by A. ROWLAND &amp; SONS, 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by all Chemists and Perfumers.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Royal Bank Buildings, <lb/><dateline> LIVERPOOL, 1852.</dateline>
</opener>
<p>WE did not feel justified, until the month of FEBRUARY of the present year, in recommending this season's imports of Black Teas, the quality of the earlier arrivals having confessedly been much inferior to those of former years. This is attributed to the continued rains which have prevailed in some parts of the Tea districts in China, owing to which the crops have been considerably deteriorated.</p>
<p>Our delay, in order to see the result of a <hi rend="italics">general importation,</hi> has already proved most beneficial to the interest of our Connexion. Watchfulness and judgment, exercised in the <hi rend="italics">selection of qualities,</hi> will we think, be more than usually appreciated this year. With this conviction, we particularly refer <hi rend="italics">Family Purchasers</hi> to the following quotations from our general list of prices.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="2">
<row>
<cell>Fine Congou, Souchong kind</cell>
<cell>3s.</cell><cell>6d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Strong Congou, Pekoe Souchong kind</cell>
<cell>3s.</cell><cell>9d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>First Class Congou, . . Rich Pekoe Sou. flavour</cell>
<cell>4s.</cell><cell>0d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The Extra Fine . . . (Very Ripe Pekoe flavour)</cell>
<cell>4s.</cell><cell>4d.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The FIRST COST of good and choice kinds being unusually reasonable, at the same time, there is an increasing demand for the commonest BLACK TEA.&mdash;This indicates that&mdash;CHEAPNESS&mdash;is more regarded by many Dealers than QUALITY&mdash;Disappointment is the necessary consequence to FAMILIES whose supplies are derived from parties not possessing the requisite advantage in Selection and Purchase.</p>
<p>&mdash;The present moderate rate of <hi rend="italics">Carriage of Parcels by Railway,</hi> affords to Families in the Country facilities for obtaining their supplies without material additional expense. Whenever desired, we <hi rend="italics">pre-pay the Carriage</hi> of parcels, including the charge in the invoice.</p>
<p>&mdash;Some parties offer to defray the carriage; we take the better alternative, <hi rend="italics">by sending</hi> A SUPERIOR QUALITY OF TEA, AT A PRICE <hi rend="italics">which must tend to secure further transactions.</hi>&mdash;</p>
<p>&mdash;&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">This Branch of our Trade&mdash;the serving of Families with Tea and Coffee&mdash;was opened in</hi> 1840, <hi rend="italics">upon a principle calculated to afford the greatest advantage in</hi> Price, <hi rend="italics">with every possible security as to</hi> Quality.</p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="2">
<head>BANKERS.</head>
<row>
<cell>The BR. BANK OF ENGLAND</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">Liverpool.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The ROYAL BANK</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">Liverpool.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The BRITISH BANK</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">London.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The BANK OF IRELAND</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">Dublin.</hi></cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Amounts paid into any of these Banking Houses, on our account, advising us of the same, will be</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">duly passed to credit, and acknowledged, without charge for Banker's Commission.</hi></p>
<p>ROB<hi rend="superscript">T</hi> ROBERTS &amp; COMP<hi rend="superscript">Y</hi>
<lb/> ROYAL BANK BUILDINGS (<hi rend="italics">Entrance up the Steps</hi>), <lb/> LIVERPOOL.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="11" id="p11"/>
<head>A NEW STOVE.&mdash;GREAT NOVELTY.</head>
<p>In the construction of the BURTON REGISTER STOVE, it was the first care of the Inventor <lb/> WILLIAM S. BURTON, <lb/> To avail himself of the most valued of modern improvements in the art of heating, and secondly, so to modify and alter the receptacle for the coals as at once to obtain the simplest and most perfect combustion; after a long series of experiments, he has, by the substitution of a graceful form of shell for the present clumsy and ill-adapted bars, succeeded in producing a stove, which for soft and brilliant light, as well as purity and quantity of heat, is not only far beyond his most sanguine expectations, but very far superior to anything yet made. Price from 63s. to &pound;15. To be seen in use daily in his show-rooms, where also are to be seen <lb/> 250 STOVES AND 325 FENDERS, <lb/> (exclusive of reserved stock) all differing in pattern, forming the largest assortment ever collected together. They are marked in plain figures, and at prices proportionate with those that have tended to make his establishment the most distinguished in this country. Bright stoves, with bronzed ornaments and two sets of bars, &pound;2 14s. to &pound;5 10s.; ditto with ormolu ornaments and two sets of bars, &pound;5 10s. to &pound;12 12s.; bronzed fenders complete, with standards, from 7s. to &pound;3; steel fenders, from &pound;2 15s. to &pound;6; ditto, with rich ormolu ornaments, from &pound;2 15s. to &pound;7 7s.; fire-irons, from 1s. 9d. the set to &pound;4 4s. Sylvester and all other patent stoves, with radiating hearth plates: and kitchen ranges, which he is enabled to sell at these very reduced charges.</p>
<p>First&mdash;from the frequency and extent of his purchases; and secondly&mdash;from those purchases being made exclusively for cash.</p>
<p>THE BEST SHOW OF IRON BEDSTEADS IN THE <lb/> KINGDOM IS WILLIAM S. BURTON'S.</p>
<p>Common Iron Bedsteads, from 12s. 6d.; Portable Folding Bedstead, from 12s. 6d.; Patent Iron Bedstead, fitted with dove-tail joints and patent sacking, from 16s. 6d.; and Cots from 20s. each; handsome Ornamental Iron and Brass Bedsteads in great variety, from &pound;3 5s. to &pound;31. Bedding of every description.</p>
<p>WILLIAM S. BURTON has TEN LARGE SHOW ROOMS (all communicating), exclusive of the shop, devoted solely to the show of <lb/> GENERAL FURNISHING IRONMONGERY, <lb/> including Cutlery, Nickel Silver, Plated, and Japanned Wares, Iron and Brass Bedsteads, so arranged and classified that purchasers may easily and at once make their selections.</p>
<p>Catalogues, with Engravings, sent (per post) free. The money returned for every article not approved of. <lb/> 39, OXFORD STREET (corner of Newman-street); Nos. 1 and 2, NEWMAN STREET; and 4 and 5, <lb/> PERRY'S PLACE.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>ROYAL INSURANCE COMPANY,</head><p>ROYAL INSURANCE BUILDINGS, LIVERPOOL, AND LOMBARD <lb/> STREET, LONDON.</p>
<p>Capital, &pound;2,000,000, in 100,000 Shares of &pound;20 each.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>TRUSTEES.</head>
<list>
<item>JOHN SHAW LEIGH, ESQ.</item><item>CHARLES TURNER, ESQ., <hi rend="italics">Chairman in Liverpool.</hi>&mdash;</item><item>R. B. B. H. BLUNDELL, ESQ.</item><item>SAMUEL BAKER, ESQ, <hi rend="italics">Chairman in London.</hi></item><item><hi rend="italics">Actuary and Manager,</hi> PERCY M. DOVE, ESQ</item>
</list>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>SPECIAL NOTICE.</head>
<p>ASSURANCES (with participation) EFFECTED ON OR BEFORE 31st DECEMBER NEXT, WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE FIRST DIVISION OF PROFITS, to be determined by the result of the Company's Life Transactions to the 31st December, 1854.</p>
<p>The Company, therefore, offers special advantages to parties assuring DURING THE PRESENT YEAR.</p>
<p>Future Division of Profits every FIVE YEARS.</p>
<p>Payment of Life Claims NEVER DISPUTED except in cases of fraud.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>FIRE BRANCH.</head>
<p>Insurances against Fire are received upon nearly all descriptions of Property. The Rates of Premium are exceedingly moderate, and governed in each case by a careful consideration of the risk proposed.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>LIFE BRANCH.</head>
<p>GUARANTEE OF AN AMPLE CAPITAL, MODERATE PREMIUMS, LARGE PARTICIPATION OF PROFITS BY THE ASSURED, AMOUNTING TO TWO-THIRDS <hi rend="italics">of its</hi> NET AMOUNT, AND SMALL CHARGE FOR MANAGEMENT, <hi rend="italics">the Expenses of the Office being borne in due proportions by the two Branches.</hi></p>
<p>Extract from the &ldquo;Post Magazine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We know of no other Institution for transacting Fire Assurance business started since the passing of the Registration Act, that can be at all compared with it, either in respect of the extent, or the success of its operations.</p>
<p>The Manager intends to visit Scotland in the present month, and is ready to receive application for Agencies from Persons of INFLUENCE and RESPECTABILITY in its various Cities and Towns.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="12" id="p12"/>
<head>Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'s REGISTERED PARDESSUS,</head><p>(6 &amp; 7 VIC. CAP. 65,) <lb/> The distinguished patronage bestowed upon this really economical and truly elegant <lb/> LIGHT SPRING AND SUMMER WALKING OVER-COAT, <lb/> (which can also be worn without another,) has had but few precedents. It is made of an extremely fine though durable cloth, and, from its peculiarly soft and silky nature, produces a sensation of the most complete ease and comfort; it may be had ready for immediate use in all sizes and colours, at the very moderate charge of TWO GUINEAS.&mdash;The Pardessus d'Ete, for Heat, Dust, and Rain, ONE GUINEA.</p>
<p>In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s. Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94, REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>CHINA CRAPE PARASOLS.</head>
<p>W. AND J. SANGSTER</p>
<p>Beg respectfully to announce that they have just received from Canton a quantity of China Crape, embroidered expressly to their order, for Parasols.</p>
<p>This beautiful material, so well adapted for the purpose by its peculiar richness and strength, will form a most novel and elegant Parasol.</p>
<p>Their stock will likewise comprise a great variety of Parasols made of Glac&eacute;, Moir&eacute; Antique, and Figured Silks from Lyons. Also, some of the richest Brocaded Silks from Spitalfields, and the Alpaca Parasol, so much approved of for the country and sea-side.</p>
<list>
<item>140, Regent Street.</item>
<item>94, Fleet Street.</item>
<item>10, Royal Exchange.</item>
<item>75, Cheapside.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="piii" n="iii"/>
<head>CHEAP EDITION <lb/> OF THE <lb/> WORKS OF MR. CHARLES DICKENS.</head>
<p>In compliance with the general wish of the purchasers of this Edition of the Works of MR. CHARLES DICKENS, terminating with &ldquo;MARTIN CHUZZLEWIT,&rdquo; it is intended to include within it the five Christmas Books:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>A CHRISTMAS CAROL.</item>
<item>THE CHIMES.</item>
<item>THE CRICKET ON THE HEARTH.</item>
<item>THE BATTLE OF LIFE.</item>
<item>THE HAUNTED MAN.</item>
</list><p>These will form, together, when their publication in Numbers shall be completed, ONE ADDITIONAL VOLUME OF THE CHEAP EDITION.</p>
<p>This additional Volume, like its predecessors (and printed to range with them), will be issued in Weekly Numbers, price 1&frac12;<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, and in Monthly Parts. The first Weekly Number will be published on the 1st of June.</p>
<p>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 193, PICCADILLY.</p>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="ii"/>
<p><figure id="ill21"><p>The Family portraits at Mr. Bayham Badger's.</p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="pv" n="iii"/>
<p><figure id="ill22"><p>Mr. Guppy's desolation.</p></figure></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pvi" n="vi"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; in Monthly Parts, and in Half-yearly Volumes,</hi></opener><head> HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head>
<p>A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p>
<p>DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST <lb/> IN THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p>
<p>FOUR VOLUMES are published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, in cloth boards, and are always on sale.</p>
<div2>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Also, published at the end of every Month, at the same Office, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi></opener><head> THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS;</head><p>Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Exchequer, a Legal Publication, not coming <lb/> within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The First and Second Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of</hi> 1850-51, <hi rend="italics">may always</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">be had, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s. each, neatly bound in cloth.</hi></p>
<p>OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter">
<pb n="97" id="p97"/>
<head>CHAPTER XI. <lb/> OUR DEAR BROTHER.</head>
<p>A TOUCH on the lawyer's wrinkled hand, as he stands in the dark room, irresolute, makes him start and say &ldquo;What's that?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's me,&rdquo; returns the old man of the house, whose breath is in his ear. &ldquo;Can't you wake him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What have you done with your candle?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's gone out. Here it is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Krook takes it, goes to the fire, stoops over the red embers, and tries to get a light. The dying ashes have no light to spare, and his endeavours are vain. Muttering, after an ineffectual call to his lodger, that he will go down stairs and bring a lighted candle from the shop, the old man departs. Mr. Tulkinghorn, for some new reason that he has, does not await his return in the room, but on the stairs outside.</p>
<p>The welcome light soon shines upon the wall, as Krook comes slowly up, with his green-eyed cat following at his heels. &ldquo;Does the man generally sleep like this?&rdquo; inquires the lawyer, in a low voice. &ldquo;Hi! I don't know,&rdquo; says Krook, shaking his head and lifting his eyebrows. &ldquo;I know next to nothing of his habits, except that he keeps himself very close.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Thus whispering, they both go in together. As the light goes in, the great eyes in the shutters, darkening, seem to close. Not so the eyes upon the bed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;God save us!&rdquo; exclaims Mr. Tulkinghorn. &ldquo;He is dead!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Krook drops the heavy hand he has taken up, so suddenly that the arm swings over the bedside.</p>
<p>They look at one another for a moment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Send for some doctor! Call for Miss Flite up the stairs, sir. Here's poison by the bed! Call out for Flite, will you?&rdquo; says Krook, with his lean hands spread out above the body like a vampire's wings.</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn hurries to the landing, and calls &ldquo;Miss Flite! Flite! Make haste, here, whoever you are! Flite!&rdquo; Krook follows him with his eyes, and, while he is calling, finds opportunity to steal to the old portmanteau, and steal back again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Run, Flite, run! The nearest doctor! Run!&rdquo; So Mr. Krook addresses a crazy little woman, who is his female lodger: who appears and vanishes in a breath: who soon returns, accompanied by a testy medical man, brought from his dinner&mdash;with a broad snuffy upper lip, and a broad Scotch tongue.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ey! Bless the hearts o' ye,&rdquo; says the medical man, looking up at them after a moment's examination. &ldquo;He's just as dead as Phairy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn (standing by the old portmanteau) inquires if he has been dead any time?</p>
<pb n="98" id="p98"/>
<p>&ldquo;Any time, sir?&rdquo; says the medical gentleman. &ldquo;It's probable he wull have been dead aboot three hours.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;About that time, I should say,&rdquo; observes a dark young man, on the other side of the bed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Air you in the maydickle prayfession yourself, sir?&rdquo; inquires the first.</p>
<p>The dark young man says yes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then I'll just tak' my depairture,&rdquo; replies the other; &ldquo;for I'm nae gude here!&rdquo; With which remark, he finishes his brief attendance, and returns to finish his dinner.</p>
<p>The dark young surgeon passes the candle across and across the face, and carefully examines the law-writer, who has established his pretensions to his name by becoming indeed No one.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I knew this person by sight, very well,&rdquo; says he. &ldquo;He has purchased opium of me, for the last year and a half. Was anybody present related to him?&rdquo; glancing round upon the three bystanders.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was his landlord,&rdquo; grimly answers Krook, taking the candle from the surgeon's outstretched hand. &ldquo;He told me once, I was the nearest relation he had.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He has died,&rdquo; says the surgeon, &ldquo;of an over-dose of opium, there is no doubt. The room is strongly flavored with it. There is enough here now,&rdquo; taking an old teapot from Mr. Krook, &ldquo;to kill a dozen people.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think he did it on purpose?&rdquo; asks Krook.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Took the over-dose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes!&rdquo; Krook almost smacks his lips with the unction of a horrible interest.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can't say. I should think it unlikely, as he has been in the habit of taking so much. But nobody can tell. He was very poor, I suppose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose he was. His room&mdash;don't look rich,&rdquo; says Krook; who might have changed eyes with his cat, as he casts his sharp glance around. &ldquo;But I have never been in it since he had it, and he was too close to name his <sic
corr="circumstances">circumstarnces</sic> to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did he owe you any rent?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Six weeks.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He will never pay it!&rdquo; says the young man, resuming his examination. &ldquo;It is beyond a doubt that he is indeed as dead as Pharaoh; and to judge from his appearance and condition, I should think it a happy release. Yet he must have been a good figure when a youth, and I dare say good-looking.&rdquo; He says this, not unfeelingly, while sitting on the bedstead's edge, with his face towards that other face, and his hand upon the region of the heart. &ldquo;I recollect once thinking there was something in his manner, uncouth as it was, that denoted a fall in life. Was that so?&rdquo; he continues, looking round.</p>
<p>Krook replies, &ldquo;You might as well ask me to describe the ladies whose heads of hair I have got in sacks down stairs. Than that he was my lodger for a year and a half, and lived&mdash;or didn't live&mdash;by law-writing I know no more of him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>During this dialogue, Mr. Tulkinghorn has stood aloof by the old portmanteau, with his hands behind him, equally removed, to all appearance, from all three kinds of interest exhibited near the bed&mdash;from the young
<pb n="99" id="p99"/>
surgeon's professional interest in death, noticeable as being quite apart from his remarks on the deceased as an individual; from the old man's unction; and the little crazy woman's awe. His imperturbable face has been as inexpressive as his rusty clothes. One could not even say he has been thinking all this while. He has shown neither patience nor impatience, nor attention nor abstraction. He has shown nothing but his shell. As easily might the tone of a delicate musical instrument be inferred from its case, as the tone of Mr. Tulkinghorn from <hi rend="italics">his</hi> case.</p>
<p>He now interposes; addressing the young surgeon, in his unmoved, professional way.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I looked in here,&rdquo; he observes, &ldquo;just before you, with the intention of giving this deceased man, whom I never saw alive, some employment at his trade of copying. I had heard of him from my stationer&mdash;Snagsby of Cook's Court. Since no one here knows anything about him, it might be as well to send for Snagsby. Ah!&rdquo; to the little crazy woman, who has often seen him in Court, and whom he has often seen, and who proposes, in frightened dumb-show, to go for the law stationer. &ldquo;Suppose you do!&rdquo;</p>
<p>While she is gone, the surgeon abandons his hopeless investigation, and covers its subject with the patchwork counterpane. Mr. Krook and he interchange a word or two. Mr. Tulkinghorn says nothing; but stands, ever, near the old portmanteau.</p>
<p>Mr. Snagsby arrives hastily, in his grey coat and his black sleeves. &ldquo;Dear me, dear me,&rdquo; he says; &ldquo;and it has come to this, has it! Bless my soul!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can you give the person of the house any information about this unfortunate creature, Snagsby?&rdquo; inquires Mr. Tulkinghorn. &ldquo;He was in arrears with his rent, it seems. And he must be buried, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir,&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, coughing his apologetic cough behind his hand; &ldquo;I really don't know what advice I could offer, except sending for the beadle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't speak of advice,&rdquo; returns Mr. Tulkinghorn. &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> could advise&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>(&ldquo;No one better, sir, I am sure,&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, with his deferential cough.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;I speak of affording some clue to his connexions, or to where he came from, or to anything concerning him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I assure you, sir,&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, after prefacing his reply with his cough of general propitiation, &ldquo;that I no more know where he came from, than I know&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where he has gone to, perhaps,&rdquo; suggests the surgeon, to help him out.</p>
<p>A pause. Mr. Tulkinghorn looking at the law-stationer. Mr. Krook, with his mouth open, looking for somebody to speak next.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As to his connexions, sir,&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, &ldquo;if a person was to say to me, &lsquo;Snagsby, here's twenty thousand pound down, ready for you in the Bank of England, if you'll only name one of 'em, I couldn't do it, sir! About a year and a half ago&mdash;to the best of my belief at the time when he first came to lodge at the present Rag and Bottle Shop&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That was the time!&rdquo; says Krook, with a nod.</p>
<p>&ldquo;About a year and a half ago,&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, strengthened, &ldquo;he
<pb n="100" id="p100"/>
came into our place one morning after breakfast, and, finding my little woman (which I name Mrs. Snagsby when I use that appellation) in our shop, produced a specimen of his handwriting, and gave her to understand that he was in wants of copying work to do, and was&mdash;not to put too fine a point upon it&mdash;&rdquo; a favorite apology for plain-speaking with Mr. Snagsby, which he always offers with a sort of argumentative frankness, &ldquo;hard up! My little woman is not in general partial to strangers, particular&mdash;not to put too fine a point upon it&mdash;when they want anything. But she was rather took by something about this person; whether by his being unshaved, or by his hair being in want of attention, or by what other ladies' reasons, I leave you to judge; and she accepted of the specimen, and likewise of the address. My little woman hasn't a good ear for names,&rdquo; proceeds Mr. Snagsby, after consulting his cough of consideration behind his hand, &ldquo;and she considered Nemo equally the same as Nimrod. In consequence of which, she got into a habit of saying to me at meals, &lsquo;Mr. Snagsby, you haven't found Nimrod any work yet!&rsquo; or &lsquo;Mr. Snagsby, why didn't you give that eight-and-thirty Chancery folio in Jarndyce, to Nimrod?&rsquo; or such like. And that is the way he gradually fell into job-work at our place; and that is the most I know of him, except that he was a quick hand, and a hand not sparing of night-work; and that if you gave him out, say five-and-forty folio on the Wednesday night, you would have it brought in on the Thursday morning. All of which&mdash;&rdquo; Mr. Snagsby concludes by politely motioning with his hat towards the bed, as much as to add, &lsquo;I have no doubt my honorable friend would confirm, if he were in a condition to do it.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hadn't you better see,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn to Krook, &ldquo;whether he had any papers that may enlighten you? There will be an Inquest, and you will be asked the question. You can read?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, I can't,&rdquo; returns the old man, with a sudden grin.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Snagsby,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn, &ldquo;look over the room for him. He will get into some trouble or difficulty, otherwise. Being here, I'll wait, if you make haste; and then I can testify on his behalf, if it should ever be necessary, that all was fair and right. If you will hold the candle for Mr. Snagsby, my friend, he'll soon see whether there is anything to help you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the first place, here's an old portmanteau, sir,&rdquo; says Snagsby.</p>
<p>Ah, to be sure, so there is! Mr. Tulkinghorn does not appear to have seen it before, though he is standing so close to it, and though there is very little else, Heaven knows.</p>
<p>The marine-store merchant holds the light, and the law-stationer conducts the search. The surgeon leans against a corner of the chimney-piece; Miss Flite peeps and trembles just within the door. The apt old scholar of the old school, with his dull black breeches tied with ribbons at the knees, his large black waistcoat, his long-sleeved black coat, and his wisp of limp white neck-kerchief tied in the bow the Peerage knows so well, stands in exactly the same place and attitude.</p>
<p>There are some worthless articles of clothing in the old portmanteau; there is a bundle of pawnbrokers' duplicates, those turnpike tickets on the road of Poverty; there is a crumpled paper, smelling of opium, on which are scrawled rough memoranda&mdash;as, took, such a day, so many grains; took, such another day, so many more&mdash;begun some time ago,
<pb n="101" id="p101"/>
as if with the intention of being regularly continued, but soon left off. There are a few dirty scraps of newspapers, all referring to Coroners' Inquests; there is nothing else. They search the cupboard, and the drawer of the ink-splashed table. There is not a morsel of an old letter, or of any other writing, in either. The young surgeon examines the dress on the law-writer. A knife and some odd halfpence are all he finds. Mr. Snagsby's suggestion is the practical suggestion after all, and the beadle must be called in.</p>
<p>So the little crazy lodger goes for the beadle, and the rest come out of the room. &ldquo;Don't leave the cat there!&rdquo; says the surgeon: &ldquo;that won't do!&rdquo; Mr. Krook therefore drives her out before him; and she goes furtively down stairs, winding her lithe tail and licking her lips.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good night!&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn; and goes home to Allegory and meditation.</p>
<p>By this time the news has got into the court. Groups of its inhabitants assemble to discuss the thing; and the outposts of the army of observation (principally boys) are pushed forward to Mr. Krook's window, which they closely invest. A policeman has already walked up to the room, and walked down again to the door, where he stands like a tower, only condescending to see the boys at his base occasionally; but whenever he does see them, they quail and fall back. Mrs. Perkins, who has not been for some weeks on speaking terms with Mrs. Piper, in consequence of an unpleasantness originating in young Perkins having &ldquo;fetched&rdquo; young Piper &ldquo;a crack,&rdquo; renews her friendly intercourse on this auspicious occasion. The potboy at the corner, who is a privileged amateur, as possessing official knowledge of life, and having to deal with drunken men occasionally, exchanges confidential communications with the policeman, and has the appearance of an impregnable youth, unassailable by truncheons and unconfinable in station-houses. People talk across the court out of window, and bareheaded scouts come hurrying in from Chancery Lane to know what's the matter. The general feeling seems to be that it's a blessing Mr. Krook warn't made away with first, mingled with a little natural disappointment that he was not. In the midst of this sensation, the beadle arrives.</p>
<p>The beadle, though generally understood in the neighbourhood to be a ridiculous institution, is not without a certain popularity for the moment, if it were only as a man who is going to see the body. The policeman considers him an imbecile civilian, a remnant of the barbarous watchmentimes; but gives him admission, as something that must be borne with until Government shall abolish him. The sensation is heightened, as the tidings spread from mouth to mouth that the beadle is on the ground, and has gone in.</p>
<p>By-and-by the beadle comes out, once more intensifying the sensation, which has rather languished in the interval. He is understood to be in want of witnesses, for the Inquest to-morrow, who can tell the Coroner and Jury anything whatever respecting the deceased. Is immediately referred to innumerable people who can tell nothing whatever. Is made more imbecile by being constantly informed that Mrs. Green's son &ldquo;was a law-writer his-self, and knowed him better than anybody&rdquo;&mdash;which son of Mrs. Green's appears, on inquiry, to be at the present time aboard a vessel bound for China, three months out, but considered accessible by telegraph, on application to the Lords of the Admiralty. Beadle goes
<pb n="102" id="p102"/>
into various shops and parlors, examining the inhabitants; always shutting the door first, and by exclusion, delay, and general idiotey, exasperating the public. Policeman seen to smile to potboy. Public loses interest, and undergoes reaction. Taunts the beadle, in shrill youthful voices, with having boiled a boy; choruses fragments of a popular song to that effect, and importing that the boy was made into soup for the workhouse. Policeman at last finds it necessary to support the law, and seize a vocalist; who is released upon the flight of the rest, on condition of his getting out of this then, come! and cutting it&mdash;a condition he immediately observes. So the sensation dies off for the time; and the unmoved policeman (to whom a little opium, more or less, is nothing), with his shining hat, stiff stock, inflexible great-coat, stout belt and bracelet, and all things fitting, pursues his lounging way with a heavy tread: beating the palms of his white gloves one against the other, and stopping now and then, at a street-corner, to look casually about for anything between a lost child and a murder.</p>
<p>Under cover of the night, the feeble-minded beadle comes flitting about Chancery Lane with his summonses, in which every Juror's name is wrongly spelt, and nothing is rightly spelt but the beadle's own name, which nobody can read or wants to know. The summonses served, and his witnesses forewarned, the beadle goes to Mr. Krook's, to keep a small appointment he has made with certain paupers; who, presently arriving, are conducted up-stairs; where they leave the great eyes in the shutter something new to stare at, in that last shape which earthly lodgings take for No one&mdash;and for Every one.</p>
<p>And, all that night, the coffin stands ready by the old portmanteau; and the lonely figure on the bed, whose path in life has lain through five-and-forty years, lies there, with no more track behind him, that any one can trace, than a deserted infant.</p>
<p>Next day the court is all alive&mdash;is like a fair, as Mrs. Perkins, more than reconciled to Mrs. Piper, says, in amicable conversation with that excellent woman. The coroner is to sit in the first-floor room at the Sol's Arms, where the Harmonic Meetings take place twice a-week, and where the chair is filled by a gentleman of professional celebrity, faced by little Swills, the comic vocalist, who hopes (according to the bill in the window) that his friends will rally round him and support first-rate talent. The Sol's Arms does a brisk stroke of business all the morning. Even children so require sustaining, under the general excitement, that a pieman, who has established himself for the occasion at the corner of the court, says his brandy-balls go off like smoke. What time the beadle, hovering between the door of Mr. Krook's establishment and the door of the Sol's Arms, shews the curiosity in his keeping to a few discreet spirits, and accepts the compliment of a glass of ale or so in return.</p>
<p>At the appointed hour arrives the Coroner, for whom the Jurymen are waiting, and who is received with a salute of kittles from the good dry skittle-ground attached to the Sol's Arms. The Coroner frequents more public-houses than any man alive. The smell of sawdust, beer, tobacco-smoke, and spirits, is inseparable in his vocation from death in its most awful shapes. He is conducted by the beadle and the landlord to the Harmonic Meeting Room, where he puts his hat on the piano, and takes a Windsor-chair at the head of a long table, formed of several short tables
<pb n="103" id="p103"/>
put together, and ornamented with glutinous rings in endless involutions, made by pots and glasses. As many of the Jury as can crowd together at the table sit there. The rest get among the spittoons and pipes, or lean against the piano. Over the Coroner's head is a small iron garland, the pendant handle of a bell, which rather gives the Majesty of the Court the appearance of going to be hanged presently.</p>
<p>Call over and swear the Jury! While the ceremony is in progress, sensation is created by the entrance of a chubby little man in a large shirt-collar, with a moist eye, and an inflamed nose, who modestly takes a position near the door as one of the general public, but seems familiar with the room too. A whisper circulates that this is little Swills. It is considered not unlikely that he will get up an imitation of the Coroner, and make it the principal feature of the Harmonic Meeting in the evening.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, gentlemen&mdash;&rdquo; the Coroner begins.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Silence there, will you!&rdquo; says the beadle. Not to the Coroner, though it might appear so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, gentlemen!&rdquo; resumes the Coroner. &ldquo;You are impanelled here, to inquire into the death of a certain man. Evidence will be given before you, as to the circumstances attending that death, and you will give your verdict according to the&mdash;skittles; they must be stopped, you know, beadle!&mdash;evidence, and not according to anything else. The first thing to be done, is to view the body.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Make way there!&rdquo; cries the beadle.</p>
<p>So they go out in a loose procession, something after the manner of a straggling funeral, and make their inspection in Mr. Krook's back second floor, from which a few of the Jurymen retire pale and precipitately. The beadle is very careful that two gentlemen not very neat about the cuffs and buttons (for whose accommodation he has provided a special little table near the Coroner, in the Harmonic Meeting Room), should see all that is to be seen. For they are the public chroniclers of such inquiries, by the line; and he is not superior to the universal human infirmity, but hopes to read in print what &ldquo;Mooney, the active and intelligent beadle of the district,&rdquo; said and did; and even aspires to see the name of Mooney as familiarly and patronisingly mentioned as the name of the Hangman is, according to the latest examples.</p>
<p>Little Swills is waiting for the Coroner and Jury on their return. Mr. Tulkinghorn, also. Mr. Tulkinghorn is received with distinction, and seated near the Coroner; between that high judicial officer, a bagatelle board, and the coal-box. The inquiry proceeds. The Jury learn how the subject of their inquiry died, and learn no more about him. &ldquo;A very eminent solicitor is in attendance, gentlemen,&rdquo; says the Coroner, &ldquo;who, I am informed, was accidentally present, when discovery of the death was made; but he could only repeat the evidence you have already heard from the surgeon, the landlord, the lodger, and the law-stationer; and it is not necessary to trouble him. Is anybody in attendance who knows anything more?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Piper pushed forward by Mrs. Perkins. Mrs. Piper sworn.</p>
<p>Anastasia Piper, gentlemen. Married woman. Now, Mrs. Piper&mdash;what have you got to say about this?</p>
<p>Why, Mrs. Piper has a good deal to say, chiefly in parenthesis and without punctuation, but not much to tell. Mrs. Piper lives in the
<pb n="104" id="p104"/>
court (which her husband is a cabinet-maker) and it has long been well beknown among the neighbours (counting from the day next but one before the half-baptising of Alexander James Piper aged eighteen months and four days old on accounts of not being expected to live such was the sufferings gentlemen of that child in his gums) as the Plaintive&mdash;so Mrs. Piper insists on calling the deceased&mdash;was reported to have sold himself. Thinks it was the Plaintive's air in which that report <sic
corr="originated">originatinin</sic>. See the Plaintive often, and considered as his air was <sic
corr="ferocious">feariocious</sic>, and not to be allowed to go about some children being timid (and if doubted hoping Mrs. Perkins may be brought <sic
corr="forward">forard</sic> for she is here and will do credit to her husband and herself and family). Has seen the Plaintive wexed and worrited by the children (for children they will ever be and you cannot expect them specially if of playful dispositions to be Methoozellers which you was not yourself). On accounts of this and his dark looks has often dreamed as she see him take a pickaxe from his pocket and split Johnny's head (which the child knows not fear and has repeatually called after him close at his eels). Never however see the Plaintive take a pickaxe or any other wepping far from it. Has seen him hurry away when run and called after as if not partial to children and never see him speak to neither child nor grown person at any time (excepting the boy that sweeps the crossing down the lane over the way round the corner which if he was here would tell you that he has been seen a speaking to him frequent).</p>
<p>Says the Coroner, is that boy here? Says the beadle, no, sir, he is not here. Says the Coroner, go and fetch him then. In the absence of the active and intelligent, the Coroner converses with Mr. Tulkinghorn.</p>
<p>O! Here's the boy, gentlemen!</p>
<p>Here he is, very muddy, very hoarse, very ragged. Now, boy!&mdash;But stop a minute. Caution. This boy must be put through a few preliminary paces.</p>
<p>Name, Jo. Nothing else that he knows on. Don't know that everybody has two names. Never heerd of sich a think. Don't know that Jo is short for a longer name. Thinks it long enough for <hi rend="italics">him. He</hi> don't find no fault with it. Spell it? No. <hi rend="italics">He</hi> can't spell it. No father, no mother, no friends. Never been to school. What's home? Knows a broom's a broom, and knows it's wicked to tell a lie. Don't recollect who told him about the broom, or about the lie, but knows both. Can't exactly say what'll be done to him arter he's dead if he tells a lie to the gentlemen here, but believes it'll be something wery bad to punish him, and serve him right&mdash;and so he'll tell the truth.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This won't do, gentlemen!&rdquo; says the Coroner, with a melancholy shake of the head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you think you can receive his evidence, sir?&rdquo; asks an attentive Juryman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Out of the question,&rdquo; says the Coroner. &ldquo;You have heard the boy. &lsquo;Can't exactly say&rsquo; won't do, you know. We can't take <hi rend="italics">that,</hi> in a Court of Justice, gentlemen. It's terrible depravity. Put the boy aside.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Boy put aside; to the great edification of the audience;&mdash;especially of Little Swills, the Comic Vocalist.</p>
<p>Now. Is there any other witness? No other witness.</p>
<p>Very well, gentlemen! Here's a man unknown, proved to have been in the habit of taking opium in large quantities for a year and a half,
<pb n="105" id="p105"/>
found dead of too much opium. If you think you have any evidence to lead you to the conclusion that he committed suicide, you will come to that conclusion. If you think it is a case of accidental death, you will find a Verdict accordingly.</p>
<p>Verdict accordingly. Accidental death. No doubt. Gentlemen, you are discharged. Good afternoon.</p>
<p>While the Coroner buttons his great coat, Mr. Tulkinghorn and he give private audience to the rejected witness in a corner.</p>
<p>That graceless creature only knows that the dead man (whom he recognised just now by his yellow face and black hair) was sometimes hooted and pursued about the streets. That one cold winter night, when he, the boy, was shivering in a doorway near his crossing, the man turned to look at him, and came back, and, having questioned him and found that he had not a friend in the world, said, &ldquo;Neither have I. Not one!&rdquo; and gave him the price of a supper and a night's lodging. That the man had often spoken to him since; and asked him whether he slept sound at night, and how he bore cold and hunger, and whether he ever wished to die; and similar strange questions. That when the man had no money, he would say in passing, &ldquo;I am as poor as you to-day, Jo;&rdquo; but that when he had any, he had always (as the boy most heartily believes) been glad to give him some.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was wery good to me,&rdquo; says the boy, wiping his eyes with his wretched sleeve. &ldquo;Wen I see him a layin' so stritched out just now, I wished he could have heerd me tell him so. He wos wery good to me, he wos!&rdquo;</p>
<p>As he shuffles down stairs, Mr. Snagsby, lying in wait for him, puts a half-crown in his hand. &ldquo;If ever you see me coming past your crossing with my little woman&mdash;I mean a lady&mdash;&rdquo; says Mr. Snagsby, with his finger on his nose, &ldquo;don't allude to it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>For some little time the Jurymen hang about the Sol's Arms colloquially. In the sequel, half-a-dozen are caught up in a cloud of pipe-smoke that pervades the parlor of the Sol's Arms; two stroll to Hampstead; and four engage to go half-price to the play at night, and top up with oysters. Little Swills is treated on several hands. Being asked what he thinks of the proceedings, characterises them (his strength lying in a slangular direction) as &ldquo;a rummy start.&rdquo; The landlord of the Sol's Arms, finding Little Swills so popular, commends him highly to the Jurymen and public; observing that, for a song in character, he don't know his equal, and that that man's character-wardrobe would fill a cart.</p>
<p>Thus, gradually the Sol's Arms melts into the shadowy night, and then flares out of it strong in gas. The Harmonic Meeting hour arriving, the gentleman of professional celebrity takes the chair; is faced (red-faced) by Little Swills; their friends rally round them, and support first-rate talent. In the zenith of the evening, Little Swills says, Gentlemen, if you'll permit me, I'll attempt a short description of a scene of real life that came off here to-day. Is much applauded and encouraged; goes out of the room as Swills; comes in as the Coroner (not the least in the world like him); describes the Inquest, with recreative intervals of piano-forte accompaniment to the refrain&mdash;With his (the Coroner's) tippy tol li doll, tippy tol lo doll, tippy tol li doll, Dee!</p>
<p>The jingling piano at last is silent, and the Harmonic friends rally
<pb n="106" id="p106"/>
round their pillows. Then there is rest around the lonely figure, now laid in its last earthly habitation; and it is watched by the gaunt eyes in the shutters through some quiet hours of night. If this forlorn man could have been prophetically seen lying here, by the mother at whose breast he nestled, a little child, with eyes upraised to her loving face, and soft hand scarcely knowing how to close upon the neck to which it crept, what an impossibility the vision would have seemed! O, if, in brighter days, the now-extinguished fire within him ever burned for one woman who held him in her heart, where is she, while these ashes are above the ground!</p>
<p>It is anything but a night of rest at Mr. Snagsby's, in Cook's Court; where Guster murders sleep, by going, as Mr. Snagsby himself allows&mdash;not to put too fine a point upon it&mdash;out of one fit into twenty. The occasion of this seizure is, that Guster has a tender heart, and a susceptible something that possibly night have been imagination, but for Tooting and her patron saint. Be it what it may, now, it was so direfully impressed at tea-time by Mr. Snagsby's account of the enquiry at which he had assisted, that at supper-time she projected herself into the kitchen, preceded by a flying Dutch-cheese, and fell into a fit of unusual duration: which she only came out of to go into another, and another, and so on through a chain of fits, with short intervals between, of which she has pathetically availed herself by consuming them in entreaties to Mrs. Snagsby not to give her warning &ldquo;when she quite comes to;&rdquo; and also in appeals to the whole establishment to lay her down on the stones, and go to bed. Hence, Mr. Snagsby, at last hearing the cock at the little dairy in Cursitor Street go into that disinterested ecstasy of his on the subject of daylight, says, drawing a long breath, though the most patient of men, &ldquo;I thought you was dead, I am sure!&rdquo;</p>
<p>What question this enthusiastic fowl supposes he settles when he strains himself to such an extent, or why he should thus crow (so men crow on various triumphant public occasions, however) about what cannot be of any moment to him, is his affair. It is enough that daylight comes, morning comes, noon comes.</p>
<p>Then the active and intelligent, who has got into the morning papers as such, comes with his pauper company to Mr. Krook's, and bears off the body of our dear brother here departed, to a hemmed-in churchyard, pestiferous and obscene, whence malignant diseases are communicated to the bodies of our dear brothers and sisters who have not departed; while our dear brothers and sisters who hang about official backstairs&mdash;would to Heaven they <hi rend="italics">had</hi> departed!&mdash;are very complacent and agreeable. Into a beastly scrap of ground which a Turk would reject as a savage abomination, and a Caffre would shudder at, they bring our dear brother here departed, to receive Christian burial.</p>
<p>With houses looking on, on every side, save where a reeking little tunnel of a court gives access to the iron gate&mdash;with every villainy of life in action close on death, and every poisonous element of death in action close on life&mdash;here, they lower our dear brother down a foot or two: here, sow him in corruption, to be raised in corruption: an avenging ghost at many a sick-bedside: a shameful testimony to future ages, how civilisation and barbarism walked this boastful island together.</p>
<p>Come night, come darkness, for you cannot come too soon, or stay too
<pb n="107" id="p107"/>
long, by such a place as this! Come, straggling lights into the windows of the ugly houses; and you who do iniquity therein, do it at least with this dread scene shut out! Come, flame of gas, burning so sullenly above the iron gate, on which the poisoned air deposits its witch-ointment slimy to the touch! It is well that you should call to every passer-by, &ldquo;Look here!&rdquo;</p>
<p>With the night, comes a slouching figure through the tunnel-court, to the outside of the iron gate. It holds the gate with its hands, and looks in between the bars; stands looking in, for a little while.</p>
<p>It then, with an old broom it carries, softly sweeps the step, and makes the archway clean. It does so, very busily and trimly; looks in again, a little while; and so departs.</p>
<p>Jo, is it thou? Well, well! Though a rejected witness, who &ldquo;can't exactly say&rdquo; what will be done to him in greater hands than men's, thou art not quite in outer darkness. There is something like a distant ray of light in thy muttered reason for this:</p>
<p>&ldquo;He wos wery good to me, he wos!&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XII. <lb/> ON THE WATCH.</head>
<p>IT has left off raining down in Lincolnshire, at last, and Chesney Wold has taken heart. Mrs. Rouncewell is full of hospitable cares, for Sir Leicester and my Lady are coming home from Paris. The fashionable intelligence has found it out, and communicates the glad tidings to benighted England. It has also found out, that they will entertain a brilliant and distinguished circle of the <hi rend="italics">&eacute;lite</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">beau monde</hi> (the fashionable intelligence is weak in English, but a giant-refreshed in French), at the ancient and hospitable family seat in Lincolnshire.</p>
<p>For the greater honor of the brilliant and distinguished circle, and of Chesney Wold into the bargain, the broken arch of the bridge in the park is mended; and the water, now retired within its proper limits and again spanned gracefully, makes a figure in the prospect from the house. The clear cold sunshine glances into the brittle woods, and approvingly beholds the sharp wind scattering the leaves and drying the moss. It glides over the park after the moving shadows of the clouds, and chases them, and never catches them, all day. It looks in at the windows, and touches the ancestral portraits with bars and patches of brightness, never contemplated by the painters. Athwart the picture of my Lady, over the great chimney-piece, it throws a broad bend-sinister of light that strikes down crookedly into the hearth, and seems to rend it.</p>
<p>Through the same cold sunshine, and the same sharp wind, my Lady and Sir Leicester, in their travelling chariot, (my Lady's woman, and Sir Leicester's man affectionate in the rumble,) start for home. With a considerable amount of jingling and whip-cracking, and many plunging demonstrations on the part of two bare-backed horses, and two Centaurs with glazed hats, jack-boots, and flowing manes and tails, they rattle out
<pb n="108" id="p108"/>
of the yard of the H&ocirc;tel Bristol in the Place Vend&ocirc;me, and canter between the sun-and-shadow-chequered colonnade of the Rue de Rivoli and the garden of the ill-fated palace of a headless king and queen, off by the Place of Concord, and the Elysian Fields, and the Gate of the Star, out of Paris.</p>
<p>Sooth to say, they cannot go away too fast; for, even here, my Lady Dedlock has been bored to death. Concert, assembly, opera, theatre, drive, nothing is new to my Lady, under the worn-out heavens. Only last Sunday, when poor wretches were gay&mdash;within the walls, playing with children among the clipped trees and the statues in the Palace Garden; walking, a score abreast, in the Elysian Fields, made more Elysian by performing dogs and wooden horses; between whiles filtering (a few) through the gloomy Cathedral of Our Lady, to say a word or two at the base of a pillar, within flare of a rusty little gridiron-full of gusty little tapers&mdash;without the walls, encompassing Paris with dancing, love-making, wine-drinking, tobacco-smoking, tomb-visiting, billiard card and domino playing, quack-doctoring, and much murderous refuse, animate and inanimate&mdash;only last Sunday, my Lady, in the desolation of Boredom and the clutch of Giant Despair, almost hated her own maid for being in spirits.</p>
<p>She cannot, therefore, go too fast from Paris. Weariness of soul lies before her, as it lies behind&mdash;her Ariel has put a girdle of it round the whole earth, and it cannot be unclasped&mdash;but the imperfect remedy is always to fly, from the last place where it has been experienced. Fling Paris back into the distance, then, exchanging it for endless avenues and cross-avenues of wintry trees! And, when next beheld, let it be some leagues away, with the Gate of the Star a white speck glittering in the sun, and the city a mere mound in a plain: two dark square towers rising out of it, and light and shadow descending on it aslant, like the angels in Jacob's dream!</p>
<p>Sir Leicester is generally in a complacent state, and rarely bored. When he has nothing else to do, he can always contemplate his own greatness. It is a considerable advantage to a man, to have so inexhaustible a subject. After reading his letters, he leans back in his corner of the carriage, and generally reviews his importance to society.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have an unusual amount of correspondence this morning?&rdquo; says my Lady, after a long time. She is fatigued with reading. Has almost read a page in twenty miles.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing in it, though. Nothing whatever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I saw one of Mr. Tulkinghorn's long effusions, I think?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You see everything,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, with admiration.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ha!&rdquo; sighs my Lady. &ldquo;He is the most tiresome of men!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He sends&mdash;I really beg your pardon&mdash;he sends,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, selecting the letter, and unfolding it, &ldquo;a message to you. Our stopping to change horses, as I came to his postscript, drove it out of my memory. I beg you'll excuse me. He says&mdash;&rdquo; Sir Leicester is so long in taking out his eye-glass and adjusting it, that my Lady looks a little irritated. &ldquo;He says &lsquo;In the matter of the right of way&mdash;&rsquo; I beg your pardon, that's not the place. He says&mdash;yes! Here I have it! He says, &lsquo;I beg my respectful compliments to my Lady, who, I hope, has benefited by the change. Will you do me the favor to mention (as it may interest
<pb n="109" id="p109"/>
her), that I have something to tell her on her return, in reference to the person who copied the affidavit in the Chancery suit, which so powerfully stimulated her curiosity. I have seen him.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, leaning forward, looks out for her window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the message,&rdquo; observes Sir Leicester.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should like to walk a little,&rdquo; says my Lady, still looking out of her window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walk?&rdquo; repeats Sir Leicester, in a tone of surprise.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should like to walk a little,&rdquo; says my Lady, with unmistakeable distinctness. &ldquo;Please to stop the carriage.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The carriage is stopped, the affectionate man alights from the rumble, opens the door, and lets down the steps, obedient to an impatient motion of my Lady's hand. My Lady alights so quickly, and walks away so quickly, that Sir Leicester, for all his scrupulous politeness, is unable to assist her, and is left behind. A space of a minute or two has elapsed before he comes up with her. She smiles, looks very handsome, takes his arm, lounges with him for a quarter of a mile, is very much bored, and resumes her seat in the carriage.</p>
<p>The rattle and clatter continue through the greater part of three days, with more or less of bell-jingling and whip-cracking, and more or less plunging of Centaurs and bare-backed horses. Their courtly politeness to each other, at the Hotels where they tarry, is the theme of general admiration. Though my Lord <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a little aged for my Lady, says Madame, the hostess of the Golden Ape, and though he might be her amiable father, one can see at a glance that they love each other. One observes my Lord with his white hair, standing, hat in hand, to help my Lady to and from the carriage. One observes my Lady, how recognisant of my Lord's politeness, with an inclination of her gracious head, and the concession of her so-genteel fingers! It is ravishing!</p>
<p>The sea has no appreciation of great men, but knocks them about like the small fry. It is habitually hard upon Sir Leicester, whose countenance it greenly mottles in the manner of sage-cheese, and in whose aristocratic system it effects a dismal revolution. It is the Radical of Nature to him. Nevertheless, his dignity gets over it, after stopping to refit; and he goes on with my Lady for Chesney Wold, lying only one night in London on the way to Lincolnshire.</p>
<p>Through the same cold sunlight&mdash;colder as the day declines,&mdash;and through the same sharp wind&mdash;sharper as the separate shadows of bare trees gloom together in the woods, and as the Ghost's Walk, touched at the western corner by a pile of fire in the sky, resigns itself to coming night,&mdash;they drive into the park. The Rooks, swinging in their lofty houses in the elm-tree avenue, seem to discuss the question of the occupancy of the carriage as it passes underneath; some agreeing that Sir Leicester and my Lady are come down; some arguing with malcontents who won't admit it, now, all consenting to consider the question disposed of; now, all breaking out again in violent debate, incited by one obstinate and drowsy bird, who will persist in putting in a last contradictory croak. Leaving them to swing and caw, the travelling chariot rolls on to the house; where fires gleam warmly through some of the windows, though not through so many as to give an inhabited expression to the darkening mass of front. But the brilliant and distinguished circle will soon do that.</p>
<pb n="110" id="p110"/>
<p>Mrs. Rouncewell is in attendance, and receives Sir Leicester's customary shake of the hand with a profound curtsey.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do you do, Mrs. Rouncewell? I am glad to see you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope I have the honor of welcoming you in good health, Sir Leicester?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In excellent health, Mrs. Rouncewell.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My Lady is looking charmingly well,&rdquo; says Mrs. Rouncewell, with another curtsey.</p>
<p>My Lady signifies, without profuse expenditure of words, that she is as wearily well as she can hope to be.</p>
<p>But Rosa is in the distance, behind the housekeeper; and my Lady, who has not subdued the quickness of her observation, whatever else she may have conquered, asks:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who is that girl?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A young scholar of mine, my Lady. Rosa.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come here, Rosa!&rdquo; Lady Dedlock beckons her, with even an appearance of interest. &ldquo;Why, do you know how pretty you are, child?&rdquo; she says, touching her shoulder with her two forefingers.</p>
<p>Rosa, very much abashed, says &ldquo;No, if you please, my Lady!&rdquo; and glances up, and glances down, and don't know where to look, but looks all the prettier.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How old are you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nineteen, my Lady.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nineteen,&rdquo; repeats my Lady, thoughtfully. &ldquo;Take care they don't spoil you by flattery.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my Lady.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady taps her dimpled cheek with the same delicate gloved fingers, and goes on to the foot of the oak staircase, where Sir Leicester pauses for her as her knightly escort. A staring old Dedlock in a panel, as large as life and as dull, looks as if he didn't know what to make of it&mdash;which was probably his general state of mind in the days of Queen Elizabeth.</p>
<p>That evening, in the housekeeper's room, Rosa can do nothing but murmur Lady Dedlock's praises. She is so affable, so graceful, so beautiful, so elegant; has such a sweet voice, and such a thrilling touch, that Rosa can feel it yet! Mrs. Rouncewell confirms all this, not without personal pride, reserving only the one point of affability. Mrs. Rouncewell is not quite sure as to that. Heaven forbid that she should say a syllable in dispraise of any member of that excellent family; above all, of my Lady, whom the whole world admires; but if my Lady would only be &ldquo;a little more free,&rdquo; not quite so cold and distant, Mrs. Rouncewell thinks she would be more affable.</p>
<p>&ldquo;'Tis almost a pity,&rdquo; Mrs. Rouncewell adds&mdash;only &ldquo;almost,&rdquo; because it borders on impiety to suppose that anything could be better than it is, in such an express dispensation as the Dedlock affairs; &ldquo;that my Lady has no family. If she had had a daughter now, a grown young lady, to interest her, I think she would have had the only kind of excellence she wants.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Might not that have made her still more proud, grandmother?&rdquo; says Watt; who has been home and come back again, he is such a good grandson.</p>
<p>&ldquo;More and most, my dear,&rdquo; returns the housekeeper with dignity,
<pb n="111" id="p111"/>
&ldquo;are words it's not my place to use&mdash;nor so much as to hear&mdash;applied to any drawback on my Lady.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, grandmother. But she <hi rend="italics">is</hi> proud, is she not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If she is, she has reason to be. The Dedlock family have always reason to be.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well!&rdquo; says Watt, &ldquo;it's to be hoped they line out of their Prayer-Books a certain passage for the common people about pride and vainglory. Forgive me, grandmother! Only a joke!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir Leicester and Lady Dedlock, my dear, are not fit subjects for joking.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir Leicester is no joke, by any means,&rdquo; says Watt; &ldquo;and I humbly ask his pardon. I suppose, grandmother, that, even with the family and their guests down here, there is no objection to my prolonging my stay at the Dedlock Arms for a day or two, as any other traveller might?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Surely, none in the world, child.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am glad of that,&rdquo; says Watt, &ldquo;because I&mdash;because I have an inexpressible desire to extend my knowledge of this beautiful neighbourhood.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He happens to glance at Rosa, who looks down, and is very shy, indeed. But, according to the old superstition, it should be Rosa's ears that burn, and not her fresh bright cheeks; for my Lady's maid is holding forth about her at this moment, with surpassing energy.</p>
<p>My Lady's maid is a Frenchwoman of two-and-thirty, from somewhere in the Southern country about Avignon and Marseilles&mdash;a large-eyed brown woman with black hair; who would be handsome, but for a certain feline mouth, and general uncomfortable tightness of face, rendering the jaws too eager, and the skull too prominent. There is something indefinably keen and wan about her anatomy; and she has a watchful way of looking out of the corners of her eyes without turning her head, which could be pleasantly dispensed with&mdash;especially when she is in an ill-humour and near knives. Through all the good taste of her dress and little adornments, these objections so express themselves, that she seems to go about like a very neat She-Wolf imperfectly tamed. Besides being accomplished in all the knowledge appertaining to her post, she is almost an English-woman in her acquaintance with the language&mdash;consequently, she is in no want of words to shower upon Rosa for having attracted my Lady's attention; and she pours them out with such grim ridicule as she sits at dinner, that her companion, the affectionate man, is rather relieved when she arrives at the spoon stage of that performance.</p>
<p>Ha, ha, ha! She, Hortense, been in my Lady's service since five years, and always kept at the distance, and this doll, this puppet caressed&mdash;absolutely caressed&mdash;by my Lady on the moment of her arriving at the house! Ha, ha! ha! &ldquo;And do you know how pretty you are child?&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;No, my Lady.&rdquo;&mdash;You are right there! &ldquo;And how old are you, child? And take care they do not spoil you by flattery, child! O how droll! It is the <hi rend="italics">best</hi> thing altogether.</p>
<p>In short, it is such an admirable thing, that Mademoiselle Hortens can't forget it; but at meals for days afterwards, even among her countrywomen and others attached in like capacity to the troop of visitors, relapses into silent enjoyment of the joke&mdash;an enjoyment expressed, in her own convivial manner, by an additional tightness of<pb
n="112" id="p112"/>
face, thin elongation of compressed lips, and sidewise look: which intense appreciation of humour is frequently reflected in my Lady's mirrors, when my Lady is not among them.</p>
<p>All the mirrors in the house are brought into action now: many of them after a long blank. They reflect handsome faces, simpering faces, youthful faces, faces of threescore-and-ten that will not submit to be old; the entire collection of faces that have come to pass a January week or two at Chesney Wold, and which the fashionable intelligence, a mighty hunter before the Lord, hunts with a keen scent, from their breaking cover at the Court of Saint James's to their being run down to Death. The place in Lincolnshire is all alive. By day, guns and voices are heard ringing in the woods, horsemen and carriages enliven the parkroads, servants and hangers-on pervade the Village and the Dedlock Arms. Seen by night, from distant openings in the trees, the row of windows in the long drawing-room, where my Lady's picture hangs over the great chimney-piece, is like a row of jewels set in a black frame. On Sunday, the chill little church is almost warmed by so much gallant company, and the general flavor of the Dedlock dust is quenched in delicate perfumes.</p>
<p>The brilliant and distinguished circle comprehends within it, no contracted amount of education, sense, courage, honor, beauty, and virtue. Yet there is something a little wrong about it, in despite of its immense advantages. What can it be?</p>
<p>Dandyism? There is no King George the Fourth now (more's the pity!) to set the dandy fashion; there are no clear-starched jack-towel neckcloths, no short-waisted coats, no false calves, no stays. There are no caricatures, now, of effeminate Exquisites so arrayed, swooning in opera boxes with excess of delight, and being revived by other dainty creatures, poking long-necked scent-bottles at their noses. There is no beau whom it takes four men at once to shake into his buckskins, or who goes to see all the Executions, or who is troubled with the self-reproach of having once consumed a pea. But is there Dandyism in the brilliant and distinguished circle notwithstanding, Dandyism of a more mischievous sort, that has got below the surface and is doing less harmless things than jack-towelling itself and stopping its own digestion, to which no rational person need particularly object?</p>
<p>Why, yes. It cannot be disguised. There <hi rend="italics">are,</hi> at Chesney Wold this January week, some ladies and gentlemen of the newest fashion, who have set up a Dandyism&mdash;in Religion, for instance. Who, in mere lackadaisical want of an emotion, have agreed upon a little dandy talk about the Vulgar wanting faith in things in general; meaning, in the things that have been tried and found wanting, as though a low fellow should unaccountably lose faith in a bad shilling, after finding it out! Who would make the Vulgar very picturesque and faithful, by putting back the hands upon the Clock of Time, and cancelling a few hundred years of history.</p>
<p>There are also ladies and gentlemen of another fashion, not so new, but very elegant, who have agreed to put a smooth glaze on the world, and to keep down all its realities. For whom everything must be languid and pretty. Who have found out the perpetual stoppage. Who are to rejoice at nothing, and be sorry for nothing. Who are not to be disturbed by ideas. On whom even the Fine Arts, attending in powder
<pb n="113" id="p113"/>
and walking backward like the Lord Chamberlain, must array themselves in the milliners' and tailors' patterns of past generations, and be particularly careful not to be in earnest, or to receive any impress from the moving age.</p>
<p>Then there is my Lord Boodle, of considerable reputation with his party, who has known what office is, and who tells Sir Leicester Dedlock with much gravity, after dinner, that he really does not see to what the present age is tending. A debate is not what a debate used to be; the House is not what the House used to be; even a Cabinet is not what it formerly was. He perceives with astonishment, that supposing the present Government to be overthrown, the limited choice of the Crown, in the formation of a new Ministry, would lie between Lord Coodle and Sir Thomas Doodle&mdash;supposing it to be impossible for the Duke of Foodle to act with Goodle, which may be assumed to be the case in consequence of the breach arising out of that affair with Hoodle. Then, giving the Home Department and the Leadership of the House of Commons to Joodle, the Exchequer to Koodle, the Colonies to Loodle, and the Foreign Office to Moodle, what are you to do with Noodle? You can't offer him the Presidency of the Council; that is reserved for Poodle. You can't put him in the Woods and Forests; that is hardly good enough for Quoodle. What follows? That the country is shipwrecked, lost, and gone to pieces (as is made manifest to the patriotism of Sir Leicester Dedlock), because you can't provide for Noodle!</p>
<p>On the other hand, the Right Honorable William Buffy, M.P., contends across the table with some one else, that the shipwreck of the country&mdash;about which there is no doubt; it is only the manner of it that is in question&mdash;is attributable to Cuffy. If you had done with Cuffy what you ought to have done when he first came into Parliament, and had prevented him from going over to Duffy, you would have got him into alliance with Fuffy, you would have had with you the weight attaching as a smart debater to Guffy, you would have brought to bear upon the elections the wealth of Huffy, you would have got in for three counties Juffy, Kuffy, and Luffy; and you would have strengthened your administration by the official knowledge and the business habits of Muffy. All this, instead of being, as you now are, dependent on the mere caprice of Puffy!</p>
<p>As to this point, and as to some minor topics, there are differences of opinion; but it is perfectly clear to the brilliant and distinguished circle, all round, that nobody is in question but Boodle and his retinue, and Buffy and <hi rend="italics">his</hi> retinue. These are the great actors for whom the stage is reserved. A People there are, no doubt&mdash;a certain large number of supernumeraries, who are to be occasionally addressed, and relied upon for shouts and choruses, as on the theatrical stage; but Boodle and Buffy, their followers and families, their heirs, executors, administrators, and assigns, are the born first-actors, managers, and leaders, and no others can appear upon the scene for ever and ever.</p>
<p>In this, too, there is perhaps more dandyism at Chesney Wold than the brilliant and distinguished circle will find good for itself in the long run. For it is, even with the stillest and politest circles, as with the circle the necromancer draws around him&mdash;very strange appearances may be seen in active motion outside. With this difference; that, being realities and not phantoms, there is the greater danger of their breaking in.</p>
<pb n="114" id="p114"/>
<p>Chesney Wold is quite full, anyhow; so full, that a burning sense of injury arises in the breasts of ill-lodged ladies' maids, and is not to be extinguished. Only one room is empty. It is a turret chamber of the third order of merit, plainly but comfortably furnished, and having an old-fashioned business air. It is Mr. Tulkinghorn's room, and is never bestowed on anybody else, for he may come at any time. He is not come yet. It is his quiet habit to walk across the park from the village, in fine weather; to drop into this room, as if he had never been out of it since he was last seen there; to request a servant to inform Sir Leicester that he is arrived, in case he should be wanted; and to appear ten minutes before dinner, in the shadow of the library door. He sleeps in his turret, with a complaining flag-staff over his head; and has some leads outside, on which, any fine morning when he is down here, his black figure may be seen walking before breakfast like a larger species of rook.</p>
<p>Every day before dinner, my Lady looks for him in the dusk of the library, but he is not there. Every day at dinner, my Lady glances down the table for the vacant place, that would be waiting to receive him if he had just arrived; but there is no vacant place. Every night, my Lady casually asks her maid:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is Mr Tulkinghorn come?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Every night the answer is, &ldquo;No, my Lady, not yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One night, while having her hair undressed, my Lady loses herself in deep thought after this reply, until she sees her own brooding face in the opposite glass, and a pair of black eyes curiously observing her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Be so good as to attend,&rdquo; says my Lady then, addressing the reflection of Hortense, &ldquo;to your business. You can contemplate your beauty at another time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pardon! It was your Ladyship's beauty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That,&rdquo; says my Lady, &ldquo;you needn't contemplate at all.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At length, one afternoon a little before sunset, when the bright groups of figures, which have for the last hour or two enlivened the Ghost's Walk, are all dispersed, and only Sir Leicester and my Lady remain upon the terrace, Mr. Tulkinghorn appears. He comes towards them at his usual methodical pace, which is never quickened, never slackened. He wears his usual expressionless mask&mdash;if it be a mask&mdash;and carries family secrets in every limb of his body, and every crease of his dress. Whether his whole soul is devoted to the great, or whether he yields them nothing beyond the services he sells, is his personal secret. He keeps it, as he keeps the secrets of his clients; he is his own client in that matter, and will never betray himself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do you do, Mr. Tulkinghorn?&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, giving him his hand.</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn is quite well. Sir Leicester is quite well. My Lady is quite well. All highly satisfactory. The lawyer, with his hands behind him, walks, at Sir Leicester's side, along the terrace. My Lady walks upon the other side.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We expected you before,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester. A gracious observation. As much as to say, &ldquo;Mr. Tulkinghorn, we remember your existence when you are not here to remind us of it by your presence. We bestow a fragment of our minds upon you, sir, you see!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="115" id="p115"/>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn, comprehending it, inclines his head, and says he is much obliged.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should have come down sooner,&rdquo; he explains, &ldquo;but that I have been much engaged with those matters in the several suits between yourself and Boythorn.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A man of a very ill-regulated mind,&rdquo; observes Sir Leicester, with severity. &ldquo;An extremely dangerous person in any community. A man of a very low character of mind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is obstinate,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is natural to such a man to be so,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, looking most profoundly obstinate himself. &ldquo;I am not at all surprised to hear it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The only question is,&rdquo; pursues the lawyer, &ldquo;whether you will give up anything.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, sir,&rdquo; replies Sir Leicester. &ldquo;Nothing. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> give up?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't mean anything of importance. That, of course, I know you would not abandon. I mean any minor point.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Tulkinghorn,&rdquo; returns Sir Leicester, &ldquo;there can be no minor point between myself and Mr. Boythorn. If I go farther, and observe that I cannot readily conceive how <hi rend="italics">any</hi> right of mine can be a minor point, I speak not so much in reference to myself as an individual, as in reference to the family position I have it in charge to maintain.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn inclines his head again. &ldquo;I have now my instructions,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;Mr. Boythorn will give us a good deal of trouble&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is the character of such a mind, Mr. Tulkinghorn,&rdquo; Sir Leicester interrupts him, &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">to</hi> give trouble. An exceedingly ill-conditioned, levelling person. A person who, fifty years ago, would probably have been tried at the Old Bailey for some demagogue proceeding, and severely punished&mdash;if not,&rdquo; adds Sir Leicester, after a moment's pause, &ldquo;if not hanged, drawn, and quartered.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester appears to discharge his stately breast of a burden, in passing this capital sentence; as if it were the next satisfactory thing to having the sentence executed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But night is coming on,&rdquo; says he, &ldquo;and my Lady will take cold. My dear, let us go in.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As they turn towards the hall-door, Lady Dedlock addresses Mr. Tulkinghorn for the first time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You sent me a message respecting the person whose writing I happened to inquire about. It was like you to remember the circumstance; I had quite forgotten it. Your message reminded me of it again. I can't imagine what association I had, with a hand like that; but I surely had some.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You had some?&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn repeats.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O yes!&rdquo; returns my Lady, carelessly. &ldquo;I think I must have had some. And did you really take the trouble to find out the writer of that actual thing&mdash;what is it!&mdash;Affidavit?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How very odd!&rdquo;</p>
<p>They pass into a sombre breakfast-room on the ground-floor, lighted in the day by two deep windows. It is now twilight. The fire glows brightly on the panelled wall, and palely on the window-glass, where,
<pb n="116" id="p116"/>
through the cold reflection of the blaze, the colder landscape shudders in the wind, and a grey mist creeps along: the only traveller besides the waste of clouds.</p>
<p>My Lady lounges in a great chair in the chimney-corner, and Sir Leicester takes another great chair opposite. The lawyer stands before the fire, with his hand out at arm's length, shading his face. He looks across his arm at my Lady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; he says, &ldquo;I inquired about the man, and found him. And, what is very strange, I found him&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not to be any out-of-the-way person, I am afraid!&rdquo; Lady Dedlock languidly anticipates.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I found him dead.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O dear me!&rdquo; remonstrated Sir Leicester. Not so much shocked by the fact, as by the fact of the fact being mentioned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was directed to his lodging&mdash;a miserable, poverty-stricken place&mdash;and I found him dead.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will excuse me, Mr. Tulkinghorn,&rdquo; observes Sir Leicester. &ldquo;I think the less said&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray, Sir Leicester, let me hear the story out;&rdquo; (it is my Lady speaking). &ldquo;It is quite a story for twilight. How very shocking! Dead?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn re-asserts it by another inclination of his head. &ldquo;Whether by his own hand&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Upon my honor!&rdquo; cries Sir Leicester. &ldquo;Really!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do let me hear the story!&rdquo; says my Lady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Whatever you desire, my dear. But, I must say&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, you mustn't say! Go on, Mr. Tulkinghorn.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester's gallantry concedes the point; though he still feels that to bring this sort of squalor among the upper classes is really&mdash;really&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was about to say,&rdquo; resumes the lawyer, with undisturbed calmness, &ldquo;that whether he had died by his own hand or not, it was beyond my power to tell you. I should amend that phrase, however, by saying that he had unquestionably died of his own act; though whether by his own deliberate intention, or by mischance, can never certainly be known. The coroner's jury found that he took the poison accidentally.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what kind of man,&rdquo; my Lady asks, &ldquo;was this deplorable creature?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very difficult to say,&rdquo; returns the lawyer, shaking his head. &ldquo;He had lived so wretchedly, and was so neglected, with his gipsy color, and his wild black hair and beard, that I should have considered him the commonest of the common. The surgeon had a notion that he had once been something better, both in appearance and condition.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What did they call the wretched being?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They called him what he had called himself, but no one knew his name.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not even any one who had attended on him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No one had attended on him. He was found dead. In fact, I found him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Without any clue to anything more?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Without any; there was,&rdquo; says the lawyer, meditatively, &ldquo;an old portmanteau; but&mdash;No, there were no papers.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="117" id="p117"/>
<p>During the utterance of every word of this short dialogue, Lady Dedlock and Mr. Tulkinghorn, without any other alteration in their customary deportment, have looked very steadily at one another&mdash;as was natural, perhaps, in the discussion of so unusual a subject. Sir Leicester has looked at the fire, with the general expression of the Dedlock on the staircase. The story being told, he renews his stately protest, saying, that as it is quite clear that no association in my Lady's mind can possibly be traceable to this poor wretch (unless he was a begging-letter writer), he trusts to hear no more about a subject so far removed from my Lady's station.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly, a collection of horrors,&rdquo; says my Lady, gathering up her mantles and furs; &ldquo;but they interest one for the moment! Have the kindness, Mr. Tulkinghorn, to open the door for me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn does so with deference, and holds it open while she passes out. She passes close to him, with her usual fatigued manner, and insolent grace. They meet again at dinner&mdash;again, next day&mdash;again, for many days in succession. Lady Dedlock is always the same exhausted deity, surrounded by worshippers, and terribly liable to be bored to death, even while presiding at her own shrine. Mr. Tulkinghorn is always the same speechless repository of noble confidences: so oddly out of place, and yet so perfectly at home. They appear to take as little note of one another, as any two people, enclosed within the same walls, could. But, whether each evermore watches and suspects the other, evermore mistrustful of some great reservation; whether each is evermore prepared at all points for the other, and never to be taken unawares; what each would give to know how much the other knows&mdash;all this is hidden, for the time, in their own hearts.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XIII. <lb/> ESTHER'S NARRATIVE.</head>
<p>WE held many consultations about what Richard was to be; first, without Mr. Jarndyce, as he had requested, and afterwards with him; but it was a long time before we seemed to make progress. Richard said he was ready for anything. When Mr. Jarndyce doubted whether he might not already be too old to enter the Navy, Richard said he had thought of that, and perhaps he was. When Mr. Jarndyce asked him what he thought of the Army, Richard said he had thought of that, too, and it wasn't a bad idea. When Mr. Jarndyce advised him to try and decide within himself, whether his old preference for the sea was an ordinary boyish inclination, or a strong impulse, Richard answered, Well, he really <hi rend="italics">had</hi> tried very often, and he couldn't make out.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How much of this indecision of character,&rdquo; Mr. Jarndyce said to me &ldquo;is chargeable on that incomprehensible heap of uncertainty and procrastination on which he has been thrown from his birth, I don't pretend to say; but that Chancery, among its other sins, is responsible for some of
<pb n="118" id="p118"/>
it, I can plainly see. It has engendered or confirmed in him a habit of putting off&mdash;and trusting to this, that, and the other chance, without knowing what chance&mdash;and dismissing everything as unsettled, uncertain, and confused. The character of much older and steadier people may be even changed by the circumstances surrounding them. It would be too much to expect that a boy's, in its formation, should be the subject of such influences, and escape them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I felt this to be true; though, if I may venture to mention what I thought besides, I thought it much to be regretted that Richard's education had not counteracted those influences, or directed his character. He had been eight years at a public school, and had learnt, I understood, to make Latin Verses of several sorts, in the most admirable manner. But I never heard that it had been anybody's business to find out what his natural bent was, or where his failings lay, or to adapt any kind of knowledge to <hi rend="italics">him. He</hi> had been adapted to the Verses, and had learnt the art of making them to such perfection, that if he had remained at school until he was of age, I suppose he could only have gone on making them over and over again, unless he had enlarged his education by forgetting how to do it. Still, although I had no doubt that they were very beautiful, and very improving, and very sufficient for a great many purposes of life, and always remembered all through life, I did doubt whether Richard would not have profited by some one studying him a little, instead of his studying them quite so much.</p>
<p>To be sure, I knew nothing of the subject, and do not even now know whether the young gentlemen of classic Rome or Greece made verses to the same extent&mdash;or whether the young gentlemen of any country ever did.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I haven't the least idea,&rdquo; said Richard, musing, &ldquo;what I had better be. Except that I am quite sure I don't want to go into the Church, it's a toss-up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have no inclination in Mr. Kenge's way?&rdquo; suggested Mr. Jarndyce.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know that, sir!&rdquo; replied Richard. &ldquo;I am fond of boating. Articled clerks go a good deal on the water. It's a capital profession!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Surgeon&mdash;&rdquo; suggested Mr. Jarndyce.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the thing, sir!&rdquo; cried Richard.</p>
<p>I doubt if he had ever once thought of it before.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the thing, sir!&rdquo; repeated Richard, with the greatest enthusiasm. &ldquo;We have got it at last. M.R.C.S.!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was not to be laughed out of it, though he laughed at it heartily. He said he had chosen his profession, and the more he thought of it, the more he felt that his destiny was clear; the art of healing was the art of all others for him. Mistrusting that he only came to this conclusion, because having never had much chance of finding out for himself what he was fitted for, and having never been guided to the discovery, he was taken by the newest idea, and was glad to get rid of the trouble of consideration, I wondered whether the Latin Verses often ended in this, or whether Richard's was a solitary case.</p>
<p>Mr. Jarndyce took great pains to talk with him, seriously, and to put
<pb n="119" id="p119"/>
it to his good sense not to deceive himself in so important a matter. Richard was a little grave after these interviews; but invariably told Ada and me &ldquo;that it was all right,&rdquo; and then began to talk about something else.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By Heaven!&rdquo; cried Mr. Boythorn, who interested himself strongly in the subject&mdash;though I need not say that, for he could do nothing weakly; &ldquo;I rejoice to find a young gentleman of spirit and gallantry devoting himself to that noble profession! The more spirit there is in it, the better for mankind, and the worse for those mercenary taskmasters and low tricksters who delight in putting that illustrious art at a disadvantage in the world. By all that is base and despicable,&rdquo; cried Mr. Boythorn, &ldquo;the treatment of Surgeons aboard ship is such, that I would submit the legs&mdash;both legs&mdash;of every member of the Admiralty Board to a compound fracture, and render it a transportable offence in any qualified practitioner to set them, if the system were not wholly changed in eight-and-forty hours!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wouldn't you give them a week?&rdquo; asked Mr. Jarndyce.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No!&rdquo; cried Mr. Boythorn, firmly. &ldquo;Not on any consideration! Eight-and-forty hours! As to Corporations, Parishes, Vestry-Boards, and similar gatherings of jolter-headed clods, who assemble to exchange such speeches that, by Heaven! they ought to be worked in quicksilver mines for the short remainder of their miserable existence, if it were only to prevent their <sic
corr="detestable">destestable</sic> English from contaminating a language spoken in the presence of the Sun&mdash;as to those fellows, who meanly take advantage of the ardor of gentlemen in the pursuit of knowledge, to recompense the inestimable services of the best years of their lives, their long study, and their expensive education, with pittances too small for the acceptance of clerks, I would have the necks of every one of them wrung, and their skulls arranged in Surgeons' Hall for the contemplation of the whole profession&mdash;in order that its younger members might understand from actual measurement, in early life, <hi rend="italics">how</hi> thick skulls may become!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He wound up this vehement declaration by looking round upon us with a most agreeable smile, and suddenly thundering, Ha, ha, ha! over and over again, until anybody else might have been expected to be quite subdued by the exertion.</p>
<p>As Richard still continued to say that he was fixed in his choice, after repeated periods for consideration had been recommended by Mr. Jarndyce, and had expired; and as he still continued to assure Ada and me, in the same final manner, that it was &ldquo;all right;&rdquo; it became advisable to take Mr. Kenge into council. Mr. Kenge, therefore, came down to dinner one day, and leaned back in his chair, and turned his eye-glasses over and over, and spoke in a sonorous voice, and did exactly what I remembered to have seen him do when I was a little girl.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; said Mr. Kenge. &ldquo;Yes. Well! A very good profession, Mr. Jarndyce; a very good profession.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The course of study and preparation requires to be diligently pursued,&rdquo; observed my Guardian, with a glance at Richard.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O, no doubt,&rdquo; said Mr. Kenge. &ldquo;Diligently.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But that being the case, more or less, with all pursuits that are
<pb n="120" id="p120"/>
worth much,&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce, &ldquo;it is not a special consideration which another choice would be likely to escape.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Truly,&rdquo; said Mr. Kenge. &ldquo;And Mr. Richard Carstone, who has so meritoriously acquitted himself in the&mdash;shall I say the classic shades?&mdash;in which his youth had been passed, will, no doubt, apply the habits, if not the principles and practice, of versification in that tongue in which a poet was said (unless I mistake) to be born, not made, to the more eminently practical field of action on which he enters.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may rely upon it,&rdquo; said Richard, in his off-hand manner, &ldquo;that I shall go at it, and do my best.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very well, Mr. Jarndyce!&rdquo; said Mr. Kenge, gently nodding his head. &ldquo;Really, when we are assured by Mr. Richard that he means to go at it, and to do his best,&rdquo; nodding feelingly and smoothly over those expressions; &ldquo;I would submit to you, that we have only to inquire into the best mode of carrying out the object of his ambition. Now, with reference to placing Mr. Richard with some sufficiently eminent practitioner. Is there any one in view at present?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No one, Rick, I think?&rdquo; said my Guardian.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No one, sir,&rdquo; said Richard,</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite so!&rdquo; observed Mr. Kenge. &ldquo;As to situation, now. Is there any particular feeling on that head?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;N&mdash;no,&rdquo; said Richard.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite so!&rdquo; observed Mr. Kenge again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should like a little variety,&rdquo; said Richard; &ldquo;&mdash;I mean a good range of experience.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very requisite, no doubt,&rdquo; returned Mr. Kenge. &ldquo;I think this may be easily arranged, Mr. Jarndyce? We have only, in the first place, to discover a sufficiently eligible practitioner; and, as soon as we make our want&mdash;and, shall I add, our ability to pay a premium?&mdash;know, our only difficulty will be in the selection of one from a large number. We have only, in the second place, to observe those little formalities which are rendered necessary by our time of life, and our being under the guardianship of the Court. We shall soon be&mdash;shall I say, in Mr. Richard's own light-hearted manner, &lsquo;going at it&rsquo;&mdash;to our heart's content. It is a coincidence,&rdquo; said Mr. Kenge, with a tinge of melancholy in his smile, &ldquo;one of those coincidences which may or may not require an explanation beyond our present limited faculties, that I have a cousin in the medical profession. He might be deemed eligible by you, and might be disposed to respond to this proposal. I can answer for him as little as for you; but he <hi rend="italics">might!</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>As this was an opening in the prospect, it was arranged that Mr. Kenge should see his cousin. And as Mr. Jarndyce had before proposed to take us to London for a few weeks, it was settled next day that we should make our visit at once, and combine Richard's business with it.</p>
<p>Mr. Boythorn leaving us within a week, we took up our abode at a cheerful lodging near Oxford Street, over an upholsterer's shop. London was a great wonder to us, and we were out for hours and hours at a time, seeing the sights; which appeared to be less capable of exhaustion than we were. We made the round of the principal theatres, too, with great
<pb n="121" id="p121"/>
delight, and saw all the plays that were worth seeing. I mention this, because it was at the theatre that I began to be made uncomfortable again, by Mr. Guppy.</p>
<p>I was sitting in front of the box one night with Ada; and Richard was in the place he liked best, behind Ada's chair; when, happening to look down into the pit, I saw Mr. Guppy, with his hair flattened down upon his head, and woe depicted in his face, looking up at me. I felt, all through the performance, that he never looked at the actors, but constantly looked at me, and always with a carefully prepared expression of the deepest misery and the profoundest dejection.</p>
<p>It quite spoiled my pleasure for that night, because it was so very embarrassing and so very ridiculous. But, from that time forth, we never went to the play, without my seeing Mr. Guppy in the pit&mdash;always with his hair straight and flat, his shirt-collar turned down, and a general feebleness about him. If he were not there when we went in, and I began to hope he would not come, and yielded myself for a little while to the interest of the scene, I was certain to encounter his languishing eyes when I least expected it, and, from that time, to be quite sure that they were fixed upon me all the evening.</p>
<p>I really cannot express how uneasy this made me. If he would only have brushed up his hair, or turned up his collar, it would have been bad enough; but to know that that absurd figure was always gazing at me, and always in that demonstrative state of despondency, put such a constraint upon me that I did not like to laugh at the play, or to cry at it, or to move, or to speak. I seemed able to do nothing naturally. As to escaping Mr. Guppy by going to the back of the box, I could not bear to do that; because I knew Richard and Ada relied on having me next them, and that they could never have talked together so happily if any body else had been in my place. So there I sat, not knowing where to look&mdash;for wherever I looked, I knew Mr. Guppy's eyes were following me&mdash;and thinking of the dreadful expense to which this young man was putting himself, on my account.</p>
<p>Sometimes I thought of telling Mr. Jarndyce. Then I feared that the young man would lose his situation, and that I might ruin him. Sometimes, I thought of confiding in Richard; but was deterred by the possibility of his fighting Mr. Guppy, and giving him black eyes. Sometimes, I thought, should I frown at him, or shake my head. Then I felt I could not do it. Sometimes, I considered whether I should write to his mother, but that ended in my being convinced that to open a correspondence would be to make the matter worse. I always came to the conclusion, finally, that I could do nothing. Mr. Guppy's perseverance, all this time, not only produced him regularly at any theatre to which we went, but caused him to appear in the crowd as we were coming out, and even to get up behind our fly&mdash;where I am sure I saw him, two or three times, struggling among the most dreadful spikes. After we got home, he haunted a post opposite our house. The upholsterer's where we lodged, being at the corner of two streets, and my bedroom window being opposite the post, I was afraid to go near the window when I went upstairs, lest I should see him (as I did one moonlight night) leaning against the post, and evidently catching cold. If Mr. Guppy had not been,
<pb n="122" id="p122"/>
fortunately for me, engaged in the day-time, I really should have had no rest from him.</p>
<p>While we were making this round of gaieties in which Mr. Guppy so extraordinarily participated, the business which had helped to bring us to town was not neglected. Mr. Kenge's cousin was a Mr. Bayham Badger, who had a good practice at Chelsea, and attended a large public Institution besides. He was quite willing to receive Richard into his house, and to superintend his studies; and as it seemed that those could be pursued advantageously under Mr. Badger's roof, and as Mr. Badger liked Richard, and as Richard said he liked Mr. Badger &ldquo;well enough,&rdquo; an agreement was made, the Lord Chancellor's consent was obtained, and it was all settled.</p>
<p>On the day when matters were concluded between Richard and Mr. Badger, we were all under engagement to dine at Mr. Badger's house. We were to be &ldquo;merely a family party,&rdquo; Mrs. Badger's note said; and we found no lady there but Mrs. Badger herself. She was surrounded in the drawing-room by various objects, indicative of her painting a little, playing the piano a little, playing the guitar a little, playing the harp a little, singing a little, working a little, reading a little, writing poetry a little, and botanising a little. She was a lady of about fifty, I should think, youthfully dressed, and of a very fine complexion. If I add, to the little list of her accomplishments, that she rouged a little, I do not mean that there was any harm in it.</p>
<p>Mr. Bayham Badger himself was a pink, fresh-faced, crisp-looking gentleman, with a weak voice, white teeth, light hair, and surprised eyes: some years younger, I should say, than Mrs. Bayham Badger. He admired her exceedingly, but principally, and to begin with, on the curious ground (as it seemed to us) of her having had three husbands. We had barely taken our seats, when he said to Mr. Jarndyce quite triumphantly,</p>
<p>&ldquo;You would hardly suppose that I am Mrs. Bayham Badger's third!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed?&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Her third!&rdquo; said Mr. Badger. &ldquo;Mrs. Bayham Badger has not the appearance, Miss Summerson, of a lady who has had two former husbands?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I said &ldquo;Not at all!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And most remarkable men!&rdquo; said Mr. Badger, in a tone of confidence. &ldquo;Captain Swosser of the Royal Navy, who was Mrs. Badger's first husband, was a very distinguished officer indeed. The name of Professor Dingo, my immediate predecessor, is one of European reputation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Badger overheard him, and smiled.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my dear!&rdquo; Mr. Badger replied to the smile, &ldquo;I was observing to Mr. Jarndyce and Miss Summerson, that you had had two former husbands&mdash;both very distinguished men. And they found it, as people generally do, difficult to believe.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was barely twenty,&rdquo; said Mrs. Badger, &ldquo;when I married Captain Swosser of the Royal Navy. I was in the Mediterranean with him; I am quite a Sailor. On the twelfth anniversary of my wedding-day, I became the wife of Professor Dingo.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(&ldquo;Of European reputation,&rdquo; added Mr. Badger in an under tone.)</p>
<pb n="123" id="p123"/>
<p>&ldquo;And when Mr. Badger and myself were married,&rdquo; pursued Mrs. Badger, &ldquo;we were married on the same day of the year. I had become attached to the day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So that Mrs. Badger has been married to three husbands&mdash;two of them highly distinguished men,&rdquo; said Mr. Badger, summing up the facts; &ldquo;and, each time, upon the twenty-first of March at Eleven in the forenoon!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We all expressed our admiration.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But for Mr. Badger's modesty,&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce, &ldquo;I would take leave to correct him, and say three distinguished men.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank you, Mr. Jarndyce! What I always tell him!&rdquo; observed Mrs. Badger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And, my dear,&rdquo; said Mr. Badger, &ldquo;what do <hi rend="italics">I</hi> always tell you? That without any affectation of disparaging such professional distinction as I may have attained (which our friend Mr. Carstone will have many opportunities of estimating), I am not so weak&mdash;no, really,&rdquo; said Mr. Badger to us generally, &ldquo;so unreasonable&mdash;as to put my reputation on the same footing with such first-rate men as Captain Swosser and Professor Dingo. Perhaps you may be interested, Mr. Jarndyce,&rdquo; continued Mr. Bayham Badger, leading the way into the next drawing-room, &ldquo;in this portrait of Captain Swosser. It was taken on his return home from the African Station, where he had suffered from the fever of the country. Mrs. Badger considers it too yellow. But it's a very fine head. A very fine head!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We all echoed &ldquo;A very fine head!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I feel when I look at it,&rdquo; said Mr. Badger, &ldquo; &lsquo;that's a man I should like to have seen!&rsquo; It strikingly bespeaks the first-class man that Captain Swosser pre-eminently was. On the other side, Professor Dingo. I knew him well&mdash;attended him in his last illness&mdash;a speaking likeness! Over the piano, Mrs. Bayham Badger when Mrs. Swosser. Over the sofa, Mrs. Bayham Badger when Mrs. Dingo. Of Mrs. Bayham Badger <hi rend="italics">in esse,</hi> I possess the original, and have no copy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dinner was now announced, and we went down stairs. It was a very genteel entertainment, very handsomely served. But the Captain and the Professor still ran in Mr. Badger's head, and, as Ada and I had the honour of being under his particular care, we had the full benefit of them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Water, Miss Summerson? Allow me! Not in that tumbler, pray. Bring me the Professor's goblet, James!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ada very much admired some artificial flowers, under a glass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Astonishing how they keep!&rdquo; said Mr. Badger. &ldquo;They were presented to Mrs. Bayham Badger when she was in the Mediterranean.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He invited Mr. Jarndyce to take a glass of claret.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not that claret!&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;Excuse me! This is an occasion, and <hi rend="italics">on</hi> an occasion I produce some very special claret I happen to have. (James, Captain Swosser's wine!) Mr. Jarndyce, this is a wine that was imported by the Captain, we will not say how many years ago. You will find it very curious. My dear, I shall be happy to take some of this wine with you. (Captain Swosser's claret to your mistress, James!) My love, your health!&rdquo;</p>
<p>After dinner, when we ladies retired, we took Mrs. Badger's first and
<pb n="124" id="p124"/>
second husband with us. Mrs. Badger gave us, in the drawing-room, a Biographical sketch of the life and services of Captain Swosser before his marriage, and a more minute account of him dating from the time when he fell in love with her, at a ball on board the Crippler, given to the officers of that ship when she lay in Plymouth Harbor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The dear old Crippler!&rdquo; said Mrs. Badger, shaking her head. &ldquo;She was a noble vessel. Trim, ship-shape, all a taunto, as Captain Swosser used to say. You must excuse me if I occasionally introduce a nautical expression; I was quite a sailor once. Captain Swosser loved that craft for my sake. When she was no longer in commission, he frequently said that if he were rich enough to buy her old hulk, he would have an inscription let into the timbers of the quarter-deck where we stood as partners in the dance, to mark the spot where he fell&mdash;raked fore and aft (Captain Swosser used to say) by the fire from my tops. It was his naval way of mentioning my eyes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Badger shook her head, sighed, and looked in the glass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was a great change from Captain Swosser to Professor Dingo,&rdquo; she resumed, with a plaintive smile. &ldquo;I felt it a good deal at first. Such an entire revolution in my mode of life! But custom, combined with science&mdash;particularly science&mdash;inured me to it. Being the Professor's sole companion in his botanical excursions, I almost forgot that I had ever been afloat, and became quite learned. It is singular that the Professor was the Antipodes of Captain Swosser, and that Mr. Badger is not in the least like either!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We then passed into a narrative of the deaths of Captain Swosser and Professor Dingo, both of whom seemed to have had very bad complaints. In the course of it, Mrs. Badger signified to us that she had never madly loved but once; and that the object of that wild affection, never to be recalled in its fresh enthusiasm, was Captain Swosser. The Professor was yet dying by inches in the most dismal manner, and Mrs. Badger was giving us imitations of his way of saying, with great difficulty, &ldquo;Where is Laura? Let Laura give me my toast and water!&rdquo; when the entrance of the gentlemen consigned him to the tomb.</p>
<p>Now, I observed that evening, as I had observed for some days past, that Ada and Richard were more than ever attached to each other's society; which was but natural, seeing that they were going to be separated so soon. I was therefore not very much surprised, when we got home, and Ada and I retired upstairs, to find Ada more silent than usual; though I was not quite prepared for her coming into my arms, and beginning to speak to me, with her face hidden.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My darling Esther!&rdquo; murmured Ada. &ldquo;I have a great secret to tell you!&rdquo;</p>
<p>A mighty secret, my pretty one, no doubt!</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is it, Ada?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O Esther, you would never guess!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Shall I try to guess?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O no! Don't! Pray, don't!&rdquo; cried Ada, very much startled by the idea of my doing so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I wonder who it can be about?&rdquo; said I, pretending to consider.</p>
<pb n="125" id="p125"/>
<p>&ldquo;It's about,&rdquo; said Ada, in a whisper. &ldquo;It's about&mdash;my cousin Richard!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my own!&rdquo; said I, kissing her bright hair, which was all I could see. &ldquo;And what about him?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O, Esther, you would never guess!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was so pretty to have her clinging to me in that way, hiding her face; and to know that she was not crying in sorrow, but in a little glow of joy, and pride, and hope; that I would not help her just yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He says&mdash;I know it's very foolish, we are both so young&mdash;but he says,&rdquo; with a burst of tears, &ldquo;that he loves me dearly, Esther.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does he indeed?&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I never heard of such a thing! Why, my pet of pets, I could have told you that, weeks and weeks ago!&rdquo;</p>
<p>To see Ada lift up her flushed face in joyful surprise, and hold me round the neck, and laugh, and cry, and blush, and laugh, was so pleasant!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, my darling!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;what a goose you must take me for! Your cousin Richard has been loving you as plainly as he could, for I don't know how long!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And yet you never said a word about it!&rdquo; cried Ada, kissing me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my love,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I waited to be told.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But now I have told you, you don't think it wrong of me; do you?&rdquo; returned Ada. She might have coaxed me to say No, if I had been the hardest-hearted Duenna in the world. Not being that yet, I said No, very freely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And now,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;I know the worst of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O, that's not quite the worst of it, Esther dear!&rdquo; cried Ada, holding me tighter, and laying down her face again upon my breast.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No?&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;Not even that?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, not even that!&rdquo; said Ada, shaking her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you never mean to say&mdash;!&rdquo; I was beginning in joke.</p>
<p>But Ada, looking up, and smiling through her tears, cried, &ldquo;Yes, I do! You know, you know I do!&rdquo; and then sobbed out, &ldquo;With all my heart I do! With all my whole heart, Esther!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I told her, laughing, why I had known that, too, just as well as I had known the other! And we sat before the fire, and I had all the talking to myself for a little while (though there was not much of it); and Ada was soon quiet and happy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you think my cousin John knows, dear Dame Durden?&rdquo; she asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Unless my cousin John is blind, my pet,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;I should think my cousin John knows pretty well as much as we know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We want to speak to him before Richard goes,&rdquo; said Ada, timidly, &ldquo;and we wanted you to advise us, and to tell him so. Perhaps you wouldn't mind Richard's coming in, Dame Durden?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O! Richard is outside, is he, my dear?&rdquo; said I.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am not quite certain,&rdquo; returned Ada, with a bashful simplicity that would have won my heart, if she had not won it long before; &ldquo;but I think he's waiting at the door.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There he was, of course. They brought a chair on either side of me,
<pb n="126" id="p126"/>
and put me between them, and really seemed to have fallen in love with me, instead of one another; they were so confiding, and so trustful, and so fond of me. They went on in their own wild way for a little while&mdash;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> never stopped them; I enjoyed it too much myself&mdash;and then we gradually fell to considering how young they were, and how there must be a lapse of several years before this early love could come to anything, and how it could come to happiness only if it were real and lasting, and inspired them with a steady resolution to do their duty to each other, with constancy, fortitude, and perseverance: each always for the other's sake. Well! Richard said that he would work his fingers to the bone for Ada, and Ada said that she would work her fingers to the bone for Richard, and they called me all sorts of endearing and sensible names, and we sat there, advising and talking, half the night. Finally, before we parted, I gave them my promise to speak to their cousin John to-morrow.</p>
<p>So, when to-morrow came, I went to my Guardian after breakfast, in the room that was our town-substitute for the Growlery, and told him that I had it in trust to tell him something.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, little woman,&rdquo; said he, shutting up his book, &ldquo;if you have accepted the trust, there can be no harm in it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope not, Guardian,&rdquo; said I. &ldquo;I can guarantee that there is no secresy in it. For it only happened yesterday.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye? And what is it, Esther?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Guardian,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;you remember the happy night when we first came down to Bleak House? When Ada was singing in the dark room?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I wished to recall to his remembrance the look he had given me then. Unless I am much mistaken, I saw that I did so.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because,&rdquo; said I, with a little hesitation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my dear!&rdquo; said he. &ldquo;Don't hurry.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;Ada and Richard have fallen in love. And have told each other so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Already?&rdquo; cried my Guardian, quite astonished.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes!&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;and to tell you the truth, Guardian, I rather expected it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The deuce you did!&rdquo; said he.</p>
<p>He sat considering for a minute or two; with his smile, at once so handsome and so kind, upon his changing face; and then requested me to let them know that he wished to see them. When they came, he encircled Ada with one arm, in his fatherly way, and addressed himself to Richard with a cheerful gravity.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rick,&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce, &ldquo;I am glad to have won your confidence. I hope to preserve it. When I contemplated these relations between us four which have so brightened my life, and so invested it with new interests and pleasures, I certainly did contemplate, afar off, the possibility of you and your pretty cousin here (don't be shy, Ada, don't be shy, my dear!) being in a mind to go through life together. I saw, and do see, many reasons to make it desirable. But that was afar off, Rick, afar off!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We look afar off, sir,&rdquo; returned Richard.</p>
<pb n="127" id="p127"/>
<p>&ldquo;Well!&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce. &ldquo;That's rational. Now, hear me, my dears! I might tell you that you don't know your own minds yet; that a thousand things may happen to divert you from one another; that it is well this chain of flowers you have taken up is very easily broken, or it might become a chain of lead. But I will not do that. Such wisdom will come soon enough, I dare say, if it is to come at all. I will assume that, a few years hence, you will be in your hearts to one another, what you are to-day. All I say before speaking to you according to that assumption is, if you <hi rend="italics">do</hi> change&mdash;if you <hi rend="italics">do</hi> come to find that you are more commonplace cousins to each other as man and woman, than you were as boy and girl (your manhood will excuse me, Rick!)&mdash;don't be ashamed still to confide in me, for there will be nothing monstrous or uncommon in it. I am only your friend and distant kinsman. I have no power over you whatever. But I wish and hope to retain your confidence, if I do nothing to forfeit it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am very sure, sir,&rdquo; returned Richard, &ldquo;that I speak for Ada, too, when I say that you have the strongest power over us both&mdash;rooted in respect, gratitude, and affection&mdash;strengthening every day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear cousin John,&rdquo; said Ada, on his shoulder, &ldquo;my father's place can never be empty again. All the love and duty I could ever have rendered to him, is transferred to you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come!&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce. &ldquo;Now for our assumption. Now we lift our eyes up, and look hopefully at the distance! Rick, the world is before you; and it is most probable that as you enter it, so it will receive you. Trust in nothing but in Providence and your own efforts. Never separate the two, like the heathen waggoner. Constancy in love is a good thing; but it means nothing, and is nothing, without constancy in every kind of effort. If you had the abilities of all the great men, past and present, you could do nothing well, without sincerely meaning it, and setting about it. If you entertain the supposition that any real success, in great things or in small, ever was or could be, ever will or can be, wrested from Fortune by fits and starts, leave that wrong idea here, or leave your cousin Ada here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I will leave <hi rend="italics">it</hi> here, sir,&rdquo; replied Richard, smiling, &ldquo;if I brought it here just now (but I hope I did not), and will work my way on to my cousin Ada in the hopeful distance.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Right!&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce. &ldquo;If you are not to make her happy, why should you pursue her?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wouldn't make her unhappy&mdash;no, not even for her love,&rdquo; retorted Richard, proudly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well said!&rdquo; cried Mr. Jarndyce; &ldquo;that's well said! She remains here, in her home with me. Love her, Rick, in your active life, no less than in her home when you revisit it, and all will go well. Otherwise, all will go ill. That's the end of my preaching. I think you and Ada had better take a walk.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ada tenderly embraced him, and Richard heartily shook hands with him, and then the cousins went out of the room&mdash;looking back again directly, though, to say that they would wait for me.</p>
<p>The door stood open, and we both followed them with our eyes, as they passed down the adjoining room on which the sun was shining, and
<pb n="128" id="p128"/>
out at its farther end. Richard with his head bent, and her hand drawn through his arm, was talking to her very earnestly; and she looked up in his face, listening, and seemed to see nothing else. So young, so beautiful, so full of hope and promise, they went on lightly through the sunlight, as their own happy thoughts might then be traversing the years to come, and making them all years of brightness. So they passed away into the shadow, and were gone. It was only a burst of light that had been so radiant. The room darkened as they went out, and the sun was clouded over.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Am I right, Esther?&rdquo; said my Guardian, when they were gone.</p>
<p>He who was so good and wise, to ask <hi rend="italics">me</hi> whether he was right!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rick may gain, out of this, the quality he wants. Wants, at the core of so much that is good!&rdquo; said Mr. Jarndyce, shaking his head. &ldquo;I have said nothing to Ada, Esther. She has her friend and counsellor always near.&rdquo; And he laid his hand lovingly upon my head.</p>
<p>I could not help shewing that I was a little moved, though I did all I could to conceal it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tut tut!&rdquo; said he. &ldquo;But we must take care, too, that our little woman's life is not all consumed in care for others.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Care? My dear Guardian, I believe I am the happiest creature in the world!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I believe so too,&rdquo; said he. &ldquo;But some one may find out, what Esther never will&mdash;that the little woman is to be held in remembrance above all other people!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have omitted to mention in its place, that there was some one else at the family dinner party. It was not a lady. It was a gentleman. It was a gentleman of a dark complexion&mdash;a young surgeon. He was rather reserved, but I thought him very sensible and agreeable. At least, Ada asked me if I did not, and I said yes.</p>
</div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1a" n="1"/>

<head>THE <lb/> BRITISH <lb/> JOURNAL.</head>
<p>Price SIXPENCE.</p>
<p>Published on the First of every Month, in a Wrapper designed by <lb/> GEORGE CRUIKSHANK.</p>
<p>THIS JOURNAL supplies the vacancy that has so long existed between our high and low priced Periodicals, and engages the highest Literary Talent to combine the best features of our established MAGAZINES with the simplicity and truthfulness of HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</p>
<p>ADMIRABLY ADAPTED TO RAILWAY READING.</p>
<p>Opinions of the Press.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;The British Journal.&rsquo; Should this cheap monthly issue continue the same character of papers, evidently written by <hi rend="italics">experienced and powerful hands,</hi> it must soon make VAST STRIDES IN PUBLIC FAVOUR. The articles are well selected, instructive, moral and pleasing, and, above all, not too long or too heavy for gratification and interest.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Court Journal.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Harry Coverdale's Courtship,&rsquo; by Frank Fairlegh, in the BRITISH JOURNAL, is a tale of high promise.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Advertiser.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;It is truly surprising that such an amount of excellent reading can be supplied for the small charge of SIXPENCE.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Glasgow Saturday Post.</hi></p>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>NOW READY.<lb/>VOLUME I. <lb/> OF THE <lb/> BRITISH JOURNAL,</head><p><hi rend="italics">Printed on a First-class Paper and handsomely Bound in</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Cloth and Gold,</hi>
<lb/> Price FOUR SHILLINGS.</p>
<p>Containing Original Papers by FRANCES BROWN, CALDER CAMPBELL, MARY COWDEN CLARKE, ALFRED W. COLE, MISS COSTELLO, FRANK FAIRLEGH, ANGUS B. REACH, CHARLES SWAIN, MISS WINNARD, and many other eminent Writers.</p>
<p>LONDON: AYLOTT &amp; JONES, PATERNOSTER ROW; <lb/> EDINBURGH: J. MENZIES. DUBLIN: J. McGLASHAN.</p>
<p>AND TO BE OBTAINED OF ALL BOOKSELLERS, AND AT THE RAILWAY STATIONS THROUGHOUT <lb/> THE KINGDOM.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p3a" n="3"/>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>WILL BE READY JULY 1, <lb/> THE MOST MAGNIFICENT AND SUPERBLY ILLUSTRATED VOLUME EVER <lb/> ISSUED FROM THE PRESS, <lb/> HANDSOMELY BOUND IN CLOTH, PRICE 6s. 6d.; EXTRA CLOTH, GILT EDGES, 7s. 6d., <lb/> THE FIRST VOLUME OF</opener>
<head>THE ILLUSTRATED EXHIBITOR <lb/> AND <lb/> MAGAZINE OF ART.</head>
<p>This Volume will be beautifully printed on 416 pages Imperial Octavo. It will contain upwards of Two HUNDRED Principal Engravings, and an equal number of Minor Engravings, Diagrams, &amp;c. The Literary matter is replete with interest, and the Engravings surpass everything of the class hitherto attempted in this country. Altogether, it will form one of the cheapest and most interesting Works ever published. Amongst the Engravings are the following:&mdash;</p>
<p>Portraits.&mdash;Her Majesty Queen Victoria, Prince Albert, the Prince of Wales, and the Princess Royal; Portraits of the Members of the First Magyar Ministry; the Right Hon. Baron Truro; Massaniello; the Duke de Brabant; Count de Flandre; Count de Paris; Duke de Chartres; M. Le Nain; Alof de Vignacourt; M. J. B. Oudry; J. M. W. Turner, R.A.; M. J. B. Chardin; M. Berzelius; J. J. Audubon; Benjamin West and Family; Sir David Wilkie; Mr. Layard; Winceslaus Hollar; James Taylor, of Birmingham; T. Wright, of Manchester.</p>
<p>Historical.&mdash;Landing of the Saxons in Britain; Henry III. and Simon de Montfort; Massaniello at the Head of the Populace; Queen Elizabeth Knighting Drake; Battle of Sempach; Layard's Discoveries at Nimroud; Elevation of an Ancient King; Ascent of Lunardi, &amp;c., in a Balloon, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Specimens from the Great Masters.&mdash;The Inundation, after Kiorbo&euml;; The Wooden Leg, by K. Girardet; The Pedlar, after Wilkie; The Vegetable Market. Metzu; Frozen Cascade of Giessbach; Wood-cutting in the Alps; The Family Repast, by Le Nain; The Young Sailor Puzzled, R. Jordan; The Course of Human Life, M. Bendemann; Ecce Homo, Titian; Fishing Vessels on the Doggerbank; View near Hampstead. Constable; The Young Messenger, Wilkie; Infancy, T. Johannot; Practical Charity, K. Girardet; Dog and Heron, M. Oudry; Flower Girl, Murillo; Disembarkment of Cleopatra, Claude; Kirkstall Abbey, Turner; Mouth of the Humber, ditto; Asking a Blessing, Chardin; The Laundress, ditto; Pegasus in Harness, 8 Engravings from Retsch; Landscape with Cattle, Paul Potter; Scene from Ben Jonson's Alchemist; Cookham, on the Thames, by Dodson; Cascade of Giessbach; Youth, T. Johannot; The Little Farmer, Loutherbourg; Rabbit on the Wall, Wilkie; Blind Fiddler, ditto; Morning, from Strada; Death and Resurrection, from Blake; Tintoret and his Daughter; The Country Doctor; The Casket, from Titian; Manhood and Old Age, T. Johannot, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Architecture.&mdash;Interior of the Chapel of Versailles; Gallery des Glaces, Versailles; Cathedral of Evreux; Bishop's Palace at Evreux; Castle of Segovia; Church of Notre Dame; Nuremberg; Winchester Congregational Chapel; Interior of ditto, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Views of Cities, Public Buildings, &amp;c.&mdash;M. Matifat's Stall in the Crystal Palace; Dover Castle; Fortress of Ham; Great Industrial Exhibition, New York; Hever Castle, Kent, 3 Engravings; Venice; Osborne, Isle of Wight; Kensington Palace; Carlsbad; Bridge of Ceret; Palaces in Spain; Grotto of St. Paul, Malta; Windsor Castle; Church at Bethlehem; Church of the Madeleine; the New House of Commone, Naples; Ascent and Descent of Mount Vesuvius, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Ornamental Sculpture.&mdash;Two Designs for Vases, by J. Lepautre; Trophy of Game; Oliver Twist, by Hughes; Vase, by M. Louis Lautz; England, a Group by Professor Fischer; Belgium and Nassau, ditto; Bas-reliefs at La Celle; Sculptures from Nineveh, 11 Engravings; Cup in Niello; Group in Silver, Turkish Coffee Pot, &amp;c.; Engraved Cup, by Hollar; Ceilings of the Church of Tilli&eacute;res, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Natural History.&mdash;Eggs of different Animals; The Apteryx; the Cassowary; Conchology, several Engravings; Fishes' Nests; Black-necked Swans; The Rhinoceros; Trees&mdash;Oak, Fir, Lime Tree, &amp;c., several Engravings; The Lyre Bird; Red-winged Thursh; Blue Jay of America; The Boa Constrictor, 2 Engravings; The Hippopotamus; Butterflies; Californian Gold, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Manufacturing Processes, &amp;c.&mdash;Gutta Percha; Wood Carving; Pellatt's Glass Works; Claussen's Flax Works; Railway Works; Iron Founding; Sugar Refining; Manufacture of Soap; Electro-plate Works; Oil Cloth Manufactory; Button-making, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Machinery and Inventions.&mdash;Micrometric Apparatus; Steam Engines: Photography; Printing Machine; Austrian Furniture; Glove-cutting Machine; Artificial Egg Hatching, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Ornamental Needlework.&mdash;Design for Note Book; Hand Screen; Lamp Mat; Lace Collars; Purses: Braces; Pardessus; Shoe; Toilet Sachet; Bertha; Crochet Counterpane; Music-stool Couvrette; Mandarin Sleeves; Blotting Case; Point Lace; Handkerchief Border; Embroidered Handkerchiefs; Chemisette; Urn Mat; Knitted Edging; Carriage Slipper; Winter Dress for a Child, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Scientific.&mdash;Kinematics; Elements of Design; Perspective; Hydrodynamics; Shadows; The Stereoscope; Hydraulics, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>Among the varied LITERARY ARTICLES will be found&mdash;Brief Memoirs of the Persons whose Portraits are given; interesting Descriptions of the Specimens of Art in Painting, Sculpture, &amp;c.; Details of Manufacturing Processes and Machinery; Papers on Natural History, Design, Perspective, Kinematics, The Stereoscope, &amp;c.; Historical Notices; Particulars respecting Public Edifices; Directions for executing the various branches of Needlework; and much interesting fragmentary matter. The whole presenting a Volume unique in character.</p>
<p>THE COMMENCEMENT OF A NEW VOLUME will afford a favourable opportunity to those Families and Individuals who have not yet obtained this Splendid Work. <hi rend="italics">The Illustrated Exhibitor and Magazine of Art</hi> is published in Weekly Numbers, Twopence each, or in Monthly Parts, 9d. or 11d. each, according to the number of weeks in each month.</p>
<p>JOHN CASSELL, 9, LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE HILL</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p4a" n="4"/>
<opener>THE EDUCATION OF FAMILIES <lb/> THROUGH THE MEDIUM OF</opener><head>&ldquo;THE POPULAR EDUCATOR.&rdquo;</head>
<p>IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT.</p>
<p>&ldquo;THE POPULAR EDUCATOR&rdquo; is intended to meet a want deeply felt&mdash;namely, a System of Universal Education&mdash;of Education <hi rend="italics">based upon sound principles, and obtainable by an expeditious method.</hi> The plan has met with decided approval, and the publication has already reached a circulation of nearly ONE HUNDRED THOUSAND. It has been found acceptable not only to the humbler classes, but to all ranks and conditions of persons who are desirous of attaining a sound education in French, Latin, German, Italian, Greek, and English Grammar; in Music; Mathematics, in all its branches; Geography, Geology, Physiology, Botany, Chemistry; History, Ancient and Modern; Biography, Natural History, &amp;c.</p>
<p>To meet the urgent wishes of numerous Families and Individuals, JOHN CASSELL has determined to publish <hi rend="italics">an Extra Edition</hi> upon superior paper: the price will be 1&frac12;d. per Number, or Monthly Parts, containing four Numbers in a neat Wrapper, 7d., or when five Numbers, 8&frac12;d. This Extra Edition will be published without the weekly headings. The FIRST PART is now ready, price 7d. Persons wishing to have this Superior Paper Edition must give their orders expressly for &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">the Extra Edition of the</hi> POPULAR EDUCATOR;&rdquo; they will otherwise receive the common edition, which is now being published in Weekly Numbers, price ONE PENNY each; or in Monthly Parts, price 5d., when four Numbers, or when five Numbers, 6d.&mdash;Orders may be sent to any Bookseller.</p>
<p>The following are the branches, Lessons in which are contained in the first two Monthly Parts already issued:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>ANCIENT HISTORY, with Engravings.</item>
<item>ENGLISH GRAMMAR.</item>
<item>MATHEMATICS.</item>
<item>ARITHMETIC.</item>
<item>GEOMETRY, with Engravings.</item>
<item>BIOGRAPHY.</item>
<item>BOTANY, with Engravings.</item>
<item>FRENCH.</item>
<item>LATIN.</item>
<item>PHYSIOLOGY, with Engravings.</item>
<item>MUSIC.</item>
<item>FEMALE EDUCATION.</item>
<item>Other Subjects will follow.</item>
</list>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>THE WORKING MAN'S FRIEND AND FAMILY INSTRUCTOR.</head>
<p>Now ready, price 3s. 6d., neatly bound in cloth, <lb/> VOLUME THE FIRST of the NEW SERIES of this highly-interesting Work, containing the <hi rend="italics">History of Hungary and its People,</hi> with upwards of Eighty Illustrative Engravings; <hi rend="italics">China and the Chinese,</hi> with Forty-six Illustrations; numerous Instructive Tales and Narratives; Biographies, with Portraits; Scientific and Miscellaneous Articles, several with Illustrations: containing altogether nearly TWO HUNDRED Pictorial Illustrations.</p>
<p>THE WORKING MAN'S FRIEND AND FAMILY INSTRUCTOR is published regularly in Weekly Numbers, <hi rend="italics">One Penny</hi> each, and in Monthly Parts, 5d. or 6d. each, according to the number of weeks in the month. Every Number contains several Illustrative Engravings,</p>
<p>A LIBRARY IN ITSELF?&mdash;THE WORKING MAN'S FRIEND AND FAMILY INSTRUCTOR, First Series, complete in Seven Volumes, price 1s. 6d. each, neatly bound. These Volumes contain a store of interesting and highly-instructive information, on all points in which the majority of the population of this country are concerned, such as is not to be found in any other publication,</p>
<p>Uniform with the above, THE LITERATURE OF WORKING MEN, with Introductory Essays, by BENJAMIN PARSONS and J. EWING RITCHIE. In Two Volumes, price 1s. 6d. each. These Volumes are devoted exclusively to the productions of Working Men. and have been spoken of in terms of admiration by several Members of Parliament, and a large portion of the Public Press.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>SCRIPTURE LIBRARY FOR THE YOUNG.</head>
<p>IN ONE SHILLING VOLUMES.</p>
<p>Now ready, in ornamental cover, embellished with beautiful Engravings, <lb/> THE HISTORY OF JOSEPH.</p>
<list>
<head>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS.</head>
<item>1. JOSEPH LET DOWN INTO THE PIT.</item>
<item>2. SOLD INTO SLAVERY.</item>
<item>3. IN PRISON.</item>
<item>4. INTERPRETING PHARAOH'S DREAMS.</item>
<item>5. JACOB SENDING HIS SONS FOR CORN.</item>
<item>6. SONS OF JACOB DETAINED IN EGYPT.</item>
<item>7. CUP FOUND IN BENJAMIN'S SACK.</item>
<item>8. JOSEPH MAKES HIMSELF KNOWN TO HIS BRETHREN.</item>
<item>9. MEETING OF JACOB AND JOSEPH.</item>
<item>10. JOSEPH AND HIS BRETHREN. With Illustrative Maps and other Engravings.</item>
</list>
<p>Also ready, <lb/> THE TABERNACLE: ITS PRIESTS AND ITS SERVICES.</p>
<list>
<head>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS.</head>
<item>1. REARING OF THE TABERNACLE.</item>
<item>2. MOUNT SINAI.</item>
<item>3. ALTAR OF BURNT OFFERING.</item>
<item>4. BRAZEN LAVER.</item>
<item>5. THE GOLDEN CANDLESTICK.</item>
<item>6. THE TABLE OF SHEWBREAD.</item>
<item>7. ALTAR OF INCENSE.</item>
<item>8. HIGH PRIEST IN THE TABERNACLE.</item>
<item>9. PRIESTS.</item>
<item>10. LEVITES.</item>
<item>11. NADAB AND ABIHU.</item>
<item>12. FEAST OF TABERNACLES.</item>
</list>
<p>JOHN CASSELL, 9, LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE HILL.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p5a" n="5"/>
<head>JOHN CASSELL'S LIBRARY, COMPLETE.</head>
<p>This Series consists of TWENTY-FIVE MONTHLY VOLUMES, 7d. each, in Paper Covers; or the whole bound in cloth, forming the complete Library, 19s.; or arranged in a Library Box, 25s. The Works may be had separately, as follows:&mdash;</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>Historical Works.</head>
<p>THE HISTORY OF ENGLAND.&mdash;BY ROBERT FERGUSON, LL.D.</p>
<p>In Four Volumes, 7d. each, or in Two Double Volumes, neatly bound in cloth, 1s. 6d. each; or the whole <lb/> bound together in One Thick Volume, 3s., or on fine paper, with Portrait of the Author, 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>THE HISTORY OF SCOTLAND.&mdash;BY ROBERT FERGUSON, LL.D.</p>
<p>In Two Volumes, 7d. each, or One Double Volume, neatly bound in cloth, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>THE HISTORY OF IRELAND.</p>
<p>In Three Volumes, 7d. each, or the Three neatly bound in One, 2s. 3d.</p>
<p>THE HISTORY AND SOURCES OF THE GREATNESS OF THE BRITISH <lb/> EMPIRE.&mdash;BY BENJAMIN PARSONS.</p>
<p>In Two Volumes, price 7d. each, or neatly bound in One, price 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>THE HISTORY OF FRANCE, <lb/> From the Earliest Period to the Present Time; with numerous Portraits. In Three Volumes, 7d. each, or <lb/> neatly bound in One, 2s. 3d.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>Scientific Works.</head>
<p>THE NATURAL HISTORY OF MAN; OR, POPULAR CHAPTERS ON <lb/> ETHNOGRAPHY.&mdash;BY JOHN KENNEDY, A.M.</p>
<p>In Two Volumes, 7d. each, or neatly bound in One, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>THE WONDERS OF THE HEAVENS.&mdash;BY FREDERICK S. WILLIAMS.</p>
<p>With Diagrams. In One Volume, price 7d.</p>
<p>THE HISTORY OF THE STEAM ENGINE.</p>
<p>From the Second Century before the Christian Era to the Time of the Great Exhibition, with many Engravings, <lb/> In One Volume, price 7d.</p>
<p>The last Two Volumes bound together, price 1s. 6d.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>Voyages and Travels.</head>
<p>SAILINGS OVER THE GLOBE, <lb/> OR THE PROGRESS OF MARITIME DISCOVERY, EAST, WEST, SOUTH, AND NORTH.</p>
<p>In Two Volumes, 7d. each, or the Two neatly bound in One, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>FOOTPRINTS OF TRAVELLERS, IN EUROPE, ASIA, AFRICA, AND AMERICA.</p>
<p>In Two Volumes, 7d. each, or the Two neatly bound in One, 1s. 6d.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>The Pathway: a Religious Magazine;</head><p>Published on the First Day of every Month, containing 32 pages large Crown Octavo, closely printed, <lb/> and stitched in a Neat Wrapper, price Twopence.</p>
<p>This Work contains a greater variety of Biblical information, Papers on Church History, Biography, Experimental and Practical Christianity, than any hitherto issued of the same extent. Testimonies to its excellence&mdash;as a Work of deep interest and utility to Families, to Sabbath-school Teachers, and to Youth generally&mdash;have been borne by a large number of Ministers in the Metropolis and various parts of the kingdom, as well as by a considerable portion of the Public Press. Volumes I. and II., each containing 336 pages, may be had, neatly bound in cloth, price 2s. 3d. each.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Now ready, price 6d., in a neat Wrapper,</opener><head>CASSELL'S EMIGRANTS' HANDBOOK:</head><p>Being a Guide to the various Fields of Emigration in all Parts of the Globe; <lb/> WITH AN INTRODUCTORY ESSAY, <lb/> ON THE IMPORTANCE OF EMIGRATION, AND THE DANGERS TO WHICH EMIGRANTS ARE EXPOSED.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;The British American Provinces; Hints to Emigrants to the North American Provinces; The United States; Laws respecting Emigrant Ships; Australia; New South Wales; South Australia; Western Australia; Van Diemen's Land; New Zealand; the Cape of Good Hope; Port Natal; Sale of Waste Lands in the Colonies; Information for Emigrants; Tables of Inland Travelling from New York, and Rate of Fares; Miscellaneous; Government Emigration Officers in the United Kingdom; Government Immigration Officers in the Colonies.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Fifteenth Thousand.&mdash;Price 6d., in a neat Wrapper,</opener><head>A SERIES OF LESSONS IN FRENCH,</head><p>On an entirely Novel and Simple Plan, by means of which a Perfect Knowledge of the French Language may be acquired without the aid of a Teacher. Reprinted, in a revised form, from THE WORKING MAN'S FRIEND.</p>
<p>By special permission of Her Majesty's Postmaster-General, this Work may be transmitted through the Post-office, and will be sent free to any address on the receipt of Seven Postage Stamps.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p6a" n="6"/>
<head>THE LIVES AND WORKS <lb/> OF THE PAINTERS OF ALL NATIONS.</head>
<p>ON JULY THE FIRST, 1852, <lb/> Will be published the First Part of a Magnificent Work, in Imperial Quarto, under the above Title.</p>
<p>As in the Great Exhibition of the Industry of All Nations, the products of the Manufacturing energies of all countries of the earth were ranged side by side, so that the mind could grasp at once the leading sources and characteristics of the wealth and power of every country, so, in the Work in question, the triumphs which have been achieved by the greatest Painters will be collected, and the noblest works of Genius so represented and contrasted, as to realise, in a permanent form, a <lb/> Great Exhibition of the Art of All Nations.</p>
<p>Every arrangement has been made to create a work of cosmopolitan interest. French and English Artists, Savans, and Capitalists have, in this instance, united in a common object&mdash;that of embodying in a popular form, which all may study and profit by, the glorious lessons conveyed by the &ldquo;Lives and Works&rdquo; of those whose energies have been concentrated on the representation of Nature in her purest and most ideal forms.</p>
<p>Many years have been already devoted to a preparation for the present Work, the publication of which has been commenced most successfully in France. Drawings have been made, and exquisite Engravings have been executed, by the first Artists, under the superintendence of that distinguished connoisseur, <lb/> M. ARMENGAUD, OF PARIS.</p>
<p>Popular Memoirs of the Painters, accompanied with Notes of a more special and technical nature, have been prepared, in the intervals of his official labours, by <lb/> M. CHARLES BLANC, <lb/> LATE DIRECTOR-IN-CHIEF OF THE GALLERY OF THE LOUVRE AT PARIS.</p>
<p>These Memoirs will be translated by <lb/> Mr. PETER BERLYN, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Translator of Lamartine's &ldquo;History of the Restoration of Monarchy in France,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.; Author of &ldquo;A Popular Narrative of the Great Exhibition,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi></p>
<p>The general Editorship of this English Edition will be intrusted to <lb/> Mr. M. DIGBY WYATT, <lb/> ARCHITECT, <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Author of the &ldquo;Industrial Arts of the Nineteenth Century,&rdquo; &ldquo;Specimens of the Geometrical Mosaics of the Middle Ages,&rdquo; a &ldquo;Report on the French Expositions of Industry;&rdquo; on &ldquo;Polychromatic Decoration in Italy previous to the Time of Raphael,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi></p>
<p>Mr. WYATT'S deep study of the Fine Arts, as well as of the connexion which should exist between their culture and industrial progress, will enable him to confer a utilitarian value upon the Work, by a judicious arrangement of the whole, and the supply of occasional notes and contributions. His intimate connexion with the Great Exhibition will have still further qualified him for this department.</p>
<p>Each Monthly Part will consist of sixteen pages of letter-press, with numerous Illustrations inserted in the type, together with several finished and separate Engravings on Wood, so executed as to demonstrate, in the most convincing and unprecedented manner, the capabilities of this process of execution for the reproduction of works of art of the highest and most refined description. The whole will be printed on the best paper, and in the most perfect style of typography.</p>
<p>Each Part (with very rare exceptions) will be complete in itself, and separately paged, so as to admit of binding in whatever series may be preferred; and will contain a Biography of the Artist; his Portrait; facsimiles of his handwriting, by which his signed pictures may be identified; and Illustrations of his most celebrated Works.</p>
<p>Although each Part, as it appears, will be independent of that by which it may be followed, it is still proposed, when twelve Parts shall have been published, to supply such title-pages, indices, &amp;c., as will render them in all respects a complete and perfect Volume.</p>
<p>The Parts will appear on the First of every month, at Two Shillings each, and will be supplied through every Bookseller in Town or Country.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>BEAUTIFUL PRESENTATION VOLUME.</opener><head>THE ILLUSTRATED EXHIBITOR FOR 1851.</head>
<p>IN ONE SPLENDID VOLUME, <lb/> Embracing upwards of 600 Pages and 1,000 Engravings of Works of Art, Machinery, and Objects of Manufacture in the Great Exhibition, with List of Prize Exhibitors, and the History of the Undertaking, 7s. 6d. or handsomely bound in extra cloth, gilt edges, admirably adapted for presents, 8s. This is a marvellous Volume, and forms one of the most interesting monumental records of the Great Exhibition published. Cases for binding the Numbers of the above in one volume, in ornamental cloth, with gold back and sides, <lb/> may be had, price 1s. 9d.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Handsomely printed in crown 8vo, elegantly gilt, price 3s.,</opener><head>THE CASSELL 200 GUINEA PRIZE ESSAY</head><p>ON THE CONDITION OF IRELAND.</p>
<p>By WILLIAM EDWARD HEARN, LL.B., Professor of Greek in Queen's College, Galway.</p>
<list>
<head>CONTENTS:</head>
<item>On the Existing Evils of Ireland, and their Causes.</item>
<item>On the Industrial Resources of Ireland.</item>
<item>On the Remedies for Irish Distress.</item>
</list><p>JOHN CASSELL, 9, LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE HILL.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p7a" n="7"/>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>In the Press, and shortly will be Published, <lb/> PRICE 3D., <lb/> A NEW MONTHLY <lb/> ILLUSTRATED MAGAZINE FOR CHILDREN, <lb/> ENTITLED</opener><head>THE DIAL OF LOVE.</head>
<p>BY MARY HOWITT.</p>
<p>London: Stevens &amp; Co., Printers, Bell Yard, Temple Bar.</p>
<p>TIME marks his progress on the Dial; and our wise ancestors placed this useful Time-keeper in every public situation for the benefit of every passer-by. It stood aloft in the market-place, and above the old street-fountain; it was to be seen on the church-porch and over the door of the school-house; it was erected on the bridge and in the garden of hall and cottage. Every where stood the dial telling with its shadow-finger the sunny progress of the hours.</p>
<p>We also would place aloft our Dial, our DIAL OF LOVE, to which we would direct the eyes of the young, of the busy, active, merry, hopeful, rising generation, as to a faithful, pleasant chronicler of passing hours.</p>
<p>Men and women, learned and unlearned, grave and gay, all have their periodicals, their dials, as it were, for profit or pastime; why should not the children have theirs also? To meet this want and fully to supply it, is the design of the present undertaking.</p>
<p>Our Dial of Love, like the dial of our ancestors, is intended for general use, and, like it, will have the peculiarity of inscribing its precious and beautiful truths in sunshine. It will be calculated alike for the boy as for the girl; for the thoughtful as well as the merry; for the poor as well as the
<pb id="p8a" n="[2]"/>
rich. It will be useful in the school-room, and as an out-of-door companion; and the cheerful light of the flickering fireside flame will mark its shadow indications no less truly than the broad sunshine of the field and the sea-shore. It will lie with the playthings on the seat in the nursery window, and on the bench of the child's garden, whilst its spirit will be loving and gentle and pure enough for a dial-plate above the entrance to the temple of worship in every child's heart.</p>
<p>To drop the metaphor somewhat, we may promise that this Illustrated Magazine for Children will comprise in itself every subject which is useful, interesting, or especially attractive to the young, accompanied by embellishments of a superior character. In its pages will be found pleasant stories; wonderful adventures; travels by sea and land; heroic deeds, ancient and modern; biographical sketches; the characteristics of the progressive seasons; rambles in the country; natural history; interesting scientific facts; hints for gardening, and bird and animal keeping; out-door and fire-side amusements: the whole interspersed with poems and ballads, occasionally accompanied with music for home-singing and recreation. In short, the young historian and traveller, the young student of natural history and botany, the young lover of literature, poetry, and the arts, will find in these pages a useful manual, whilst the tens of thousands who seek above all things to be amused will be lured to them from that very cause.</p>
<p>Not unfrequently also will our Dial devote a portion of its time to the wonders of the great metropolis, to the ancient treasures of the British Museum or some other of our national institutions; while, at the same time, it will derive additional attractions from the literature of various nations.</p>
<p>In fine, the objects of this Dial of Love are to instruct, to interest, to amuse; to waken a spirit of kindliness to all created things, and to scatter the flowers of intellectual enjoyment along the path of life's serious acquisitions.</p>
<p>Holborn Hill, March, 1852.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="9"/>
<head>STANDARD JUVENILE BOOKS.</head>
<div3>
<head>DARTON'S <lb/> SELECT <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BOOKS;<lb/>JUVENILE, HISTORICAL, SCIENTIFIC, AND EDUCATIONAL, <lb/> FOR SCHOOLS AND FAMILIES.</head>
<p>RELIGIOUS AND MORAL,</p><p>OR <lb/> BOOKS ADAPTED MORE ESPECIALLY TO THE DEVELOPMENT <lb/> OF THE RELIGIOUS AND MORAL FEELINGS.</p>
<p>Price 4s. 6d., prettily bound, with numerous Steel Engravings, from Drawings by <lb/> ANNA MARY HOWITT, <lb/> STORIES OF THE REFORMATION.</p>
<p>BY THE REV. B. G. JOHNS, <lb/> HEAD MASTER OF THE GRAMMAR SCHOOL, DULWICH.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In these days of excitement regarding the spread of the Roman Catholics in this country, the Stories from the History of the Reformation will be particularly acceptable. They are illustrated by Anna Mary Howitt, and the illustrations are in every way worthy of the subject.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Scholastic Reporter.</hi></p>
<p>THE PRINCE OF PEACE,</p><p>OR <lb/> TRUTHS FOR YOUNG DISCIPLES; <lb/> WITH A PREFACE BY <lb/> THE REV. EDWARD BICKERSTETH, <lb/> RECTOR OF WATTON, BERKS, <lb/> Price 3s.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This interesting volume may safely be put into the hands of young persons, and will powerfully tend to lead them in the way of truth, that they may hold the faith in the unity of the spirit and the bond of peace.&rdquo;</p>
<p>POPULAR BOOKS FOR YOUNG CHILDREN,</p><p>By the Author of &ldquo;Chickseed without Chickweed,&rdquo; <lb/> Of which upwards of 50,000 have been sold in an incredibly short time.</p>
<p>Price 1s. 6d., royal 16mo., beautifully bound, <lb/> BIBLE STORIES FOR YOUNG CHILDREN; <lb/> By the Author of &ldquo;Chickseed without Chickweed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;These stories are intended for the use of Children as soon as they can read. The stories are chosen from those parts of the Sacred Scriptures most likely to awaken attention in a child's mind, and to create a desire for hearing more of them; and they are as nearly as possible in the words of Holy Writ.&rdquo;</p>
<pb id="p10a" n="10"/>
<p>THE LIFE OF OUR SAVIOUR,</p><p>WITH COLOURED PLATES, <lb/> FOR VERY YOUNG CHILDREN.</p>
<p>THE CHILDREN OF SCRIPTURE,</p><p>WITH COLOURED PLATES, <lb/> Explaining to Children those parts of the Bible which have especial reference <lb/> to them.</p>
<p>CHICKSEED WITHOUT CHICKWEED.</p>
<p>PRINTED FOR VERY YOUNG CHILDREN.</p>
<p>*LITTLE LESSONS FOR LITTLE FOLKS</p><p>IN EASY WORDS FOR YOUNG CHILDREN.</p>
<p>*EARLY SEEDS TO PRODUCE SPRING FLOWERS,</p><p>A COMPANION FOR <lb/> LITTLE LESSONS FOR LITTLE LEARNERS.</p>
<p>*PAPA'S STORIES FOR HIS YOUNGER CHILDREN.</p>
<p>*PLAIN THINGS FOR LITTLE FOLKS.</p>
<p>* These four little works, by the author of &ldquo;Chickseed without Chickweed,&rdquo; may be had, strongly bound, in cloth, with coloured Plates, 1s. each; or, plain Plates, illuminated Wrappers and Gold, at 6d. each.</p>
<p>DARTON'S OUTLINE MAPS.</p>
<p>PRINTED ON FINE PAPER; <lb/> Size, 20&frac12; inches by 16&frac12; inches, price 6d. each Map.</p>
<list>
<item>Eastern Hemisphere.</item>
<item>Western Hemisphere.</item>
<item>Europe.</item>
<item>Asia.</item>
<item>Africa.</item>
<item>America.</item>
<item>England.</item>
<item>Scotland.</item>
<item>Ireland.</item>
<item>Palestine.</item>
</list><p>Key Maps to the above, coloured, on the same scale, at the same price.</p>
<p>THE EARLY EDUCATOR;</p><p>OR, <lb/> FIRST LESSONS IN USEFUL KNOWLEDGE: <lb/> BY WM. MARTIN.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Martin has been long and deservedly celebrated as being one of the first improvers of the systems of modern education, and his numerous publications prove him to be not merely a theorist, but a thorough practical teacher; a great advantage to those who prepare books for the young.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Morning Herald.</hi></p>
<p>GUTTA PERCHA, AND ITS USES TO MAN;</p><p>WITH COLOURED PLATES, <lb/> Foolscap 4to., and Wrapper printed in Gold, price 1s.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p11a" n="11"/>
<head>JUVENILE AND EDUCATIONAL.</head>
<p>Strongly bound in cloth, in 18mo., <lb/> THE MOTHER'S QUESTION BOOK; <lb/> on <lb/> CHILD'S FIRST GUIDE TO KNOWLEDGE, <lb/> COMPRISING THE FIRST, SECOND, AND THIRD MOTHER'S CATECHISMS, <lb/> BY THE REV. DAVID BLAIR.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The name of Dr. Blair is identified with elementary knowledge; and these, the genuine productions of his pen, are well worthy the attention of the parent and teacher.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Educational Magazine.</hi></p>
<p>SPECIMEN OF THE ABOVE FROM PAGE 52.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Q. What are the objects of all manufactures?</p>
<p>&ldquo;A. To make the necessaries and conveniences of life; as clothing, tools, and furniture.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Q. Of what is clothing made?</p>
<p>&ldquo;A. Clothing is made of wool, flax, cotton, silk, or leather; and there are great manufactures of each of these.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Q. Of what are tools made?</p>
<p>&ldquo;A. Of wood, iron, steel, and brass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Q. Of what is furniture made?</p>
<p>&ldquo;A. Of oak and deal, with brass ornaments, with beds of cotton or linen, and hair mattresses or feather beds.&rdquo;</p>
<p>THE CHILD'S BOOK OF FACTS,</p><p>COMPRISING THE FIRST, SECOND, AND THIRD CATECHISMS OF COMMON THINGS</p>
<p>BY THE REV. T. WILSON.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This work may be regarded as a sequel to the &lsquo;Mother's Question Book,&rsquo; which the author has, in his style and method, followed as a model. It presents an immense quantity of interesting facts to the young mind, and affords information of the most useful kind rendered clear and simple.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Journal of Education.</hi></p>
<p>SPECIMEN OF THE QUESTIONS.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is meant by the terms art and science?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What are the principal of the arts?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How are they distinguished?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Neatly and strongly bound in cloth, <lb/> LESSONS ON NATURAL PHILOSOPHY, <lb/> FOR CHILDREN, <lb/> BY THE REV. T. WILSON.</p>
<p>&ldquo;These Lessons consist of initiatory information upon the Phenomena of Nature, the Mechanical Powers, Astronomy, Geography, Light and Heat, Electricity, Attraction, Chemistry, Magnetism, and include a great variety of valuable matter. condensed and simplified in a very clever manner by the author.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Monthly Magazine.</hi></p>
<p>SPECIMEN OF THE ABOVE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When you open a door, what is the weight that you move&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When you throw a ball, what becomes of it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What makes the weight go down to the bottom of a lock</p>
<pb id="p12a" n="12"/>
<p>Neatly bound in cloth, <lb/> FIRST LINES OF BOTANY, <lb/> BY W. BERNHARD TEGETMEIER.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This little work is a complete compendium of botanical science, written in a very clear and embodying manner, and embodying the most popular classification of plants. It is a work that may be consulted by the old as well as the young with great advantage, and to those who are fond of gardening it will be of great practical use.&rdquo;</p>
<p>SPECIMEN FROM PAGE 57.</p>
<p>THE CONVOLVULUS TRIBE.</p>
<p>&ldquo;181. The common bind-weed of our hedges may be taken as the representative of this very natural tribe of plants, distinguished by their <hi rend="italics">twining habit,</hi> and by the peculiar <hi rend="italics">plaited manner</hi> in which the corolla is folded in the bud.</p>
<p>&ldquo;182. The calyx consists of five sepals, two of which are outside the remainder; there are five stamens, and a superior pistil, containing three or four cells, with about two seeds in each.&rdquo;</p>
<p>QUESTIONS APPENDED AT THE FOOT.</p>
<p>&ldquo;181. What are the marks distinguishing the convolvulus tribe? 182. Describe the remaining parts of the flower?&rdquo;</p>
<p>JUST PUBLISHED, PRICE NINEPENCE EACH, <lb/> THE CATECHISM OF MODERN HISTORY; <lb/> ALSO, New Editions of the following Catechisms, <lb/> BY THE REV. T. WILSON:</p>
<list>
<item>CATECHISM OF THE HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF BIBLE HISTORY.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF ENGLISH GRAMMAR.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF ASTRONOMY.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF GEOGRAPHY.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF MUSIC.</item>
<item>FIRST CATECHISM OF COMMON THINGS.</item>
<item>SECOND CATECHISM OF COMMON THINGS.</item>
<item>THIRD CATECHISM OF COMMON THINGS.</item>
<item>FIRST CATECHISM OF NATURAL PHILOSOPHY.</item>
<item>SECOND CATECHISM OF NATURAL PHILOSOPHY.</item>
<item>THIRD CATECHISM OF NATURAL PHILOSOPHY.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF BOTANY. Two Parts.</item>
<item>CATECHISM OF BIOGRAPHY. Two Parts.</item>
</list>
<p>&ldquo;The Catechisms of the Rev. T. Wilson stand foremost in the rank of this mode of teaching, and the series fills a hiatus in this department of literature. They embody a vast amount of information in every branch of science, and are well worthy the attention of Schoolmasters, Pupil Teachers, and Governesses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>For upwards of a hundred favourable critiques from the London and Provincial Press, see Darton's printed Lists.</p>
<p>POPULAR JUVENILE BOOKS,<lb/>Of established reputation, which may be safely placed into the hands of Children, <lb/> blending Amusement with Instruction.</p>
<p>DARTON'S HOLIDAY LIBRARY.</p>
<p>A SERIES OF <lb/> SHILLING VOLUMES FOR THE YOUNG, <lb/> BY APPROVED AUTHORS.</p>
<p>No. 1.&mdash;MARY LEESON, by MARY HOWITT. Illustrated by JOHN ABSOLON.</p>
<p>No. 2.&mdash;TAKE CARE OF No. 1, or Good to Me includes Good to Thee, by S. E. GOODRICH, Esq. (the Original Peter Parley). Illustrated by GILBERT.</p>
<p>No. 3.&mdash;HOW TO SPEND A WEEK HAPPILY, by Mrs. BURBURY. With Illustrations.</p>
<p>No. 4.&mdash;POEMS FOR YOUNG CHILDREN, by &ldquo;ADELAIDE,&rdquo; one of the amiable Authoresses of &ldquo;Original Poems.&rdquo; With Illustrations.</p>
<p>No. 5.&mdash;THE YOUNG LORD, by CAMILLA TOULMIN; and VICTORINE DUROCHER, by Mrs. SHERWOOD. With Illustrations.</p>
<p>No. 6.&mdash;PAULINE. A Tale from the German. With Illustrations.</p>
<p>No. 7.&mdash;HOUSEHOLD STORIES. With Illustrations.</p>
<p>Nos. 8 and 9.&mdash;IN-DOOR AND OUT-DOOR SPORTS.</p>
<p>No. 10:&mdash;STORIES OF ENTERPRISE AND ADVENTURE; or AN EXCITEMENT TO READING. Illustrated with Wood Engravings, from designs by ABSOLON.</p>
<p>No. 11.&mdash;THE BOOK OF RIDDLES, ETC.</p>
<p>CRITICAL REMARKS.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Volumes of DARTON'S HOLIDAY LIBRARY which have reached us, comprise a most interesting Series of Books for Young People, written by some of our most Popular Authors, and all having a tendency towards the formation of correct principles and habits in the minds of the Young. They blend amusement with instruction in the most delightful manner. We cordially recommend them as by far the best books of their class.&rdquo;</p>
<pb id="p13a" n="13"/>
<p>BLAIR'S MOTHER'S CATECHISMS.</p>
<p>PRICE 9d. EACH, <lb/> THE FIRST, OR MOTHER'S CATECHISM, <lb/> BY THE REV. DAVID BLAIR.</p>
<p>THE SECOND, OR MOTHER'S CATECHISM.</p>
<p>ALSO, <lb/> THE THIRD, OR MOTHER'S CATECHISM.</p>
<p>The extensive demand which yet prevails for these excellent Catechisms proves that they continue to sustain their well-deserved popularity, as mediums of instruction, and that, notwithstanding the many compilations and imitations which have been brought into existence solely by the success of these favourite little books. BLAIR'S CATECHISMS are still regarded by the intelligent portion of the public, as unequalled for the variety and accuracy of the information they contain, as well as for the admirable simplicity and perspicuity with which that information is conveyed.</p>
<p>THE LADY'S LIBRARY;</p><p>IN SIX MONTHLY PARTS, <lb/> Price 1s. each; free by post, 1s. 6d.</p>
<list>
<item>PART 1. BRAIDING AND EMBROIDERY.</item>
<item>PART 2. CROTCHET AND LACE WORK.</item>
<item>PART 3. POINT LACE AND TATTING.</item>
<item>PART 4. KNITTING AND NETTING EMRROIDERY.</item>
<item>PART 5. FRUITS AND FLOWERS IN WAX-WORK.</item>
<item>PART 6. PAPIER-MACHE AND JAPAN WORK.</item>
</list><p>Each Part forms a complete Book in itself. With numerous Illustrations, by the <lb/> First Artists.</p>
<p>The LADY'S LIBRARY contains clear instructions for the practice of all those elegant and useful arts which form the occupation and amusement of thousands of Englishwomen, with directions for the choice and preparation of materials, selection of colours, and every other requisite for the profitable employment of feminine taste and talent. Each article has been accurately engraved, and the entire work is a suitable gift to all who desire to increase their comforts and luxuries by the exercise of industry and ingenuity.</p>
<p>THE LADY'S KEEPSAKE;</p><p>Or, TREASURES OF THE NEEDLE; <lb/> Being the first Four Parts of the &ldquo;LADY'S LIBRARY,&rdquo; in one volume, price 5s.</p>
<p>PETER PARLEY'S CHILD'S OWN LIBRARY.</p>
<p>In a Mahogany Case, with Glass Front, Lock and Key, price 21s.</p>
<p>This elegant Gift, or Keepsake, for the Young, suitable as a Prize, Birthday, or Family Present, contains ten volumes of the most popular Historical, Geographical, and Moral Tales, by the Original PETER PARLEY, with about Five Hundred engraved Illustrations. Each volume is published at 2s. 6d. separately, thus a saving of about 30 per cent. is made by purchasing the combined set, and the most complete JUVENILE LIBRARY obtained ever offered to the young, from the works of this favourite Author.</p>
<p>Illustrated with several Steel Engravings, price 2s. 6d., <lb/> THE TWO KNIGHTS, OR BELANCY CASTLE.</p>
<p>This is a highly interesting tale, founded on a Family Legend, attached to one of the most interesting periods of our history, and illustrates the mode by which Providence sometimes effects important ends by the ministration of babes and sucklings, and is a useful historical illustration of the manners and events of the time to which it refers.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p14a" n="14"/>
<head>DARTON'S SCHOOL LIBRARY;</head><p>An entirely New Series of Elementary Works adapted for <lb/> SCHOOLS, FAMILIES, AND PUPIL TEACHERS.</p>
<p>EDITED BY THE <lb/> REV. B. G. JOHNS, <lb/> Head Master of the Grammar School, Dulwich College, <lb/> PRICE ONE SHILLING EACH, IN CLOTH, 18MO.</p>
<p>THE ELEMENTS OF GEOGRAPHY ON A NEW PLAN, <lb/> AND <lb/> THE HISTORY OF ENGLAND.</p>
<p>THE great success of &ldquo;DARTON'S HOLIDAY LIBRARY&rdquo; has suggested to the Proprietors the publication of a Series of School Books, of a similar form and price, to appear at successive intervals, under the above title.</p>
<p>The earnest endeavour of the Editor and Authors who have been engaged to carry out this design will be to combine, in the treatment of each subject, the best method, the latest information, and the most judicious selection of matter, expressed as briefly as is consistent with clearness. Their experience as Teachers has taught them that Elementary Books err more often and with more injurious results, on the side of redundancy and diffuseness, than on the other. Hence, the mind of the learner is too often burdened and discouraged by matter which, if it be good in itself, is yet not adapted for the stage of progress to which he has arrived.</p>
<p>With such views, they do not hesitate to express their dissatisfaction with most of the School Books at present in use for the Class of Pupils they have in view. They have themselves practically felt the want which they intend to do their best to supply; for this end, the desire of the Publishers to bring out a <hi rend="italics">Uniform Series,</hi> at a <hi rend="italics">very low price,</hi> in a most convenient form, affords them a fortunate opportunity.</p>
<p>To most of the volumes will be prefixed Hints for Teachers on the Right Methods of Teaching the several Subjects. To these, brief as they are, the Editor would confidently call attention, as the result of matured experience and careful thought.</p>
<p>FIRST READING BOOK FOR JUNIOR CLASSES.</p>
<p>THE <lb/> POETICAL SCHOOL BOOK FOR JUNIOR CLASSES.</p>
<p>EXERCISE FOR THE SENSES.</p>
<p>SHORT INTRODUCTION TO FRENCH.</p>
<p>EACH VOLUME 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>MRS. SHERWOOD'S JUVENILE BOOKS.</p>
<p>ONE SHILLING BOOKS,</p><p>With many beautiful Wood-cuts and Copper-plate Frontispieces, fancy cloth, royal square 16mo. <lb/> 13 for 8s.</p>
<list>
<item>Sisterly Love.</item>
<item>The Traveller.</item>
<item>Troublesome Tom.</item>
<item>Jack, the Sailor Boy.</item>
<item>Think before you Act.</item>
<item>Grandmamma Parker.</item>
<item>Frank Beauchamp.</item>
<item>Uncle Manners, or Self-will Cured.</item>
</list>
<p>SIXPENNY BOOKS,</p><list>
<item>Frank Beauchamp.</item>
<item>The Heron's Plume.</item>
<item>The Wreck of the Walpole.</item>
<item>The Fall of Pride, &amp;c.</item>
</list>
<p>TWO-PENNY BOOKS,</p><list>
<item>How to Please.</item>
<item>Conceit Checked.</item>
<item>Willy Cory.</item>
<item>The Druids of Bochara.</item>
<item>What could I do without Grandmother.</item>
<item>The Child is but a Child.</item>
<item>The Parting Cup.</item>
<item>Your's is the Best.</item>
<item>What's the use of that.</item>
<item>The Blind Gentleman.</item>
<item>Let me take care of Myself.</item>
<item>Comfort in Death.</item>
</list>
<p>PENNY BOOKS,</p><list>
<item>Lucy Going to school</item>
<item>The Useful Dog.</item>
<item>The Flood.</item>
<item>The Shawl.</item>
<item>Horses and Coaches.</item>
<item>Dangerous Sport.</item>
<item>The Honey Drop.</item>
<item>Eyes and Ears.</item>
<item>The Land of Snow.</item>
<item>Susan's Feast Money.</item>
<item>The Indian Chief.</item>
<item>Going to the Fair.</item>
</list>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p15a" n="15"/>
<head>WATERLOW'S <lb/> PATENT IMPROVED AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, <lb/> OR PORTABLE <lb/> PRINTING MACHINE,</head><p>FOR THE COUNTING-HOUSE, OFFICE, OR LIBRARY, <lb/> BY MEANS OF WHICH <lb/> EVERY PERSON MAY BECOME HIS OWN PRINTER.</p>
<p>The process is simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing, or piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.</p>
<p>Many hundreds of these Presses have now been sold, and are being successfully used by Railway and Public Companies, Bankers, Merchants, Amateurs, &amp;c, &amp;c.; also in Public and Private Schools, for the production of lessons in Music, Drawing, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
<p>The Press may be seen at work at the Patentees,&rsquo; and specimens of its production will be forwarded free, upon application.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="2">
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>PRICES.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>On Mahogany Stand.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To print a Subject</cell>
<cell>11 &times; 9</cell>
<cell>&pound;7</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>&pound;9</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To print a Subject</cell>
<cell>16&frac12; &times; 10&frac12;</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To print a Subject</cell>
<cell>18 &times; 13&frac12;</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div2>
<head>PATENT AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS FOR TRAVELLERS,</head><p>WHICH FROM ITS COMPACT FORM IS RECOMMENDED FOR USE ON <lb/> VOYAGES AND FOREIGN MISSIONS.</p>
<p>To Print a Subject 11 &times; 9 Price complete &pound;9 9 0.</p>
<p>PATENTEES&mdash;WATERLOW &amp; SONS, MANUFACTURING STATIONERS, &amp;c. <lb/> 65 to 68, LONDON WALL, LONDON.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">For Notices of the Press, see other side.</hi></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p16a" n="16"/>
<head>THE <lb/> PATENT AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS,</head><p>(HAND POWER), <lb/> ADAPTED FOR EXPORTATION TO THE COLONIES, <lb/> OCCUPYING LITTLE SPACE AND VERY PORTABLE.</p>
<p>The attention of MERCHANTS and SHIPPERS is particularly called to the importance of this invention, for the Colonies and Foreign Countries: and when it is considered that in many places no printer is to be found, and that in some countries, especially in the East, the complication of the numerous Oriental characters renders it necessary for all documents to be multiplied by the tedious process of transcribing, the peculiar advantages of the Autographic Press become manifest.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="8">
<row>
<cell></cell>
<cell>PRICES.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To Print a Subject</cell>
<cell>14 &times; 9</cell>
<cell>&pound;4</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To Print a Subject</cell>
<cell>16 &times; 10</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>To Print a Subject</cell>
<cell>18 &times; 13</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>PATENTEES-WATERLOW AND SONS, LONDON.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head>
<div3 type="section">
<head>From the City Article of &ldquo;The TIMES.&rdquo;</head>
<p>A very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW &amp; SONS, which will be productive of great convenience to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared paper with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly valuable.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<pb id="p17a" n="17"/>
<head>&ldquo;MORNING CHRONICLE.&rdquo;</head>
<p>AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS.&mdash;An invention has been patented which is likely to prove of great utility to public companies and men of business generally. It will become a great desideratum to merchants in the colonies, and will be found very useful at the chief offices of banks, in suspending the necessity for copying any number of circulars which it may be necessary to send to the Branches from time to time. We understand it has received the pa'ronage of His Royal Highness Prince Albert, and it is the invention of Messrs. WATERLOW and SONS, London Wall, by whom it has been patented.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;WESTMINSTER REVIEW.&rdquo;</head>
<p>THE AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS, OR PORTABLE PRINTING MACHINE.&mdash;Under this name the Messrs. WATERLOW, of London wall have patented a very simple but effective apparatus, the merits of which cannot fail to be duly appreciated as soon as they are known. The subject to be printed is transferred from paper to the surface of a highly-polished metallic plate, and being charged with ink in the usual manner, the paper on which it is to be printed is placed upon it, and the tympan being laid down, a wooden scraper with a sharp edge is passed over it by the hand, when a perfect impression is at once obtained. All this may be done even upon the drawing-room table; and the whole of the apparatus, when not in use, is enclosed in a neat French-polished box, which may be carried beneath the arm. The utility of such a simple application of the lithographic principle must be obvious to mercantile men and others, who require a number of copies of their correspondence.</p>
<p>The name of &ldquo;Autographic Press&rdquo; may perhaps induce the idea that this is some cumbrous machine similar to that used in lithographic printing. Such, however, is not the case, for no <hi rend="italics">press,</hi> in the ordinary acceptation of the term, is used at all, the impression, as we have before mentioned, being produced by hand. The requisite number of copies having been obtained, the design is effaced from the plate, which is then ready to receive another.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;ATLAS.&rdquo;</head>
<p>BANKERS' AND MERCHANTS' CIRCULARS. &mdash; An invention has been submitted to us, which is likely to prove of great utility to public companies and men of business generally. It consists of a press and materials, by means of which any person may, from a document previously written on paper, produce any required number of copies. Circulars, letters, prospectuses, &amp;c., can be produced by this invention with the greatest facility; and any number of designs, music, plans, &amp;c., may be expeditiously printed in the same manner. The apparatus is extremely simple, and is all contained in a box of small size, perfectly portable. It will become a great desideratum to merchants in the colonies, and will be found very useful at the chief offices of banks, in suspending the necessity for copying any number of circulars which it may be necessary to send to the Branches from time to time. We understand it has received the patronage of H.R.H. Prince Albert, and it is the invention of Messrs. WATERLOW and SONS, London Wall, by whom it has been patented.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;ILLUSTRATED LONDON NEWS.&rdquo;</head>
<p>WATERLOW'S AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS.&mdash;Amongst the most practically useful inventions which have recently come under our notice, whether we regard it in reference to the commercial world, or as an instrument in the hands of a private gentleman &ldquo;The Autographic Press,&rdquo; patented by WATERLOW and SONS, is entitled to foremost mention. By this apparatus, any person may with facility print any number of letters, circulars, pen and ink sketches, musical notations, or other matters in which duplicate copies are wanted; the whole machinery being compassed in a neat box not larger than a lady's writing-case. The mode in which the transfer is effected may be briefly described. For instance: a letter is written on prepared paper, and then transferred to a polished metallic plate by means of hand-power, assisted by a &ldquo;scraper.&rdquo; The paper is then washed off the plate with water, when the writing remains on the plate, and is charged with ink from a roller somewhat similar to the ordinary printing roller. Paper is now laid on the plate, and upon the application of pressure, in the manner before described, the impression is derived, and the process may be repeated sixty or seventy times in the hour, the plate being subjected to the ink roller for each impression. When sufficient copies are cast off, the plate is cleaned, and ready for a fresh operation. The specimens we have seen are equal to lithography.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;BANKERS' MAGAZINE.&rdquo;</head>
<p>AUTOGRAPHIC PRESS.&mdash;An invention of great utility. Bankers' Circulars may be printed from it with the greatest facility. It will become very useful at the chief offices of banks, in suspending the necessity for copying any number of circulars which it may be necessary to send to the branches from time to time. It has received the patronage of H.R.H. Prince Albert, to whom it has been submitted by the Patentees, Messrs. WATERLOW and SONS, London Wall.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;SAUNDERS'S DUBLIN NEWS LETTER.&rdquo;</head>
<p>During the course of the week we have had exhibited to us a novel but highly useful machine, called the &ldquo;Autographic Press,&rdquo; invented and patented by WATERLOW and SONS, of London. The object of the inventors is to enable merchants, bankers, clerks, &amp;c., to take an <hi rend="italics">ad infinitum</hi> number of copies of their circulars, letters, documents, &amp;c. It entirely supersedes the old mode of copying by the ordinary press, and far outstrips the &ldquo;manifold&rdquo; system. In fact, it is a complete lithographic press, put up in a neat portable box, and can be purchased at a moderate price. To the commercial community it must prove a great desideratum.&rdquo;</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;BOMBAY GAZETTE.&rdquo;</head>
<p>We see that a very useful invention has been patented by Messrs. WATERLOW and SONS, of London, which with be productive of great convenience to banking establishments, and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the &ldquo;Autographic Press,&rdquo; and a letter written on prepared paper, with which it is furnished, can be transferred, by a short process, to a metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common paper, and by ordinary pressure. In the Colonies, and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, this invention is represented as being likely to prove particularly valuable.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="section">
<head>&ldquo;RAILWAY RECORD.&rdquo;</head>
<p>GENERAL ORDERS TO STATION CLERKS.&mdash;Messrs. WATERLOW and SONS, London Wall, have recently patented an invention which is likely to prove of great utility to all public Companies. A press and material are put together in a neat box, in such a way that any person may, with the greatest facility, reproduce from MS. any number of copies that may be required. It is called the &ldquo;Autographic Press&rdquo;&mdash;is very neat, and perfectly portable. Railway Companies would find it exceedingly convenient in issuing orders to their Stations; and it would in point of expense very soon repay its moderate cost.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p18a" n="18"/>
<head>PATENT LETTER COPYING PRESSES.</head>
<p>These Machines, although <hi rend="italics">lower in price than those of any other manufacturer,</hi> are all <hi rend="italics">warranted,</hi> and will be immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>Lever Press.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>Screw Press.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>1st quality, Screw.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>Screw Press, wrt. iron beam.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>Mahogany Tables.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>Damping Boxes.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Large 4to</cell>
<cell>&pound;1</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>&pound;2</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>&pound;3</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>&pound;3</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>&pound;1</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>11s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Foolscap Folio</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>12s</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Post Folio</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>14s.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="12">
<head>Fittings for Quarto Machine.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell>
<cell>2<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell>Damping Brush</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Drying Book or Sheets</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="4" cols="12">
<head>Fittings for Foolscap Machine.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell>
<cell>3<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Damping Brush</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Drying Book or Sheets</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="4" cols="12">
<head>Fittings for Folio Machine.</head><row>
<cell>Cloth Pads, per pair</cell>
<cell>4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell>6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Damping Brush</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Drying Books or Sheets</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>6 Oiled Sheets</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="9">
<head>COPYING BOOKS, OF BLUE OR CREAM-WOVE COPYING PAPER, OF FIRST QUALITY TYPE-PAGED BY STEAM POWER,</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>QUARTER BOUND.</cell>
<cell>Each.</cell>
<cell>per doz.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell>HALF ROUND.</cell>
<cell>Each.</cell>
<cell>per doz.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>500</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>8s.</cell>
<cell>84s.</cell>
<cell>500</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>10s.</cell>
<cell>102s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>750</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>10s.</cell>
<cell>105s.</cell>
<cell>750</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>13s.</cell>
<cell>138s.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1000</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>12s.</cell>
<cell>126s.</cell>
<cell>1000</cell>
<cell>LEAVES</cell>
<cell>15s.</cell>
<cell>156s.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>COPYING PAPER,</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="8">
<head>BEST FRENCH MAKE.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Two Reams for</cell>
<cell>16</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Five Reams for</cell>
<cell>35</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row><row role="label">
<cell>Ten Reams for</cell>
<cell>60</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="4" cols="8">
<head>BEST ENGLISH MAKE.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Two Reams for</cell>
<cell>17</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Five Reams for</cell>
<cell>37</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ten Reams for</cell>
<cell>65</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<div3>
<head>Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink, <lb/> FOR COPYING LETTERS.</head>
<p>The only <hi rend="italics">really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="italics">used</hi> in most of the <hi rend="italics">Principal Establishments in the City,</hi>
<lb/> and is universally admitted the best yet produced.</p>
<p>Per PINT, 2s. Per QUART, 3s. Per DOZEN QUARTS, 30s. Per GALLON, 10s <lb/> Per HALF-GALLON, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per GALLON, do., do., 12s.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>PORTABLE COPYING MACHINE FOR TRAVELLERS,</head><p>Highly finished and fitted <lb/> complete, &pound;6 6 0</p>
<p>Highly finished Polished Steel, <lb/> &pound;7 7 0</p>
<p>WATERLOW &amp; SONS, <lb/> Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and Engravers, <lb/> 65 to 68, London Wall, London.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p19a" n="19"/>
<head>A Suit in Chancery and a Suit out of Chancery.</head>
<p>IT is not necessary to talk of frightful monsters&mdash;nor of spirits, once very disturbing to good people's rest and quiet; a Chancery Suit is justly enough considered as one of the most frightful apparitions which can haunt any domicile. We can generally manage pretty well with natural affairs, and can show courage like Britons at broad daylight; but it is these shadows and this darkness which renders us so timid, because they are supernatural: this must be the case with heavy&mdash;<hi rend="italics">gloomy&mdash;dusty&mdash;mouldy&mdash;heartbreaking&mdash;brainkilling Chancery Suits.</hi> Now the difference between a Suit in Chancery and a Suit out of Chancery is just this:&mdash;in the former a man is every moment <hi rend="italics">tormented, worried, plagued, twisted, sharpened,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">threatened,</hi> until his very visage becomes like a Chancery Suit&mdash;quite a supernatural affair. But a Suit out of Chancery, especially a Suit of Summer Dress from the Establishments of E. MOSES &amp; SON is <hi rend="italics">light, brilliant, heartcheering,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">brainreviving;</hi> brushing up one's spirits with the most gratifying assurances of <hi rend="italics">comfort</hi> and <hi rend="italics">pleasure.</hi> But a Suit in Chancery is a very different matter, with this precious portion if a gentleman has property he is in a fair way for losing it; if he has a good suit he may wear it out in expectation, and possibly may find it difficult to get another. On the other hand, a Suit out of Chancery, from E. MOSES &amp; SON'S, is the best portion of a Gentleman's estate, maintained at the least expense, exceeding the most sanguine expectations&mdash;the very essence of all novel and fascinating styles.</p>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>LIST OF PRICES,<lb/>READY MADE OR MADE TO MEASURE.</head>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>SPRING AND SUMMER OVERCOATS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The New Vicuna Summer Overcoat</cell>
<cell>from 0</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Lustre Coats, in a variety of light and elegant textures</cell>
<cell>from 8s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The Albert Wrapper, in a registered light material</cell>
<cell>from 15s. to 1</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Super light texture cloths, in every shape, including the Bequeme</cell>
<cell>from 18s. to 2</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The New Parisian Coat-Cape, made only by E. MOSES &amp; SON</cell>
<cell>from 30s. to 3</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>The Nepaulese Wrapper, weighing only six ounces</cell>
<cell>from 1</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Boys Spring and Summer Coats, in all the above materials and shapes, at proportionably low prices.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>LOUNGING AND MORNING COATS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Holland Cambridge Coats</cell>
<cell>from 0</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Alpaca Lustre Coats</cell>
<cell>from 5s. to 0</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cashmere and Orleans Coats</cell>
<cell>6s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>14</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Mixed Summer Cloth, in all shades</cell>
<cell>from 15s. to 1</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Super cloth, of a light texture, black and coloured</cell>
<cell>from 16s. to 2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Shooting Jackets, in a variety of materials, &amp;c</cell>
<cell>from 10s. 6d. to 2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>DRESS COATS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Dress Coat</cell>
<cell>from 17s. to 1</cell>
<cell>5</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Super Saxony Coat</cell>
<cell>from 25s. to 1</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Imperial, usually called best</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Best quality, West of England</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>FROCK COATS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Frock Coat</cell>
<cell>from 1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Super Coat</cell>
<cell>from 1</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Saxony Coat</cell>
<cell>from 2</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Imperial Coat</cell>
<cell>from 2</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Very best</cell>
<cell>from 3</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>SPRING AND SUMMER WAISTCOATS.</head>

<row>
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fancy Quilting Vest</cell>
<cell>from 2s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Plain and long Alpaca Lustre</cell>
<cell>from 3s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>White Quilting, for Dress</cell>
<cell>from 4s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>9</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Black Cassimere</cell>
<cell>from 4s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>13</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Embroidered Cloth</cell>
<cell>from 10s. 6d. to 2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>A large assortment of Fancy Thibets and other materials</cell>
<cell>from 4s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>13</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>SPRING AND SUMMER TROUSERS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tweeds</cell>
<cell>from 4s. 8d. to 0</cell>
<cell>7</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Scotch Tweeds, in great variety</cell>
<cell>from 8s. 6d. to 9</cell>
<cell>16</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Black Cassimere, for Dress</cell>
<cell>from 9s. 6d. to 1</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Fancy Summer Doeskin</cell>
<cell>from 8s. 6d. to 1</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>A large variety of Fancy Checks and Stripes, with borders</cell>
<cell>from 10s. 6d. to 1</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>White Drill Trousers</cell>
<cell>from 5s. 6d. to 0</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Plain and Fancy Gambroon</cell>
<cell>from 6s. to 0</cell>
<cell>12</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>A splendid assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskin</cell>
<cell>18s., 22s. to 1</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Summer cloth, with &frac78; train, from</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Superior cloth</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Superfine cloth</cell>
<cell>4</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>LIVERIES.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Page's suit, from</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>8</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Footman's</cell>
<cell>2</cell>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Groom's</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coachman's</cell>
<cell>3</cell>
<cell>10</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="5" cols="6">
<head>MOURNING.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell></cell>
<cell>&pound;</cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">s.</hi></cell>
<cell><hi rend="italics">d.</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ready made at Five Minutes' Notice.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Suit complete</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>16</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Boy's complete</cell>
<cell>0</cell>
<cell>18</cell>
<cell>6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Made to Measure in Five Hours.</cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
<cell></cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>A HANDSOME ALMANACK for the year 1852, to be had Gratis on application.</p>
<p>NOTICE.&mdash;The Parasol and Mantle Departments are now replete with every novelty of the season.</p>
<p>A New Book, entitled &ldquo;The Library of Elegance,&rdquo; containing full directions for self-measurement, can be had gratis on application or forwarded post free to any part of the kingdom.</p>
<p>OBSERVE.&mdash;Any article purchased either ready made or made to measure, if not approved of, will be exchanged or the money returned.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON have no connection with any other house, in or out of London, except the following:&mdash;</p>
<p>London City Establishments:&mdash;154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, 86, Aldgate, opposite the Church, all communicating.</p>
<p>London West End Branch:&mdash;506, 507, 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, 3, Hartstreet, all communicating.</p>
<p>Bradford, Yorkshire Branch, 19, Bridge-street.</p>
<p>Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</p>
<p>TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT &amp; SHOE MAKERS, <lb/> AND GENERAL OUTFITTERS FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed from sunset, on Friday, till sunset, on Saturday, when business is</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">resumed till</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p20a" n="20"/>
<head>HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS,</head><p>Sent free by post.</p>
<p>It contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One <lb/> Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, <lb/> Mahogany, Rosewood, &amp; Walnut Tree Woods; <lb/> Also their <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">Their New Warerooms enable them to keep one of each design fixed for inspection.</hi></p>
<p>They have also, in addition to their usual stock, a great variety of the best designs of <lb/> PARISIAN BEDSTEADS, <lb/> BOTH IN WOOD AND IRON, WHICH THEY HAVE JUST IMPORTED.</p>
<p>HEAL &amp; SON, <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTURERS, <lb/> 196, (opposite the Chapel), Tottenham Court Road.</p>
<p>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
