<?xml version="1.0" ?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>Bleak House, No. IX:</emph> Electronic Edition.</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp><name>Browne, H. K. (Hablot Knight), 1815-1882</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Maura McKee</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Matthew Kern and Natalia Smith</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca.  240 K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page"> Bleak House</title>

<author>Charles Dickens</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>H. K. Browne</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>


<extent> 61 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
<date>1852</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number RBC Dickens 21 c. 2  (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p></p>
</projectDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
</p><p>The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords>
<list>
<item><!-- LC headings go here --></item>
</list>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>


<change>
<date>2002-09-10, </date><respStmt><name> Natalia Smith, </name><resp>project manager, </resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-04, </date><respStmt><name>Matthew Kern</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-14, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="title"><p>[Title Page Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<div1 type="title page image"><p><figure id="verso"><p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p></figure></p></div1>

<titlePage>

<docTitle><titlePart> No. IX. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docDate> NOVEMBER.</docDate>

<docEdition>Price 1s.</docEdition><docTitle><titlePart>BLEAK <lb/> HOUSE 
</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>BY</byline>
<docAuthor>CHARLES DICKENS.</docAuthor>

<docAuthor>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY H. K. BROWNE
</docAuthor><docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>BRADBURY &amp; EVANS, BOUVERIE STREET.</publisher>
AGENTS: J. MENZIES, EDINBURGH; MURRAY AND SON, GLASGOW; J. M'GLASHAN, DUBLIN.<lb/>
The Author of this Work notifies that it is his intention to reserve the <lb/> right of translating it.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>


<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pii" n="verso"/>
<head>WILLIAM S. BURTON'S <lb/> GENERAL FURNISHING IRONMONGERY WAREHOUSE,</head><p>39, OXFORD STREET, <lb/> (CORNER OF NEWMAN STREET); <lb/> Nos. 1 &amp; 2, Newman Street; and 4 &amp; 5, Perry's Place, London.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>The Best Show of IRON BEDSTEADS in the Kingdom is <lb/> WILLIAM S. BURTON'S.</head>
<p>He has added to his SHOW-ROOMS Two very large ones, which are devoted to the exclusive show of IRON and BRASS BEDSTEADS and CHILDREN'S COTS, with appropriate Bedding and Mattresses. Many of these are quite new, and all are marked in plain figures, at prices proportionate with those that have tended to make his Establishment the most distinguished in this country. Common Iron Bedsteads, from 12s. 6d.; Portable Folding Bedsteads, from 12s. 6d.; Patent Iron Bedsteads, fitted with dove-tail joints and patent sacking, from 16s. 6d.; and Cots from 20s. each. Handsome Ornamental Iron and Brass Bedsteads in great variety, from &pound;3 5s. to &pound;31.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>NEW AND CHEERFUL REGISTERED STOVE.</head>
<p>In the construction of the BURTON REGISTERED STOVE, it was the first care of the Inventor, WILLIAM S. BURTON, to avail himself of the most valued of modern improvements in the art of heating, and secondly, so to modify and alter the receptacle for the coals as at once to obtain the simplest and most perfect combustion; after a long series of experiments, he has, by the substitution of a graceful form of shell for the present clumsy and ill-adapted bars, succeeded in producing a stove which for soft and brilliant light, as well as purity and quantity of heat, is far beyond his most sanguine expectations, while for cleanliness and cheerfulness it is utterly unapproachable. Price from 56s. to &pound;15. To be seen in use daily in his show-rooms, where also are to be seen <lb/> 250 STOVES and 325 FENDERS, <lb/> (exclusive of reserved stock) all differing in pattern, forming the largest assortment ever collected together. They are marked in plain figures, and at prices proportionate with those that have tended to make his Establishment the most distinguished in this country. Bright stoves, with bronzed ornaments and 2 sets of bars, &pound;2 14s. to &pound;5 10s.; ditto with ormolu ornaments and 2 sets of bars, &pound;5 10s. to &pound;12 12s.; bronze fenders complete, with standards, from 7s. to &pound;3; steel fenders, from &pound;2 15s. to &pound;6; ditto, with rich ormolu ornaments, from &pound;2 15s. to &pound;7 7s.; fire irons, from 1s. 9d. the set to &pound;4 4s. Sylvester and all other patent stoves, with radiating hearth plates, and kitchen ranges, which he is enabled to sell at these very reduced charges, <lb/> First&mdash;From the frequency and extent of his purchases; and <lb/> Secondly&mdash;From those purchases being made exclusively for cash.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>The Perfect Substitute for Silver.</head>
<p>THE REAL NICKEL SILVER, <lb/> Introduced twenty years ago by WILLIAM S. BURTON, when plated by the patent process of Messrs. Elkington &amp; Co., is beyond all comparison the very best article next to sterling silver that can he employed as such, either usefully or ornamentally, as by no possible test can it be distinguished from real silver.</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> Fiddle Pattern. </cell> 
<cell> Thread or Brunswick Pattern. </cell> 
<cell> King's Pattern </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons, per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 18s. </cell> 
<cell> 23s. </cell> 
<cell> 36s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Forks </cell> 
<cell> 30s. </cell> 
<cell> 42s. </cell> 
<cell> 58s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons </cell> 
<cell> 30s. </cell> 
<cell> 42s. </cell> 
<cell> 62s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Forks </cell> 
<cell> 40s. </cell> 
<cell> 55s. </cell> 
<cell> 70s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons </cell> 
<cell> 40s. </cell> 
<cell> 55s. </cell> 
<cell> 75s. </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Tea and Coffee Sets, Waiters, Candlesticks, &amp;c., at proportionate prices. All kinds of re-plating done by the patent process.</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="4">
<head>CHEMICALLY PURE NICKEL NOT PLATED.</head>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> Fiddle. </cell> 
<cell> Thread. </cell> 
<cell> King's. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons and Forks, full size, per doz </cell> 
<cell> 12s. </cell> 
<cell> 28s. </cell> 
<cell> 30s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons and Forks </cell> 
<cell> 10s. </cell> 
<cell> 21s. </cell> 
<cell> 25s. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons </cell> 
<cell> 5s. </cell> 
<cell> 11s. </cell> 
<cell> 12s. </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>WILLIAM S. BURTON</head><p>Has TEN LARGE SHOW-ROOMS (all communicating), exclusive of the shop, devoted solely to the show of <lb/> GENERAL FURNISHING IRONMONGERY, <lb/> including Cutlery, Nickel Silver, Plated, and Japanned Wares, Iron and Brass Bedsteads, so arranged and classified that purchasers may easily and at once make their selections.</p>
<p>Catalogues, with Engravings, sent (per post) free. The money returned for every article not approved of.</p>
<closer>39, OXFORD STREET (corner of Newman-street); Nos. 1 and 2, NEWMAN STREET; and 4 and 5, <lb/> PERRY'S PLACE.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1" n="[1]"/>
<opener>No. IX.&mdash;NOVEMBER, 1852.</opener>
<head>BLEAK HOUSE ADVERTISER.</head>
<div2>
<head>New Works to be published this Season.</head>
<div3 type="section">
<p>MR. BARTLETT'S NEW GIFT BOOK.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">On November</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">th, in super royal</hi> 8<hi rend="italics">vo, uniform with the &ldquo;Nile Boat,&rdquo;</hi>
<lb/> SICILY; ITS SCENERY AND ITS ANTIQUITIES: <lb/> Greek, Saracenic, and Norman.</p>
<p>By W. H. BARTLETT, <lb/> Author of &ldquo;Walks about Jerusalem,&rdquo; &ldquo;Forty Days in the Desert,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>This work will contain 31 beautiful Vignette Illustrations engraved on Steel, several Woodcuts, and <lb/> nearly 300 pages of Letterpress, handsomely printed and bound.</p>
</div3><div3><head>II.</head><p>  NEW WORKS BY THE REV. JOHN CUMMING, D.D.</p>
<p>EXPOSITORY READINGS ON THE BOOK OF REVELATIONS. Expositions of the Chapter read on Sabbath Evenings, in the Scottish National Church, Crown-court, Covent Garden, forming a CONTINUOUS AND COMPLETE COMMENTARY ON THE APOCALYPSE. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Early in November.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>III. </head><p> NEW SERIES OF LECTURES ON THE PENTATEUCH.</p>
<p>THE CHURCH BEFORE THE FLOOD; a Series of Lectures on the Book of GENESIS, by Rev. JOHN CUMMING, D.D., uniform with &ldquo;Apocalyptic Sketches.&rdquo; </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">At Christmas.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>IV. </head><p> MEMORIALS OF EARLY CHRISTIANITY. Presenting in a graphic, compact, and popular form, some of the Memorable Events of early Ecclesiastical History. By the Rev. J. G. MIALL, Author of &ldquo;Footsteps of our Forefathers.&rdquo; In post 8vo, with Illustrations. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">In November.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>V.</head><p>  NEW WORK BY THE AUTHOR OF &ldquo;MARY POWELL.&rdquo; <lb/> THE COLLOQUIES OF EDWARD OSBORNE, Citizen and Cloth Worker of London. Uniform with &ldquo;The Household of Sir Thomas More,&rdquo; &amp;c. In post 8vo, with Frontispiece, &amp;c., cloth antique. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">On November</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">th.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>VI. </head><p> THE OLD FOREST RANGER; Or, Wild Sports of India on THE NEILGHERRY HILLS, IN THE JUNGLES, AND ON THE PLAINS. By MAJOR WALTER CAMPBELL, of Skipness. New Edition. In post 8vo, with Illustrations on Steel. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Early in November.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>VII. </head><p> A SECOND SERIES OF <lb/> PILGRIMAGES TO ENGLISH SHRINES. By Mrs. S. C. Hall, With Notes and Illustrations by W. H. FAIRHOLT, F.S.A. In 8vo, handsomely bound and gilt. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">Early in November.</hi></p>
</div3><div3><head>VIII. </head><p> THE THIRD VOLUME OF <lb/> THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF WILLIAM JERDAN; with his Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences and Correspondence, during the last Forty Years. With a Portrait of L. E. L., engraved by Robinson, after the original by Pickersgill. </p>
<p>[<hi rend="italics">On November</hi> 1<hi rend="italics">st.</hi></p>

</div3><closer>ARTHUR HALL, VIRTUE, &amp; CO., 25, PATERNOSTER ROW.</closer></div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p2" n="2"/>
<opener>Now ready, price 6d.</opener>
<head>HOW TO PRINT, AND WHEN TO PUBLISH.</head>
<p>PRACTICAL ADVICE TO AUTHORS, <lb/>Possessors of Manuscripts, and Inexperienced Writers, on the efficient Publication of Books intended for general circulation or private distribution, sent gratis and post free to orders enclosing Six Stamps, addressed to MESSRS. SAUNDERS AND OTLEY, PUBLISHERS, CONDUIT-STREET, HANOVER-SQUARE, <lb/> Who have just ready for publication, <lb/> A NEW WORK BY MR. CARLETON. 3 vols.</p>
<p>II. <lb/> THE GOSSIP, BY THE HON. MRS. E. NORTON.</p>
<p>III. <lb/> THE VICISSITUDES OF COMMERCE. 2 vols.</p>
<p>By a Gentleman of high standing in the Commercial World.</p>
<p>IV. <lb/> A NEW NOVEL by the AUTHOR of SIN &amp; SORROW. 3 vols.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>NEW WORK by the Author of &ldquo;VANITY FAIR,&rdquo; &ldquo;PENDENNIS,&rdquo; &amp;c.</opener>
<head>Mr. Thackeray's Novel, <lb/> ENTITLED <lb/> The History of Henry Esmond, Esq.,</head><p>A Colonel in the service of Her Majesty Q. Anne, <lb/> WRITTEN BY HIMSELF, <lb/> Is now ready, and may be had at all the Libraries, in Three Volumes, <lb/> crown 8vo, price 1<hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi></p>
<closer>LONDON: SMITH, ELDER, &amp; CO., 65, CORNHILL.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Just published, crown 8vo, price 5s. cloth,</opener><head>SPIRITS OF THE PAST.</head>
<p>AN HISTORICAL POEM; with copious Biographical Notes. By NICHOLAS MICHELL, Author of &ldquo;Ruins <lb/> of many Lands,&rdquo; &amp;c.</p>
<p>CONTENTS:&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Scripture Characters:</hi> Cain to Esther.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Military Heroes:</hi> Xerxes to Napoleon.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Celebrated Women:</hi> Aspasia of Athens to Lady Jane Grey.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here we have vigour, picturesqueness, and variety. Let us add Mr. Michell is not only a skillful limner, but he dips his pencil in philosophy. The Third Book is a vision of fair women, and perhaps the most attractive portion of a volume which does not lack attraction in any one page.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Church and State Gazette.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;This work will be no less admired for the richness of its historical lore, than for the beauty of its diction, and the fidelity of its portraits. The sketch of Napoleon is very remarkable for its power; and the last great struggle at Waterloo is painted in vivid colours.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool Albion.</hi></p>
<closer>London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; CO, 85, Queen street, Cheapside; and all Booksellers.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>In Two Volumes, imperial 8vo, cloth, price &pound;4 10s.,</opener><head>THE IMPERIAL DICTIONARY, <lb/> ENGLISH, TECHNOLOGICAL, AND SCIENTIFIC,</head><p>Adapted to the Present State of Literature. Science, and Art. comprising ALL WORDS PURELY ENGLISH, and the principal and most generally used Technical and Scientific Terms, together with their Ktymologies, and their pronunciation, according to the best authorities.</p>
<p>ILLUSTRATED BY UPWARDS OF TWO THOUSAND ENGRAVINGS ON WOOD.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<opener>Just published, Volume 1, cloth, price &pound;2 7s. 6d.,</opener><head>THE IMPERIAL GAZETTEER; <lb/> A GENERAL DICTIONARY OF GEOGRAPHY; PHYSICAL, POLITICAL, STATISTICAL, AND DESCRIPTIVE.</head>
<p>Including Comprehensive Accounts of the Countries, Cities, Principal Towns, Villages, Seas, Lakes, Rivers, Islands, Mountains, Valleys, &amp;c., in the world. Illustrated by upwards of seven hundred Views, Maps, Plans, <lb/> &amp;c., complied from the latest and best authorities.</p>
<closer>BLACKIE &amp; SON, LONDON, EDINBURGH, AND GLASGOW.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p3" n="3"/>
<opener>On the 1st of November will be published, Part I., containing Four Plates, price 1s. 6d., to be completed in <lb/> Five Monthly Divisions.</opener>
<head>HANNAH BOLTON'S FIRST DRAWING BOOK.</head>
<p>A WALK THROUGH A HOUSE, SHOWN BY SCENES IN THE JOURNEY.</p>
<p>BY HANNAH BOLTON, Author of &ldquo;Drawing from Objects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The above will form a Series of Original Drawings, upon a new and philosophic plan, adapted for home instruction, and for schools, public and private, designed with the view of lawfully diminishing the labour of the master, and of giving intelligent assistance to the scholar; and while training the hand will instruct the mind, and lead to the higher attainment&mdash;that of drawing from the objects themselves.</p>
<closer>London: GROOMBRIDGE &amp; SONS, 5, Paternoster-row; and the Home and Colonial Schools, Gray's Inn-road.</closer>
</div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>TEGG'S CONCERTINA PRECEPTOR.</head>
<p>Imperial 8vo, sewed, price 2s.</p>
<p>CONCERTINA PRECEPTOR, containing the Rudiments of Music, Glossary of Musical Terms, &amp;c., Exercises and Scales; also a selection of the most popular Tunes, arranged and fingered in an easy manner for that fashionable instrument. By JAMES F. HASKINS, Member of the Royal Conservatory of Music at Paris, and Editor of the Geneuphonic Theory of Music.</p>
<p>ALSO MAY BE HAD.</p>
<p>The following New Editions of <lb/> HANCOCK'S IMPROVED FLUTE PRECEPTOR, price 2s.</p>
<p>HANCOCK'S VIOLIN PRECEPTOR, price 2s.</p>
<p>HANCOCK'S INSTRUCTIONS FOR THE ACCORDION, greatly enlarged, price 2s.</p>
<closer>London: WILLIAM TEGG &amp; Co., 85, Queen-street, Cheapside.</closer>
</div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>THE MOST BEAUTIFUL AND ACCURATE <lb/> EDITIONS OF THE</opener><head>ORATORIOS</head><p>are universally acknowledged to be those Edited by JOHN BISHOP, of Cheltenham, and published by ROBERT COCKS &amp; Co., of London.</p>
<p>These Editions are distinguished for extreme correctness (having been compared with the <hi rend="italics">original scores</hi>), bold notation, careful printing, handsome binding, and moderate price, each Vol. being 15s.</p>
<p>The arrangements give the full vocal score, combining in the accompaniment for the Organ and Pianoforte the instrumental effects of Handel's original score.</p>
<p>FOLIO SIZE, SO THAT THREE OR FOUR PERSONS CAN READ FROM ONE COPY.</p>
<p>ALSO <lb/> WARREN'S COMPLETE EDITION OF DR. BOYCE'S CATHEDRAL MUSIC, 3 vols., extra folio, &pound;6 6s.</p>
<div3>
<head>SOCIAL MUSIC.</head>
<p>NEW VOCAL DUETTS, by the highly popular composer, STEPHEN GLOVER, viz.:&mdash;What are the Wild Waves Saying?&mdash;The Murmuring Sea&mdash;Why do you Watch?&mdash;Tell me where do Fairies dwell?&mdash;A Voice from the Waves&mdash;The Stream and the Willow&mdash;Over the Waves we Float&mdash;and twenty others by the same. Each 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Also, TWELVE EASY PART SONGS (four voices), by FRANZ ABT, of Zurich, words by J. E. CARPENTER, 6s. And, <lb/> COCKS'S MUSICAL MISCELLANY, 16 pages quarto, on the first of every month, 5d.; stamped 6d.</p>
<closer>London: ROBERT COCKS &amp; CO, New Burlington-street, Publishers to the Queen.</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TEN GUINEA HARMONIUM</head><p>has the full compass of five octaves, a powerful rich tone, and never requires tuning: is suited for Churches, Chapels, Schools, &amp;c., producing a sustained tone, susceptible of the utmost expression. An extensive variety of HARMONIUMS, with the Patent Pianoforte Hammer Action, from Sixteen to Twenty Guineas each.</p>
<p>WARREN'S TUTOR for the above, 4s. WHEATSTONE &amp; CO., Inventors and Patentees of the Concertina, who were awarded the only Exhibition Prize Medal for Harmoniums, 20, CONDUIT STREET, REGENT STREET.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>AUTHENTICATED TARTANS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> CLANS AND FAMILIES OF SCOTLAND.</head>
<p>WITH HISTORICAL AND TRADITIONAL <lb/> ACCOUNTS.</p>
<p>Just published, a New Edition of this work, the only one in which the Scottish Tartans are painted in a style worthy of their national importance. In a work of this kind the beauty of the paintings must form one of its chief qualities, as nothing can be more incongruous than to see these ancient setts disfigured in the pages of those very works which profess to bequeath their beauties to posterity. The care with which the selection of the setts has been made, is evidenced by the fact that the work has received the approval of the Antiquarian Society of Scotland.</p>
<p>W. &amp; A. SMITH, Mauchline, Ayrshire; A. &amp; C. BLACK, <lb/> Edinburgh.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>IMPROVED MODERATOR LAMPS,</head><p>THOMAS PEARCE AND SON recommend their Lamps with great confidence to the notice of the public. They are made expressly for their house by the first manufacturer in Paris, and bear T. P. &amp; Son's name. Besides being cheaper, they possess the advantage over those usually offered for sale, of being on an improved principle; are finished with more care, and the patterns are in better taste; while their cleanliness, simplicity of management, and the extreme economy of a brilliant and unfading light are proverbial.</p>
<closer>THOMAS PEARCE &amp; SON, <lb/> 23, LUDGATE HILL.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>ALBANY LAMP AND CANDLE-MANUFACTORY &mdash;</head><p>CLARKE'S Russian Wax Candles, 1s. per lb., burn superior to all others. Best Albany Composite Candles, 8d. per lb., do not require snuffing; for ordinary purposes the Cheapest Candles that can be used, Moulds, 6d., Store Candles, 5d. per lb; Express Pale Soap. very old and dry, 54s. per cwt.; Good Yellow, 50s. and 44s.; Best Mottled, 56s.; Honey Soap, 1s.; Old Brown Windsor, 2s.; all other Scented Soaps, 1s. 6d. per lb.; Patent Albany Oil, 5s. 6d. per gallon, superior to Sperm; CLARKE'S Refined Oil for French Lamps, 4s. 6d. per gallon; Solar, 3s. 6d. Italian goods of the finest quality at the Wholesale Price; Lamps of every description manufactured on the premises, for cash only.</p>
<p>SAMUEL CLARKE, Albany Lamp and Candle Manufactory, 55, Albany-street, Regent's-park, London, within two minutes' walk of the Colosseum.</p>
<p>N.B. Country Orders, amounting to &pound;10 or upwards, Carriage Free.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE TOILET OF BEAUTY</head><p>furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which GOWLAND'S LOTION is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions. This elegant preparation comprehends the preservation of the complexion, both from the effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing its delicacy, and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.&mdash;&ldquo;ROBERT SHAW, London,&rdquo; is in while letters on the government stamp, without which none is genuine. Price 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4"/>
<head>PUBLIC LIBRARY, CONDUIT-STREET.</head>
<p>THE NEW TERMS of SUBSCRIPTION to this extensive and valuable Library are NOW READY. Subscriptions are graduated from One Guinea a year and upwards, according to the number of Volumes required. Every Subscriber has the choice of ALL THE NEW WORKS, and of all the Standard Works contained in the Library, accumulated during the last half century, comprising upwards of 100,000 Volumes in the English, French, Italian, and German Languages. Catalogues and Library Boxes gratis. Terms sent post free to orders, addressed, Messrs. SAUNDERS AND OTLEY, PUBLISHERS, CONDUIT-STREET. Also &ldquo;ADVICE TO AUTHORS ON THE EFFICIENT PUBLICATION OF NEW WORKS&rdquo; sent to orders enclosing Six Stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>UNDER THE IMMEDIATE PATRONAGE OF THE COURTS OF EUROPE, THE ARISTOCRACY, <lb/> AND THE UPPER CLASSES.</opener>
<head>ROWLAND'S MACASSAR OIL</head><p>is a delightfully fragrant and transparent preparation for the Hair, and as an invigorator and purifier, beyond all precedent. In dressing the hair, nothing can equal the effect of Rowlands' Macassar Oil, either on natural or artificial hair, rendering it so admirably soft that it will lie in any direction, producing beautifully flowing curls, and imparting a transcendent lustre.&mdash;Price 3s. 6d., 7s, Family Bottles (equal to four small), 10s. 6d., and double that size, 21s. per bottle.</p>
<div3>
<head>ROWLANDS' KALYDOR.</head>
<p>For the SKIN and COMPLEXION, is unequalled for its rare and inestimable qualities. The radiant bloom it imparts to the CHEEK; the softness and delicacy which it induces on the HANDS and ARMS; its capability of soothing irritation and removing CUTANEOUS DEFECTS, DISCOLORATIONS, and all unsightly appearances, render it indispensable to every toilet.&mdash;Price 4s. 6d. and 8s. 6d. per bottle.</p>
</div3><div3>
<head>ROWLANDS' ODONTO, <lb/> OR, PEARL DENTIFRICE.</head>
<p>A WHITE POWDER compounded of the choicest and most recherch&eacute; Ingredients of the ORIENTAL HERBAL. It bestows on the teeth a Pearl-like whiteness, frees them from Tartar, and prevents premature decay. It induces a healthy action of the GUMS, and renders the BREATH sweet and pure.&mdash;Price 2s. 9d. per box.</p>
<p>BEWARE OF SPURIOUS IMITATIONS!!! <lb/> The ONLY GENUINE of each bears the Name of &ldquo;ROWLANDS' &rdquo; preceding that of the Article on the Wrapper or Label. Sold by them at 20, Hatton Garden, London, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>RIMMEL'S TOILET VINEGAR</head><p>(as exhibited in the Fountain at the Crystal Palace) is far superior to Eau-de-Cologne as a Tonic and Refreshing Lotion for the Toilet or Bath; a reviving Perfume, a pleasant Dentifrice, and a powerful Dixinfectant for Apartments and Sick Rooms. Its numerous useful and sanitary properties render it an indispensable requisite in all families.</p>
<p>Price 2s. 6d. and 5s.</p>
<div3>
<head>RIMMEL'S HAIR DYE</head><p>imparts instantaneously to the Hair, Whiskers, &amp;c., a natural and permanent Black or Brown Shade, without the trouble or danger attending other Dyes.&mdash;Price 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>RIMMEL'S Guards' Bouquet, Jockey Club Bouquet, and other fashionable perfumes. RIMMEL'S Odontine for the Teeth, Nutritive Cream for the Hair, &amp;c., are also highly recommended.&mdash;Beware of counterfeits.</p>
<p>Sold by all Perfumers and Chemists, and by E. RIMMEL, 39. Gerard-street, Soho, London</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>&ldquo;THE BEST IS THE CHEAPEST.&rdquo;</head>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> The Best Congon Tea </cell> 
<cell> 3s. </cell> 
<cell> 8d. </cell> 
<cell> per 1b. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Best Imperial Souchong Tea </cell> 
<cell> 4s. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> per 1b. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Best Moyune Gunpowder </cell> 
<cell> 5s. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> per 1b. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Best Plantation Coffee </cell> 
<cell> 1s. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> per 1b. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Best Mocha Coffee </cell> 
<cell> 1s. </cell> 
<cell> 4d. </cell> 
<cell> per 1b. </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Tea or Coffee to the value of 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> or upwards sent, Carriage Free, to any part of England, by <lb/> PHILLIPS &amp; COMPANY, <lb/> TEA MERCHANTS, <lb/> 8, KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY, LONDON.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>SOYER'S RELISH.</head>
<p>&ldquo;To describe the Sauce would be to make our renders hungry,&mdash;rich, savoury, exotic, it infuses an ambrosial flavour into the substance on which it is poared.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Bell's Life.</hi></p>
<p>THIS JUSTLY CELEBRATED SAUCE is now in universal use throughout the world. The great renown acquired by M. SOYER, having induced the introduction of several imitations of his Relish, purchasers are requested particularly to observe that every genuine bottle bears his portrait on the label, accompanied by the names of his wholesale Agents, <lb/> CROSSE AND BLACKWELL, 21, SOHO SQUARE, LONDON, <lb/> of whom also may be had his Original Sauces for Ladies and Gentlemen.</p>
<closer>GORE HOUSE, KENSINGTON.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="5" id="p5"/>
<head>RODGERS'S IMPROVED SHIRT.</head>
<p>No. 84.</p>
<p>31s. 6d. &amp; 37s. 6d, the Half-dozen.</p>
<p>THE most comfortable and perfect-fitting Shirts extant, combining the highest degree of excellence at the smallest cost. Satisfaction (as usual) guaranteed, or the money returned.</p>
<p>Superb Dress Shirts for evening wear, 6s. 6d., 7s, 6d., and 8s. 6d, each. Also, Fashionable Coloured Shirts, ready made, or made to order, 20s. 26s., and 31s. 6d. the half-dozen. A choice of 200 New Patterns.</p>
<p>The general Ready-made Stock is the best, the cheapest, and the largest assortment of Shirts in London, and embraces all the recent improvements in the art.</p>
<p>Illustrated Priced Lists, with directions for self-measurement, and full particulars, gratis and post-free.</p>
<p>Patterns of the new and elegant designs for Coloured Shirts sent post-paid on receipt of Four Stamps.</p>
<p>FODGERS &amp; CO., Shirt Makers, 59, St. Martin's-lane, Charing Cross, and No. 29, at the Corner of New-street, Covent-garden, London. Established Sixty Years.&mdash;N.B. Boys' Shirts in all Sizes.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT!</head><head>METALLIC PEN MAKER TO THE QUEEN.</head>
<head><sic corr="BY">RY</sic> ROYAL COMMAND.</head>
<p>JOSEPH GILLOTT most respectfully begs to inform the Commercial World, Scholastic institutions, and the Public generally, that by a novel application of his unrivalled Machinery for making Steel Pens, and in accordance with the scientific spirit of the times he has introduced a <hi rend="italics">new series</hi> of his useful productions, which for <hi rend="italics">excellence of temper, quality of material,</hi> and, above all, <hi rend="italics">cheapness in price,</hi> he believes will ensure universal approbation, and defy competition. Each pen bears the impress of his name as a guarantee of quality; and they are put up in the usual style of Boxes, containing One Gross each, with Label outside, and fac-simile of his signature.</p>
<closer>
Victoria Works, Graham-street, Birmingham.<lb/>April 20th, 1852.
</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS.</head>
<p>HOLLOWAY'S OINTMENT AND PILLS have effected another wonderful cure of a bad leg, of seven years standing.&mdash;Extract of a letter from Mr. E. Pollard, druggist, of 32, Catherine-street, Devonport, dated May, 19, 1852, to Professor Holloway:&mdash;&ldquo;Sir,&mdash;Mr. Blanker, of Charlotte-street, Newpassage, near Devonport, suffered severely, for more than seven years, from a wound in his leg. He tried every remedy that medical aid could devise, but in vain, as it would not heal by their treatment. At length he had recourse to your ointment and pills, which in the course of a few weeks, perfectly cured it, and he is now in most excellent health.&rdquo; Sold by all Druggists, and at Professor Holloway's Establishment, 244, Strand, London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>Chubb's Fire-proof Safes and Locks.</head>
<p>CHUBB &amp; SON <lb/> Have now on Sale, at their Warehouses, an Assortment <lb/> of their <lb/> FIRE-PROOF SAFES, <lb/> WHICH GAINED THE PRIZE MEDAL, WITH <lb/> SPECIAL APPROBATION, <lb/> at the Great Exhibition, this distinction being awarded to them SOLELY by the Jurors of Class XXII., after a careful comparison with those of other makers from all parts of England.</p>
<p>These SAFES, undoubtedly the MOST SECURE FROM FORCE, FRAUD, and FIRE, are sold at moderate prices.</p>
<p>CHUBB'S LOCKS, with all the recent improvements, CASH BOXES and DEED BOXES of all sizes, may be inspected.</p>
<p>IRON DOORS and FRAMES for Strong Rooms.</p>
<p>Complete Lists, with Prices, will be sent on application.</p>
<p>CHUBB &amp; SON, 57, St. Paul's Churchyard, London; 28, Lord-street, Liverpool; 16, Market-street, Manchester; and Hornsley Fields, Wolverhampton.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>HUBERT'S ROSEATE POWDER</head><p>is the most certain and elegant preparation for the removal of superfluous hair on the arms, neck, and face, so inimical to beauty. The genuine is perfectly innocent, is easy and pleasant to use, and has been signed &ldquo;G. H. Hogard&rdquo; for the last 40 years. Sold for the proprietor by Mr. HOOPER, Chemist, 24, Russell-street, Covent-garden, and 43, London-bridge, City, and by all respectable Perfumers, in packets, price 4s.; double ditto, 7s.; or by post, free, for 50 or 88 postage stamps.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>BRITISH COLLEGE of HEALTH</head><p>Hamilton-place, New-road, London.</p>
<p>FOREIGN GENERAL AGENTS FOR THE SALE OF <lb/> MORISON'S PILLS, <lb/> THE VEGETABLE UNIVERSAL MEDICINE.</p>
<p>
<table rows="38" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Amsterdam </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Jacob Meihuzen. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Baltimore (U.S.) </cell> 
<cell> J. C. French and Son. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Barbadoes </cell> 
<cell> J. Montefiore and Co. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Barcelona (Spain) </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. Charles Sola, Miret, and Cuyas. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Basle (Switzerland) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Roderick Scholp. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Brody (Germany) </cell> 
<cell> N. Kornfeld, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Buffalo (U.S.) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Czeicke. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cadiz </cell> 
<cell> Mr. J. Bensusan. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Calcutta </cell> 
<cell> T. Gardner, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cape Breton </cell> 
<cell> Lieut. J. M`Kinnon. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Carthagena </cell> 
<cell> Rafael Cauto, Muralla del Mar. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Constantinople </cell> 
<cell> Mr. A. Stampa. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Copenhagen </cell> 
<cell> Mr. C. S. Holm and Mr. Michaelsen. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Cracow </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Muldner. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Curacoa (W.I.) </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. Senior. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Douglas (I. of Man) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Johnson. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Elsinore </cell> 
<cell> Mr. O. S. Steenburg. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frankfort </cell> 
<cell> Berck, Fr&egrave;res. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> George Town City (Demerara) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. John M`Douall. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gibraltar </cell> 
<cell> Mr. T. H. Roberts. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Guernsey </cell> 
<cell> Mr. James Cochrane. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Halifax (N.S.) </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. A. and W. Mackiulay. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Hamburg </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. Krauskopf and Co. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Kempton (Bavaria) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. M. Gayrhos. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Kingston (Jamaica) </cell> 
<cell> Miss Kington. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Melbourne (Port Phillip) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. A. Charlwood. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Madras </cell> 
<cell> R. L. Pereira, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Madrid </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. Saavedra and Co. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Matanzas (Cuba) </cell> 
<cell> Dr. Ambrosio C. Sauto, Calle del Medio, No. 13. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Mexico </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Jean Togne. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Montreal </cell> 
<cell> Mr. R. Trudeau. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> New York (U.S.) </cell> 
<cell> Messrs. Firth, Pond and Co. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Odessa (Russia) </cell> 
<cell> Wm. Wagner. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Paris </cell> 
<cell> M. Arthaud, 33, Rue Louis-le grand. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Passau </cell> 
<cell> Carl Herman. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pernambuco (Brazils) </cell> 
<cell> A. S. Corbett, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Valencia </cell> 
<cell> Mr. Antonio Andrews. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Bishop's Auckland (New Zealand) </cell> 
<cell> Mr. R. Parris. </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="6" id="p6"/>
<head>CHILDREN'S FROCKS, COATS, &amp; PELISSES</head><p>of every description, <lb/> LONG AND SHORT ROBES. WITH EVERY <lb/> OTHER REQUISITE FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p>
<p>IN FULL DRESS.</p>
<p>WALKING AND SCHOOL WEAR.</p>
<p>SEVERAL HUNDREDS CONSTANTLY ON <lb/> VIEW, <lb/> AT SHEARMAN'S, 5, FINSBURY PAVEMENT, <lb/> BETWEEN THE BANK AND FINSBURY SQUARE.</p>
<p>INFANTS' DRESSES, CLOAKS, HOODS, <lb/> HATS, BONNETS, ROBES, CAPS, GOWNS, OPEN <lb/> SHIRTS, ROBE BLANKETS, <lb/> BOYS' AND GIRLS' OVER GARMENTS, <lb/> WITH EVERY OTHER ARTICLE IN CLOTHING <lb/> REQUIRED FOR A YOUNG FAMILY.</p>
<p>BABY LINEN IN COMPLETE SETS OR OTHERWISE.</p>
<p>TRIMMED BASSINET BASKETS AND CUSHIONS.</p>
<p>An ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLET, affording additional <lb/> information, sent free on receipt of a paid letter.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GORGET PATENT SELF ADJUSTING SHIRT</head><p>THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> TO FASTEN AT THE BACK, <lb/> WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p>
<p>A most perfect and easy-fitting Shirt, and by a simple invention of the Patentee, adjusts itself to all movements of the body, both back and front, either walking, sitting, or riding. Price, including the REGISTERED ELLIPTIC WRISTBAND, 42s. the half dozen. The Elliptic Collar, quite unique, in all shapes, with Patent Elastic Fastening, 12s. the dozen. The Patent Elastic Collar Fastening can be attached to any Collar, opening back or front Six sent by post on receipt of 13 Postage Stamps. Illustrated Priced List forwarded free.</p>
<p>THE ELLIPTIC COLLAR, <lb/> TO FASTEN IN FRONT.</p>
<p>WITH PATENT ELASTIC FASTENING.</p>
<list>
<head>Directions for Self Measurement.</head>
<item>1. Round the Chest, taken tight over the Shirt.</item>
<item>2. Round the Waist, taken tight over the Shirt.</item>
<item>3. Round the Neck, taken about the middle of the Throat.</item>
<item>4. Round the Wrist.</item>
<item>5. The length of Coat Sleeve, from the centre of Back, down the scam of Sleeve to bottom of cuff.</item>
<item>6. The length of Shirt from the bottom of Neckband.</item>
</list>
<closer>PATENTEE, <lb/> GEO. P. COOPER, <lb/> TAILOR TO HER MAJESTY &amp; PRINCE <lb/> ALBERT, <lb/> 6, Suffolk-street, Pall Mall East, <lb/> London.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>THE GENTLEMAN'S REAL HEAD OF HAIR, OR INVISIBLE PERUKE.&mdash;</head><p>The principle upon which this Peruke is made is so superior to everything yet produced, that the Manufacturer invites the honour of a visit from the Sceptic and the Connoisseur, that one may be convinced, and the other gratified, by inspecting this and other novel and beautiful specimens of the Perruqueian Art, at the Establishment of the Sole Inventor, F. BROWNE, 47, FENCHURCH-STREET.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>F. BROWNE'S INFALLIBLE MODE OF MEASURING THE HEAD.</head>
<row>
<cell> Round the Head in manner of a fillet, leaving the Ears loose </cell> 
<cell> As dotted 1 to 1. </cell> 
<cell> Inches. </cell> 
<cell> Eighths. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> From the Forehead over to the poll, as deep each way as required </cell> 
<cell> As dotted 2 to 2. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> From one Temple to the other, across the rise or Crown of the Head to where the Hair grows </cell> 
<cell> As marked 3 to 3. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>THE CHARGE FOR THIS UNIQUE HEAD OF HAIR, <lb/> ONLY &pound;1 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="7" id="pxxx3"/>
<head>PRIZE MEDAL.</head>
<head>WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN'S <lb/> GOLD CHAINS.</head>
<p>By Troy Weight, and Workmanship at Wholesale <lb/> Manufacturers' Prices.</p>
<p>THE Great Exhibition having established the Advantage of Purchasing from the Wholesale Manufacturer, wherever it can be accomplished, and thereby dispensing with an intermediate profit, WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to announce that, in obedience to the numerous calls made upon them, they have thrown open their Manufactory to the Public at the same prices they have been in the habit (for the last half century) of charging to the Trade in London, India, and the Colonies.</p>
<p>WATHERSTON &amp; BROGDEN beg to caution the Public against the Electro Gold Chain and Polished Zinc Gold, so extensively put forth in the present day, under the titles of &ldquo;Pure Gold&rdquo; and &ldquo;Fine Gold,&rdquo; and to call attention to the genuine Gold Chains made from their own ingots, and sold by Troy Weight at its bullion or realisable value.</p>
<p>The system of Weighing Chains against Sovereigns being one of the greatest frauds ever practised on the Public, WATHERSTON AND BROGDEN guarantee the Gold in their Chains, and will re-purchase it at the price charged; the workmanship according to the intricacy or simplicity of the pattern.</p>
<p>EXAMPLE.&mdash;Intrinsic value of a Chain of 15-Carat</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell> Gold, weighing 1 &frac18; Ounces </cell> 
<cell> &pound;3 </cell> 
<cell> 19 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Supposing the workmanship to be </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Total </cell> 
<cell> &pound;5 </cell> 
<cell> 19 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>By this arrangement, the purchaser will see at a glance the proportion charged for <hi rend="italics">labour</hi> compared with the <hi rend="italics">Bullion</hi> in a Gold Chain, and being always able to realise the one, will have only to decide on the value of the other.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">An extensive assortment of Jewellery, all of the first quality, made at their Manufactory.</hi></p>
<closer>16, HENRIETTA STREET, COVENT GARDEN, LONDON.</closer>
<closer>ESTABLISHED A.D. 1798.</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>MOTHERS! MOTHERS!! MOTHERS!!!</head>
<p>THE BEST MEDICINE IN THE WORLD for INFANTS AND YOUNG CHILDREN IS ATKINSON AND BARKER'S ROYAL INFANTS' PRESERVATIVE.&mdash;Under the Patronage of the Queen.&mdash;The high and universal celebrity which this medicine continues to maintain for the prevention and cure of those disorders incident to infants; affording instant relief in convulsions, flatulency, affections of the bowels, difficult teething, the thrush, rickets, measles, hooping-cough, cow-pox, or vaccine inoculation, and may be given with safety immediately after birth. It is no misnomer cordial!&mdash;no stupefactive, deadly narcotic!&mdash;but a veritable preserver of infants! Mothers would do well in always keeping it in the nursery. Many thousands of children are annually saved by this much-esteemed medicine, which is an immediate remedy, and the infants rather like it than otherwise.</p>
<p>Prepared only by ROBERT BARKER, Ollerenshaw Hall, Chapel-en-le-Frith, Derbyshire, late of Manchester, (Chemist to Her most Gracious Majesty Queen Victoria), in bottles at 1s. 1&frac12;d., 2s. 9d., 4s. 6d., and 11s. each.</p>
<p>Sold by all druggists and medicine vendors throughout the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;Observe the name of &ldquo;ATKINSON &amp; BARKER,&rdquo; on the Government Stamp. Established in the year 1793.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS</head><p>Differ from other Patterns, not merely in shape and design, but in their great superiority of Fit, quality of Material, and Workmanship.&mdash;<hi rend="italics">Globe, April</hi> 12, 1852. They are of two prices; viz. Six for 40s.; Second Quality Six for 30s. in both of which the principle is strictly carried out.</p>
<p>List of Prices, and mode of Self-measurement sent free per Post.</p>
<p>FORD'S REGISTERED SHIRT COLLARS, 11s. per dozen.</p>
<p>Patterns of the New Coloured Shirtings in every variety of Colours. Upwards of 200 different styles for making FORD'S EUREKA SHIRTS sent to select from on the receipt of six postage stamps. Price 27s. the half dozen.</p>
<closer>RICHARD FORD, 38, POULTRY, <lb/> LONDON, (Late 185, Strand.)</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb n="8" id="pxxx4"/>
<head>Messrs. POULSON &amp; Co.'s REGISTERED PARDESSUS,
<lb/>
OF FINE AUSTRALIAN and LLAMA WOOLS, (6TH &amp; 7TH VICTORIA, CAP. 65), <lb/> FOR WALKING OR RIDING.</head>
<p>THIS is an improved style of Coat, of a light convenient form, which admits of its being worn either over or without the ordinary coat. It is neatly and handsomely made, care being bestowed in its construction, to impart to it that graceful and appropriate character which, since its first introduction, has so greatly recommended it to public favour; it is produced in all colours with silk sleeve linings, at the very moderate price of TWO GUINEAS; and for Winter wear, richly lined and quilted, TWO-AND-A-HALF and THREE GUINEAS. The IMPROVED WINTER GUINEA TROUSERS are also ready for selection from a choice variety of patterns.</p>
<p>In London only at the Sole Patentees and Manufacturers, B. POULSON &amp; CO.'s, Court, Clerical, Naval and Military Tailors, 94 REGENT STREET, and in the country and colonies of their recognised Agents.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>GREAT EXHIBITION, JURY REPORT.</head>
<p>CLASS XXIX., p. 661.</p>
<p>&ldquo;W. &amp; J. SANGSTER, Prize Medal for Silk Parasols and Umbrellas of excellent quality, and for their application of Alpaca Cloth to the Coverings of Umbrellas and Parasols.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the merit in an Umbrella consists in its strength, combined with extreme lightness, W. &amp; J. S. beg to say that they are now prepared to offer for the first time an Umbrella made on Fox's Paragon Frames, possessing these requirements, and rendering it an article perfectly unique, whether in Silk or Alpaca.</p>
<p>W. AND J. SANGSTER,</p><list>
<item>140, Regent Street.</item>
<item>94, Fleet Street.</item>
<item>10, Royal Exchange.</item>
<item>75, Cheapside.</item>
</list><closer>AGENTS FOR THE UNITED STATES, <lb/> MESSRS. F. DERBY &amp; CO., 12, PARK PLACE, NEW YORK.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="ii"/>
<p><figure><p><hi rend="italics">The Young Man of the Name of Guppy.</hi></p></figure></p>
</div1>

<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piv" n="iv"/>
<p>An accident having happened to the Plate, it has been necessary to cancel one of the Illustrations to the present Number. It will be supplied in the next Monthly Part.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pv" n="v"/>
<opener><hi rend="italics">In Weekly Numbers, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.; in Monthly Parts, and in Half-yearly Volumes,</hi></opener><head>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</head>
<p>A Weekly Journal, conducted by CHARLES DICKENS.</p>
<p>DESIGNED FOR THE INSTRUCTION AND AMUSEMENT OF ALL CLASSES OF READERS, AND TO ASSIST <lb/> IN THE DISCUSSION OF THE SOCIAL QUESTIONS OF THE TIME.</p>
<p>FIVE VOLUMES are published, price 5<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> each, in cloth boards, and are always on sale,</p><div2>
<opener><hi rend="italics">Also, published at the end of every Month, at the same Office, price</hi> 2<hi rend="italics">d., or stamped for post,</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">d.,</hi>
</opener><head>THE HOUSEHOLD NARRATIVE OF <lb/> CURRENT EVENTS;</head><p>Which being declared, by the Judgment of the Court of Exchequer, a Legal Publication, not coming <lb/> within the provisions of the Stamp Act, will be regularly continued and much improved.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The First and Second Volumes, being a Record of the Public Events of</hi> 1850&mdash;51, <hi rend="italics">may always</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">be had, price</hi> 3<hi rend="italics">s. each, neatly bound in cloth.</hi></p>
<p>OFFICE, No. 16, WELLINGTON STREET NORTH. Sold by all Booksellers and Newsmen.</p>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter">
<pb id="p257" n="257"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXVI. <lb/> SHARPSHOOTERS.</head>
<p>WINTRY morning, looking with dull eyes and sallow face upon the neighbourhood of Leicester Square, finds its inhabitants unwilling to get out of bed. Many of them are not early risers at the brightest of times, being birds of night who roost when the sun is high, and are wide awake and keen for prey when the stars shine out. Behind dingy blind and curtain, in upper story and garret, skulking more or less under false names, false hair, false titles, false jewellery, and false histories, a colony of brigands lie in their first sleep. Gentlemen of the green baize road who could discourse, from personal experience, of foreign galleys and home treadmills; spies of strong governments that eternally quake with weakness and miserable fear, broken traitors, cowards, bullies, gamesters, shufflers, swindlers, and false witnesses; some not unmarked by the branding-iron, beneath their dirty braid; all with more cruelty in them than was in Nero, and more crime than is in Newgate. For, howsoever bad the devil can be in fustian or smock-frock (and he can be very bad in both) he is a more designing, callous, and intolerable devil when he sticks a pin in his shirt-front, calls himself a gentleman, backs a card or color, plays a game or so of billiards, and knows a little about bills and promissory notes, than in any other form he wears. And in such form Mr. Bucket shall find him, when he will, pervading the tributary channels of Leicester Square.</p>
<p>But the wintry morning wants him not and wakes him not. It wakes Mr. George of the Shooting Gallery, and his Familiar. They arise, roll up and stow away their mattresses. Mr. George, having shaved himself before a looking-glass of minute proportions, then marches out, bare-headed and bare-chested, to the Pump, in the little yard, and anon comes back shining with yellow soap, friction, drifting rain, and exceedingly cold water. As he rubs himself upon a large jack-towel, blowing like a military sort of diver just come up: his crisp hair curling tighter and tighter on his sunburnt temples, the more he rubs it, so that it looks as if it never could be loosened by any less coercive instrument than an iron rake or a curry-comb&mdash;as he rubs, and puffs, and polishes, and blows, turning his head from side to side, the more conveniently to excoriate his throat, and standing with his body well bent forward, to keep the wet from his martial legs&mdash;Phil, on his knees lighting a fire, looks round as if it were enough washing for him to see all that done, and sufficient renovation, for one day, to take in the superfluous health his master throws off.</p>
<p>When Mr. George is dry, he goes to work to brush his head with two hard brushes at once, to that unmerciful degree that Phil, shouldering his way round the gallery in the act of sweeping it, winks with sympathy. This chafing over, the ornamental part of Mr. George's toilet is soon performed. He fills his pipe, lights it, and marches up and down smoking, as his custom is, while Phil, raising a powerful odour of hot rolls and coffee, prepares breakfast. He smokes gravely, and marches in
<pb n="258" id="p258"/>
slow time. Perhaps this morning's pipe is devoted to the memory of Gridley in his grave.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And so, Phil,&rdquo; says George of the Shooting Gallery, after several turns in silence; &ldquo;you were dreaming of the country last night?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Phil, by the bye, said as much, in a tone of surprise, as he scrambled out of bed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, guv'ner.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What was it like?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hardly know what it was like, guv'ner,&rdquo; says Phil, considering.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How did you know it was the country?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;On accounts of the grass, I think. And the swans upon it,&rdquo; says Phil, after further consideration.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What were the swans doing on the grass.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They was a eating of it, I expect,&rdquo; says Phil.</p>
<p>The master resumes his march, and the man resumes his preparation of breakfast. It is not necessarily a lengthened preparation, being limited to the setting forth of very simple breakfast requisites for two, and the broiling of a rasher of bacon at the fire in the rusty grate; but as Phil has to sidle round a considerable part of the gallery for every object he wants, and never brings two objects at once, it takes time under the circumstances. At length the breakfast is ready. Phil announcing it, Mr. George knocks the ashes out of his pipe on the hob, stands his pipe itself in the chimney corner, and sits down to the meal. When he has helped himself, Phil follows suit; sitting at the extreme end of the little oblong table, and taking his plate on his knees. Either in humility, or to hide his blackened hands, or because it is his natural manner of eating.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The country,&rdquo; says Mr. George, plying his knife and fork; &ldquo;why, I suppose you never clapped your eyes on the country, Phil?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I see the marshes once,&rdquo; says Phil, contentedly eating his breakfast.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What marshes?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">The</hi> marshes, commander,&rdquo; returns Phil.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where are they?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know where they are,&rdquo; says Phil; &ldquo;but I see 'em, guv'ner. They was flat. And miste.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Governor and Commander are interchangeable terms with Phil, expressive of the same respect and deference, and applicable to nobody but Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was born in the country, Phil.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Was you indeed, commander?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes. And bred there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Phil elevates his one eyebrow, and, after respectfully staring at his master to express interest, swallows a great gulp of coffee, still staring at him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's not a bird's note that I don't know,&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;Not many an English leaf or berry that I couldn't name. Not many a tree that I couldn't climb yet, if I was put to it. I was a real country boy, once. My good mother lived in the country.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She must have been a fine old lady, gav'ner,&rdquo; Phil observes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay! and not so old either, five-and-thirty years ago,&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;But I'll wager that at ninety she would be near as upright as me, and near as broad across the shoulders.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did she die at ninety, guv'ner?&rdquo; enquires Phil.</p>
<pb n="259" id="p259"/>
<p>&ldquo;No. Bosh! Let her rest in peace, God bless her!&rdquo; says the trooper. &ldquo;What set me on about country boys, and runaways and good for nothings? You, to be sure! So you never clapped your eyes upon the country&mdash;marshes and dreams excepted. Eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Phil shakes his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you want to see it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;N-no, I don't know as I do, particular,&rdquo; says Phil.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The town's enough for you, eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, you see, commander,&rdquo; says Phil, &ldquo;I ain't acquainted with any-think else, and I doubt if I ain't a getting too old to take to novelties.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How old <hi rend="italics">are</hi> you, Phil?&rdquo; asks the trooper, pausing as he conveys his smoking saucer to his lips.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'm something with a eight in it,&rdquo; says Phil. &ldquo;It can't be eighty. Nor yet eighteen. It's betwixt 'em, somewheres.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George, slowly putting down his saucer without tasting the contents, is laughingly beginning, &ldquo;Why, what the deuce, Phil&rdquo;&mdash;when he stops, seeing that Phil is counting on his dirty fingers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was just eight,&rdquo; says Phil, &ldquo;agreeable to the parish calculation, when I went with the tinker. I was sent on a errand, and I see him a sittin under a old buildin with a fire all to himself wery comfortable, and he says, &lsquo;Would you like to come along a me, my man?&rsquo; I says &lsquo;Yes,&rsquo; and him and me and the fire goes home to Clerkenwell together. That was April Fool Day. I was able to count up to ten; and when April Fool Day come round again, I says to myself, &lsquo;Now, old chap, you're one and a eight in it.&rsquo; April Fool Day after that, I says, &lsquo;Now old chap, you're two and a eight in it.&rsquo; In course of time, I come to ten and a eight in it; two tens and a eight in it. When it got so high, it got the upper hand of me; but this is how I always know there's a eight in it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; says Mr. George, resuming his breakfast. &ldquo;And where's the tinker?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Drink put him in the hospital, guv'ner, and the hospital put him&mdash;in a glass-case, I <hi rend="italics">have</hi> heerd,&rdquo; Phil replies mysteriously.</p>
<p>&ldquo;By that means you got promotion? Took the business, Phil?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, commander, I took the business. Such as it was. It wasn't much of a beat &mdash; round Saffron Hill, Hatton Garden, Clerkenwell, Smiffeld, and there&mdash;poor neighbourhood, where they uses up the kettles till they're past mending. Most of the tramping tinkers used to come and lodge at our place; that was the best part of my master's earnings. But they didn't come to me. I warn't like him. He could sing 'em a good song. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> couldn't! He could play 'em a tune on any sort of pot you please, so as it was iron or block tin. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> never could do nothing with a pot, but mend it or bile it&mdash;never had a note of music in me. Besides, I was too ill-looking, and their wives complained of me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They were mighty particular. You would pass muster in a crowd, Phil!&rdquo; says the trooper with a pleasant smile.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, guv'ner,&rdquo; returns Phil, shaking his head. &ldquo;No, I shouldn't. I was passable enough when I went with the tinker, though nothing to boast of then: but what with blowing the fire with my mouth when I was young, and spileing my complexion, and singeing my hair off, and swallering the smoke; and what with being nat'rally unfort'nate in the way of running against hot metal, and marking myself by sich means; and what with having turn-ups with the tinker as I got older, almost whenever he was too far gone in drink&mdash;which was almost always&mdash;my beauty
<pb n="260" id="p260"/>
was queer, wery queer, even at that time. As to since; what with a dozen years in a dark forge, where the men was given to larking; and what with being scorched in a accident at a gasworks; and what with being blowed out of winder, case-filling at the firework business; I am ugly enough to be made a show on!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Resigning himself to which condition with a perfectly satisfied manner, Phil begs the favor of another cup of coffee. While drinking it, he says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was after the case-filling blow-up, when I first see you, commander. You remember?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I remember, Phil. You were walking along in the sun.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Crawling, guv'ner, again a wall&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;True, Phil&mdash;shouldering your way on&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In a nightcap!&rdquo; exclaims Phil, excited.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In a nightcap&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And hobbling with a couple of sticks!&rdquo; cries Phil, still more excited.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With a couple of sticks. When&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When you stops, you know,&rdquo; cries Phil, putting down his cup and saucer, and hastily removing his plate from his knees, &ldquo;and says to me, &lsquo;What, comrade! You have been in the wars!&rsquo; I didn't say much to you, commander, then, for I was took by surprise, that a person so strong and healthy and bold as you was, should stop to speak to such a limping bag of bones as I was. But you says to me, says you, delivering it out of your chest as hearty as possible, so that it was like a glass of something hot, &lsquo;What accident have you met with? You have been badly hurt. What's amiss, old boy? Cheer up, and tell us about it!&rsquo; Cheer up! I was cheered already! I says as much to you, you says more to me, I says more to you, you says more to me, and here I am, commander! Here I am, commander!&rdquo; cries Phil, who has started from his chair and <sic corr="unaccountably">unnaccountably</sic> begun to sidle away. &ldquo;If a mark's wanted, or if it will improve the business, let the customers take aim at me. They can't spoil <hi rend="italics">my</hi> beauty. <hi rend="italics">I</hi>'m all right. Come on! If they want a man to box at, let 'em box at me. Let 'em knock me well about the head. <hi rend="italics">I</hi> don't mind! If they want a light-weight, to be throwed for practice, Cornwall, Devonshire, or Lancashire, let 'em throw me. They won't hurt <hi rend="italics">me.</hi> I have been throwed, all sorts of styles, all my life!&rdquo;</p>
<p>With this unexpected speech, energetically delivered, and accompanied by action illustrative of the various exercises referred to, Phil Squod shoulders his way round three sides of the gallery, and abruptly tacking off at his commander, makes a butt at him with his head, intended to express devotion to his service. He then begins to clear away the breakfast.</p>
<p>Mr. George, after laughing cheerfully, and clapping him on the shoulder, assists in these arrangements, and helps to get the gallery into business order. That done, he takes a turn at the dumb-bells; and afterwards weighing himself, and opining that he is getting &ldquo;too fleshy,&rdquo; engages with great gravity in solitary broadsword practice. Meanwhile, Phil has fallen to work at his usual table, where he screws and unscrews, and cleans, and files, and whistles into small apertures, and blackens himself more and more, and seems to do and undo everything that can be done and undone about a gun.</p>
<p>Master and man are at length disturbed by footsteps in the passage, where they make an unusual sound, denoting the arrival of unusual company. These steps, advancing nearer and nearer to the gallery, bring
<pb n="261" id="p261"/>
into it a group, at first sight scarcely reconcilable with any day in the year but the fifth of November.</p>
<p>It consists of a limp and ugly figure carried in a chair by two bearers, and attended by a lean female with a face like a pinched mask, who might be expected immediately to recite the popular verses, commemorative of the time when they did contrive to blow old England up alive, but for her keeping her lips tightly and defiantly closed as the chair is put down. At which point, the figure in it gasping, &ldquo;O Lord! O dear me! I am shaken!&rdquo; adds, &ldquo;How de do, my dear friend, how de do?&rdquo; Mr. George then descries, in the procession, the venerable Mr. Smallweed out for an airing, attended by his grand-daughter Judy as body-guard.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. George, my dear friend,&rdquo; says grandfather Smallweed, removing his right arm from the neck of one of his bearers, whom he has nearly throttled coming along, &ldquo;how de do? You're surprised to see me, my dear friend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should hardly have been more surprised to see your friend in the city,&rdquo; returns Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am very seldom out,&rdquo; pants Mr. Smallweed. &ldquo;I haven't been out for many months. It's inconvenient&mdash;and it comes expensive. But I longed so much to see you, my dear Mr. George. How de do, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am well enough,&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;I hope you are the same.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You can't be too well, my dear friend.&rdquo; Mr. Smallweed takes him by both hands. &ldquo;I have brought my grand-daughter Judy. I couldn't keep her away. She longed so much to see you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hum! She bears it calmly!&rdquo; mutters Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So we got a hackney cab, and put a chair in it, and just round the corner they lifted me out of the cab and into the chair, and carried me here, that I might see my dear friend in his own establishment! This,&rdquo; says grandfather Smallweed, alluding to the bearer, who has been in danger of strangulation, and who withdraws adjusting his windpipe, &ldquo;is the driver of the cab. He has nothing extra. It is by agreement included in his fare. This person,&rdquo; the other bearer, &ldquo;we engaged in the street outside for a pint of beer. Which is twopence. Judy, give the person twopence. I was not sure you had a workman of your own here, my dear friend, or we needn't have employed this person.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Grandfather Smallweed refers to Phil, with a glance of considerable terror, and a half-subdued &ldquo;O Lord! O dear me!&rdquo; Nor is his apprehension, on the surface of things, without some reason; for Phil, who has never beheld the apparition in the black velvet cap before, has stopped short with a gun in his hand, with much of the air of a dead shot, intent on picking Mr. Smallweed off as an ugly old bird of the crow species.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Judy, my child,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, &ldquo;give the person his twopence. It's a great deal for what he has done.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The person, who is one of those extraordinary specimens of human fungus that spring up spontaneously in the western streets of London, ready dressed in an old red jacket, with a &ldquo;Mission&rdquo; for holding horses and calling coaches, receives his twopence with anything but transport, tosses the money into the air, catches it over-handed, and retires.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Mr. George,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, &ldquo;would you be so kind as help to carry me to the fire? I am accustomed to a fire, and I am an old man, and I soon chill. O dear me!&rdquo;</p>
<p>His closing exclamation is jerked out of the venerable gentleman by
<pb n="262" id="p262"/>
the suddenness with which Mr. Squod, like a genie, catches him up, chair and all, and deposits him on the hearthstone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O Lord!&rdquo; says Mr. Smallweed, panting. &ldquo;O dear me! O my stars! My dear friend, your workman is very strong&mdash;and very prompt. O Lord, he is very prompt! Judy, draw me back a little. I'm being scorched in the legs;&rdquo; which indeed is testified to the noses of all present by the smell of his worsted stockings.</p>
<p>The gentle Judy, having backed her grandfather a little way from the fire, and having shaken him up as usual, and having released his overshadowed eye from its black velvet extinguisher, Mr. Smallweed again says, &ldquo;O dear me! O Lord!&rdquo; and looking about, and meeting Mr. George's glance, again stretches out both hands.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend! So happy in this meeting! And this is your establishment? It's a delightful place. It's a picture! You never find that anything goes off here, accidentally; do you, my dear friend?&rdquo; adds Grandfather Smallweed, very ill at ease.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no. No fear of that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And your workman. He&mdash;O dear me!&mdash;he never lets anything off without meaning it; does he, my dear friend?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He has never hurt anybody but himself,&rdquo; says Mr. George, smiling.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But he might, you know. He seems to have hurt himself a good deal, and he might hurt somebody else,&rdquo; the old gentleman returns. &ldquo;He mightn't mean it&mdash;or he even might. Mr. George, will you order him to leave his infernal fire-arms alone, and go away?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Obedient to a nod from the trooper, Phil retires, empty-handed, to the other end of the gallery. Mr. Smallweed, reassured, falls to rubbing his legs.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And you're doing well, Mr. George?&rdquo; he says to the trooper, squarely standing faced-about towards him with his broadsword in his hand. &ldquo;You are prospering, please the Powers?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George answers with a cool nod, adding, &ldquo;Go on. You have not come to say that, I know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are so sprightly, Mr. George,&rdquo; returns the venerable grandfather. &ldquo;You are such good company.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ha ha! Go on!&rdquo; says Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend!&mdash;But that sword looks awful gleaming and sharp. It might cut somebody, by accident. It makes me shiver, Mr. George&mdash;Curse him!&rdquo; says the excellent old gentleman apart to Judy, as the trooper takes a step or two away to lay it aside. &ldquo;He owes me money, and might think of paying off all scores in this murdering place. I wish your Brimstone grandmother was here, and he'd shave her head off!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George, returning, folds his arms, and looking down at the old man, sliding every moment lower and lower in his chair, says quietly, &ldquo;Now for it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ho!&rdquo; cries Mr. Smallweed, rubbing his hands with an artful chuckle. &ldquo;Yes. Now for it. Now for what, my dear friend?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;For a pipe,&rdquo; says Mr. George; who with great composure sets his chair in the chimney-corner, takes his pipe from the grate, fills it and lights it, and falls to smoking peacefully.</p>
<p>This tends to the discomfiture of Mr. Smallweed, who finds it so difficult to resume his object, whatever it may be, that he becomes exasperated, and secretly claws the air with an impotent vindictiveness expressive of an intense desire to tear and rend the visage of Mr. George.
<pb n="263" id="p263"/>
As the excellent old gentleman's nails are long and leaden, and his hands lean and veinous, and his eyes green and watery; and, over and above this, as he continues, while he claws, to slide down in his chair and to collapse into a shapeless bundle; he becomes such a ghastly spectacle, even in the accustomed eyes of Judy, that that young virgin pounces at him with something more than the ardor of affection, and so shakes him up, and pats and pokes him in divers parts of his body, but particularly in that part which the science of self-defence would call his wind, that in his grievous distress he utters enforced sounds like a paviour's rammer.</p>
<p>When Judy has by these means set him up again in his chair, with a white face and a frosty nose (but still clawing), she stretches out her weazen forefinger, and gives Mr. George one poke in the back. The trooper raising his head, she makes another poke at her esteemed grandfather; and, having thus brought them together, stares rigidly at the fire.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye, aye! Ho, ho! U&mdash;u&mdash;u&mdash;ugh!&rdquo; chatters Grandfather Smallweed, swallowing his rage. &ldquo;My dear friend!&rdquo; (still clawing).</p>
<p>&ldquo;I tell you what,&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;If you want to converse with me, you must speak out. I am one of the Roughs, and I can't go about and about. I haven't the art to do it. I am not clever enough. It don't suit me. When you go winding round and round me,&rdquo; says the trooper, putting his pipe between his lips again, &ldquo;damme, if I don't feel as if I was being smothered!&rdquo;</p>
<p>And he inflates his broad chest to its utmost extent, as if to assure himself that he is not smothered yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you have come to give me a friendly call,&rdquo; continues Mr. George, &ldquo;I am obliged to you; how are you? If you have come to see whether there's any property on the premises, look about you; you are welcome. If you want to out with something, out with it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The blooming Judy, without removing her gaze from the fire, gives her grandfather one ghostly poke.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You see! It's her opinion, too. And why the devil that young woman won't sit down like a Christian,&rdquo; says Mr. George, with his eyes musingly fixed on Judy, &ldquo;<hi rend="italics">I</hi> can't comprehend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She keeps at my side to attend to me, sir,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed. &ldquo;I am an old man, my dear Mr. George, and I need some attention. I can carry my years; I am not a Brimstone poll-parrot;&rdquo; (suarling and looking unconsciously for the cushion;) &ldquo;but I need attention, my dear friend.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well!&rdquo; returns the trooper, wheeling his chair to face the old man. &ldquo;Now then?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My friend in the city, Mr. George, has done a little business with a pupil of yours.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Has he?&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;I am sorry to hear it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir.&rdquo; Grandfather Smallweed rubs his legs. &ldquo;He is a fine young soldier now, Mr. George, by the name of Carstone. Friends came forward, and paid it all up, honorable.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did they?&rdquo; returns Mr. George. &ldquo;Do you think your friend in the city would like a piece of advice?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think he would, my dear friend. From you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I advise him, then, to do no more business in that quarter. There's no more to be got by it. The young gentleman, to my knowledge, is brought to a dead halt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, my dear friend. No, no, Mr. George. No, no, no, sir,&rdquo; remonstrates Grandfather Smallweed, cunningly rubbing his spare legs.
<pb n="264" id="p264"/>
&ldquo;Not quite a dead halt, I think. He has good friends, and he is good for his pay, and he is good for the selling price of his commission, and he is good for his chance in a lawsuit, and he is good for his chance in a wife, and&mdash;oh, do you know, Mr. George, I think my friend would consider the young gentleman good for something yet!&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, turning up his velvet cap, and scratching his ear like a monkey.</p>
<p>Mr. George, who has put aside his pipe and sits with an arm on his chair-back, beats a tattoo on the ground with his right foot, as if he were not particularly pleased with the turn the conversation has taken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But to pass from one subject to another,&rdquo; resumes Mr. Smallweed. &ldquo;To promote the conversation, as a joker might say. To pass, Mr. George, from the ensign to the captain.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What are you up to, now?&rdquo; asks Mr. George, pausing with a frown in stroking the recollection of his moustache. &ldquo;What captain?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Our captain. The captain we know of. Captain Hawdon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O! that's it, is it?&rdquo; says Mr. George, with a low whistle, as he sees both grandfather and grand-daughter looking hard at him; &ldquo;you are there! Well? what about it? Come, I won't be smothered any more. Speak!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend,&rdquo; returns the old man, &ldquo;I was applied&mdash;Judy, shake me up a little!&mdash;I was applied to, yesterday, about the captain; and my opinion still is, that the captain is not dead.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bosh!&rdquo; observes Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What was your remark, my dear friend?&rdquo; enquires the old man with his hand to his ear.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bosh!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ho!&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed. &ldquo;Mr. George, of my opinion you can judge for yourself, according to the questions asked of me, and the reasons given for asking 'em. Now, what do you think the lawyer making the inquiries wants?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A job,&rdquo; says Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing of the kind!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can't be a lawyer, then,&rdquo; says Mr. George, folding his arms with an air of confirmed resolution.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend, he is a lawyer, and a famous one. He wants to see some fragment in Captain Hawdon's writing. He don't want to keep it. He only wants to see it, and compare it with a writing in his possession.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Mr. George. Happening to remember the advertisement concerning Captain Hawdon, and any information that could be given respecting him, he looked it up and came to me&mdash;just as you did, my dear friend. <hi rend="italics">Will</hi> you shake hands? So glad you came, that day! I should have missed forming such a friendship, if you hadn't come!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Mr. Smallweed?&rdquo; says Mr. George again, after going through the ceremony with some stiffness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I had no such thing. I have nothing but his signature. Plague pestilence and famine, battle murder and sudden death upon him,&rdquo; says the old man, making a curse out of one of his few remembrances of a prayer, and squeezing up his velvet cap between his angry hands, &ldquo;I have half a million of his signatures, I think! But you,&rdquo; breathlessly recovering his mildness of speech, as Judy re-adjusts the cap on his skittle-ball of a head; &ldquo;you, my dear Mr. George, are likely to have some letter or paper that would suit the purpose. Anything would suit the purpose, written in the hand.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="265" id="p265"/>
<p>&ldquo;Some writing in that hand,&rdquo; says the trooper, pondering, &ldquo;may be, I have.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dearest friend!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;May be, I have not.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ho!&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, crest-fallen.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But if I had bushels of it, I would not show as much as would make a cartridge, without knowing why.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir, I have told you why. My dear Mr. George, I have told you why.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not enough,&rdquo; says the trooper, shaking his head. &ldquo;I must know more, and approve it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, will you come to the lawyer? My dear friend, will you come and see the gentleman?&rdquo; urges Grandfather Smallweed, pulling out a lean old silver watch, with hands like the legs of a skeleton. &ldquo;I told him it was probable I might call upon him, between ten and eleven this forenoon; and it's now half after ten. Will you come and see the gentleman, Mr. George?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hum!&rdquo; says he, gravely. &ldquo;I don't mind that. Though why this should concern you so much, I don't know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Everything concerns me, that has a chance in it of bringing anything to light about him. Didn't he take us all in? Didn't he owe us immense sums, all round? Concern me? Who can anything about him concern, more than me? Not, my dear friend,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, lowering his tone, &ldquo;that I want <hi rend="italics">you</hi> to betray anything. Far from it. Are you ready to come, my dear friend?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay! I'll come in a moment. I promise nothing, you know.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my dear Mr. George; no.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And you mean to say you're going to give me a lift to this place, wherever it is, without charging for it?&rdquo; Mr. George enquires, getting his hat, and thick wash-leather gloves.</p>
<p>This pleasantry so tickles Mr. Smallweed, that he laughs, long and low, before the fire. But ever while he laughs, he glances over his paralytic shoulder at Mr. George, and eagerly watches him as he unlocks the padlock of a homely cupboard at the distant end of the gallery, looks here and there upon the higher shelves, and ultimately takes something out with a rustling of paper, folds it, and puts it in his breast. Then Judy pokes Mr. Smallweed once, and Mr. Smallweed pokes Judy once.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am ready,&rdquo; says the trooper, coming back. &ldquo;Phil, you can carry this old gentleman to his coach, and make nothing of him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O dear me! O Lord! Stop a moment!&rdquo; says Mr. Smallweed. &ldquo;He's so very prompt! Are you sure you can do it carefully, my worthy man?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Phil makes no reply; but seizing the chair and its load sidles away, tightly hugged by the now speechless Mr. Smallweed, and bolts along the passage, as if he had an acceptable commission to carry the old gentleman to the nearest volcano. His shorter trust, however, terminating at the cab, he deposits him there; and the fair Judy takes her place beside him, and the chair embellishes the roof, and Mr. George takes the vacant place upon the box.</p>
<p>Mr. George is quite confounded by the spectacle he beholds from time to time as he peeps into the cab, through the window behind him; where the grim Judy is always motionless, and the old gentleman with his cap over one eye is always sliding off the seat into the straw, and looking upward at him, out of his other eye, with a helpless expression of being jolted in the back.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<pb id="p266" n="266"/>
<head>CHAPTER XXVII. <lb/> MORE OLD SOLDIERS THAN ONE.</head>
<p>MR. GEORGE has not far to ride with folded arms upon the box, for their destination is Lincoln's Inn Fields. When the driver stops his horses, Mr. George alights, and looking in at the window, says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What, Mr. Tulkinghorn's your man, is he?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my dear friend. Do you know him, Mr. George?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I have heard of him&mdash;seen him too, I think. But I don't know him, and he don't know me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There ensues the carrying of Mr. Smallweed up-stairs; which is done to perfection with the trooper's help. He is borne into Mr. Tulkinghorn's great room, and deposited on the Turkey rug before the fire. Mr. Tulkinghorn is not within at the present moment, but will be back directly. The occupant of the pew in the hall, having said thus much, stirs the fire, and leaves the triumvirate to warm themselves.</p>
<p>Mr. George is mightily curious in respect of the room. He looks up at the painted ceiling, looks round at the old law-books, contemplates the portraits of the great clients, reads aloud the names on the boxes.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet,&rsquo; &rdquo; Mr. George reads thoughtfully. &ldquo;Ha! &lsquo;Manor of Chesney Wold.&rsquo; Humph!&rdquo; Mr. George stands looking at these boxes a long while&mdash;as if they were pictures&mdash;and comes back to the fire, repeating, &ldquo;Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet, and Manor of Chesney Wold, hey?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Worth a mint of money, Mr. George!&rdquo; whispers Grandfather Smallweed, rubbing his legs. &ldquo;Powerfully rich!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who do you mean? This old gentleman, or the Baronet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;This gentleman, this gentleman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So I have heard; and knows a thing or two, I'll hold a wager. Not bad quarters either,&rdquo; says Mr. George, looking round again. &ldquo;See the strong box, yonder!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This reply is cut short by Mr. Tulkinghorn's arrival. There is no change in him, of course. Rustily drest, with his spectacles in his hand, and their very case worn threadbare. In manner, close and dry. In voice, husky and low. In face, watchful behind a blind; habitually not uncensorious and contemptuous perhaps. The peerage may have warmer worshippers and faithfuller believers than Mr. Tulkinghorn, after all, if everything were known.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good morning, Mr. Smallweed, good morning!&rdquo; he says as he comes in. &ldquo;You have brought the serjeant, I see. Sit down, serjeant.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As Mr. Tulkinghorn takes off his gloves and puts them in his hat, he looks with half-closed eyes across the room to where the trooper stands, and says within himself perchance, &ldquo;You'll do, my friend!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sit down, serjeant,&rdquo; he repeats, as he comes to his table, which is set on one side of the fire, and takes his easy chair. &ldquo;Cold and raw this morning, cold and raw!&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn warms before the bars, alternately, the palms and knuckles of his hands, and looks (from behind that blind which is always down) at the trio sitting in a little semicircle before him.</p>
<pb n="267" id="p267"/>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I can feel what I am about!&rdquo; (as perhaps he can in two senses) &ldquo;Mr. Smallweed.&rdquo; The old gentleman is newly shaken up by Judy, to bear his part in the conversation. &ldquo;You have brought our good friend the serjeant, I see.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir,&rdquo; returns Mr. Smallweed, very servile to the lawyer's wealth and influence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what does the serjeant say about this business?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. George,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, with a tremulous wave of his shrivelled hand, &ldquo;this is the gentleman, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George salutes the gentleman; but otherwise sits bolt upright and profoundly silent&mdash;very forward in his chair, as if the full complement of regulation appendages for a field day hung about him.</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn proceeds: &ldquo;Well, George?&mdash;I believe your name is George?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is so, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do you say, George?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I ask your pardon, sir,&rdquo; returns the trooper, &ldquo;but I should wish to know what <hi rend="italics">you</hi> say?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you mean in point of reward?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I mean in point of everything, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is so very trying to Mr. Smallweed's temper, that he suddenly breaks out with &ldquo;You're a Brimstone beast!&rdquo; and as suddenly asks pardon of Mr. Tulkinghorn; excusing himself for this slip of the tongue, by saying to Judy, &ldquo;I was thinking of your grandmother, my dear.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I supposed, serjeant,&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn resumes, as he leans on one side of his chair and crosses his legs, &ldquo;that Mr. Smallweed might have sufficiently explained the matter. It lies in the smallest compass, however. You served under Captain Hawdon at one time, and were his attendant in illness, and rendered him many little services, and were rather in his confidence, I am told. That is so, is it not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, sir, that is so,&rdquo; says Mr. George, with military brevity.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Therefore you may happen to have in your possession something&mdash;anything, no matter what&mdash;accounts, instructions, orders, a letter, anything&mdash;in Captain Hawdon's writing. I wish to compare his writing with some that I have. If you can give me the opportunity, you shall be rewarded for your trouble. Three, four, five, guineas, you would consider handsome, I dare say.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Noble, my dear friend!&rdquo; cries Grandfather Smallweed, screwing up his eyes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If not, say how much more, in your conscience as a soldier, you can demand. There is no need for you to part with the writing, against your inclination&mdash;though I should prefer to have it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George sits squared in exactly the same attitude, looks at the ground, looks at the painted ceiling, and says never a word. The irascible Mr. Smallweed scratches the air.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The question is,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn in his methodical, subdued, uninterested way, &ldquo;first, whether you have any of Captain Hawdon's writing?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;First, whether I have any of Captain Hawdon's writing, sir,&rdquo; repeats Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Secondly, what will satisfy you for the trouble of producing it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Secondly, what will satisfy me for the trouble of producing it, sir,&rdquo; repeats Mr. George.</p>
<pb n="268" id="p268"/>
<p>&ldquo;Thirdly, you can judge for yourself whether it is at all like that,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn, suddenly handing him some sheets of written paper tied together.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Whether it is at all like that, sir. Just so,&rdquo; repeats Mr. George.</p>
<p>All three repetitions Mr. George pronounces in a mechanical manner, looking straight at Mr. Tulkinghorn; nor does he so much as glance at the affidavit in Jarndyce and Jarndyce, that has been given to him for his inspection (though he still holds it in his hand), but continues to look at the lawyer with an air of troubled meditation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well?&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn. &ldquo;What do you say?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir,&rdquo; replies Mr. George, rising erect and looking immense, &ldquo;I would rather, if you'll excuse me, have nothing to do with this.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn, outwardly quite undisturbed, demands &ldquo;Why not?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, sir,&rdquo; returns the trooper. &ldquo;Except on military compulsion, I am not a man of business. Among civilians I am what they call in Scotland a ne'er-do-weel. I have no head for papers, sir. I can stand any fire better than a fire of cross questions. I mentioned to Mr. Smallweed, only an hour or so ago, that when I come into things of this kind I feel as if I was being smothered. And that is my sensation,&rdquo; says Mr. George, looking round upon the company, &ldquo;at the present moment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With that, he takes three strides forward to replace the papers on the lawyer's table, and three strides backward to resume his former station: where he stands perfectly upright, now looking at the ground, and now at the painted ceiling, with his hands behind him as if to prevent himself from accepting any other document whatever.</p>
<p>Under this provocation, Mr. Smallweed's favorite adjective of disparagement is so close to his tongue, that he begins the words &ldquo;my dear friend&rdquo; with the monosyllable &ldquo;Brim;&rdquo; thus converting the possessive pronoun into Brimmy, and appearing to have an impediment in his speech. Once past this difficulty, however, he exhorts his dear friend in the tenderest manner not to be rash, but to do what so eminent a gentleman requires, and to do it with a good grace: confident that it must be unobjectionable as well as profitable. Mr. Tulkinghorn merely utters an occasional sentence, as &ldquo;You are the best judge of your own interest, serjeant.&rdquo; &ldquo;Take care you do no harm by this.&rdquo; &ldquo;Please yourself, please yourself.&rdquo; &ldquo;If you know what you mean, that's quite enough.&rdquo; These he utters with an appearance of perfect indifference, as he looks over the papers on his table, and prepares to write a letter.</p>
<p>Mr. George looks distrustfully from the painted ceiling to the ground, from the ground to Mr. Smallweed, from Mr. Smallweed to Mr. Tulkinghorn, and from Mr. Tulkinghorn to the painted ceiling again: often in his perplexity changing the leg on which he rests.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do assure you, sir,&rdquo; says Mr. George, &ldquo;not to say it offensively, that between you and Mr. Smallweed here, I really am being smothered fifty times over. I really am, sir. I am not a match for you gentlemen. Will you allow me to ask, why you want to see the captain's hand, in the case that I could find any specimen of it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn quietly shakes his head. &ldquo;No. If you were a man of business, serjeant, you would not need to be informed that there are confidential reasons, very harmless in themselves, for many such wants, in the profession to which I belong. But if you are afraid of doing any injury to Captain Hawdon, you may set your mind at rest about that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay! he is dead, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="269" id="p269"/>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Is</hi> he?&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn quietly sits down to write.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, sir,&rdquo; says the trooper, looking into his hat, after another disconcerted pause; &ldquo;I am sorry not to have given you more satisfaction. If it would be any satisfaction to any one, that I should be confirmed in my judgment that I would rather have nothing to do with this, by a friend of mine, who has a better head for business than I have, and who is an old soldier, I am willing to consult with him. I&mdash;I really am so completely smothered myself, at present,&rdquo; says Mr. George, passing his hand hopelessly across his brow, &ldquo;that I don't know but what it might be a satisfaction to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Smallweed, hearing that this authority is an old soldier, so strongly inculcates the expediency of the trooper's taking counsel with him, and particularly informing him of its being a question of five guineas or more, that Mr. George engages to go and see him. Mr. Tulkinghorn says nothing either way.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll consult my friend, then, by your leave, sir,&rdquo; says the trooper, &ldquo;and I'll take the liberty of looking in again with a final answer in the course of the day. Mr. Smallweed, if you wish to be carried down stairs&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In a moment, my dear friend, in a moment. Will you first let me speak half a word with this gentleman, in private?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly, sir. Don't hurry yourself on my account.&rdquo; The trooper retires to a distant part of the room, and resumes his curious inspection of the boxes; strong, and otherwise.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If I wasn't as weak as a Brimstone Baby, sir,&rdquo; whispers Grandfather Smallweed, drawing the lawyer down to his level by the lappel of his coat, and flashing some half-quenched green fire out of his angry eyes, &ldquo;I'd tear the writing away from him. He's got it buttoned in his breast. I saw him put it there. Judy saw him put it there. Speak up, you crabbed image for the sign of a walking-stick shop, and say you saw him put it there!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This vehement conjuration the old gentleman accompanies with such a thrust at his grand-daughter, that it is too much for his strength, and he slips away out of his chair, drawing Mr. Tulkinghorn with him, until he is arrested by Judy, and well shaken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Violence will not do for me, my friend,&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn then remarks coolly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, I know, I know, sir. But it's chafing and galling&mdash;it's&mdash;it's worse than your smattering chattering Magpie of a grandmother,&rdquo; to the imperturbable Judy, who only looks at the fire, &ldquo;to know he has got what's wanted, and won't give it up. He, not to give it up! <hi rend="italics">He!</hi> A vagabond! But never mind, sir, never mind. At the most, he has only his own way for a little while. I have him periodically in a vice. I'll twist him, sir. I'll screw him, sir. If he won't do it with a good grace, I'll make him do it with a bad one, sir!&mdash;Now, my dear Mr. George,&rdquo; says Grandfather Smallweed, winking at the lawyer hideously, as he releases him, &ldquo;I am ready for your kind assistance, my excellent friend!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn, with some shadowy sign of amusement manifesting itself through his self-possession, stands on the hearth-rug with his back to the fire, watching the disappearance of Mr. Smallweed, and acknowledging the trooper's parting salute with one slight nod.</p>
<p>It is more difficult to get rid of the old gentleman, Mr. George finds,
<pb n="270" id="p270"/>
than to bear a hand in carrying him down stairs; for, when he is replaced in his conveyance, he is so loquacious on the subject of the guineas, and retains such an affectionate hold of his button&mdash;having, in truth, a secret longing to rip his coat open, and rob him&mdash;that some degree of force is necessary on the trooper's part to effect a separation. It is accomplished at last, and he proceeds alone in quest of his adviser.</p>
<p>By the cloisterly Temple, and by Whitefriars (there, not without a glance at Hanging-sword Alley, which would seem to be something in his way), and by Blackfriars-bridge, and Blackfriars-road, Mr. George sedately marches to a street of little shops lying somewhere in that ganglion of roads from Kent and Surrey, and of streets from the bridges of London, centering in the far-famed Elephant who has lost his Castle formed of a thousand four-horse coaches, to a stronger iron monster than he, ready to chop him into mince-meat any day he dares. To one of the little shops in this street, which is a musician's shop, having a few fiddles in the window, and some Pan's pipes and a tambourine, and a triangle, and certain elongated scraps of music, Mr. George directs his massive tread. And halting at a few paces from it, as he sees a soldierly looking woman, with her outer skirts tucked up, come forth with a small wooden tub, and in that tub commence a whisking and a splashing on the margin of the pavement, Mr. George says to himself, &ldquo;She's as usual, washing greens. I never saw her, except upon a baggage-wagon, when she wasn't washing greens!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The subject of this reflection is at all events so occupied in washing greens at present, that she remains unsuspicious of Mr. George's approach; until, lifting up herself and her tub together, when she has poured the water off into the gutter, she finds him standing near her. Her reception of him is not flattering.</p>
<p>&ldquo;George, I never see you, but I wish you was a hundred mile away!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The trooper, without remarking on this welcome, follows into the musical instrument shop, where the lady places her tub of greens upon the counter, and having shaken hands with him, rests her arms upon it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;George, consider Matthew Bagnet safe a minute when you're near him. You are that restless and that roving&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes! I know I am, Mrs. Bagnet. I know I am.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You know you are!&rdquo; says Mrs. Bagnet. &ldquo;What's the use of that? <hi rend="italics">Why</hi> are you?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The nature of the animal, I suppose,&rdquo; returns the trooper good-humouredly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; cries Mrs. Bagnet, something shrilly, &ldquo;but what satisfaction will the nature of the animal be to me, when the animal shall have tempted my Mat away from the musical business to New Zealand or Australey!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Bagnet is not at all an ill-looking woman. Rather large-boned, a little coarse in the grain, and freckled by the sun and wind which have tanned her hair upon the forehead; but healthy, wholesome, and bright-eyed. A strong, busy, active, honest-faced woman, of from forty-five to fifty. Clean, hardy, and so economically dressed (though substantially), that the only article of ornament of which she stands possessed appears to be her wedding ring; around which her finger has grown to be so large since it was put on, that it will never come off again until it shall mingle with Mrs. Bagnet's dust.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Bagnet,&rdquo; says the trooper, &ldquo;I am on my parole with you. Mat will get no harm from me. You may trust me so far.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="271" id="p271"/>
<p>&ldquo;Well, I think I may. But the very looks of you are unsettling,&rdquo; Mrs. Bagnet rejoins. &ldquo;Ah George, George! If you had only settled down, and married Joe Pouch's widow when he died in North America, <hi rend="italics">she'd</hi> have combed your hair for you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was a chance for me, certainly,&rdquo; returns the trooper, half-laughingly, half-seriously, &ldquo;but I shall never settle down into a respectable man now. Joe Pouch's widow might have done me good&mdash;there was something in her&mdash;and something of her&mdash;but I couldn't make up my mind to it. If I had had the luck to meet with such a wife as Mat found!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Bagnet, who seems in a virtuous way to be under little reserve with a good sort of fellow, but to be another good sort of fellow herself for that matter, receives this compliment by flicking Mr. George in the face with a head of greens, and taking her tub into the little room behind the shop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, Quebec, my poppet,&rdquo; says George, following, on invitation, into that apartment. &ldquo;And little Malta, too! Come and kiss your Bluffy!&rdquo;</p>
<p>These young ladies&mdash;not supposed to have been actually christened by the names applied to them, though always so called in the family, from the places of their birth in barracks&mdash;are respectively employed on three-legged stools: the younger (some five or six years old), in learning her letters out of a penny primer: the elder (eight or nine perhaps), in teaching her, and sewing with great assiduity. Both hail Mr. George with acclamations as an old friend, and after some kissing and romping plant their stools beside him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how's Young Woolwich?&rdquo; says Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! There now!&rdquo; cries Mrs. Bagnet, turning about from her saucepans (for she is cooking dinner), with a bright flush on her face. &ldquo;Would you believe it? Got an engagement at the Theayter, with his father, to play the fife in a military piece.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well done, my godson!&rdquo; cries Mr. George, slapping his thigh.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I believe you!&rdquo; says Mrs. Bagnet. &ldquo;He's a Briton. That's what Woolwich is. A Briton.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And Mat blows away at his bassoon, and you're respectable civilians one and all,&rdquo; says Mr. George. &ldquo;Family people. Children growing up. Mat's old mother in Scotland, and your old father somewhere else, corresponded with; and helped a little; and&mdash;well, well! To be sure, I don't know why I shouldn't be wished a hundred mile away, for I have not much to do with all this!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. George is becoming thoughtful; sitting before the fire in the white-washed room, which has a sanded floor, and a barrack smell, and contains nothing superfluous, and has not a visible speak of dirt or dust in it, from the faces of Quebec and Malta to the bright tin pots and pannikins upon the dresser shelves;&mdash;Mr. George is becoming thoughtful, sitting here while Mrs. Bagnet is busy, when Mr. Bagnet and Young Woolwich opportunely come home. Mr. Bagnet is an ex-artilleryman, tall and upright, with shaggy eyebrows, and whiskers like the fibres of a cocoanut, not a hair upon his head, and a torrid complexion. His voice, short, deep, and resonant, is not at all unlike the tones of the instrument to which he is devoted. Indeed there may be generally observed in him an unbending, unyielding, brass-bound air, as if he were himself the bassoon of the human orchestra. Young Woolwich is the type and model of a young drummer.</p>
<p>Both father and son salute the trooper heartily. He saying, in due
<pb n="272" id="p272"/>
season, that he has come to advise with Mr. Bagnet, Mr. Bagnet hospitably declares that he will hear of no business until after dinner; and that his friend shall not partake of his counsel, without first partaking of boiled pork and greens. The trooper yielding to this invitation, he and Mr. Bagnet, not to embarrass the domestic preparations, go forth to take a turn up and down the little street, which they promenade with measured tread and folded arms, as if it were a rampart.</p>
<p>&ldquo;George,&rdquo; says Mr. Bagnet. &ldquo;You know me. It's my old girl that advises. She has the head. But I never own to it before her. Discipline must be maintained. Wait till the greens is off her mind. Then, we'll consult. Whatever the old girl says, do&mdash;do it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I intend to, Mat,&rdquo; replies the other. &ldquo;I would sooner take her opinion than that of a college.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;College,&rdquo; returns Mr. Bagnet, in short sentences, bassoon-like. &ldquo;What college could you leave&mdash;in another quarter of the world&mdash;with nothing but a grey cloak and an umbrella&mdash;to make its way home to Europe? The old girl would do it to-morrow. Did it once!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are right,&rdquo; says Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What college,&rdquo; pursues Bagnet, &ldquo;could you set up in life&mdash;with two penn'orth of white lime&mdash;a penn'orth of fuller's earth&mdash;a ha'porth of sand&mdash;and the rest of the change out of sixpence, in money? That's what the old girl started on. In the present business.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am rejoiced to hear it's thriving, Mat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The old girl,&rdquo; says Mr. Bagnet, acquiescing, &ldquo;saves. Has a stocking somewhere. With money in it. I never saw it. But I know she's got it. Wait till the greens is off her mind. Then she'll set you up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She is a treasure!&rdquo; exclaims Mr. George.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She's more. But I never own to it before her. Discipline must be maintained. It was the old girl that brought out my musical abilities. I should have been in the artillery now, but for the old girl. Six years I hammered at the fiddle. Ten at the flute. The old girl said it wouldn't do; intention good, but want of flexibility; try the bassoon. The old girl borrowed a bassoon from the bandmaster of the Rifle Regiment. I practised in the trenches. Got on, got another, get a living by it!&rdquo;</p>
<p>George remarks that she looks as fresh as a rose, and as sound as an apple.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The old girl,&rdquo; says Mr. Bagnet in reply, &ldquo;is a thoroughly fine woman. Consequently, she is like a thoroughly fine day. Gets finer as she gets on. I never saw the old girl's equal. But I never own to it before her. Discipline must be maintained!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Proceeding to converse on indifferent matters, they walk up and down the little street, keeping step and time, until summoned by Quebec and Malta to do justice to the pork and greens; over which Mrs. Bagnet, like a military chaplain, says a short grace. In the distribution of these comestibles, as in every other household duty, Mrs. Bagnet developes an exact system; sitting with every dish before her; allotting to every portion of pork its own portion of pot-liquor, greens, potatoes, and even mustard; and serving it out complete. Having likewise served out the beer from a can, and thus supplied the mess with all things necessary, Mrs. Bagnet proceeds to satisfy her own hunger, which is in a healthy state. The kit of the mess, if the table furniture may be so denominated, is chiefly composed of utensils of horn and tin, that have
<pb n="273" id="p273"/>
done duty in several parts of the world. Young Woolwich's knife, in particular, which is of the oyster kind, with the additional feature of a strong shutting-up movement which frequently balks the appetite of that young musician, is mentioned as having gone in various hands the complete round of foreign service.</p>
<p>The dinner done, Mrs. Bagnet, assisted by the younger branches (who polish their own cups and platters, knives and forks), makes all the dinner garniture shine as brightly as before, and puts it all away; first sweeping the hearth, to the end that Mr. Bagnet and the visitor may not be retarded in the smoking of their pipes. These household cares involve much pattening and counter-pattening in the back yard, and considerable use of a pail, which is finally so happy as to assist in the ablutions of Mrs. Bagnet herself. That old girl reappearing by and by, quite fresh, and sitting down to her needlework, then and only then&mdash;the greens being only then to be considered as entirely off her mind&mdash;Mr. Bagnet requests the trooper to state his case.</p>
<p>This, Mr. George does with great discretion; appearing to address himself to Mr. Bagnet, but having an eye solely on the old girl all the time, as Bagnet has himself. She, equally discreet, busies herself with her needlework. The case fully stated, Mr. Bagnet resorts to his standard artifice for the maintenance of discipline.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the whole of it, is it, George?&rdquo; says he.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the whole of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You act according to my opinion?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall be guided,&rdquo; replies George, &ldquo;entirely by it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Old girl,&rdquo; says Mr. Bagnet, &ldquo;give him my opinion. You know it. Tell him what it is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is, that he cannot have too little to do with people who are too deep for him, and cannot be too careful of interference with matters he does not understand; that the plain rule is, to do nothing in the dark, to be a party to nothing under-handed or mysterious, and never to put his foot where he cannot see the ground. This, in effect, is Mr. Bagnet's opinion as delivered through the old girl; and it so relieves Mr. George's mind, by confirming his own opinion and banishing his doubts, that he composes himself to smoke another pipe on that exceptional occasion, and to have a talk over old times with the whole Bagnet family, according to their various ranges of experience.</p>
<p>Through these means it comes to pass, that Mr. George does not again rise to his full height in that parlour until the time is drawing on when the bassoon and fife are expected by a British public at the theatre; and as it takes time even then for Mr. George, in his domestic character of Bluffy, to take leave of Quebec and Malta, and insinuate a sponsorial shilling into the pocket of his godson, with felicitations on his success in life, it is dark when Mr. George again turns his face towards Lincoln's Inn Fields.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A family home,&rdquo; he ruminates, as he marches along, &ldquo;however small it is, makes a man like me look lonely. But it's well I never made that evolution of matrimony. I shouldn't have been fit for it. I am such a vagabond still, even at my present time of life, that I couldn't hold to the gallery a month together, if it was a regular pursuit, or if I didn't camp there, gypsey fashion. Come! I disgrace nobody and cumber nobody: that's something. I have not done that, for many a long year!&rdquo;</p>
<p>So he whistles it off, and marches on.</p>
<pb n="274" id="p274"/>
<p>Arrived in Lincoln's Inn Fields, and mounting Mr. Tulkinghorn's stair, he finds the outer door closed, and the chambers shut; but the trooper not knowing much about outer doors, and the staircase being dark besides, he is yet fumbling and groping about, hoping to discover a bell handle or to open the door for himself, when Mr. Tulkinghorn comes up the stairs (quietly, or course), and angrily asks:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who is that? What are you doing there?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I ask your pardon, sir. It's George. The serjeant.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And couldn't George, the serjeant, see that my door was locked?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why no, sir, I couldn't. At any rate, I didn't,&rdquo; says the trooper, rather nettled.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you changed your mind? or are you in the same mind?&rdquo; Mr. Tulkinghorn demands. But he knows well enough at a glance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the same mind, sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought so. That's sufficient. You can go. So, you are the man,&rdquo; says Mr. Tulkinghorn, opening his door with the key, &ldquo;in whose hiding-place Mr. Gridley was found?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, I <hi rend="italics">am</hi> the man,&rdquo; says the trooper, stopping two or three stairs down. &ldquo;What then, sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What then? I don't like your associates. You should not have seen the inside of my door this morning, if I had thought of your being that man. Gridley? A threatening, murderous, dangerous fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With these words, spoken in an unusually high tone for him, the lawyer goes into his rooms, and shuts the door with a thundering noise.</p>
<p>Mr. George takes this dismissal in great dudgeon; the greater, because a clerk coming up the stairs has heard the last words of all, and evidently applies them to him. &ldquo;A pretty character to bear,&rdquo; the trooper growls with a hasty oath, as he strides down stairs. &ldquo;A threatening, murderous, dangerous fellow!&rdquo; and looking up, he sees the clerk looking down at him, and marking him as he passes a lamp. This so intensifies his dudgeon, that for five minutes he is in an ill humour. But he whistles that off, like the rest of it; and marches home to the Shooting Gallery.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXVIII. <lb/> THE IRONMASTER.</head>
<p>SIR LEICESTER DEDLOCK has got the better, for the time being, of the family gout; and is once more, in a literal no less than in a figurative point of view, upon his legs. He is at his place in Lincolnshire; but the waters are out again on the low-lying grounds, and the cold and damp steal into Chesney Wold, though well defended, and eke into Sir Leicester's bones. The blazing fires of faggot and coal&mdash;Dedlock timber and antediluvian forest&mdash;that blaze upon the broad wide hearths, and wink in the twilight on the frowning woods, sullen to see how trees are sacrificed, do not exclude the enemy. The hot-water pipes that trail themselves all over the house, the cushioned doors and windows, and the screens and curtains, fail to supply the fires' deficiencies, and to satisfy Sir Leicester's need. Hence the fashionable intelligence proclaims one morning to the listening earth, that Lady Dedlock is expected shortly to return to town for a few weeks.</p>
<pb n="275" id="p275"/>
<p>It is a melancholy truth that even great men have their poor relations. Indeed great men have often more than their fair share of poor relations; inasmuch as very red blood of the superior quality, like inferior blood unlawfully shed, <hi rend="italics">will</hi> cry aloud, and <hi rend="italics">will</hi> be heard. Sir Leicester's cousins, in the remotest degree, are so many Murders, in the respect that they &ldquo;will out.&rdquo; Among whom there are cousins who are so poor, that one might almost dare to think it would have been the happier for them never to have been plated links upon the Dedlock chain of gold, but to have been made of common iron at first, and done base service.</p>
<p>Service, however (with a few limited reservations: genteel but not profitable), they may not do, being of the Dedlock dignity. So they visit their richer cousins, and get into debt when they can, and live but shabbily when they can't, and find&mdash;the women no husbands, and the men no wives&mdash;and ride in borrowed carriages, and sit at feasts that are never of their own making, and so go through high life. The rich family sum has been divided by so many figures, and they are the something over that nobody knows what to do with.</p>
<p>Everybody on Sir Leicester Dedlock's side of the question, and of his way of thinking, would appear to be his cousin more or less. From my Lord Boodle, through the Duke of Foodle, down to Noodle, Sir Leicester, like a glorious spider, stretches his threads of relationship. But while he is stately in the counsinship of the Everybodys, he is a kind and generous man, according to his dignified way, in the cousinship of the Nobodys; and at the present time, in despite of the damp, he stays out the visit of several such cousins at Chesney Wold, with the constancy of a martyr.</p>
<p>Of these, foremost in the first rank stands Volumnia Dedlock, a young lady (of sixty), who is doubly highly related; having the honor to be a poor relation, by the mother's side, to another great family. Miss Volumnia, displaying in early life a pretty talent for cutting ornaments out of colored paper, and also for singing to the guitar in the Spanish tongue, and propounding French conundrums in country houses, passed the twenty years of her existence between twenty and forty in a sufficiently agreeable manner. Lapsing then out of date, and being considered to bore mankind by her vocal performances in the Spanish language, she retired to Bath; where she lives slenderly on an annual present from Sir Leicester, and whence she makes occasional resurrections in the country houses of her cousins. She has an extensive acquaintance at Bath among appalling old gentlemen with thin legs and nankeen trousers, and is of high standing in that dreary city. But she is a little dreaded elsewhere, in consequence of an indiscreet profusion in the article of rouge, and persistency in an obsolete pearl necklace like a rosary of little bird's-eggs.</p>
<p>In any country in a wholesome state, Volumnia would be a clear case for the pension list. Efforts have been made to get her on it; and when William Buffy came in, it was fully expected that her name would be put down for a couple of hundred a-year. But William Buffy somehow discovered, contrary to all expectation, that these were not times when it could be done; and this was the first clear indication Sir Leicester Dedlock had conveyed to him, that the country was going to pieces.</p>
<p>There is likewise the Honorable Bob Stables, who can make warm mashes with the skill of a veterinary surgeon, and is a better shot than most gamekeepers. He has been for some time particularly desirous to serve his country in a post of good emoluments, unaccompanied by any
<pb n="276" id="p276"/>
trouble or responsibility. In a well regulated body politic, this natural desire on the part of a spirited young gentleman so highly connected, would be speedily recognised; but somehow William Buffy found when he came in, that these were not times in which he could manage that little matter, either; and this was the second indication Sir Leicester Dedlock had conveyed to him, that the country was going to pieces.</p>
<p>The rest of the cousins are ladies and gentlemen of various ages and capacities; the major part, amiable and sensible, and likely to have done well enough in life if they could have overcome their cousinship; as it is, they are almost all a little worsted by it, and lounge in purposeless and listless paths, and seem to be quite as much at a loss how to dispose of themselves, as anybody else can be how to dispose of them.</p>
<p>In this society, and where not, my Lady Dedlock reigns supreme. Beautiful, elegant, accomplished, and powerful in her little world (for the world of fashion does not stretch <hi rend="italics">all</hi> the way from pole to pole), her influence in Sir Leicester's house, however haughty and indifferent her manner, is greatly to improve it and refine it. The cousins, even those older cousins who were paralysed when Sir Leicester married her, do her feudal homage; and the Honorable Bob Stables daily repeats to some chosen person, between breakfast and lunch, his favourite original remark that she is the best groomed woman in the whole stud.</p>
<p>Such the guests in the long drawing-room at Chesney Wold this dismal night, when the step on the Ghost's Walk (inaudible here, however) might be the step of a deceased cousin shut out in the cold. It is near bed-time. Bed-room fires blaze brightly all over the house, raising ghosts or grim furniture on wall and ceiling. Bed-room candlesticks bristle on the distant table by the door, and cousins yawn on ottomans. Cousins at the piano, cousins at the soda-water tray, cousins rising from the card-table, cousins gathered round the fire. Standing on one side of his own peculiar fire (for there are two), Sir Leicester. On the opposite side of the broad hearth, my Lady at her table. Volumnia, as one of the more privileged cousins, in a luxurious chair between them. Sir Leicester glancing, with magnificent displeasure, at the rouge and the pearl necklace.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I occasionally meet on my staircase here,&rdquo; drawls Volumnia, whose thoughts perhaps are already hopping up it to bed, after a long evening of very desultory talk, &ldquo;one of the prettiest girls, I think, that I ever saw in my life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A <hi rend="italics">proteg&eacute;e</hi> of my lady's,&rdquo; observes Sir Leicester.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought so. I felt sure that some uncommon eye must have picked that girl out. She really is a marvel. A dolly sort of beauty perhaps,&rdquo; says Miss Volumnia, reserving her own sort, &ldquo;but in its way, perfect; such bloom I never saw!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester with his magnificent glance of displeasure at the rouge, appears to say so too.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed,&rdquo; remarks my Lady, languidly, &ldquo;if there is any uncommon eye in the case, it is Mrs. Rouncewell's, and not mine. Rosa is her discovery.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your maid, I suppose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No. My anything; pet&mdash;secretary&mdash;messenger&mdash;I don't know what.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You like to have her about you, as you would like to have a flower, or a bird, or a picture, or a poodle&mdash;no, not a poodle, though&mdash;or anything else that was equally pretty?&rdquo; says Volumnia, sympathising. &ldquo;Yes, how charming now! and how well that delightful old soul
<pb n="277" id="p277"/>
Mrs. Rouncewell is looking. She must be an immense age, and yet she is as active and handsome!&mdash;She is the dearest friend I have, positively!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester feels it to be right and fitting that the housekeeper of Chesney Wold should be a remarkable person. Apart from that, he has a real regard for Mrs. Rouncewell, and likes to hear her praised. So he says, &ldquo;You are right, Volumnia;&rdquo; which Volumnia is extremely glad to hear.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She has no daughter of her own, has she?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Rouncewell? No, Volumnia. She has a son. Indeed, she had two.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, whose chronic malady of boredom has been sadly aggravated by Volumnia this evening, glances wearily towards the candlesticks and heaves a noiseless sigh.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And it is a remarkable example of the confusion into which the present age has fallen; of the obliteration of landmarks, the opening of floodgates, and the uprooting of distinctions,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester with stately gloom; &ldquo;that I have been informed, by Mr. Tulkinghorn, that Mrs. Rouncewell's son has been invited to go into Parliament.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Volumnia utters a little sharp scream.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, indeed,&rdquo; repeats Sir Leicester. &ldquo;Into Parliament.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never heard of such a thing! Good gracious, what is the man?&rdquo; exclaims Volumnia.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is called, I believe&mdash;an&mdash;Ironmaster.&rdquo; Sir Leicester says it slowly, and with gravity and doubt, as not being sure but that he is called a Leadmistress; or that the right word may be some other word expressive of some other relationship to some other metal.</p>
<p>Volumnia utters another little scream.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He has declined the proposal, if my information from Mr. Tulkinghorn be correct, as I have no doubt it is, Mr. Tulkinghorn being always correct and exact; still that does not,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, &ldquo;that does not lessen the anomaly; which is fraught with strange considerations&mdash;startling considerations, as it appears to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Volumnia rising with a look candlestick-wards, Sir Leicester politely performs the grand tour of the drawing-room, brings one, and lights it at my Lady's shaded lamp.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I must beg you, my Lady,&rdquo; he says while doing so, &ldquo;to remain a few moments; for this individual of whom I speak, arrived this evening shortly before dinner, and requested&mdash;in a very becoming note;&rdquo; Sir Leicester, with his habitual regard to truth, dwells upon it; &ldquo;I am bound to say, in a very becoming and well expressed note&mdash;the favor of a short interview with yourself and <hi rend="italics">my</hi>self, on the subject of this young girl. As it appeared that he wished to depart to-night, I replied that we would see him before retiring.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Miss Volumnia with a third little scream takes flight, wishing her hosts&mdash;O Lud!&mdash;well rid of the&mdash;what is it?&mdash;Ironmaster!</p>
<p>The other cousins soon disperse, to the last cousin there. Sir Leicester rings the bell. &ldquo;Make my compliments to Mr. Rouncewell, in the housekeeper's apartments, and say I can receive him now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, who has heard all this with slight attention outwardly, looks towards Mr. Rouncewell as he comes in. He is a little over fifty perhaps, of a good figure, like his mother; and has a clear voice, a broad forehead from which his dark hair has retired, and a shrewd, though open face. He is a responsible-looking gentleman dressed in black, portly enough,
<pb n="278" id="p278"/>
but strong and active. Has a perfectly natural and easy air, and is not in the least embarrassed by the great presence into which he comes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir Leicester and Lady Dedlock, as I have already apologised for intruding on you, I cannot do better than be very brief. I thank you, Sir Leicester.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The head of the Dedlocks has motioned towards a sofa between himself and my Lady. Mr. Rouncewell quietly takes his seat there.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In these busy times, when so many great undertakings are in progress, people like myself have so many workmen in so many places, that we are always on the flight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester is content enough that the ironmaster should feel that there is no hurry there; there, in that ancient house, rooted in that quiet park, where the ivy and the moss have had time to mature, and the gnarled and warted elms, and the umbrageous oaks, stand deep in the fern and leaves of a hundred years; and where the sun-dial on the terrace has dumbly recorded for centuries that Time, which was as much the property of every Dedlock&mdash;while he lasted&mdash;as the house and lands. Sir Leicester sits down in an easy chair, opposing his repose and that of Chesney Wold to the restless flights of ironmasters.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lady Dedlock has been so kind,&rdquo; proceeds Mr. Rouncewell, with a respectful glance and a bow that way, &ldquo;as to place near her a young beauty of the name of Rosa. Now, my son has fallen in love with Rosa; and has asked my consent to his proposing marriage to her, and to their becoming engaged if she will take him&mdash;which I suppose she will. I have never seen Rosa until to-day, but I have some confidence in my son's good sense&mdash;even in love. I find her what he represents her, to the best of my judgment; and my mother speaks of her with great commendation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She in all respects deserves it,&rdquo; says my Lady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am happy, Lady Dedlock, that you say so; and I need not comment on the value to me of your kind opinion of her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That,&rdquo; observes Sir Leicester, with unspeakable grandeur; for he thinks the ironmaster a little too glib; &ldquo;must be quite unnecessary.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite unnecessary, Sir Leicester. Now, my son is a very young man, and Rosa is a very young woman. As I made my way, so my son must make his; and his being married at present is out of the question. But supposing I gave my consent to his engaging himself to this pretty girl, if this pretty girl will engage herself to him, I think it a piece of candor to say at once&mdash;I am sure, Sir Leicester and Lady Dedlock, you will understand and excuse me&mdash;I should make it a condition that she did not remain at Chesney Wold. Therefore, before communicating further with my son, I take the liberty of saying that if her removal would be in any way inconvenient or objectionable, I will hold the matter over with him for any reasonable time, and leave it precisely where it is.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Not remain at Chesney Wold! Make it a condition! All Sir Leicester's old misgivings relative to Wat Tyler, and the people in the iron districts who do nothing but turn out by torchlight, come in a shower upon his head: the fine grey hair of which, as well as of his whiskers, actually stirs with indignation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Am I to understand, sir,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, &ldquo;and is my Lady to understand;&rdquo; he brings her in thus specially, first as a point of gallantry, and next as a point of prudence, having great reliance on her sense; &ldquo;am I to understand, Mr. Rouncewell, and is my Lady to understand, sir,
<pb n="279" id="p279"/>
that you consider this young woman too good for Chesney Wold, or likely to be injured by remaining here?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly not, Sir Leicester.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am glad to hear it.&rdquo; Sir Leicester very lofty indeed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray, Mr. Rouncewell,&rdquo; says my Lady, warning Sir Leicester off with the slightest gesture of her pretty hand, as if he were a fly, &ldquo;explain to me what you mean.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Willingly, Lady Dedlock. There is nothing I could desire more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Addressing her composed face, whose intelligence, however, is too quick and active to be concealed by any studied impassiveness, however habitual, to the strong Saxon face of the visitor, a picture of resolution and perseverance, my Lady listens with attention, occasionally slightly bending her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am the son of your housekeeper, Lady Dedlock, and passed my childhood about this house. My mother has lived here half a century, and will die here I have no doubt. She is one of those examples&mdash;perhaps as good a one as there is&mdash;of love, and attachment, and fidelity in such a station, which England may well be proud of; but of which no order can appropriate the whole pride or the whole merit, because such an instance bespeaks high worth on two sides; on the great side, assuredly; on the small one, no less assuredly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester snorts a little to hear the law laid down in this way; but in his honor and his love of truth, he freely, though silently, admits the justice of the ironmaster's proposition.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pardon me for saying what is so obvious, but I wouldn't have it hastily supposed,&rdquo; with the least turn of his eyes towards Sir Leicester, &ldquo;that I am ashamed of my mother's position here, or wanting in all just respect for Chesney Wold and the family. I certainly may have desired&mdash;I certainly have desired, Lady Dedlock&mdash;that my mother should retire after so many years, and end her days with me. But, as I have found that to sever this strong bond would be to break her heart, I have long abandoned that idea.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester very magnificent again, at the notion of Mrs. Rouncewell being spirited off from her natural home, to end her days with an ironmaster.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been,&rdquo; proceeds the visitor, in a modest clear way, &ldquo;an apprentice, and a workman. I have lived on workman's wages, years and years, and beyond a certain point have had to educate myself. My wife was a foreman's daughter, and plainly brought up. We have three daughters, besides this son of whom I have spoken; and being fortunately able to give them greater advantages than we had ourselves, we have educated them well; very well. It has been one of our great cares and pleasures to make them worthy of any station.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A little boastfulness in his fatherly tone here, as if he added in his heart, &ldquo;even of the Chesney Wold station.&rdquo; Not a little more magnificence, therefore, on the part of Sir Leicester.</p>
<p>All this is so frequent, Lady Dedlock, where I live, and among the class to which I belong, that what would be generally called unequal marriages are not of such rare occurrence with us as elsewhere. A son will sometimes make it known to his father that he has fallen in love, say with a young woman in the factory. The father, who once worked in a factory himself, will be a little disappointed at first, very possibly. It may be that he had other views for his son. However, the chances are, that having
<pb n="280" id="p280"/>
ascertained the young woman to be of unblemished character, he will say to his son, &lsquo;I must be quite sure that you are in earnest here. This is a serious matter for both of you. Therefore I shall have this girl educated for two years&rsquo;&mdash;or, it may be&mdash;&lsquo;I shall place this girl at the same school with your sisters for such a time, during which you will give me your word and honor to see her only so often. If, at the expiration of that time, when she has so far profited by her advantages as that you may be upon a fair equality, you are both in the same mind, I will do my part to make you happy.&rsquo; I know of several cases such as I describe, my Lady, and I think they indicate to me my own course now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester's magnificence explodes. Calmly, but terribly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Rouncewell,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, with his right hand in the breast of his blue coat&mdash;the attitude of state in which he is painted in the gallery: &ldquo;do you draw a parallel between Chesney Wold, and a&mdash;&rdquo; here he resists a disposition to choke&mdash;&ldquo;a factory?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I need not reply, Sir Leicester, that the two places are very different; but, for the purposes of this case, I think a parallel may be justly drawn between them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester directs his majestic glance down one side of the long drawing-room, and up the other, before he can believe that he is awake.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are you aware, sir, that this young woman whom my Lady&mdash;my Lady&mdash;has placed near her person, was brought up at the village school outside the gates?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir Leicester, I am quite aware of it. A very good school it is, and handsomely supported by this family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, Mr. Rouncewell,&rdquo; returns Sir Leicester, &ldquo;the application of what you have said, is, to me, incomprehensible.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Will it be more comprehensible, Sir Leicester, if I say,&rdquo; the ironmaster is reddening a little, &ldquo;that I do not regard the village-school as teaching everything desirable to be known by my son's wife?&rdquo;</p>
<p>From the village school of Chesney Wold, intact as it is this minute, to the whole framework of society; from the whole framework of society, to the aforesaid framework receiving tremendous cracks in consequence of people (ironmasters, lead-mistresses, and what not) not minding their catechism, and getting out of the station unto which they are called&mdash;necessarily and for ever, according to Sir Leicester's rapid logic, the first station in which they happen to find themselves; and from that, to their educating other people out of <hi rend="italics">their</hi> stations, and so obliterating the landmarks, and opening the floodgates, and all the rest of it; this is the swift progress of the Dedlock mind.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My Lady, I beg your pardon. Permit me, for one moment!&rdquo; She has given a faint indication of intending to speak. &ldquo;Mr. Rouncewell, our views of duty, and our views of station, and our views of education, and our views of&mdash;in short, <hi rend="italics">all</hi> our views&mdash;are so diametrically opposed, that to prolong this discussion must be repellant to your feelings, and repellant to my own. This young woman is honored with my Lady's notice and favor. If she wishes to withdraw herself from that notice and favor, or if she chooses to place herself under the influence of any one who may in his peculiar opinions&mdash;you will allow me to say, in his peculiar opinions, though I readily admit that he is not accountable for them to me&mdash;who may, in his peculiar opinions, withdraw her from that notice and favor, she is at any time at liberty to do so. We are obliged to you for the plainness
<pb n="281" id="p281"/>
with which you have spoken. It will have no effect of itself, one way or other, on the young woman's position here. Beyond this, we can make no terms; and here we beg&mdash;if you will be so good&mdash;to leave the subject.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The visitor pauses a moment to give my Lady an opportunity, but she says nothing. He then rises and replies:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir Leicester and Lady Dedlock, allow me to thank you for your attention, and only to observe that I shall very seriously recommend my son to conquer his present inclinations. Good night!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Rouncewell,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester, with all the nature of a gentleman shining in him, &ldquo;it is late, and the roads are dark. I hope your time is not so precious but that you will allow my Lady and myself to offer you the hospitality of Chesney Wold, for to-night at least.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope so,&rdquo; adds my Lady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am much obliged to you, but I have to travel all night, in order to reach a distant part of the country, punctually at an appointed time in the morning.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Therewith the ironmaster takes his departure; Sir Leicester ringing the bell, and my Lady rising as he leaves the room.</p>
<p>When my Lady goes to her boudoir, she sits down thoughtfully by the fire; and, inattentive to the Ghost's Walk, looks at Rosa, writing in an inner room. Presently my Lady calls her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come to me, child. Tell me the truth. Are you in love?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;O! My Lady!&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, looking at the downcast and blushing face, says smiling:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who is it? Is it Mrs. Rouncewell's grandson?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, if you please, my Lady. But I don't know that I am in love with him&mdash;yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yet, you silly little thing? Do you know that he loves <hi rend="italics">you,</hi> yet?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think he likes me a little, my Lady.&rdquo; And Rosa bursts into tears.</p>
<p>Is this Lady Dedlock standing beside the village beauty, smoothing her dark hair with that motherly touch, and watching her with eyes so full of musing interest? Aye, indeed it is!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Listen to me, child. You are young and true, and I believe you are attached to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed I am, my Lady. Indeed there is nothing in the world I wouldn't do, to show how much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And I don't think you would wish to leave me just yet, Rosa, even for a lover.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, my Lady! O no!&rdquo; Rosa looks up for the first time, quite frightened at the thought.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Confide in me, my child. Don't fear me. I wish you to be happy, and will make you so&mdash;if I can make anybody happy on this earth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Rosa, with fresh tears, kneels at her feet and kisses her hand. My Lady takes the hand with which she has caught it, and, standing with her eyes fixed on the fire, puts it about and about between her own two hands, and gradually lets it fall. Seeing her so absorbed, Rosa softly withdraws; but still my Lady's eyes are on the fire.</p>
<p>In search of what? Of any hand that is no more, of any hand that never was, of any touch that might have magically changed her life? Or does she listen to the Ghost's Walk, and think what step does it most resemble? A man's? A woman's? The pattering of a little child's feet, ever coming on&mdash;on&mdash;on? Some melancholy influence is upon her;
<pb n="282" id="p282"/>
or why should so proud a lady close the doors, and sit alone upon the hearth so desolate?</p>
<p>Volumnia is away next day, and all the cousins are scattered before dinner. Not a cousin of the batch but is amazed to hear from Sir Leicester, at breakfast time, of the obliteration of landmarks, and opening of floodgates, and cracking of the framework of society, manifested through Mrs. Rouncewell's son. Not a cousin of the batch but is really indignant, and connects it with the feebleness of William Buffy when in office, and really does feel deprived of a stake in the country&mdash;or the pension list&mdash;or something&mdash;by fraud and wrong. As to Volumnia, she is handed down the great staircase by Sir Leicester, as eloquent upon the theme, as if there were a general rising in the North of England to obtain her rouge-pot and pearl necklace. And thus, with a clatter of maids and valets&mdash;for it is one appurtenance of their cousinship, that, however difficult they may find it to keep themselves, they <hi rend="italics">must</hi> keep maids and valets&mdash;the cousins disperse to the four winds of heaven; and the one wintry wind that blows to-day shakes a shower from the trees near the deserted house, as if all the cousins had been changed into leaves.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XXIX. <lb/> THE YOUNG MAN.</head>
<p>CHESNEY WOLD is shut up, carpets are rolled into great scrolls in corners of comfortless rooms, bright damask does penance in brown holland, carving and gilding puts on mortification, and the Dedlock ancestors retire from the light of day again. Around and around the house the leaves fall thick&mdash;but never fast, for they come circling down with a dead lightness that is sombre and slow. Let the gardener sweep and sweep the turf as he will, and press the leaves into full barrows, and wheel them off, still they lie ankle-deep. Howls the shrill wind round Chesney Wold; the sharp rain beats, the windows rattle, and the chimneys growl. Mists hide in the avenues, veil the points of view, and move in funeral wise across the rising grounds. On all the house there is a cold, blank smell, like the smell of the little church, though something dryer: suggesting that the dead and buried Dedlocks walk there, in the long nights, and leave the flavor of their graves behind them.</p>
<p>But the house in town, which is rarely in the same mind as Chesney Wold at the same time; seldom rejoicing when it rejoices, or mourning when it mourns, excepting when a Dedlock dies; the house in town shines out awakened. As warm and bright as so much state may be, as delicately redolent of pleasant scents that bear no trace of winter as hothouse flowers can make it; soft and hushed, so that the ticking of the clocks and the crisp burning of the fires alone disturb the stillness in the rooms; it seems to wrap those chilled bones of Sir Leicester's in rainbow-colored wool. And Sir Leicester is glad to repose in dignified contentment before the great fire in the library, condescendingly perusing the backs of his books, or honoring the fine arts with a glance of approbation. For he has his pictures, ancient and modern. Some, of the Fancy Ball School in which Art occasionally condescends to become a master, which would be best catalogued
<pb n="283" id="p283"/>
like the miscellaneous articles in a sale. As, &ldquo;Three high-backed chairs, a table and cover, long-necked bottle (containing wine), one flask, one Spanish female's costume, three-quarter face portrait of Miss Jogg the model, and a suit of armour containing Don Quixote.&rdquo; Or, &ldquo;One stone terrace (cracked), one gondola in distance, one Venetian senator's dress complete, richly embroidered white satin costume with profile portrait of Miss Jogg the model, one scimetar superbly mounted in gold with jewelled handle, elaborate Moorish dress (very rare), and Othello.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tulkinghorn comes and goes pretty often; there being estate business to do, leases to be renewed, and so on. He sees my Lady pretty often, too; and he and she are as composed, and as indifferent, and take as little heed of one another, as ever. Yet it may be that my Lady fears this Mr. Tulkinghorn, and that he knows it. It may be that he pursues her doggedly and steadily, with no touch of compunction, remorse, or pity. It may be that her beauty, and all the state and brilliancy surrounding her, only give him the greater zest for what he is set upon, and make him the more inflexible in it. Whether he be cold and cruel, whether immovable in what he has made his duty, whether absorbed in love of power, whether determined to have nothing hidden from him in ground where he has burrowed among secrets all his life, whether he in his heart despises the splendor of which he is a distant beam, whether he is always treasuring up slights and offences in the affability of his gorgeous clients&mdash;whether he be any of this, or all of this, it may be that my Lady had better have five thousand pairs of fashionable eyes upon her, in distrustful vigilance, than the two eyes of this rusty lawyer, with his wisp of neckcloth and his dull black breeches tied with ribbons at the knees.</p>
<p>Sir Leicester sits in my Lady's room&mdash;that room in which Mr. Tulkinghorn read the affidavit in Jarndyce and Jarndyce&mdash;particularly complacent. My Lady&mdash;as on that day&mdash;sits before the fire with her screen in her hand. Sir Leicester is particularly complacent, because he has found in his newspaper some congenial remarks bearing directly on the floodgates and the framework of society. They apply so happily to the late case, that Sir Leicester has come from the library to my Lady's room expressly to read them aloud. &ldquo;The man who wrote this article,&rdquo; he observes by way of preface, nodding at the fire as if he were nodding down at the man from a Mount, &ldquo;has a well-balanced mind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The man's mind is not so well balanced but that he bores my Lady, who, after a languid effort to listen, or rather a languid resignation of herself to a show of listening, becomes distraught, and falls into a contemplation of the fire as if it were her fire at Chesney Wold, and she had never left it. Sir Leicester, quite unconscious, reads on through his double eye-glass, occasionally stopping to remove his glass and express approval, as &ldquo;Very true indeed,&rdquo; &ldquo;Very properly put,&rdquo; &ldquo;I have frequently made the same remark myself;&rdquo; invariably losing his place after each observation, and going up and down the column to find it again.</p>
<p>Sir Leicester is reading, with infinite gravity and state, when the door opens, and the Mercury in powder makes this strange announcement:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The young man, my Lady, of the name of Guppy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sir Leicester pauses, stares, repeats in a killing voice:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The young man of the name of Guppy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Looking round, he beholds the young man of the name of Guppy,
<pb n="284" id="p284"/>
much discomfited, and not presenting a very impressive letter of introduction in his manner and appearance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray,&rdquo; says Sir Leicester to Mercury, &ldquo;what do you mean by announcing with this abruptness a young man of the name of Guppy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, Sir Leicester, but my Lady said she would see the young man whenever he called. I was not aware that you were here, Sir Leicester.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With this apology, Mercury directs a scornful and indignant look at the young man of the name of Guppy, which plainly says, &ldquo;What do you come calling here for, and getting <hi rend="italics">me</hi> into a row?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's quite right. I gave him those directions,&rdquo; says my Lady. &ldquo;Let the young man wait.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By no means, my Lady. Since he has your orders to come, I will not interrupt you.&rdquo; Sir Leicester in his gallantry retires, rather declining to accept a bow from the young man as he goes out, and majestically supposing him to be some shoemaker of intrusive appearance.</p>
<p>Lady Dedlock looks imperiously at her visitor, when the servant has left the room; casting her eyes over him from head to foot. She suffers him to stand by the door, and asks him what he wants?</p>
<p>&ldquo;That your ladyship would have the kindness to oblige me with a little conversation,&rdquo; returns Mr. Guppy, embarrassed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are, of course, the person who has written me so many letters?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Several, your ladyship. Several, before your ladyship condescended to favor me with an answer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And could you not take the same means of rendering a conversation unnecessary? Can you not still?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Guppy screws his mouth into a silent &ldquo;No!&rdquo; and shakes his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You have been strangely importunate. If it should appear, after all, that what you have to say does not concern me&mdash;and I don't know how it can, and don't expect that it will&mdash;you will allow me to cut you short with but little ceremony. Say what you have to say, if you please.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, with a careless toss of her screen, turns herself towards the fire again, sitting almost with her back to the young man of the name of Guppy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With your ladyship's permission, then,&rdquo; says the young man, &ldquo;I will now enter on my business. Hem! I am, as I told your ladyship in my first letter, in the law. Being in the law, I have learnt the habit of not committing myself in writing, and therefore I did not mention to your ladyship the name of the firm with which I am connected, and in which my standing &mdash; and I may add income &mdash; is tolerably good. I may now state to your ladyship, in confidence, that the name of that firm is Kenge and Carboy, of Lincoln's Inn; which may not be altogether unknown to your ladyship in connexion with the case in Chancery of Jarndyce and Jarndyce.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady's figure begins to be expressive of some attention. She has ceased to toss the screen, and holds it as if she were listening.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, I may say to your ladyship at once,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, a little emboldened, &ldquo;it is no matter arising out of Jarndyce and Jarndyce that made me so desirous to speak to your ladyship, which conduct I have no doubt did appear, and does appear, obtrusive&mdash;in fact, almost black-guardly.&rdquo; After waiting for a moment to receive some assurance to the contrary, and not receiving any, Mr. Guppy proceeds. &ldquo;If it had been
<pb n="285" id="p285"/>
Jarndyce and Jarndyce, I should have gone at once to your ladyship's solicitor, Mr. Tulkinghorn of the Fields. I have the pleasure of being acquainted with Mr. Tulkinghorn&mdash;at least we move when we meet one another&mdash;and if it had been any business of that sort, I should have gone to him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady turns a little round, and says &ldquo;You had better sit down.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank your ladyship.&rdquo; Mr. Guppy does so. &ldquo;Now, your ladyship;&rdquo; Mr. Guppy refers to a little slip of paper on which he has made small notes of his line of argument, and which seems to involve him in the densest obscurity whenever he looks at it; &ldquo;I&mdash;O yes!&mdash;I place myself entirely in your ladyship's hands. If your ladyship was to make any complaint to Kenge and Carboy, or to Mr. Tulkinghorn, of the present visit, I should be placed in a very disagreeable situation. That, I openly admit. Consequently, I rely upon your ladyship's honor.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady, with a disdainful gesture of the hand that holds the screen, assures him of his being worth no complaint from her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Thank your ladyship,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, &ldquo;quite satisfactory. Now&mdash;I&mdash;dash it!&mdash;The fact is, that I put down a head or two here of the order of the points I thought of touching upon, and they're written short, and I can't quite make out what they mean. If your ladyship will excuse me taking it to the window half a moment, I&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Guppy going to the window tumbles into a pair of love-birds, to whom he says in his confusion, &ldquo;I beg your pardon, I am sure.&rdquo; This does not tend to the greater legibility of his notes. He murmurs, growing warm and red, and holding the slip of paper now close to his eyes, now a long way off, &ldquo;C. S. What's C. S. for? O! &lsquo;E. S!&rsquo; O, I know! Yes, to be sure!&rdquo; And comes back enlightened.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am not aware,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, standing midway between my Lady and his chair, &ldquo;whether your ladyship ever happened to hear of, or to see, a young lady of the name of Miss Esther Summerson.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My Lady's eyes look at him full. &ldquo;I saw a young lady of that name not long ago. This past autumn.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, did it strike your ladyship that she was like anybody?&rdquo; asks Mr. Guppy, crossing his arms, holding his head on one side, and scratching the corner of his mouth with his memoranda.</p>
<p>My Lady removes her eyes from him no more.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not like your ladyship's family?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think your ladyship,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, &ldquo;can hardly remember Miss Summerson's face?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I remember the young lady very well. What has this to do with me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship, I do assure you, that having Miss Summerson's image imprinted on my art&mdash;which I mention in confidence&mdash;I found, when I had the honor of going over your ladyship's mansion of Chesney Wold, while on a short out in the county of Lincolnshire with a friend, such a resemblance between Miss Esther Summerson and your ladyship's own portrait, that it completely knocked me over; so much so, that I didn't at the moment even know what it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> that knocked me over. And now I have the honor of beholding your ladyship near, (I have often, since that, taken the liberty of looking at your ladyship in your carriage in the park, when I dare say you was not aware of me, but
<pb n="286" id="p286"/>
I never saw your ladyship so near), it's really more surprising than I thought it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Young man of the name of Guppy! There have been times, when ladies lived in strongholds, and had unscrupulous attendants within call, when that poor life of yours would not have been worth a minute's purchase, with those beautiful eyes looking at you as they look at this moment.</p>
<p>My Lady, slowly using her little hand-screen as a fan, asks him again, what he supposes that his taste for likenesses has to do with her?</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship,&rdquo; replies Mr. Guppy, again referring to his paper, &ldquo;I am coming to that. Dash these notes. O! &lsquo;Mrs. Chadband.&rsquo; Yes.&rdquo; Mr. Guppy draws his chair a little forward, and seats himself again. My Lady reclines in her chair composedly, though with a trifle less of graceful ease than usual, perhaps; and never falters in her steady gaze. &ldquo;A&mdash;stop a minute, though!&rdquo; Mr. Guppy refers again. &ldquo;E. S. twice? O yes! yes, I see my way now, right on.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Rolling up the slip of paper as an instrument to point his speech with, Mr. Guppy proceeds.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship, there is a mystery about Miss Esther Summerson's birth and bringing up. I am informed of that fact, because&mdash;which I mention in confidence&mdash;I know it in the way of my profession at Kenge and Carboy's. Now, as I have already mentioned to your ladyship, Miss Summerson's image is imprinted on my art. If I could clear this mystery for her, or prove her to be well related, or find that having the honor to be a remote branch of your ladyship's family she had a right to be made a party in Jarndyce and Jarndyce, why, I might make a sort of a claim upon Miss Summerson to look with an eye of more decided favor on my proposals than she has exactly done as yet. In fact, as yet she hasn't favored them at all.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A kind of angry smile just dawns upon my Lady's face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, it's a very singular circumstance, your ladyship,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, &ldquo;though one of those circumstances that do fall in the way of us professional men&mdash;which I may call myself, for though not admitted yet I have had a present of my articles made to me by Kenge and Carboy, on my mother's advancing from the principal of her little income the money for the stamp, which comes heavy&mdash;that I have encountered the person, who lived as servant with the lady who brought Miss Summerson up, before Mr. Jarndyce took charge of her. That lady was a Miss Barbary, your ladyship.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Is the dead color on my Lady's face, reflected from the screen which has a green silk ground, and which she holds in her raised hand as if she had forgotten it; or is it a dreadful paleness that has fallen on her?</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did your ladyship,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, &ldquo;ever happen to hear of Miss Barbary?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know. I think so. Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Was Miss Barbary at all connected with your ladyship's family?&rdquo;</p>
<p>My lady's lips move, but they utter nothing. She shakes her head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Not</hi> connected?&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy. &ldquo;O! Not to your ladyship's knowledge, perhaps? Ah! But might be? Yes.&rdquo; After each of these interrogatories, she has inclined her head. &ldquo;Very good! Now, this Miss Barbary was extremely close&mdash;seems to have been extraordinarily close for a female, females being generally (in common life at least) rather given to conversation&mdash;and my witness never had an idea whether she
<pb n="287" id="p287"/>
possessed a single relative. On one occasion, and only one, she seems to have been confidential to my witness, on a single point; and she then told her that the little girl's real name was not Esther Summerson, but Esther Hawdon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My God!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Guppy stares. Lady Dedlock sits before him, looking him through, with the same dark shade upon her face, in the same attitude even to the holding of the screen, with her lips a little apart, her brow a little contracted, but, for the moment, dead. He sees her consciousness return, sees a tremor pass across her frame like a ripple over water, sees her lips shake, sees her compose them by a great effort, sees her force herself back to the knowledge of his presence, and of what he has said. All this, so quickly, that her exclamation and her dead condition seem to have passed away like the features of those long-preserved dead bodies sometimes opened up in tombs, which, struck by the air like lightning, vanish in a breath.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship is acquainted with the name of Hawdon?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have heard it before.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Name of any collateral, or remote, branch of your ladyship's family?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, your ladyship,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, &ldquo;I come to the last point of the case, so far as I have got it up. It's going on, and I shall gather it up closer and closer as it goes on. Your ladyship must know&mdash;if your ladyship don't happen, by any chance, to know already&mdash;that there was found dead at the house of a person named Krook, near Chancery Lane, some time ago, a law-writer in great distress. Upon which law-writer, there was an inquest; and which law-writer was an anonymous character, his name being unknown. But, your ladyship, I have discovered, very lately, that that law-writer's name was Hawdon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what is <hi rend="italics">that</hi> to me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye, your ladyship, that's the question! Now, your ladyship, a queer thing happened after that man's death. A lady started up; a disguised lady, your ladyship, who went to look at the scene of action, and went to look at his grave. She hired a crossing-sweeping boy to show it her. If your ladyship would wish to have the boy produced in corroboration of this statement, I can lay my hand upon him at any time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The wretched boy is nothing to my Lady, and she does <hi rend="italics">not</hi> wish to have him produced.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, I assure your ladyship it's a very queer start indeed,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy. &ldquo;If you was to hear him tell about the rings that sparkled on her fingers when she took her glove off, you'd think it quite romantic.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There are diamonds glittering on the hand that holds the screen. My Lady trifles with the screen, and makes them glitter more; again with that expression which in other times might have been so dangerous to the young man of the name of Guppy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was supposed, your ladyship, that he left no rag or scrap behind him by which he could possibly be identified. But he did. He left a bundle of old letters.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The screen still goes, as before. All this time, her eyes never once release him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;They were taken and secreted. And to-morrow night, your ladyship, they will come into my possession.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Still I ask you, what is this to me?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="288" id="p288"/>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship, I conclude with that.&rdquo; Mr. Guppy rises. &ldquo;If you think there's enough, in this chain of circumstances put together&mdash;in the undoubted strong likeness of this young lady to your ladyship, which is a positive fact for a jury&mdash;in her having been brought up by Miss Barbary&mdash;in Miss Barbary stating Miss Summerson's real name to be Hawdon&mdash;in your ladyship's knowing both those names <hi rend="italics">very well</hi>&mdash;and in Hawdon's dying as he did&mdash;to give your ladyship a family interest in going further into the case, I will bring those papers here. I don't know what they are, except that they are old letters: I have never had them in my possession yet. I will bring those papers here, as soon as I get them; and go over them for the first time with your ladyship. I have told your ladyship my object. I have told your ladyship that I should be placed in a very disagreeable situation, if any complaint was made; and all is in strict confidence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Is this the full purpose of the young man of the name of Guppy, or has he any other? Do his words disclose the length, breadth, depth, of his object and suspicion in coming here; or, if not, what do they hide? He is a match for my Lady there. She may look at him, but he can look at the table, and keep that witness-box face of his from telling anything.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may bring the letters,&rdquo; says my Lady, &ldquo;if you choose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your ladyship is not very encouraging, upon my word and honor,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy, a little injured.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You may bring the letters,&rdquo; she repeats, in the same tone, &ldquo;if you&mdash;&mdash;please.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It shall be done. I wish your ladyship good day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On a table near her is a rich bauble of a casket, barred and clasped like an old strong chest. She, looking at him still, takes it to her and unlocks it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh! I assure your ladyship I am not actuated by any motives of that sort,&rdquo; says Mr. Guppy; &ldquo;and I couldn't accept of anything of the kind. I wish your ladyship good day, and am much obliged to you all the same.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So the young man makes his bow, and goes down-stairs; where the supercilious Mercury does not consider himself called upon to leave his Olympus by the hall-fire, to let the young man out.</p>
<p>As Sir Leicester basks in his library, and dozes over his newspaper, is there no influence in the house to startle him; not to say, to make the very trees at Chesney Wold fling up their knotted arms, the very portraits frown, the very armour stir?</p>
<p>No. Words, sobs, and cries, are but air; and air is so shut in and shut out throughout the house in town, that sounds need be uttered trumpet-tongued indeed by my Lady in her chamber, to carry any faint vibration to Sir Leicester's ears; and yet this cry is in the house, going upward from a wild figure on its knees.</p>
<p>&ldquo;O my child, my child! Not dead in the first hours of her life, as my cruel sister told me; but sternly nurtured by her, after she had renounced me and my name! O my child, O my child!&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p1a" n="[1]"/>
<head>ALLSOPP'S <lb/> PALE OR BITTER ALE.</head>
<head>REMARKS <lb/> UPON <lb/> THE ALLEGED USE OF STRYCHNINE <lb/> IN THE <lb/> MANUFACTURE OF PALE ALE.</head>
<docAuthor>BY BARON LIEBIG.</docAuthor>
<head>(IN A LETTER TO HENRY ALLSOPP, ESQ., BURTON-ON-TRENT.)</head>
<p>THE unguarded remark of a French chemist, that the strychnine imported into England is employed in part as a substitute for hops in the manufacture of beer, has lately spread alarm among the lovers of pale ale. <hi rend="italics">Having been appealed to by you, to express my opinion on this subject,</hi> which appears to me to be, in a dietetic point of view, one of considerable public interest, I now offer the following brief statement.</p>
<p>About a quarter of a century ago, a brewer in Westphalia fell into the practice of adulterating his beer with <hi rend="italics">nux vomica,</hi> from which it is well known that strychnine is obtained. The peculiar morbid symptoms, however, which resulted from the consumption of this adulterated beer, speedily led to the detection of the fraud. The effects produced by <hi rend="italics">nux vomica</hi> and strychnine are so characteristic, that every medical man will readily detect their origin. The French novelist, Alexandre Dumas, has described them, though with more imagination than truth, in his romance of &ldquo;Monte Christo.&rdquo; It is possible that the Westphalian case, which from being made the subject of a criminal trial obtained great notoriety, has given rise to the assumption that in England the strychnine imported is used for the purpose of mixing with beer. But nobody, at all acquainted with the great breweries of that country, could seriously entertain the suspicion of an adulteration of beer with strychnine or any other
<pb n="2" id="p2a"/>
deleterious substance. It is practically impossible that any operation of a doubtful character could be carried out in these extensive establishments, on account of the large number of workmen employed in them. Any attempt on the part of the brewer to impart qualities to his beer in an illicit manner, which are not to be obtained from malt or hops, would necessarily lead to his ruin; as he would be obliged to communicate his secret to too many persons, and to employ too many accomplices. The draymen themselves, as good connoisseurs in beer, would protest against any manipulation of a suspicious character. The case has even occurred of an eminent brewer not venturing to make use of a method suggested to him, for the purpose of clearing his beer more effectually, because the addition of a new material to the wort might have induced a suspicion in the minds of his workmen that it was an illicit proceeding, and this would have endangered the good reputation which his beer enjoyed. He stated to me at the same time, that no improvement could be introduced into a brewery, the object of which was not perfectly evident to everybody.</p>
<p>During a sojourn of several days at Burton-on-Trent, I had an opportunity of becoming intimately acquainted with the method pursued in the manufacture of pale ale. I convinced myself that the qualities of this excellent beverage depended mainly upon the care used in the selection of the best kinds of malt and hops, and upon the ingenuity exhibited in conducting the processes of mashing and fermenting. Our continental brewers have much to learn in these points to come up to the English brewers. I have no hesitation in saying that England possesses the greatest adepts in malting. I know positively that the chief brewers of Munich, who undoubtedly produce the best beer in Germany, have gone through an apprenticeship in Burton. This may account for the predilection entertained by the general public, as well as by medical men, for these varieties of beer; for the instinct of humanity and experience appear to be as good guides in the choice of things that contribute to health and enjoyment as the profoundest philosophy.</p>
<p>Professors GRAHAM and HOFMANN, in the excellent Report already addressed to you upon the alleged Adulteration of the pale ale by Strychnine, have indicated a very simple process for detecting the
<pb n="3" id="p3a"/>
most minute quantity of strychnine contained in beer. I have satisfied myself of the great convenience and accuracy of their method, and have farther assured myself, <hi rend="italics">by an analysis of several specimens of pale ale obtained from London houses, supplied by your establishment,</hi> of the utter groundlessness of the imputation, that this beer was poisoned with strychnine. I am positive, and am supported in my views by the concordant analyses of all chemists who have occupied themselves with the examination of beer, that the poisoning of pale ale with strychnine has never occurred. I believe I may safely add, that it never will take place; for although an ignorant brewer might be induced from interested motives, to add <hi rend="italics">nux vomica</hi> to his beer, the word strychnine so forcibly suggests one of the most virulent poisons, that whoever has heard anything about strychnine at all, is sure to be aware of this. By adulterating his beer with strychnine, the brewer would be knowingly committing a crime which, in the present state of science, must be followed by immediate detection and punishment.</p>
<p>Mr. E. MERCK, of Darmstadt, one of the most extensive strychnine manufacturers in Europe, informs me that this substance is peculiarly adapted to destroy vermin of all kinds. In many parts of Germany it is the popular poison for rats and mice. This fact fully accounts for the large amount of the drug that has lately been introduced into commerce.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The specimens of your pale ale sent to me, have afforded me another opportunity of confirming its valuable qualities. I am myself an admirer of this beverage, and my own experience enables me to recommend it, in accordance with the opinion of the most eminent English physicians, as a very agreeable and efficient tonic, and as a general beverage both for the invalid and the robust.</hi></p>
<closer>
<signed>JUSTUS LIEBIG.</signed>
<dateline>GIESSEN, MAY 6, 1852.</dateline>
</closer>
</div1><div1 type="advertisement">
<pb n="4" id="p4a"/>
<head>ALLSOPP'S <lb/> PALE OR BITTER ALE.</head>
<p>IN consequence of the reported adulteration of some descriptions of Bitter Beer, Messrs. SAMUEL ALLSOPP and SONS have received numerous incidental TESTIMONIALS to the excellence, purity, and salutary effects of their ALES. They consider it due to the Medical Profession, who have so long recommended ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE in all cases where dietetic regimen is required, to give publicity to these Testimonials, as a means of disabusing the public mind of any possible prejudice on the subject.</p>
<p>By the following extracts, among a number from the most eminent medical men, the Profession throughout the country will have the satisfaction of finding their just appreciation of the remedial advantages of ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE amply confirmed by the concurring testimony of the most able Physicians and Surgeons, as well as the most illustrious Chemists of the time:&mdash;</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM BARON LIEBIG.</head>
<p>&ldquo;The specimens of your Pale Ale sent to me afforded me another opportunity of confirming its valuable qualities. I am myself an admirer of this beverage, and my own experience enables me to recommend it, in accordance with the opinion of the most eminent English physicians, as a very agreeable and efficient tonic, <hi rend="italics">and as a general beverage, both for the invalid and the robust.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Giessen, May</hi> 6.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM PROFESSOR GRAHAM, F.R.S.</head>
<p>University College, London; and <lb/> PROFESSOR HOFMANN, PH.D. F.R.S. <lb/> College of Chemistry, London.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The sifting nature of the chemical examination which the Beers of Messrs. ALLSOPP'S manufacture for many mouths past have been subjected to, fully establishes their incontestable purity. The process of brewing Pale Ale is one in which nothing but water and the best malt and hops, of the first quality, are used; <hi rend="italics">it is an operation of the greatest delicacy and care,</hi> which would be entirely ruined by any tampering with the materials employed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">London, April</hi> 26.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM THE ANALYTICAL SANITARY COMMISSIONER OF THE &ldquo;LANCET.&rdquo; <lb/> MAY 15, 1852.</head>
<p>&ldquo;From the pure and wholesome nature of the ingredients employed, the moderate proportion of alcohol present, and the very considerable quantity of aromatic anodyne bitter derived from hops contained in these Beers, they tend to preserve the tone and vigour of the stomach, and conduce to the restoration of the health of that organ when in a state of weakness or debility. They resemble, indeed, from their lightness, a WINE OF MALT rather than an ordinary fermented infusion; and it is very satisfactory to find that a beverage of such general consumption is entirely free from every kind of impurity.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM PROFESSOR MUSPRATT, F.R.S.E. <lb/> Member of the Royal Irish Academy.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have carefully examined and analysed samples of your Ales, and find that they do not contain a particle of any injurious substance. <hi rend="italics">I and my family have used your Ales for years, and with perfect confidence in their purity.</hi> I know that Pale Ale, when prepared, as it must be in your Brewery, under scientific surveillance, contains a large quantity of nutritious matter; and the hop, by its tonic properties, gives a healthy tone to the stomach.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">College of Chemistry, Liverpool, April</hi> 20.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM SIR CHARLES M. CLARKE, BART. <lb/> Physician to her late Majesty the Queen Dowager.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have frequently recommended Bitter Ale medicinally, and when my home-brewed ale has been exhausted, I have been supplied with Ale <hi rend="italics">from your brewery.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Wiggington Lodge, May</hi> 2.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM THOMAS WATSON, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;In the genuineness and salubrity of Pale Ale and Bitter Beer as manufactured at Burton my confidence remains unshaken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Henrietta-street, Cavendish-square, May</hi> 5.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM GEORGE BUDD, M.D. <lb/> Senior Physician of King's College Hospital.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I did not want any testimony to satisfy me of the perfect purity of the Pale Ale <hi rend="italics">manufactured by you.</hi> A close observation of its effects upon myself, and upon many others to whom I have prescribed it, long ago convinced me, as much as the most searching chemical analysis could do, <hi rend="italics">that it contains nothing more than malt and hops, and that it is a first-rate beverage.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Dover-street, May</hi> 1.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<pb n="5" id="p5a"/>
<head>FROM MARSHALL HALL, M.D., F.R.S.</head>
<p>&ldquo;My confidence in the purity of your Pale Ale remains unshaken, and my opinion of <hi rend="italics">its great value</hi> in a dietetic and remedial point of view is entirely confirmed by long time and experience.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Grosvenor-street, April</hi> 30.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM BENJAMIN TRAVERS, ESQ., F.R.S.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I do not hesitate to affirm that no deleterious substance is employed in ALLSOPP'S Pale Ale and Bitter Beer, and that my confidence in <hi rend="italics">its wholesomeness as a beverage remains unshaken.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Green-street, April</hi> 30.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM WILLIAM FERGUSSON, ESQ., F.R.S.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I can fancy that the foolish rumour must have caused you some anxiety, but I believe that this history may prove the practical character of the proverb, that &lsquo;out of evil cometh good,&rsquo; for the report of the chemists very clearly shows that the <hi rend="italics">wholesome beverage</hi> which you supply to the public may be relied upon as of <hi rend="italics">the purest description.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">George-street, Hanover Square, May</hi> 5.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM GEORGE ROBERT ROWE, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;For the last twelve years I have prescribed the Pale Ale to invalids suffering from the various forms of indigestion, particularly in those cases resulting from the morbid effects of tropical climates, and I have no hesitation in asserting, with the happiest success. <hi rend="italics">I believe the Bitter Beer to be one of the greatest modern improvements in malt liquor,</hi> for, when properly prepared, it contains a larger quantity of farinaceous nutritive matter, and a less proportion of spirit; while the hop, by its tonic and narcotic properties, tends to give strength to the stomach and to allay its morbid irritability. The daily adoption I witness of the future drinking of Pale Ale by former invalids, leads to an additional conclusion in my mind <hi rend="italics">of its value and salubrity.</hi> I am induced to believe that Bitter Beer is an excellent adjunct to the physician in the exercise of his professional duties if properly administered, and consequently <hi rend="italics">a boon to mankind.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Cavendish Square, March</hi> 31.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM BANFIELD VIVIAN, ESQ., SURGEON.</head>
<p>&lsquo;ALLSOPP'S Pale and Bitter Ale is <hi rend="italics">one of the most useful of beverages, possessing exceedingly valuable tonic properties in an elegant form,</hi> Lupuline, or the active principles of the hop, is a well known tonic, but is apt to disagree with the stomach when given simply; it is usual, then, when prescribed, to combine it with some corrigent; no better can be than the extractive matters of malt; hence, as the analysis of your Beer has proved it to be a fermented solution of malt and hops only, we have a most useful medicine in a most acceptable form.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Crowan, Cornwall, June</hi> 7.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM JAMES HEYGATE, M.D., F.R.S.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I beg to say that I have been for years in the habit of recommending Messrs. ALLSOPP'S Pale Ale for invalids, and delicate stomachs, and that I consider it <hi rend="italics">a pure and wholesome beverage.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Derby, June</hi> 2.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM FREDERICK LEMAN, ESQ. <lb/> Senior Surgeon to the Teignmouth and Dawlish Infirmary.</head>
<p>&ldquo;My opinion of the good qualities of ALLSOPP'S Bitter Beer has never been shaken. I should hope that the public could not be deterred by such idle insinuation from the continued use of <hi rend="italics">so agreeable and healthful a beverage.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Teignmouth, May</hi> 3.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM B. NORTH ARNOLD, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I consider ALLSOPP'S Burton Ales as forming <hi rend="italics">the best malt beverage that can be taken, either in health or disease.</hi> From an experience of twelve years, I can most positively assert that in those cases in which malt liquors are suitable, none meet the desired effect more certainly; none are prescribed with more confidence by the physician. The absurd attempt lately made to prejudice them in the eyes of the public, will utterly fail in its object, both from their long continued use without the slightest injury to the most delicate constitution, and the high position they hold in the estimation of the medical profession, from the absence of all deleterious ingredients, and their tonic influence on the system.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Sutton Coldfield, May</hi> 5.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM GEORGE FABIAN EVANS, M.D. <lb/> Physician to the Birmingham General Hospital.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I deem it my duty to state that I have been in the habit of recommending the use of Burton and Bitter Ale, and of <hi rend="italics">using in my own family that of Messrs. ALLSOPP and SONS for many years.</hi> I have the greatest confidence in expressing my belief that the Burton Bitter Ale is not only free from adulteration, but is even <hi rend="italics">more wholesome than common home-brewed ale.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Birmingham, May</hi> 4.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM RICHARD FORMBY, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I often order to my patients &lsquo;ALLSOPP'S Bitter Beer,&rsquo; with marked advantage. I attribute this to the pure extract of hops and malt which the beer contains.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool, April</hi> 30.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<pb n="6" id="p6a"/>
<head>FROM JAMES PETRIE, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;For many years I have been in the habit of recommending the use of ALLSOPP'S Bitter Beer as a beverage to invalids who required a regulated diet; and I certainly could not have done so, unless from the evidence that the liquor was perfectly fermented, and made from the best and most wholesome ingredients. Where drinks of a nutritive and stomachic character are indicated, <hi rend="italics">I know of none, as yet, on which I feel I could so safely depend for doing good, as ALLSOPP'S Bitter Beer.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool, May</hi> 6.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM DAVID MACRORIE, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have been in the habit of recommending &lsquo;ALLSOPP'S Bitter Ale&rsquo; for invalids, ever since the time it was first made, <hi rend="italics">and do so still, as much as ever I did;</hi> and I am of opinion that it is in many cases an excellent and safe stomachic, and that it may often supersede the use of a medicated form of tonic, or strengthening medicine.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool, May</hi> 29.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM JAMES R. W. VOSE, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;It has long been my habit to recommend the use of Bitter Beer to invalids, and I shall <hi rend="italics">continue</hi> to do so, believing that it is one of <hi rend="italics">the most agreeable and valuable tonics we possess.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Liverpool, May</hi> 3.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM JOLLIFFE TUFNELL, ESQ. <lb/> Surgeon, City of Dublin Hospital.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I am in the habit of prescribing Bitter Beers as the drink for dinner use in very many cases.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Mount-street, Merrion Square, Dublin, May</hi> 3.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM CHRISTOPHER T. A. HUNTER, ESQ., SURGEON, &amp;c.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I recommend ALLSOPP'S Ale strongly to all my patients. <hi rend="italics">To me it is much more agreeable than that of other brewers.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Downham, Norfolk, May</hi> 16.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM THOMAS DAVIES, ESQ., SURGEON.</head>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">For several years I have drank myself, and have recommended to my patients, ALLSOPP'S Pale Ale.</hi> The careful manner in which the fermentation is conducted causes it to assimilate to the foreign wines much more than the ordinary ales of this country, and on this account it does not occasion that acidity of stomach, which the less perfectly fermented ales and home-made wines do.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Cheshunt, Herts, June</hi> 24.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM LLEWELYN JONES, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I continue the consumption of ALLSOPP'S Pale Ale <hi rend="italics">in my own family,</hi> and in the two public institutions with which I am connected, viz, our County Infirmary and the Cheshire Lunatic Asylum.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Chester, May</hi> 6.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM RICHARD P. JONES, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have often recommended Pale Ale to young children and persons suffering from excessive debility, and <hi rend="italics">shall continue to do so,</hi> from the good effects that have resulted.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Stanley-place, Chester, April</hi> 30.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM RAWSON SENIOR, ESQ., SURGEON, &amp;c.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have much pleasure in bearing my testimony to the <hi rend="italics">great value</hi> the celebrated Burton Ales exercise in many dyspeptic complaints, being a perfect medicine in numerous cases, tending to restore and to invigorate the tone of the stomach, which effects are doubtless attributable to the presence of the hop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Bowden, near Manchester, May</hi> 18.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM WM. MACLAREN ESQ., SURGEON.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I never believed the report for a moment. Your permitting your celebrated Burton Ale to be tested by two such eminent chemists as Professors Graham and Hofmann, will not only tend to calm the public mind; but will also tend to make such <hi rend="italics">an useful and wholesome beverage</hi> more generally brought into use.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Aberdeen, May</hi> 7.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM THOMAS MACAULAY, ESQ., <lb/> Surgeon to the Leicester Infirmary.</head>
<p>&ldquo;It will require a great deal more than a newspaper paragraph to shake my confidence in the <hi rend="italics">entire purity</hi> and <hi rend="italics">superlative wholesomeness of your Pale Bitter Ales.</hi> Having used them for many years in <hi rend="italics">my own family,</hi> and recommended them extensively amongst a large circle of patients, I am competent to bear the most unqualified testimony to your merits as manufacturers of what my experience tells me is the <hi rend="italics">very best form of malt liquor ever supplied to the public.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Leicester, May</hi> 5.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM WILLIAM GRAY, M.D.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have repeatedly recommended your Bitter Ale to my patients, when I find any of them require a mild, bitter, and pleasant beverage for giving increased impetus and vigour to a weak and low stomach; and so often have I seen decided advantages accrue from its use, that you may rest assured I shall still <hi rend="italics">continue</hi> to suggest its being drunk in numerous cases where a gentle tonic appears requisite.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Thorn, May</hi> 4.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<pb n="7" id="p7"/>
<head>FROM JAMES TEEVAN, ESQ., M.R.C.S.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I believe you continue to possess, and in a higher degree than ever, the confidence of the public. The strong man finds your Pale Ale an agreeable and nutritious beverage, the invalid discovers in it a pure and efficient tonic. <hi rend="italics">I shall continue to recommend it,</hi> believing it to be a most useful adjunct to medical treatment, equally <hi rend="italics">calculated to regain health and to preserve it.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Chesham-street, Belgrave-square, May</hi> 15<hi rend="italics">th,</hi> 1852.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM EDWARD C. HILL, ESQ., SURGEON.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I constantly recommend to my patients ALLSOPP'S Pale Ale as a wholesome beverage and tonic.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Cranbourne, near Salisbury, May</hi> 11.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM JAMES HAYWARD, ESQ. <lb/> Professional Chemist.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have for many years been in the habit of using the Bitter Beer of Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS <hi rend="italics">in my house,</hi> and have had frequent opportunities of examining the same analytically.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Sheffield.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM JOHN HARRISON, ESQ., SURGEON.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I am particularly glad that so foul an aspersion has been removed from <hi rend="italics">so valuable</hi> an article, as it would otherwise have deprived the Profession of recommending to their patients what they have hitherto found to be of <hi rend="italics">so much service,</hi> in so many cases <hi rend="italics">where other beverages were inadmissible.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Nicholas-street, Chester, May</hi> 4.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM J. H. PEPPER, F.C.S. A.C.E., &amp;c. <lb/> Professor of Chemistry, Royal Polytechnic Institution.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have examined a great many samples of the Bitter Beer brewed by the firm of Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS, and I cannot by chemical analysis discover any other matter but that procurable from malt, hops, and water. <hi rend="italics">From my own experience, I consider it a most wholesome beverage, well adapted to those in health,</hi> and calculated to <hi rend="italics">strengthen and invigorate the system in hot climates.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Royal Polytechnic Institution, June</hi> 17.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM THOMAS INMAN, M.D. Lecturer on Materia Medica and Medical Jurisprudence, Liverpool Royal Infirmary.</head>
<p>&ldquo;I have been in the habit of drinking ALLSOPP'S Bitter Ale for many years, and recommending it <hi rend="italics">in preference to any other beverage of a similar kind.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;16, <hi rend="italics">Rodney-street, Liverpool, May</hi> 1.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM &ldquo;PROVINCIAL MEDICAL JOURNAL,&rdquo; JUNE 23.</head>
<p>&ldquo;LIEBIG'S letter to Mr. ALLSOPP will satisfy any remaining doubts as to the purity of an article which is now so generally recommended by the Profession. We are bound to consider that that recommendation is founded in truth. <hi rend="italics">That it is so, there can now be no doubt whatever.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>FROM &ldquo;MONTHLY JOURNAL OF MEDICAL SCIENCE,&rdquo; AUGUST.</head>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. ALLSOPP'S advertisements contain medical names, <hi rend="italics">which are a guarantee against suspicion in their instances.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<p>Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS cannot refrain from reminding the Public, that it is entirely owing to the exertions of their House that Burton-on-Trent possesses its present important trade in Pale Ale. Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS first introduced this article to the Indian markets 30 years ago, since which period its great popularity has remained unshaken. These circumstances have induced Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS to come forward in defence of the peculiar manufacture in which they are engaged, and they cannot but refer with satisfaction to the triumphant refutation which has been given to the attacks recently made on this universal beverage.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<pb n="8" id="p8"/>
<head>BARON LIEBIG ON CERTAIN LATE ANONYMOUS <lb/> ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
<p>Extract of a Letter dated Munich, 12th September, 1852, from BARON LIEBIG to Mr. HENRY ALLSOPP, <lb/> Brewery, Burton-on-Trent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To my great astonishment and concern, my attention has lately been called to several anonymous articles and advertisements headed by my name, such as in the &mdash;, whose author altogether misrepresents the motives of my remarks, and even goes so far as to say &lsquo;that I had never analysed your beer, nor, perhaps, ever tasted it in my life,&rsquo; and to allege a retractation on my part of the original statement.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I emphatically declare that I had not the slightest knowledge of these anonymous articles, the contents of which I entirely disapprove of; and that in every respect I adhere to the statement made in my letter to you, which certainly you were, and are at perfect liberty to publish. (Signed) JUSTUS LIEBIG.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Munich,</hi> 12<hi rend="italics">th September,</hi> 1852.</p>
<p>&ldquo;HENRY ALLSOPP, ESQ.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>ALLSOPP'S PALE ALE AND DR. GLOVER.</head>
<p>The circulation given to a statement tending to invalidate the expression of Dr. Glover's opinion in favour of Pale Ale, compels Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS to connect this remarkable distribution of a calumny with other insidious attacks upon their firm which they have reason to know proceed from an unworthy and unneighbourly jealousy.</p>
<p>Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS, in reply, deem it their best course to adopt the same line of conduct as in the case of the similar perversion and mutilation of Baron Liebig's meaning, so indignantly repudiated by that eminent man himself. They publish, therefore, without abridgement, the letter they received from Dr. Glover (having his permission to do so); a letter the more valuable because it was not intended for publication, and is an unpremeditated evidence of that learned chemist's just appreciation of Pale Ale.</p>
<div3 type="section">
<head>DR. GLOVER TO MR. ALLSOPP.</head>
<p>&ldquo;SIR,&mdash;It was not my intention, in writing the hasty note to &lsquo;The Lancet,&rsquo; to cast any reflections upon or to implicate in any way, respectable brewers of Pale Ale.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I first saw the statement about the alleged use of strychnine in bittering ale, I looked upon the assertion as incredible, both on account of the price of the drug and the symptoms it would create; but, on experiment, I found that strychnine possesses such wonderful bitterness, that it might, perhaps, be used as AN ADJUVANT, at least by UNPRINCIPLED PERSONS. In short, my object was simply to show that the thing was not altogether so impossible as it appeared at first sight to be.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My opinion is, that hops should not enjoy the exclusive privilege of being used for bittering beer; but I do not pretend to discuss the point with practical men.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know there are bitters which might be used beneficially, in a medical point of view.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With regard to analysing your beer, my time is taken up, so far as analysing and chemistry are concerned, with two kinds of inquiries&mdash;1st. those which are purely scientific, and 2nd, those which are profitable. If you wish me, in the latter capacity, to analyse and report on your beer, I, of course, can have no objection.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have to prepare for an absence of three or four days to-morrow, and so beg you to excuse me replying to the letter of Mr. Bottinger, for which I am much obliged.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Newcastle-on-Tyne, April</hi> 11. (Signed) R. M. GLOVER.</p>
<p>&ldquo;P.S.&mdash;I presume you will hardly expect me to write to &ldquo;The Lancet.&rdquo; However, I shall be at home on Thursday evening, and most assuredly I have no desire to say anything which could weaken the confidence of the public in your beer. <hi rend="italics">But that I am not now in the habit of drinking Bitter Beer, I should be glad to show my confidence by drinking plenty of it.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;HENRY ALLSOPP, ESQ.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS beg to refer to the letter of Mr. HENRY ALLSOPP on this subject, in the &ldquo;Monthly Journal of Medical Science&rdquo; for October, in the concluding paragraph of which it is said&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I inserted Dr. Glover's good-natured remark on my Bitter Beer as an &lsquo;incidental testimonial&rsquo;&mdash;no more. I never called it &lsquo;a certificate,&rsquo; nor did I apply to him, or any other medical gentleman, for one. I am not responsible that such a construction has been placed upon the off-hand expressions of good opinion which have been <sic corr="sent">seut</sic> to me from all quarters.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Messrs. ALLSOPP AND SONS, in conclusion, wish to draw the attention of the public and the trade to the fact, that, by this disingenuous system of attack, and the perversions of facts gratuitously adopted, they are unwillingly drawn into that publicity the courting of which is made an accusation against them.</p>
<closer>
<dateline>Burton-on-Trent, October 8th, 1852.</dateline>
</closer>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="section">
<head>ALLSOPP'S PALE OR BITTER ALE</head>
<p>May be obtained in Casks of 18 Gallons and upwards, from the BREWERY, BURTON-ON-TRENT; and from the undermentioned BRANCH ESTABLISHMENTS:&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>LONDON, at 61, KING WILLIAM STREET, CITY;</item>
<item>LIVERPOOL, at COOK STREET;</item>
<item>MANCHESTER, at DUCIE PLACE;</item>
<item>DUDLEY, at BURNT TREE;</item>
<item>GLASGOW, at 115, ST. VINCENT STREET;</item>
<item>DUBLIN, at ULSTER CHAMBERS, DAME STREET;</item>
<item>BIRMINGHAM, at MARKET HALL;</item>
</list><p>At either of which places a list of respectable parties who supply the Beer in Bottles (and also in Casks at the same prices as from the Brewery), may at any time be seen.</p>

</div2>
<trailer>London: Bradbury &amp; Evans, Printers, Whitefriars</trailer></div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p9a" n="[9]"/>
<opener>12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</opener>
<head>MOTT'S <lb/> NEW SILVER ELECTRO PLATE,</head><p>Possessing in a pre-eminent degree the qualities of Sterling Silver.</p>
<p>A table may be elegantly furnished with this beautiful manufacture at a <lb/> fifth of the cost of Silver, from which it cannot be distinguished.</p>
<p>W. MOTT invites particular attention to his very extensive stock of all articles of Plate required for the Sideboard, Dinner and Breakfast Tables, now manufactured in this elegant material, comprising superb Epergnes, Candelabra, Salad Stands, Wine Coolers, Waiters, Corner Dishes, Meat and Venison Dishes, Dish Covers, Cruet Frames, Liqueur Stands, Spoons, and Forks, Tea and Coffee Services, Tea Kettles, Toast Racks, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="7">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> TEA POTS from </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 to </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 0 each. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> CRUET FRAMES, great variety from </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 to </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 each. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> LIQUEUR FRAMES, elegant designs from </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 18 </cell> 
<cell> 0 to </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 each. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> WAITERS, of every size, from 8 to 24 inches, commencing at </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 each. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> FLOWER VASES, with glass linings from </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 to </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 0 each. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> DISH COVERS, 12 to 20 Guineas the set. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

</p>
<p>SPOONS AND FORKS.</p>
<p>
<table rows="11" cols="11">
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> Fiddle. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> Threaded. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> King's. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
</row>
<row role="label">
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Spoons </cell> 
<cell> per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 8 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Table Forks </cell> 
<cell> per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 8 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Spoons </cell> 
<cell> per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 16 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Dessert Forks </cell> 
<cell> per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 16 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tea Spoons </cell> 
<cell> per dozen </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gravy Spoons </cell> 
<cell> per pair </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Sauce Ladles </cell> 
<cell> per pair </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 8 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 13 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Soup Ladles </cell> 
<cell> each </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 17 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 1 </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Salt Spoons </cell> 
<cell> per pair </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>ILLUSTRATED PAMPHLETS OF PRICES GRATIS.</p>
<p>W. MOTT, 12, CHEAPSIDE, CITY.</p>

<note><p>[Turn over</p></note><div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p10a" n="[10]"/>
<opener>Manufactory, 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON.</opener>
<head>English Watches that may be relied upon for <lb/> Accuracy and Durability.</head>
<head>MOTT'S <lb/> English Patent Levers in Gold Cases and <lb/> Gold Dial. Ten Guineas.</head>
<p>In order to assimilate as nearly as possible the cost of his best English Watches to the price of Foreign, over which they possess an immeasurable superiority in the grand requirements of correct performance and durability, W. MOTT has made a considerable reduction in the scale of prices, at the same time maintaining the high character by which, for so many years, they have been distinguished.</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="4">
<head>GOLD CASES.</head>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, double back and gold dial </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, with engraved back </cell> 
<cell> 11 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, full size, highly finished </cell> 
<cell> 14 </cell> 
<cell> 14 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Ladies' Gold Watches, engraved back </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, enamel dial </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial </cell> 
<cell> 13 </cell> 
<cell> 13 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, engraved back </cell> 
<cell> 14 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Gentlemen's Gold Watches, gold dial, very flat construction </cell> 
<cell> 18 </cell> 
<cell> 18 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="15" cols="4">
<head>SILVER CASES.</head>
<row>
<cell> Patent Lever, double back, jewelled </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, to go while winding </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Patent Lever, four holes jewelled, very flat construction </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Patent Lever, Hunting cases </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>WATCHES REPAIRED, AND ONE LENT GRATIS DURING THE TIME, <lb/> AT THE <lb/> MANUFACTORY, <lb/> No. 36, CHEAPSIDE, LONDON, <lb/> CORNER OF FRIDAY STREET.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="p11a" n="[11]"/>
<head>PUBLICATIONS AND WORKS
<lb/>
ISSUED BY <lb/> JOHN CASSELL, <lb/> LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE HILL, <lb/> LONDON.</head>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>UNCLE TOM'S CABIN,
<lb/>
WITH <lb/> TWENTY-SEVEN ILLUSTRATIONS BY GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, ESQ.</head>

<div3>
<opener>On Saturday, October 23, was published the First Number of</opener><head>UNCLE TOM'S CABIN,</head><p>To be continued Weekly, price Twopence.</p>
<p>The Work will be completed in Thirteen Weekly Numbers, each containing 32 pages large crown octavo, and Two elaborate Engravings, designed by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, Esq., to be printed separately on the finest Plate Paper. The whole work will be printed on good paper, in a bold type, hotpressed, and enclosed in a neat Wrapper. All persons who have read &ldquo;UNCLE TOM'S CABIN&rdquo; will, no doubt, secure this Edition for permanent preservation.</p>
<p>The Volume will be completed by Christmas, handsomely bound, price 3s. Cases for binding <lb/> will be issued at 6d. each.</p>
</div3>
<div3>
<opener>Now ready, price One Shilling, beautifully printed on 64 Pages super-royal 8vo, The</opener><head>UNCLE TOM'S CABIN ALMANACK; <lb/> Or, The Abolitionist Memento for 1853.</head>
<p>With Splendid Illustrations by GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, Esq.; J. GILBERT, Esq.; W. HARVEY, Esq.; <lb/> H. K. BROWNE, Esq. (&ldquo;Phiz&rdquo;); and other eminent Artists.</p>
<p>This Almanack, while affording all the information common to Almanacks, will furnish abundant demonstration of the truth of the statements made in Mrs. Harriet Beccher Stowe's popular Work, &ldquo;Uncle Tom's Cabin,&rdquo; including Narratives of the most striking Incidents in the Lives of Negro Slaves, such as Frederick Douglass, Rev. J. Pennington, D.D., Lewis Clarke, W. Wells Brown, Rev. J. Henson, M. Clarke, Gustavus Vassa, Ignatius Sancho, Toussaint L'Ouverture, &amp;c.; Important Phases in the Working of the Slavery System and the Fugitive Slave Law; Statistics of Slavery in the United States of America; Opinions of various Christian Ministers in favour of Slavery and Slaveholding; Visits to the Fugitive Slaves in Upper Canada; Comparative Results of Free and Slave Labour; Prospects of the Abolitionists; Appeal against Slavery, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>Among the Illustrations are the following, in the production of which no expense has been spared:&mdash;</p>
<p>
<table rows="13" cols="2">
<row>
<cell> Scene on the Coast of Africa </cell> 
<cell> By J. GILBERT, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Rev. J. Henson, when seven years old, separated from his Mother, and sold at a Slave Mart </cell> 
<cell> By GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frederick Douglass, when a lad, whipped by Covey, the Slave Breaker </cell> 
<cell> By J. GILBERT, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Frederick Douglass, the escaped Slave, on an English platform, denouncing Slaveholders and their Religious Abettors </cell> 
<cell> By J. GILBERT, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Slaves proceeding to the South to be Sold; from the Life of W. Wells Brown </cell> 
<cell> By J. GILBERT, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Flight of Fugitives guided by the North Star </cell> 
<cell> By W. HARVEY, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Fugitive Preston carried off by the Slave-hunters </cell> 
<cell> By H. K. BROWNE, Esq. (&ldquo;Phiz.&rdquo;) </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Landing of the Fugitives in Canada </cell> 
<cell> By W. HARVEY, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Rev. Dr. Pennington received by W. W. on his escape from Slavery </cell> 
<cell> By J. GILBERT, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Fugitive Seized while Happy in the midst of his Family </cell> 
<cell> By GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Fugitive Slave Flying from the Slave-hunters and their Bloodhounds </cell> 
<cell> By GEORGE CRUIKSHANK, Esq. </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Mrs. Banton's Treatment of her young Slaves; an Incident in the Life of Lewis Clarke </cell> 
<cell> By H. K. BROWNE, Esq. (&ldquo;Phiz.&rdquo;) </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Chase of a Slaver at Sea; The Interior of a Slave-Ship, &amp;c. &amp;c. </cell> 
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Now ready, price Sixpence,</opener><head>THE ILLUSTRATED EXHIBITOR ALMANACK <lb/> For 1853.</head>
<p>WITH UPWARDS OF THIRTY SPLENDID ENGRAVINGS, <lb/> Which will be found greatly to surpass all others for the variety, number, and beauty of its Illustrations.</p>
<p>The Original matter consists of Articles explanatory of the Engravings; in addition to which are given a Calendar, with very numerous Biographical and Historical Notices; Tide Tables; Astronomical Memoranda; List of Members of both Houses of Parliament; Government and Civic Officers, Bankers, Post-office Regulations, and other matters interesting to Tradesmen, Families, &amp;c.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pxxx11" n="[12]"/>
<opener>Price Twopence,</opener><head>THE POPULAR EDUCATOR ALMANACK <lb/> FOR 1853;</head><p>Containing Forty-eight Pages of most interesting and valuable Educational Statistics; including a Comparative View of Education at Home and Abroad; Essays on the Leading Sciences; Brief Notices of Eminent Scholars; Exposition of Technical Terms, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
</div2><div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Also, price Twopence,</opener><head>THE ILLUSTRATED TEMPERANCE ALMANACK,</head><p>Which, in addition to all the matter pertaining to such an Almanack, will contain a powerfully written tale by Mrs. Harriett Beecher Stowe, entitled, &ldquo;The Pledge Taken; or, the Husband Saved, and the Family made Happy.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Price Sixpence,</opener><head>The Protestant Dissenters' Illustrated Almanack,</head><p>Is now ready, with Twelve beautiful Engravings, designed by GILBERT, illustrative of some striking <lb/> events in the History of Nonconformity.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>Preparing for immediate publication, price 2s. 6d.,</opener><head>THE LADIES' WORK BOOK,</head><p>Containing full Instructions for every kind of Ladies' Work, in Point Lace, Knitting, Embroidery, Crochet, &amp;c., forming the most splendid Book for the Work-table ever issued. This Work will contain an immense number of the Newest Designs for Ladies' Work, of every description, and will be produced in a style perfectly unique.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>THE BOOK FOR EVERY FAMILY! <lb/> Now ready, the First Volume of</opener><head>THE POPULAR EDUCATOR,</head><p>The most comprehensive Educational Work ever issued from the Press. The ordinary Edition, with the usual Weekly Headings, price 3s. 6d. neatly bound; the Fine Paper Edition, without the Weekly Headings, price 4s. 6d. well bound in cloth.</p>
<p>The POPULAR EDUCATOR includes a regular course of instruction in English and English Grammar, French, German, Latin, Geometry, Arithmetic, Geography, Geology, Natural History, Botany, Biography, Ancient History, Architecture, Music, Physiology, &amp;c.</p>
<p>The POPULAR EDUCATOR, No. I. of Volume the Second, is illustrated with a Map of Europe (measuring 11 inches by 9), without any additional charge; and the succeeding Lessons in Geography will be accompanied by a Series of Twelve Maps, engraved on copper. These Maps will appear at regular intervals, and will be printed in the text, so as to admit of being separated if necessary, and studied along with the description of the different countries to which they belong.</p>
<p>The POPULAR EDUCATOR is published in Weekly Numbers,&mdash;the Common Edition, 1d.; the Fine Paper, 1&frac12;d. each. Also, in Monthly Parts,&mdash;Fine Edition, without the Weekly Headings, 7d., or if Five Numbers, 8&frac12;d.; Common Edition, with the Weekly Headings, 5d., or when Five Numbers, 6d. each.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>CASSELL'S SHILLING EDITION OF EUCLID,<lb/>Price 1s. in stiff covers, or 1s. 6d. neat cloth,</opener><head>THE ELEMENTS OF GEOMETRY;</head><p>Being the First Six Books, with the Eleventh and Twelfth, of Euclid.</p>
<p>From the Text of ROBERT SIMSON, M.D., Emeritus Professor of Mathematics in the University of Glasgow; with Corrections, Annotations, and Exercises, by ROBERT WALLACE, A.M., of the University of Glasgow, and Collegiate Tutor of the University of London.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<opener>UNIFORM WITH CASSELL'S EDITION OF EUCLID, <lb/> Price 1s. in stiff covers, or 1s. 6d. neat cloth,</opener><head>CASSELL'S ELEMENTS OF ARITHMETIC,</head><p>Being a Companion to Cassell's Euclid, <lb/> Leading the Student from Simple Numeration through all the Elementary and Practical Rules required for Mathematics and the Counting-house. Edited by Professor WALLACE, A.M., of the same University.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<head>JOHN CASSELL'S &ldquo;LIBRARY,&rdquo; COMPLETE.</head>
<p>This Series consists of Twenty-six Volumes, at 7d. each, in stiff covers; or neatly bound in Double Volumes, cloth gilt, at 1s. 6d.; or three Volumes in one, 2s. 3d.; or the Series complete, at 19s. 6d. in cloth, or in a neat Library Box, glazed, with lock and key, 25s.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pxxx12" n="[13]"/>
<head>THE ILLUSTRATED MAGAZINE OF ART.</head>
<p>ON TUESDAY, FEBRUARY 1, 1853, WILL BE PUBLISHED, <lb/> PRICE ONE SHILLING, <lb/> THE FIRST MONTHLY PART <lb/> OF <lb/> THE ILLUSTRATED MAGAZINE OF ART: <lb/> BEING A NEW AND GREATLY IMPROVED SERIES OF <lb/> THE ILLUSTRATED EXHIBITOR &amp; MAGAZINE OF ART.</p>
<p>JOHN CASSELL considers it to be due to himself, as well as to the numerous purchasers of the ILLUSTRATED EXHIBITOR AND MAGAZINE OF ART, briefly to state his reasons for making any alterations in a Work which, in its present form, has secured such extensive patronage.</p>
<p>1. AS TO THE TITLE:&mdash;that of &ldquo;Illustrated Exhibitor,&rdquo; has led many persons to suppose that the present series is a continued illustration of the &ldquo;Great Exhibition;&rdquo; this is not the fact, and the new title will describe its true character&mdash;namely, that of a rich collection of choice Specimens of Art, including Painting, Sculpture, Architecture, Ornamental Design, Portraits, Natural History, Machinery, Manufacturing Processes, &amp;c.; together with original Literary Articles, explanatory of the Engravings, or on miscellaneous subjects of interest.</p>
<p>2. As to the issue in <hi rend="italics">Monthly Parts.</hi> It was the intention of JOHN CASSELL, from the very first, that the work should be worthy of occupying a permanent station, as a regular Library Volume, not only an interesting Family Book, but a companion for the Drawing-room or the Study. In consequence, however, of the plan of <hi rend="italics">weekly</hi> issue, this design has not been carried out to the extent which is considered desirable. By the new arrangement, each Monthly Part will exhibit a completeness and beauty which otherwise would scarcely have been practicable. But as among those persons who have taken in the <hi rend="italics">Weekly Numbers,</hi> there is a large class to whom it will be most convenient to continue it in that form, the monthly parts will be divided into weekly portions as heretofore, but with this difference, that, in addition to the sixteen pages of letter-press, with engravings in the text, there will be a first-class engraving, printed separately on fine plate paper, and the whole enclosed in a neat wrapper. The Weekly Numbers, with this enlargement and improvement, will be <hi rend="italics">threepence</hi> each.</p>
<p>In order to render this a truly magnificent work, and to make it really what its name imports&mdash;a Magazine of Art, and the most interesting Pictorial Work of the age, JOHN CASSELL intends, in addition to a profusion of fine engravings throughout the work, to give at least four principal engravings in each Monthly Part, to be printed separately, in very superior style, upon superfine plate paper; the designing and engraving of these will cost from &pound;25 to &pound;40 each. Amongst other new features of the forthcoming work, not the least interesting, will be a series entitled, &ldquo;THE MEN AND WOMEN OF THE AGE,&rdquo; with Portraits and original Biographical Sketches. Other departments will include Specimens of the Works of the Great Masters; remarkable Historical Events; the Triumphs of Architectural Art; the Wonders of Natural History; Views of Public Buildings, Mansions, &amp;c.; Machinery and Inventions; Various Sciences; and Ornamental Needle-work.</p>
<p>In other respects, too, the ILLUSTRATED MAGAZINE OF ART will be decidedly superior to its predecessor, upon which such high eulogiums have been pronounced by all portions of the Public Press. The paper, the typography, the engravings, the literary articles, will all be of an improved character; and six of the Monthly portions when completed will form a Volume, which, for interest, value, and beauty, will defy successful competition.</p>
<p>JOHN CASSELL, LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE-HILL.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pxxx13" n="[14]"/>
<head>DOMESTIC WORSHIP.</head>
<div3>
<opener>On the First of January, 1853, will be published, printed in a new, bold, and handsome type, demy quarto, <lb/> PRICE ONE SHILLING, <lb/> PART I, OF</opener><head>THE ALTAR OF THE HOUSEHOLD:</head><p>A SERIES OF <lb/> Services for Domestic Worship for every Morning and Evening in the Year; <lb/> SELECT PORTIONS OF HOLY WRIT, <lb/> AND <lb/> PRAYERS AND THANKSGIVINGS FOR PARTICULAR OCCASIONS; <lb/> With an Address to Heads of Families.</p>
<p>EDITED BY THE REV. JOHN HARRIS, D.D., <lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Principal of New College. St. John's Wood; Author of &ldquo;The Great Teacher;&rdquo; &ldquo;Mammon;&rdquo;</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">&ldquo;Pre-Adamite Earth,&rdquo; &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
</div3><div3>
<head>ASSISTED BY EMINENT CONTRIBUTORS.</head>
<p>&ldquo;The principal part of family religion,&rdquo; said Archbishop Tillotson, &ldquo;is prayer every morning and evening, and reading some portion of Scripture; and this is so necessary to keep alive a sense of God and religion in the minds of men, that, when it is neglected, I do not see how any family can, in reason, be esteemed a family of Christians, or indeed, have any religion at all.&rdquo; And, says Doddridge, in his &ldquo;Address to the Master of a Family,&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;God only knows what a Church may arise from one godly family, what a harvest may spring up from a single seed; and, on the other hand, it is impossible to say how many souls may perish by the treacherous neglect of a single person, and to speak plainly, by <hi rend="italics">your own.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Work now announced is designed to be eminently SCRIPTURAL. For each Service there will be a portion of HOLY WRIT, which, in accordance with its original structure, will appear as <hi rend="italics">continuous statement,</hi> or in <hi rend="italics">poetic feet,</hi> so necessary to its being rightly understood on the part of the reader, and, consequently, to its due effect on others.</p>
<p>To each portion of Scripture will succeed a few OBSERVATIONS, by way of popular explanation or enforcement; while the concluding PRAYER will accord with the feeling of the passage, so that it may act as fuel to kindle or sustain the hallowed flame of devout desire or grateful thanksgiving. At the same time, due <hi rend="italics">brevity</hi> will be preserved.</p>
<p>Scriptural in its character, the Work will be adapted to all sections of the Christian Church; as a guarantee for which, the Publisher feels great pleasure in appealing not only to the distinguished Editor, but to other Ministers engaged in its preparation, among whom may now be mentioned&mdash;</p>
<list>
<item>THE REV. J. SHERMAN,</item>
<item>THE REV. W. URWICK, D.D.,</item>
<item>THE REV. GEORGE SMITH,</item>
<item>THE REV. R. FERGUSON, LL.D.,</item>
<item>THE REV. PROFESSOR LORIMER,</item>
<item>THE REV. NEWMAN HALL, B.A.,</item>
<item>THE REV. DR. BEAUMONT,</item>
<item>THE REV. WILLIAM. M. BUNTING,</item>
<item>THE REV. WILLIAM BROCK,</item>
<item>THE REV. JOHN KENNEDY, A.M.,</item>
<item>THE REV. WILLIAM LEASK,</item>
<item>THE REV. CHARLES WILLIAMS,</item>
<item>THE REV. W. W. EWBANK,</item>
<item>THE REV. SAMUEL MARTIN.</item>
</list><p>The Publisher, therefore, confidently promises as the result, a Work of singular ability, adapted to every Family where such aid in Domestic Worship is occasionally or regularly required.</p>
<p>The Work will be completed in Twelve Parts, one to appear on the first day of each successive month; the whole to form One Splendid Volume; with Frontispiece and Title-page engraved on steel by first-rate Artists.</p>

</div3>
</div2>
<trailer>JOHN CASSELL, LA BELLE SAUVAGE YARD, LUDGATE-HILL.</trailer></div1>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pxxx14" n="[15]"/>
<head>LEGAL EXPECTATIONS.</head>
<p>IN some cases these are as perplexing as any emotions a person can endure, fraught with a thousand casualties, and subject to numberless caprices, which seem to make everybody the sport of chance, very frequently the whole struggles, expenses, journeys, &amp;c. of a series of years, with loads of rusty documents and piles of papers, neatly tied with red tape, are in one moment, for some unlucky word, swept into oblivion for a whole term, and hope deferred sickens the heart of client and advocate. Happily no such circumstance can occur in the LEGAL EXPECTATIONS of the PUBLIC, as they refer to E. MOSES &amp; SON's settlement of every SUIT for the SEASON. In this respect every one may <hi rend="italics">legally expect</hi> the best, the most novel, and the most elegant and substantial DRESS for AUTUMN and WINTER, their New Styles being the essence of ART, TASTE, and FASHION; comprehending a vast array of New Materials, a magnificent exposition of the Manufacture of every Country in the World&mdash;but a triumphant display of skill in designs for DRESS, which alone can render these materials available for the season.</p>
<p>WHEREAS, E. MOSES &amp; SON <hi rend="italics">have</hi> LEGALLY <hi rend="italics">bought, prior to any advances in the markets, and for ready money, the largest, choicest, and most valuable stock of fabrics specially designed for this season, and comprising every kind of material, which, from its strength, elegance, and beauty, is worth calling a Novelty; and have liberally remunerated the best Artistes and workmen for making these into the most fashionable kinds of</hi> AUTUMN <hi rend="italics">and</hi> WINTER OVERCOATS, PALET&Ocirc;TS, WEAPPERS, CAPES, &amp;c. &amp;c. <hi rend="italics">Prodigious transactions rendering small profits remunerative, and amazing advantages in purchases on the most gigantic scale, warrant every patron of</hi> E. MOSES &amp; SON'S <hi rend="italics">Establishment, and its Branches,</hi> LEGALLY <hi rend="italics">to expect the most fashionable, the best, and the cheapest Dress ever presented.</hi></p>
<p>OUTFITS to all parts of the World cheaper, better, and more suitable than can be had elsewhere.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head>E. MOSES &amp; SON'S <lb/> AUTUMN AND WINTER LIST OF PRICES.</head>
<p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>MEN'S WINTER COATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The New BEQUEME Over-Coat, designed by E. MOSES &amp; SON </cell> 
<cell> from 25<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to 4 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Pea Coats </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 8 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Chesterfields and Codringtons, various materials </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Witney Wrapper </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 16 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Derby Coat, made to wear as an Over or Surtout Coat </cell> 
<cell> from 21<hi rend="italics">s</hi> to 2 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The MELTON MOWBRAY, a new and elegant Overcoat </cell> 
<cell> from 25<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 2 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Wellington Sac, made to form Coat, Cloak, and Traveller's Companion, designed by and only to be had of E. Moses &amp; Son, </cell> 
<cell> from 40<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>BOYS' WINTER COATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Byron Coat </cell> 
<cell> from 0 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Chesterfield </cell> 
<cell> from 0 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Bulwer, in cloth of all colours, and the new Melton Mowbray material, a neat gentlemanly style of Coat </cell> 
<cell> 10<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>WALKING, FISHING &amp; SHOOTING COATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Plaid Shooting Coats </cell> 
<cell> from 0 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> The Melton Mowbray Cambridge Coat, quite a new material </cell> 
<cell> 21<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Fishing Coats in endless variety, suited either for Sporting, Gardening, or House Coat, </cell> 
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 5 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>AUTUMN AND WINTER WAISTCOATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> White Quiltings (for Dress) </cell> 
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 0 </cell> 
<cell> 9 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Kerseymere </cell> 
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 0 </cell> 
<cell> 13 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Doeskins, Tweeds, &amp;c. </cell> 
<cell> 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 0 </cell> 
<cell> 9 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Embroidered Cloth </cell> 
<cell> from 0 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> A large assortment of Fancy Thibets, and a variety of Fancy Materials </cell> 
<cell> from 4<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 0 </cell> 
<cell> 13 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>Particular attention is requested to the immense STOCK OF WAISTCOATS FOR BALLS, WEDDINGS, &amp;c., They are the richest and most novel that can be produced.</p>
<p>UNIFORMS FOR THE ARMY AND NAVY.</p>
<p>According to the Present Regulations.</p>
<p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>AUTUMN AND WINTER TROUSERS.</head>
<row>
<cell> &nbsp; </cell> 
<cell> &pound; </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> </cell> 
<cell> <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Tweeds </cell> 
<cell> from 4s. 6d. to 0 </cell> 
<cell> 7 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Kerseymere, for Dress </cell> 
<cell> from 9s. 6d. to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Black Doeskin, for Dress </cell> 
<cell> from 9<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 6 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> A large assortment of West of England Plain and Fancy Doeskins </cell> 
<cell> 18s., 22s. to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>DRESS COATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Dress Coat </cell> 
<cell> from 0 </cell> 
<cell> 17 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best quality </cell> 
<cell> from 2 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>FROCK COATS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Frock Coat </cell> 
<cell> from 1 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Best Coat </cell> 
<cell> from 3 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>JUVENILE CLOTHING.</head>
<row>
<cell> Tunic and Hussar Suit </cell> 
<cell> from 15<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 12 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Polka Jacket, handsomely trimmed </cell> 
<cell> 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italics">d.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Spanish Dress from </cell> 
<cell> 26<hi rend="italics">s.</hi> to 1 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p><p>
<table rows="44" cols="4">
<head>LIVERIES.</head>
<row>
<cell> Page's suit </cell> 
<cell> from 1 </cell> 
<cell> 8 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Footman's </cell> 
<cell> 2 </cell> 
<cell> 15 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Groom's </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Coachman's </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">All the above materials are made into Suits to match, and form a very comfortable dress, either for Travelling, Walking, or Office.</hi></p>
<p>LADIES' AND GENTLEMEN'S HOSIERY.</p>
<p>The Largest Stock in the Kingdom,</p><p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<head>LADIES' RIDING HABITS.</head>
<row>
<cell> Summer Cloth Habits, with &frac78; train </cell> 
<cell> from 2 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superior Cloth Habits </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 3 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
<row>
<cell> Superfine quality </cell> 
<cell> 4 </cell> 
<cell> 10 </cell> 
<cell> 0 </cell> 
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>HATS AND CAPS, THE NEWEST STYLES AT THE LOWEST PRICES.</p>
<p>A large Assortment of HUNTING and SHOOTING BOOTS, including the celebrated GROUSE BOOT.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">An Immense Stock of the most superior Sea Boots, at</hi>
 14<hi rend="italics">s. per pair.</hi></p>
<p>GENTLEMEN'S DRESS BOOTS, THE MOST RECHERCHE.</p>
<p>Boots for the &ldquo;Diggings.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The FUR and SHAWL DEPARTMENT is now replete with every Novelty.</p>
<p>A New Book, entitled &ldquo;The World's Pharos,&rdquo; containing the Emigrant's Guide, and directions for self-measurement, with full Lists of Prices, may be had on application, or post free.</p>
<p>Any Article purchased or made to measure, if not approved, will be exchanged, or, if preferred, the money returned.</p>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Establishments are closed every Friday Evening at sunset, until Saturday Evening sunset, when business is</hi>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">resumed until</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock.</hi></p>
<p>CAUTION.&mdash;E. MOSES &amp; SON regret having to guard the Public against imposition, having learned that the <hi rend="italics">untradesmanlike falsehood</hi> of &ldquo;being connected with their Establishment,&rdquo; or &ldquo;It's the same concern,&rdquo; has been resorted to in many instances, and for obvious reasons. They beg to state they have NO CONNECTION WITH ANY OTHER HOUSE IN OR OUT OF LONDON, EXCEPT THEIR OWN ESTABLISHMENTS, as follows:&mdash;</p>
<p>London City Establishments:&mdash;154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, and 86, Aldgate, opposite the Church.</p>
<p>London West End Branch:&mdash;506, 507, and 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, and 3, corner of Hart-street.</p>
<p>Bradford, &ldquo;Yorkshire&rdquo; Branch, 19, Bridge-st. Sheffield Branch, 36. Fargate.</p>
<p>MERCHANT TAILORS, CLOTHIERS, DRAPERS, HATTERS, HOSIERS, FURRIERS, BOOT AND <lb/> SHOE MANUFACTURERS, GENERAL WAREHOUSEMEN, AND OUTFITTERS <lb/> FOR LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="pxxx15" n="[16]"/>
<head>HEAL &amp; SON'S <lb/> EIDER DOWN QUILT,</head><p>The most luxurious Covering for the Bed, the Couch, or the Carriage.</p>
<p>PRICED LIST SENT POST-FREE.</p>
<p>The Catalogue contains Designs and Prices of upwards <lb/> of One Hundred Different Bedsteads, <lb/> In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, <lb/> Mahogany, Rosewood, &amp; Walnut Tree Woods.</p>
<p>HEAL AND SON'S ILLUSTRATED <lb/> CATALOGUE OF BEDSTEADS <lb/> AND <lb/> PRICED LIST OF BEDDING, <lb/> SENT FREE BY POST <lb/> FROM THEIR <lb/> BEDSTEAD AND BEDDING MANUFACTORY, <lb/> 196, TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD, <lb/> LONDON.</p>
<closer>BRADBURY AND EVANS, PRINTERS, WHITEFRIARS.</closer>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
