<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><emph>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. VI:</emph>
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp>
<name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name>
<name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name>
<name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name>
<name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>

<respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>M. Brooke Phillips</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc. and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 115K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. VI</title>

<author>Boz</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>R. Seymour and Phiz</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>   37 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall, 186, Strand</publisher>
<date>1836</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number Dickens 13 pt. 6 (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language id="eng">English</language>

</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>

<change>
<date>2002-11-18, </date><respStmt><name> Jill Kuhn Sexton </name><resp></resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-25, </date><respStmt><name>Harris Henderson</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text>
<front>
<titlePage>


<titlePart> No. VI.]</titlePart>

<docEdition>[PRICE  1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PICKWICK CLUB <lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE <lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES <lb/> AND <lb/> Sporting Transactions <lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS.  </titlePart></docTitle>

<docAuthor>
EDITED BY &ldquo;BOZ.&rdquo;
</docAuthor>

<docEdition>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.
</docEdition>

<docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVI</docDate>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="pii" n="ii"/>
<p>
<figure id="ill1">
<p><hi rend="italics">Page 154</hi></p>
</figure>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="iii"/>
<p>
<figure id="ill2">
<p><hi rend="italics">Page 159</hi></p>
</figure>
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="text">
<pb id="p147" n="147"/>

<head>[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER XV.</head>

<head>IN WHICH IS GIVEN A FAITHFUL PORTRAITURE OF TWO DISTINGUISHED PERSONS; AND AN ACCURATE DESCRIPTION OF A PUBLIC BREAKFAST IN THEIR HOUSE AND GROUNDS: WHICH PUBLIC BREAKFAST, LEADS TO THE RECOGNITION OF AN OLD ACQUAINTANCE, AND THE COMMENCEMENT OF ANOTHER CHAPTER.</head>

<p>MR. Pickwick's conscience had been somewhat reproaching him, for his recent neglect of his friends at the Peacock; and he was just on the point of walking forth in quest of them, on the third morning after the election had terminated, when his faithful valet put into his hand a card, on which was engraved the following inscription.</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="quote">
<head>Mrs. Leo Hunter.</head>
<p><hi rend="italics">The Den. Eatanswill.</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</q>
<p>&ldquo;Person's a waitin',&rdquo; said Sam, epigrammatically.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does the person want me, Sam?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He wants you partickler; and no one else'll do, as the Devil's private secretary said, ven he fetched avay Doctor Faustus,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">He.</hi> Is it a gentleman?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A wery good imitation o' one, if it an't,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But this is a lady's card,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Given me by a gen'lm'n, hows'ever,&rdquo; replied Sam, &ldquo;and he's a waitin' in the drawing-room&mdash;said he'd rather wait all day, than not see you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick on hearing this determination, descended to the drawing-room, where sat a grave man, who started up on his entrance, and said, with an air of profound respect&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Pickwick, I presume?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The same.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Allow me, Sir, the honour of grasping your hand&mdash;permit me Sir, to shake it,&rdquo; said the grave man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>The stranger shook the extended hand, and then continued.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We have heard of your fame, Sir. The noise of your antiquarian discussion has reached the ears of Mrs. Leo Hunter&mdash;my wife, Sir: <hi
rend="italics">I</hi> am <hi rend="italics">Mr.</hi> Leo Hunter&rdquo;&mdash;the stranger paused, as if he expected that Mr. Pickwick would be overcome by the disclosure; but seeing that he remained perfectly calm, proceeded.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My wife, Sir&mdash;Mrs. Leo Hunter&mdash;is proud to number among her acquaintance, all those who have rendered themselves celebrated by their works and talents. Permit me, Sir, to place in a conspicuous part
<pb n="148" id="p148"/>
of the list, the name of Mr. Pickwick, and his brother members of the club that derives its name from him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall be extremely happy to make the acquaintance of such a lady, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You <hi rend="italics">shall</hi> make it, Sir,&rdquo; said the grave man. &ldquo;To-morrow morning, Sir, we give a public breakfast&mdash;a <hi
rend="italics">f&ecirc;te champetre</hi>&mdash;to a great number of those who have rendered themselves celebrated by their works and talents. Permit Mrs. Leo Hunter, Sir, to have the gratification of seeing you at the Den.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With great pleasure,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Leo Hunter has many of these breakfasts, Sir,&rdquo; resumed the new acquaintance&mdash;&ldquo; &lsquo;Feasts of reason, Sir, and flows of soul,&rsquo; as somebody who wrote a sonnet to Mrs. Leo Hunter on her breakfasts, feelingly and originally observed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Was <hi rend="italics">he</hi> celebrated for his works, and talents?&rdquo; inquired Mr Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He was, Sir,&rdquo; replied the grave man, &ldquo;all Mrs. Leo Hunter's acquaintance are; it is her ambition, Sir, to have no other acquaintance.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is a very noble ambition,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I inform Mrs. Leo Hunter, that that remark fell from <hi
rend="italics">your</hi> lips, Sir, she will indeed be proud,&rdquo; said the grave man. &ldquo;You have a gentleman in your train, who has produced some beautiful little poems, I think, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My friend Mr. Snodgrass has a great taste for poetry,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So has Mrs. Leo Hunter, Sir. She dotes on poetry, Sir. She adores it; I may say that her whole soul and mind are wound up, and entwined with it. She has produced some delightful pieces, herself, Sir. You may have met with her &lsquo;Ode to an expiring Frog,&rsquo; Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't think I have,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You astonish me, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Leo Hunter. &ldquo;It created an immense sensation. It was signed with an &lsquo;L&rsquo; and eight stars, and appeared originally in a Lady's Magazine. It commenced</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>&ldquo;Can I view thee panting, lying</l>
<l>On thy stomach, without sighing;</l>
<l>Can I unmoved see thee dying</l>
<l>On a log,</l>
<l>Expiring frog!&rdquo;</l>
</lg>
<p>&ldquo;Beautiful!&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Fine,&rdquo; said Mr. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;so simple.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The next verse is still more touching. Shall I repeat it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you please,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It runs thus,&rdquo; said the grave man, still more gravely.</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>&ldquo;Say, have fiends in shape of boys,</l>
<l>With wild hallo and brutal noise,</l>
<l>Hunted thee from marshy joys,</l>
<l>With a dog,</l>
<l>Expiring frog!&rdquo;</l>
</lg>
<pb n="149" id="p149"/>
<p>&ldquo;Finely expressed,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;All point, Sir, all point,&rdquo; said Mr. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;but you shall hear Mrs. Leo Hunter repeat it. <hi
rend="italics">She</hi> can do justice to it, Sir. She will repeat it, in character, Sir, to-morrow morning.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In character!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;As Minerva. But I forgot&mdash;it's a fancy dress dejeune.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, glancing at his own figure&mdash;&ldquo;I can't possibly&rdquo;&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can't Sir; can't!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Leo Hunter. &ldquo;Solomon Lucas the Jew in the High Street, has thousands of fancy dresses. Consider, Sir, how many appropriate characters are open for your selection. Plato, Zeno, Epicurus, Pythagoras&mdash;all founders of clubs.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know that,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;but as I cannot put myself in competition with those great men, I cannot presume to wear their dresses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The grave man considered deeply, for a few seconds, and then said,</p>
<p>&ldquo;On reflection, Sir, I don't know whether it would not afford Mrs. Leo Hunter greater pleasure, if her guests saw a gentleman of your celebrity in his own costume, rather than in an assumed one. I may venture to promise an exception in your case, Sir&mdash;yes, I am quite certain that on behalf of Mrs. Leo Hunter, I may venture to do so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In that case,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;I shall have great pleasure in coming.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But I waste your time, Sir,&rdquo; said the grave man, as if suddenly recollecting himself. &ldquo;I know its value, Sir. I will not detain you. I may tell Mrs. Leo Hunter, then, that she may confidently expect you and your distinguished friends? Good morning, Sir, I am proud to have beheld so eminent a personage&mdash;not a step, Sir; not a word.&rdquo; And without giving Mr. Pickwick time to offer remonstrance or denial Mr. Leo Hunter stalked gravely away.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick took up his hat, and repaired to the Peacock, but Mr. Winkle had conveyed the intelligence of the fancy ball there, before him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Pott's going,&rdquo; were the first words with which he saluted his leader.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is she?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As Apollo,&rdquo; replied Mr. Winkle. &ldquo;Only Pott objects to the tunic.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is right. He is quite right,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick emphatically.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes;&mdash;so she's going to wear a white satin gown with gold spangles.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They'll hardly know what she's meant for; will they?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Snodgrass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course they will,&rdquo; replied Mr. Winkle indignantly. &ldquo;They'll see her lyre, won't they?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;True;&rdquo; I forgot that,&rdquo; said Mr. Snodgrass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I shall go as a Bandit,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What!&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, with a sudden start.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As a bandit,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Tupman, mildly.</p>
<pb n="150" id="p150"/>
<p>&ldquo;You don't mean to say,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, gazing with solemn sternness at his friend, &ldquo;You don't mean to say, Mr. Tupman, that it is your intention to put yourself into a green velvet jacket, with a two-inch tail?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Such <hi rend="italics">is</hi> my intention, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Tupman warmly. &ldquo;And why not, Sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, considerably excited&mdash;&ldquo;Because you are too old, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Too old!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And if any further ground of objection be wanting,&rdquo; continued Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;you are too fat, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman, his face suffused with a crimson glow. &ldquo;This is an insult.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick in the same tone, &ldquo;It is not half the insult to you, that your appearance in my presence in a green velvet jacket, with a two-inch tail, would be to me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman, &ldquo;you're a fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;you're another!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tupman advanced a step or two, and glared at Mr. Pickwick. Mr. Pickwick returned the glare, concentrated into a focus by means of his spectacles, and breathed a bold defiance. Mr. Snodgrass and Mr. Winkle, looked on, petrified at beholding such a scene between two such men.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman, after a short pause, speaking in a low, deep voice, &ldquo;you have called me old.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And fat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I reiterate the charge.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And a fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So you are!&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a fearful pause.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My attachment to your person, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman, speaking in a voice tremulous with emotion, and tucking up his wristbands meanwhile, &ldquo;is great&mdash;very great&mdash;but upon that person, I must take summary vengeance.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come on, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick. Stimulated by the exciting nature of the dialogue, the heroic man actually threw himself into a paralytic attitude, confidently supposed by the two by-standers to have been intended as a posture of defence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Snodgrass, suddenly recovering the power of speech, of which intense astonishment had previously bereft him, and rushing between the two, at the imminent hazard of receiving an application on the temple from each. &ldquo;What! Mr. Pickwick, with the eyes of the world upon you! Mr. Tupman! who, in common with us all, derives a lustre from his undying name! For shame, gentlemen; for shame.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The unwonted lines which momentary passion had ruled in Mr. Pickwick's clear and open brow, gradually melted away, as his young friend spoke, like the marks of a black-lead pencil beneath the softening
<pb n="151" id="p151"/>
influence of India rubber. His countenance had resumed its usual benign expression ere he concluded.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been hasty,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;very hasty. Tupman; your hand.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The dark shadow passed from Mr. Tupman's face, as he warmly grasped the hand of his friend.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have been hasty, too,&rdquo; said he.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no,&rdquo; interrupted Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;the fault was mine. You will wear the green velvet jacket?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no,&rdquo; replied Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To oblige me, you will,&rdquo; resumed Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, well, I will,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>It was accordingly settled that Mr. Tupman, Mr. Winkle, and Mr. Snodgrass, should all wear fancy dresses. Thus Mr. Pickwick was led by the very warmth of his own good feelings to give his consent to a proceeding from which his better judgment would have recoiled&mdash;a more striking illustration of his amiable character could hardly have been conceived, even if the events recorded in these pages had been wholly imaginary.</p>
<p>Mr. Leo Hunter had not exaggerated the resources of Mr. Solomon Lucas. His wardrobe was extensive&mdash;very extensive&mdash;not strictly classical perhaps, nor quite new, nor did it contain any one garment made precisely after the fashion of any age or time, but every thing was more or less spangled; and what <hi
rend="italics">can</hi> be prettier than spangles? It may be objected that they are not adapted to the daylight, but everybody knows that they would glitter if there were lamps; and nothing can be clearer than that if people give fancy balls in the day-time, and the dresses do not show quite as well as they would by night, the fault lies solely with the people who give the fancy balls, and is in no wise chargeable on the spangles. Such was the convincing reasoning of Mr. Solomon Lucas; and influenced by such arguments did Mr. Tupman, Mr. Winkle, and Mr. Snodgrass, engage to array themselves in costumes which his taste and experience induced him to recommend as admirably suited to the occasion.</p>
<p>A carriage was hired from the Town Arms, for the accommodation of the Pickwickians, and a chariot was ordered from the same repository, for the purpose of conveying Mr. and Mrs. Pott to Mrs. Leo Hunter's grounds, which Mr. Pott, as a delicate acknowledgment of having received an invitation, had already confidently predicted in the Eatanswill Gazette &ldquo;would present a scene of varied and delicious enchantment&mdash;a bewildering coruscation of beauty and talent&mdash;a lavish and prodigal display of hospitality&mdash;above all, a degree of splendour softened by the most exquisite taste; and adornment refined with perfect harmony and the chastest good-keeping&mdash;compared with which, the fabled gorgeousness of Eastern Fairy Land itself, would appear to be clothed in as many dark and murky colours, as must be the mind of the splenetic and unmanly being who could presume to taint with the venom of his envy, the preparations making by the virtuous and highly distinguished lady, at whose shrine this humble tribute of admiration was offered.&rdquo; This last
<pb n="152" id="p152"/>
was a piece of biting sarcasm against the Independent, who in consequence of not having been invited at all, had been through four numbers affecting to sneer at the whole affair, in his very largest type, with all the adjectives in capital letters.</p>
<p>The morning came; it was a pleasant sight to behold Mr. Tupman in full Brigand's costume, with a very tight jacket, sitting like a pincushion over his back and shoulders: the upper portion of his legs encased in the velvet shorts, and the lower part thereof swathed in the complicated bandages to which all Brigands are peculiarly attached. It was pleasing to see his open and ingenuous countenance, well mustachioed and corked, looking out from an open shirt collar; and to contemplate the sugar-loaf hat, decorated with ribbons of all colours, which he was compelled to carry on his knee, inasmuch as no known conveyance with a top to it, would admit of any man's carrying it between his head and the roof. Equally humourous and agreeable, was the appearance of Mr. Snodgrass in blue satin trunks and cloak, white silk tights and shoes, and Grecian helmet, which everybody knows (and if they do not, Mr. Solomon Lucas did) to have been the regular, authentic, every-day costume of a Troubadour, from the earliest ages down to the time of their final disappearance from the face of the earth. All this was pleasant, but this was as nothing compared with the shouting of the populace when the carriage drew up, behind Mr. Pott's chariot, which chariot itself drew up at Mr. Pott's door, which door itself opened, and displayed the great Pott accoutred as a Russian officer of justice, with a tremendous knout in his hand&mdash;tastefully typical of the stern and mighty power of the Eatanswill Gazette, and the fearful lashings it bestowed on public offenders.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bravo!&rdquo; shouted Mr. Tupman and Mr. Snodgrass from the passage, when they beheld the walking allegory.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bravo!&rdquo; Mr. Pickwick was heard to exclaim, from the passage.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hoo&mdash;roar Pott,&rdquo; shouted the populace. Amid these salutations, Mr. Pott, smiling with that kind of bland dignity which sufficiently testified that he felt his power, and knew how to exert it, got into the chariot.</p>
<p>Then there emerged from the house, Mrs. Pott, who would have looked very like Apollo if she hadn't had a gown on: conducted by Mr. Winkle, who in his light red-coat, could not possibly have been mistaken for any thing but a sportsman, if he had not borne an equal resemblance to a general postman. Last of all, came Mr. Pickwick, whom the boys applauded as loudly as anybody, probably under the impression that his tights and gaiters were some remnants of the dark ages; and then the two vehicles proceeded towards Mrs. Leo Hunter's, Mr. Weller (who was to assist in waiting) being stationed on the box of that in which his master was seated.</p>
<p>Every one of the men, women, boys, girls, and babies, who were assembled to see the visiters in there fancy dresses, screamed with delight and extasy, when Mr. Pickwick, with the Brigand on one arm, and the Troubadour on the other, walked solemnly up the entrance. Never were such shouts heard, as those which greeted Mr. Tupman's efforts
<pb n="153" id="p153"/>
to fix the sugar-loaf hat on his head, by way of entering the garden in style.</p>
<p>The preparations were on the most delightful scale; fully realising the prophetic Pott's anticipations about the gorgeousness of Eastern Fairy-land, and at once affording a sufficient contradiction to the malignant statements of the reptile Independent. The grounds were more than an acre and a quarter in extent, and they were filled with people! Never was such a blaze of beauty, and fashion, and literature. There was the young lady who &ldquo;did&rdquo; the poetry in the Eatanswill Gazette, in the garb of a sultana, leaning upon the arm of the young gentleman who &ldquo;did&rdquo; the review department, and who was appropriately habited in a field marshal's uniform&mdash;the boots excepted. There were hosts of these geniuses, and any reasonable person would have thought it honour enough to meet them. But more than these, there were half a dozen lions from London&mdash;authors, real authors, who had written whole books, and printed them afterwards&mdash;and here you might see 'em, walking about, like ordinary men, smiling, and talking&mdash;aye, and talking pretty considerable nonsense too, no doubt with the benign intention of rendering themselves intelligible to the common people about them. Moreover, there was a band of music in pasteboard caps; four something-ean singers in the costume of their country, and a dozen hired waiters in the costume of <hi
rend="italics">their</hi> country&mdash;and very dirty costume too. And above all, there was Mrs. Leo Hunter in the character of Minerva, receiving the company, and overflowing with pride and gratification at the notion of having called such distinguished individuals together.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Pickwick, Ma'am,&rdquo; said a servant, as that gentleman approached the presiding goddess, with his hat in his hand, and the Brigand and Troubadour on either arm.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What&mdash;where!&rdquo; exclaimed Mrs. Leo Hunter, starting up, in an affected rapture of surprise.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is it possible that I have really the gratification of beholding Mr. Pickwick himself!&rdquo; ejaculated Mrs. Leo Hunter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No other, Ma'am,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, bowing very low. &ldquo;Permit me to introduce my friends&mdash;Mr. Tupman&mdash;Mr. Winkle&mdash;Mr. Snodgrass&mdash;to the authoress of &lsquo;The Expiring Frog.&rsquo; &rdquo;</p>
<p>Very few people but those who have tried it, know what a difficult process it is, to bow in green velvet smalls, and a tight jacket and high-crowned-hat, or in blue satin trunks and white silks, or knee-cords and top-boots that were never made for the wearer, and have been fixed upon him without the remotest reference to the comparative dimensions of himself and the suit. Never were such distortions as Mr. Tupman's frame underwent in his efforts to appear easy and graceful&mdash;never was such ingenious posturing, as his fancy-dressed friends exhibited.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mr. Pickwick,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;I must make you promise not to stir from my side the whole day. There are hundreds of people here, that I must positively introduce you to.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="154" id="p154"/>
<p>&ldquo;You are very kind, Ma'am,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the first place, here are my little girls; I had almost forgotten them,&rdquo; said Minerva, carelessly pointing towards a couple of full-grown young ladies, of whom one might be about twenty, and the other a year or two older, and who were dressed in very juvenile costumes&mdash;whether to make them look young, or their mamma younger, Mr. Pickwick does not distinctly inform us.</p>
<p>&ldquo;They are very beautiful,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, as the juveniles turned away, after being presented.</p>
<p>&ldquo;They are very like their mamma, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Pott, majestically.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh you naughty man,&rdquo; exclaimed Mrs. Leo Hunter, playfully tapping the Editor's arm with her fan (Minerva with a fan!)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why now, my dear Mrs. Hunter,&rdquo; said Mr. Pott, who was trumpeter in ordinary at the Den, &ldquo;you <hi
rend="italics">know</hi> that when your picture was in the Exhibition of the Royal Academy, last year, everybody inquired whether it was intended for you, or your youngest daughter; for you were so much alike that there was no telling the difference between you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, and if they did, why need you repeat it, before strangers?&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter, bestowing another tap on the slumbering lion of the Eatanswill Gazette.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Count, Count,&rdquo; screamed Mrs. Leo Hunter to a well-whiskered individual in a foreign uniform, who was passing by.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! you want me?&rdquo; said the Count, turning back.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I want to introduce two very clever people to each other,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter. &ldquo;Mr. Pickwick, I have great pleasure in introducing you to Count Smorltork.&rdquo; She added in a hurried whisper to Mr. Pickwick&mdash;&ldquo;the famous foreigner&mdash;gathering materials for his great work on England&mdash;hem!&mdash;Count Smorltork, Mr. Pickwick.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick saluted the Count with all the reverence due to so great a man, and the Count drew forth a set of tablets.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What you say, Mrs. Hunt?&rdquo; inquired the Count, smiling graciously on the gratified Mrs. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;Pig Vig or Big Vig&mdash;what you call&mdash;Lawyer&mdash;eh? I see&mdash;that is it. Big Vig&rdquo;&mdash;and the Count was proceeding to enter Mr. Pickwick in his tablets, as a gentleman of the long-robe, who derived his name from the profession to which he belonged, when Mrs. Leo Hunter interposed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no, Count,&rdquo; said the lady, &ldquo;Pick-wick.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, ah, I see,&rdquo; replied the Count. &ldquo;Peek&mdash;christian name; Weeks&mdash;surname; good, ver good. Peek Weeks. How you do Weeks?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite well, I thank you,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, with all his usual affability. &ldquo;Have you long in England?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Long&mdash;ver long time&mdash;fortnight&mdash;more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you stay here long?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;One week.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will have enough to do,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, smiling, &ldquo;to gather all the materials you want, in that time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Eh, they are gathered,&rdquo; said the Count.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Indeed!&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<pb n="155" id="p155"/>
<p>&ldquo;They are here,&rdquo; added the Count, tapping his forehead significantly. &ldquo;Large book at home&mdash;full of notes&mdash;music, picture, science, potry, poltic; all things.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The word politics, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;comprises, in itself, a difficult study of no inconsiderable magnitude.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; said the Count, drawing out the tablets again, &ldquo;ver good&mdash;fine words to begin a chapter. Chapter forty-seven. Poltics. The word poltic surprises by himself&mdash;&rdquo; And down went Mr. Pickwick's remark, in Count Smorltork's tablets, with such variations and additions as the Count's exuberant fancy suggested, or his imperfect knowledge of the language, occasioned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Count,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mrs. Hunt,&rdquo; replied the Count.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is Mr. Snodgrass, a friend of Mr. Pickwick's, and a poet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stop,&rdquo; exclaimed the Count, bringing out the tablets once more. &ldquo;Head, potry&mdash;chapter, literary friends&mdash;name, Snowgrass; ver good. Introduced to Snowgrass&mdash;great poet, friend of Peek Weeks&mdash;by Mrs. Hunt, which wrote other sweet poem&mdash;what is that name?&mdash;Frog&mdash;Perspiring Frog&mdash;ver good&mdash;ver good indeed.&rdquo; And the Count put up his tablets, and with sundry bows and acknowledgments walked away, thoroughly satisfied that he had made the most important and valuable additions to his stock of information.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wonderful man, Count Smorltork,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sound philosopher,&rdquo; said Pott.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Clear-headed, strong-minded person,&rdquo; added Mr. Snodgrass.</p>
<p>A chorus of by-standers took up the shout of Count Smorltork's praise, shook their heads sagely, and unanimously cried &ldquo;Very!&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the enthusiasm in Count Smorltork's favour ran very high, his praises might have been sung until the end of the festivities, if the four something-ean singers had not ranged themselves in front of a small apple-tree, to look picturesque, and commenced singing their national songs, which appeared by no means difficult of execution, inasmuch as the grand secret seemed to be, that three of the something-ean singers should grunt, while the fourth howled. This interesting performance having concluded amidst the loud plaudits of the whole company, a boy forthwith proceeded to entangle himself with the rails of a chair, and to jump over it, and crawl under it, and fall down with it, and do every thing but sit upon it, and then to make a cravat of his legs, and tie them round his neck, and then to illustrate the ease with which a human being can be made to look like a magnified toad&mdash;all which feats yielded high delight and satisfaction to the assembled spectators. After which, the voice of Mrs. Pott was heard to chirp faintly forth, something which courtesy interpreted into a song, which was all very classical, and strictly in character, because Apollo was himself a composer, and composers can very seldom sing their own music or anybody else's, either. This was succeeded by Mrs. Leo Hunter's recitation of her far-famed ode to an Expiring Frog, which was encored once, and would have been encored twice, if the major part of the guests, who thought
<pb n="156" id="p156"/>
it was high time to get something to eat, had not said that it was perfectly shameful to take advantage of Mrs. Hunter's good nature. So although Mrs. Leo Hunter professed her perfect willingness to recite the ode again, her kind and considerate friends wouldn't hear of it on any account; and the refreshment room being thrown open, all the people who had ever been there before, scrambled in with all possible despatch: Mrs. Leo Hunter's usual course of proceeding, being, to issue cards for a hundred, and breakfast for fifty, or in other words to feed only the very particular lions, and let the smaller animals take care of themselves.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where is Mr. Pott?&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter, as she placed the aforesaid lions around her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here I am,&rdquo; said the editor, from the very furthest end of the room; far beyond all hope of food, unless something was done for him by the hostess.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't you come up here?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh pray don't mind him,&rdquo; said Mrs. Pott, in the most obliging voice&mdash;&ldquo;you give yourself a great deal of unnecessary trouble, Mrs. Hunter. You'll do very well there, won't you&mdash;dear.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly&mdash;love,&rdquo; replied the unhappy Pott, with a grim smile. Alas for the knout! The nervous arm that wielded it, with such gigantic force upon public characters, was paralysed beneath the glance of the imperious Mrs. Pott.</p>
<p>Mrs. Leo Hunter looked round her, in triumph. Count Smorltork was busily engaged in taking notes of the contents of the dishes; Mr. Tupman was doing the honours of the lobster salad to several lionesses, with a degree of grace which no Brigand ever exhibited before; Mr. Snodgrass having cut out the young gentleman who cut up the books for the Eatanswill Gazette, was engaged in an impassioned argument with the young lady who did the poetry: and Mr. Pickwick was making himself universally agreeable. Nothing seemed wanting to render the select circle complete, when Mr. Leo Hunter&mdash;whose department on these occasions, was to stand about in door-ways, and talk to the less important people&mdash;suddenly called out&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear; here's Mr. Charles Fitz-Marshall.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh dear,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;how anxiously I have been expecting him. Pray make room, to let Mr. Fitz-Marshall pass. Tell Mr. Fitz-Marshall, my dear, to come up to me directly, to be scolded for coming so late.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Coming, my dear Ma'am,&rdquo; cried a voice, &ldquo;as quick as I can&mdash;crowds of people&mdash;full room&mdash;hard work&mdash;very.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's knife and fork fell from his hand. He stared across the table at Mr. Tupman, who had dropped <hi
rend="italics">his</hi> knife and fork, and was looking as if he were about to sink into the ground without further notice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; cried the voice, as its owner pushed his way among the last five and twenty Turks, officers, cavaliers, and Charles the Seconds, that remained between him and the table, &ldquo;regular mangle&mdash;Baker's patent&mdash;not a crease in my coat, after all this squeezing&mdash;might have &lsquo;got up
<pb n="157" id="p157"/>
my linen, as I came along&mdash;ha! ha! not a bad idea, that&mdash;queer thing to have it mangled when it's upon one, though&mdash;trying process&mdash;very.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With these broken words, a young man dressed as a naval officer made his way up to the table, and presented to the astonished Pickwickians, the identical form and features of Mr. Alfred Jingle.</p>
<p>The offender had barely time to take Mrs. Leo Hunter's proffered hand, when his eyes encountered the indignant orbs of Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hallo!&rdquo; said Jingle. &ldquo;Quite forgot&mdash;no directions to postilion&mdash;give 'em at once&mdash;back in a minute.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The servant, or Mr. Hunter will do it in a moment, Mr. Fitz-Marshall,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no&mdash;I'll do it&mdash;shan't be long&mdash;back in no time,&rdquo; replied Jingle. With these words he disappeared among the crowd.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Will you allow me to ask you, Ma'am,&rdquo; said the excited Mr. Pickwick, rising from his seat, &ldquo;who that young man is, and where he resides?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is a gentleman of fortune, Mr. Pickwick,&rdquo; said Mrs. Leo Hunter, &ldquo;to whom I very much want to introduce you. The Count will be delighted with him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, hastily. &ldquo;His residence&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is at present at the Angel at Bury.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At Bury?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;At Bury St. Edmunds, not many miles from here. But dear me, Mr. Pickwick, you are not going to leave us: surely Mr. Pickwick you cannot think of going so soon.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But long before Mrs. Leo Hunter had finished speaking, Mr. Pickwick had plunged through the throng, and reached the garden, whither he was shortly afterwards joined by Mr. Tupman, who had followed his friend closely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's of no use,&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman. &ldquo;He has gone.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know it,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;and I will follow him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Follow him. Where?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To the Angel at Bury,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, speaking very quickly. &ldquo;How do we know whom he is deceiving there? He deceived a worthy man once, and we were the innocent cause. He shall not do it again, if I can help it; I'll expose him. Sam! Where's my servant?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here you are, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller, emerging from a sequestered spot, where he had been engaged in discussing a bottle of Madeira, which he had abstracted from the breakfast-table, an hour or two before. &ldquo;Here's your servant, Sir. Proud o' the title, as the Living Skellinton said, ven they show'd him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Follow me instantly,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;Tupman, if I stay at Bury, you can join me there, when I write. Till then, good-bye.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Remonstrances were useless. Mr. Pickwick was roused, and his mind was made up. Mr. Tupman returned to his companions; and in another hour had drowned all present recollection of Mr. Alfred Jingle, or Mr. Charles Fitz-Marshall, in an exhilarating quadrille and a bottle
<pb n="158" id="p158"/>
of champagne. By that time, Mr. Pickwick and Sam Weller, perched on the outside of a stage coach, were every succeeding minute placing a less and less distance between themselves and the good old town of Bury Saint Edmunds.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XVI.</head>
<head>
TOO FULL OF ADVENTURE TO BE BRIEFLY DESCRIBED.
</head>
<p>THERE is no month in the whole year, in which nature wears a more beautiful appearance than in the month of August. Spring has many beauties, and May is a fresh and blooming month, but the charms of this time of year, are enhanced by their contrast with the winter season. August has no such advantage. It comes when we remember nothing but clear skies, green fields, and sweet-smelling flowers&mdash;when the recollection of snow, and ice, and bleak winds, has faded from our minds as completely as they have disappeared from the earth,&mdash;and yet what a pleasant time it is. Orchards and corn-fields ring with the hum of labour; trees bend beneath the thick clusters of rich fruit which bow their branches to the ground; and the corn, piled in graceful sheaves, or waving in every light breath that sweeps above it, as if it wooed the sickle, tinges the landscape with a golden hue. A mellow softness appears to hang over the whole earth; the influence of the season seems to extend itself to the very wagon, whose slow motion across the well-reaped field, is perceptible only to the eye, but strikes with no harsh sound upon the ear.</p>
<p>As the coach rolls swiftly past the fields and orchards which skirt the road, groups of women and children, piling the fruit in sieves, or gathering the scattered ears of corn, pause for an instant from their labour, and shading the sun-burnt face with a still browner hand, gaze upon the passengers with curious eyes, while some stout urchin, too small to work, but too mischievous to be left at home, scrambles over the side of the basket in which he has been deposited for security, and kicks and screams with delight. The reaper stops in his work, and stands with folded arms, looking at the vehicle as it whirls past; and the rough cart-horses bestow a sleepy glance upon the smart coach team, which says, as plainly as a horse's glance can, &ldquo;It's all very fine to look at, but slow going, over a heavy field, is better than warm work like that, upon a dusty road, after all.&rdquo; You cast a look behind you, as you turn a corner of the road. The women and children have resumed their labour, the reaper once more stoops to his work, the cart-horses have moved on, and all are again in motion.</p>
<p>The influence of a scene like this, was not lost upon the well-regulated mind of Mr. Pickwick. Intent upon the resolution he had formed, of exposing the real character of the nefarious Jingle, in any quarter in
<pb n="159" id="p159"/>
which he might be pursuing his fraudulent designs, he sat at first taciturn and contemplative, brooding over the means by which his purpose could be best attained. By degrees his attention grew more and more attracted by the objects around him; and at last he derived as much enjoyment from the ride, as if it had been undertaken for the pleasantest reason in the world.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Delightful prospect, Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Beats the chimbley pots, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller, touching his hat.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose you have hardly seen anything but chimney-pots and bricks and mortar, all your life, Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, smiling.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I worn't always a boots, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller, with a shake of the head. &ldquo;I was a vagginer's boy, once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When was that?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When I vas first pitched neck and crop into the world, to play at leap-frog with its troubles,&rdquo; replied Sam. &ldquo;I vas a carrier's boy at startin': then a vagginer's, then a helper, then a boots. Now I'm a gen'lm'n's servant. I shall be a gen'lm'n myself one of these days, perhaps, with a pipe in my mouth, and a summer-house in the back garden. Who knows? <hi
rend="italics">I</hi> shouldn't be surprised, for once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are quite a philosopher, Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It runs in the family, I b'lieve Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller. &ldquo;My father's wery much in that line, now. If my mother-in-law blows him up, he whistles. She flies in a passion, and breaks his pipe; he steps out, and gets another. Then she screams wery loud, and falls into 'sterics; and he smokes wery comfortably 'till she comes to agin. That's philosophy Sir, an't it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;A very good substitute for it, at all events,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, laughing. &ldquo;It must have been of great service to you, in the course of your rambling life, Sam.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Service Sir,&rdquo; exclaimed Sam. &ldquo;You may say that. Arter I run away from the carrier, and afore I took up with the vagginer, I had unfurnished lodgin's for a fortnight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Unfurnished lodgings?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes&mdash;the dry arches of Waterloo Bridge. Fine sleeping-place&mdash;vithin ten minutes' walk of all the public offices&mdash;only if there is any objection to it, it is that the sitivation's <hi
rend="italics">rayther</hi> too airy. I see some queer sights there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, I suppose you did,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, with an air of considerable interest.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sights, Sir,&rdquo; resumed Mr. Weller, &ldquo;as 'ud penetrate your benevolent heart, and come out on the other side. You don't see the reg'lar wagrants there; trust 'em, they knows better than that. Young beggars, male and female, as hasn't made a rise in their profession, takes up their quarters there sometimes; but it's generally the worn-out, starving, houseless creeturs as rolls themselves up in the dark corners o' them lonesome places&mdash;poor creeturs as an't up to the twopenny rope.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And pray Sam, what <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the twopenny rope?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<pb n="160" id="p160"/>
<p>&ldquo;The twopenny rope, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller, &ldquo;is just a cheap lodgin'house, vere the beds is twopence a night.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do they call a bed a rope for?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bless your innocence, Sir, that a'nt it,&rdquo; replied Sam. &ldquo;Ven the lady and gen'lm'n as keeps the Hot-el, first begun business, they used to make the beds on the floor; but this wouldn't do at no price, 'cos instead o' taking a moderate twopenn'orth o' sleep, the lodgers used to lie there half the day. So now they has two ropes, 'bout six foot apart, and three from the floor, which goes right down the room; and the beds are made of slips of coarse sacking, stretched across 'em.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller, &ldquo;the adwantage o' the plan's hobvious. At six o'clock every mornin', they lets go the ropes at one end, and down falls all the lodgers. 'Consequence is, that being thoroughly waked, they get up wery quietly, and walk away!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Beg your pardon, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam, suddenly breaking off in his loquacious discourse. &ldquo;Is this Bury Saint Edmunds?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>The coach rattled through the well paved streets of a handsome little town, of thriving and cleanly appearance, and stopped before a large inn situated in a wide open street, nearly facing the old abbey.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And this,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, looking up, &ldquo;is the Angel. We alight here, Sam. But some caution is necessary. Order a private room, and do not mention my name. You understand.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Right as a trivet, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller, with a wink of intelligence; and having dragged Mr. Pickwick's portmanteau from the hind boot, into which it had been hastily thrown when they joined the coach at Eatanswill, Mr. Weller disappeared on his errand. A private room was speedily engaged; and into it, Mr. Pickwick was ushered without delay.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;the first thing to be done is to&rdquo;&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Order dinner, Sir,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Weller. &ldquo;Its wery late, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, so it is,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, looking at his watch. &ldquo;You are right, Sam.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And if I might adwise, Sir,&rdquo; added Mr. Weller, &ldquo;I'd just have a good night's rest arterwards, and not begin inquiring arter this here deep 'un 'till the mornin'. There's nothin' so refreshin' as sleep, Sir, as the servant-girl said afore she drank the egg-cup-full o' laudanum.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think you are right, Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;But I must first ascertain that he is in the house, and not likely to go away.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Leave that to me, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam. &ldquo;Let me order you a snug little dinner, and make my inquiries below while it's a getting ready; I could worm ev'ry secret out o' the boots's heart in five minutes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do so,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick: and Mr. Weller at once retired.</p>
<p>In half an hour, Mr. Pickwick was seated at a very satisfactory dinner; and in three-quarters Mr. Weller returned with the intelligence that Mr. Charles Fitz-Marshall had ordered his private room to be retained for him, until further notice. He was going to spend the evening at
<pb n="161" id="p161"/>
some private house in the neighbourhood, had ordered the boots to sit up until his return, and had taken his servant with him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now Sir,&rdquo; argued Mr. Weller, when he had concluded his report, &ldquo;if I can get a talk with this here servant in the mornin', he'll tell me all his master's concerns.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do you know that?&rdquo; interposed Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bless your heart, Sir, servants always do,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, ah, I forgot that,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;Well.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then you can arrange what's best to be done, Sir, and we can act accordingly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;As it appeared that this was the best arrangement that could be made, it was finally agreed upon. Mr. Weller, by his master's permission, retired to spend the evening in his own way; and was shortly afterwards, elected, by the unanimous voice of the assembled company, into the tap-room chair, in which honourable post he acquitted himself so much to the satisfaction of the gentlemen-frequenters, that their roars of laughter and approbation penetrated to Mr. Pickwick's bed-room, and shortened the term of his natural rest, by at least three hours.</p>
<p>Early on the ensuing morning, Mr. Weller was dispelling all the feverish remains of the previous evening's conviviality, through the instrumentality of a halfpenny shower-bath (having induced a young gentleman attached to the stable-department, by the offer of that coin, to pump over his head and face, until he was perfectly restored), when he was attracted by the appearance of a young fellow in mulberry-coloured livery, who was sitting on a bench in the yard, reading what appeared to be a hymn-book, with an air of deep abstraction, but who occasionally stole a glance at the individual under the pump, as if he took some interest in his proceedings, nevertheless.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a rum 'un to look at, you are,&rdquo; thought Mr. Weller the first time his eyes encountered the glance of the stranger in the mulberry-coloured suit, who had a large, sallow, ugly face: very sunken eyes, and a gigantic head, from which depended a quantity of lank black hair. &ldquo;You're a rum 'un,&rdquo; thought Mr. Weller; and thinking this, he went on washing himself, and thought no more about him.</p>
<p>Still the man kept glancing from his hymn-book to Sam, and from Sam to his hymn-book, as if he wanted to open a conversation. So at last, Sam, by way of giving him an opportunity, said, with a familiar nod&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How are you, governor?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am happy to say, I am pretty well, Sir,&rdquo; said the man, speaking with great deliberation, and closing the book. &ldquo;I hope you are the same, Sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, if I felt less like a walking brandy-bottle, I shouldn't be quite so staggery this mornin',&rdquo; replied Sam. &ldquo;Are you stoppin' in this house, old 'un?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The mulberry man replied in the affirmative.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How was it, you worn't one of us, last night?&rdquo; inquired Sam, scrubbing his face with the towel. &ldquo;You seem one of the jolly sort&mdash;looks
<pb n="162" id="p162"/>
as conwivial as a live trout in a lime-basket,&rdquo; added Mr. Weller, in an under tone.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was out last night, with my master,&rdquo; replied the stranger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's his name?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Weller, colouring up very red with sudden excitement, and the friction of the towel combined.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Fitz-Marshall,&rdquo; said the mulberry-man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Give us your hand,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller, advancing; &ldquo;I should like to know you. I like your appearance, old fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, that is very strange,&rdquo; said the mulberry man, with great simplicity of manner. &ldquo;I like your's so much, that I wanted to speak to you, from the very first moment I saw you under the pump.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you though?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Upon my word. Now, isn't that curious?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wery sing'ler,&rdquo; said Sam, inwardly congratulating himself upon the softness of the stranger. &ldquo;What's your name, my patriarch?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Job.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And a wery good name it is; only one, I know, that ain't got a nickname to it. What's the other name?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Trotter,&rdquo; said the stranger. &ldquo;What is yours?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sam bore in mind his master's caution, and replied,</p>
<p>&ldquo;My name's Walker; my master's name's Wilkins. Will you take a drop o' somethin' this mornin', Mr. Trotter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Trotter acquiesced in this agreeable proposal: and having deposited his book in his coat-pocket, accompanied Mr. Weller to the tap, where they were soon occupied in discussing an exhilarating compound, formed by mixing together, in a pewter vessel, certain quantities of British Hollands, and the fragrant essence of the clove.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And what sort of a place have you got?&rdquo; inquired Sam, as he filled his companion's glass, for the second time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Bad,&rdquo; said Job, smacking his lips, &ldquo;very bad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You don't mean that,&rdquo; said Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do, indeed. Worse than that, my master's going to be married.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes; and worse than that, too, he's going to run away with an immense rich heiress, from boarding-school.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a dragon,&rdquo; said Sam, refilling his companion's glass. &ldquo;It's some boarding-school in this town, I suppose, a'nt it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Now, although this question was put in the most careless tone imaginable, Mr. Job Trotter plainly showed, by gestures, that he perceived his new friend's anxiety to draw forth an answer to it. He emptied his glass, looked mysteriously at his companion, winked both of his small eyes, one after the other, and finally made a motion with his arm, as if he were working an imaginary pump-handle: thereby intimating that he (Mr. Trotter) considered himself as undergoing the process of being pumped, by Mr. Samuel Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, no,&rdquo; said Mr. Trotter, in conclusion, &ldquo;that's not to be told to everybody. That is a secret&mdash;a great secret, Mr. Walker.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the mulberry man said this, he turned his glass upside down, by
<pb n="163" id="p163"/>
way of reminding his companion that he had nothing left wherewith to slake his thirst. Sam observed the hint; and feeling the delicate manner in which it was conveyed, ordered the pewter vessel to be refilled, whereat the small eyes of the mulberry man glistened.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And so it's a secret,&rdquo; said Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I should rather suspect it was,&rdquo; said the mulberry man, sipping his liquor, with a complacent face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I suppose your mas'r's very rich?&rdquo; said Sam.</p>
<p>Mr. Trotter smiled, and holding his glass in his left hand, gave four distinct slaps on the pocket of his mulberry indescribables with his right, as if to intimate that his master might have done the same without alarming anybody much by the chinking of coin.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah,&rdquo; said Sam, &ldquo;that's the game, is it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The mulberry man nodded significantly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, and don't you think, old feller,&rdquo; remonstrated Mr. Weller, &ldquo;that if you let your master take in this here young lady, you're a precious rascal?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know that,&rdquo; said Job Trotter, turning upon his companion a countenance of deep contrition, and groaning slightly. &ldquo;I know that and that's what it is that preys upon my mind. But what am I to do?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do!&rdquo; said Sam; &ldquo;di-wulge to the missis, and give up your master.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who'd believe me?&rdquo; replied Job Trotter. &ldquo;The young lady's considered the very picture of innocence and discretion. She'd deny it, and so would my master. Who'd believe me? I should lose my place, and get indicted for a conspiracy, or some such thing; that's all I should take by my motion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's somethin' in that,&rdquo; said Sam, ruminating; &ldquo;there's somethin' in that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If I knew any respectable gentleman who would take the matter up,&rdquo; continued Mr. Trotter, &ldquo;I might have some hope of preventing the elopement; but there's the same difficulty, Mr. Walker, just the same. I know no gentleman in this strange place; and ten to one if I did, whether he would believe my story.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come this way,&rdquo; said Sam, suddenly jumping up, and grasping the mulberry man by the arm. &ldquo;My mas'r's the man you want, I see.&rdquo; And after a slight resistance on the part of Job Trotter, Sam led his newly-found friend to the apartment of Mr. Pickwick, to whom he presented him, together with a brief summary of the dialogue we have just repeated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am very sorry to betray my master, Sir,&rdquo; said Job Trotter, applying to his eyes a pink check pocket handkerchief of about three inches square.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The feeling does you a great deal of honour,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick; &ldquo;but it is your duty, nevertheless.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know it is my duty, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job, with great emotion. &ldquo;We should all try to discharge our duty, Sir, and I humbly endeavour to discharge mine, Sir; but it is a hard trial to betray a master, Sir,
<pb n="164" id="p164"/>
whose clothes you wear, and whose bread you eat, even though he is a scoundrel, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are a very good fellow,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, much affected &ldquo;an honest fellow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come, come,&rdquo; interposed Sam, who had witnessed Mr. Trotter's tears with considerable impatience, &ldquo;blow this here water-cart bis'ness. It won't do no good, this won't.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, reproachfully, &ldquo;I am sorry to find that you have so little respect for this young man's feelings.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;His feelins is all wery well, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller; &ldquo;and as they're so wery fine, and it's a pity he should lose 'em, I think he'd better keep 'em in his own bussum, than let 'em ewaporate in hot water, 'specially as they do no good. Tears never yet wound up a clock, or worked a steam ingin'. The next time you go out to a smoking party, young feller, fill your pipe with that 'ere reflection; and for the present, just put that bit of pink gingham into your pocket. 'T'a'n't so handsome that you need keep waving it about, as if you was a tight-rope dancer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My man is in the right,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, accosting Job, &ldquo;although his mode of expressing his opinion is somewhat homely, and occasionally incomprehensible.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is, Sir, very right,&rdquo; said Mr. Trotter, &ldquo;and I will give way no longer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very well,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;Now, where is this boarding-school?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is a large, old, red-brick house, just outside the town, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job Trotter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And when,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;when is this villainous design to be carried into execution&mdash;when is this elopement to take place?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To-night, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To-night!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This very night, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job Trotter. &ldquo;That is what alarms me so much.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Instant measures must be taken,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;I will see the lady who keeps the establishment, immediately.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I beg your pardon, Sir,&rdquo; said Job, &ldquo;but that course of proceeding will never do.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why not?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My master, Sir, is a very artful man.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know he is,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And he has so wound himself round the old lady's heart, Sir,&rdquo; resumed Job, &ldquo;that she would believe nothing to his prejudice, if you went down on your bare knees, and swore it; especially as you have no proof but the word of a servant, who, for anything she knows (and my master would be sure to say so), was discharged for some fault, and does this, in revenge.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&lsquo;What had better be done, then?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&lsquo;Nothing but taking him in the very fact of eloping, will convince the old lady, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job.</p>
<pb n="165" id="p165"/>
<p>&ldquo;All them old cats <hi rend="italics">will</hi> run their heads agin mile-stones,&rdquo; observed Mr. Weller in a parenthesis.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But this taking him in the very act of elopement, would be a very difficult thing to accomplish, I fear,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't know, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Trotter, after a few moments' reflection. &ldquo;I think it might be very easily done.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How?&rdquo; was Mr. Pickwick's inquiry.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why,&rdquo; replied Mr. Trotter, &ldquo;my master and I, being in the confidence of the two servants, will be secreted in the kitchen at ten o'clock. When the family have retired to rest, we shall come out of the kitchen, and the young lady out of her bed-room. A post-chaise will be waiting, and away we go.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, Sir, I have been thinking that if you were waiting in the garden behind, alone&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Alone,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;Why alone?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I thought it very natural,&rdquo; replied Job, &ldquo;that the old lady wouldn't like such an unpleasant discovery to be made before more persons than can possibly be helped. The young lady too, Sir&mdash;consider her feelings.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are very right,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;The consideration evinces great delicacy of feeling. Go on; you are very right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well Sir, I was thinking that if you were waiting in the back garden alone, and I was to let you in, at the door which opens into it, from the end of the passage, at exactly half-past eleven o'clock, you would be just in the very moment of time, to assist me in frustrating the designs of this bad man, by whom I have been unfortunately ensnared.&rdquo; Here Mr. Trotter sighed deeply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't distress yourself on that account,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;if he had one grain of the delicacy of feeling which distinguishes you, humble as your station is, I should have some hopes of him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Job Trotter bowed low; and in spite of Mr. Weller's previous remonstrance, the tears again rose to his eyes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never see such a feller,&rdquo; said Sam. &ldquo;Blessed if I don't think he's got a main in his head as is always turned on.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, with great severity. &ldquo;Hold your tongue.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Wery well, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't like this plan,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, after deep meditation. &ldquo;Why cannot I communicate with the young lady's friends?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Because they live one hundred miles from here, Sir,&rdquo; responded Job Trotter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's a clincher, said Mr. Weller, aside.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then this garden,&rdquo; resumed Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;How am I to get into it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The wall is very low, Sir, and your servant will give you a leg up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My servant will give me a leg up,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Pickwick, mechanically. &ldquo;You will be sure to be near this door, that you speak of?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You cannot mistake it, Sir; it's the only one that opens into the
<pb n="166" id="p166"/>
garden. Tap at it, when you hear the clock strike, and I will open it instantly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't like the plan,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick; &ldquo;but as I see no other and as the happiness of this young lady's whole life is at stake, I adopt it. I shall be sure to be there.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Thus, for the second time, did Mr. Pickwick's innate good-feeling involve him in an enterprise, from which he would most willingly have stood aloof.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is the name of the house?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Westgate House, Sir. You turn a little to the right when you get to the end of the town; it stands by itself, some little distance off the high road, with the name on a brass plate on the gate.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know it,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;I observed it once before, when I was in this town. You may depend upon me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Trotter made another bow, and turned to depart, when Mr. Pickwick thrust a guinea into his hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a fine fellow,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;and I admire your goodness of heart. No thanks. Remember&mdash;eleven o'clock.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is no fear of my forgetting it, Sir,&rdquo; replied Job Trotter. With these words he left the room, followed by Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I say,&rdquo; said the latter, &ldquo;not a bad notion that 'ere crying. I'd cry like a rain-water spout in a shower, on such good terms. How do you do it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It comes from the heart, Mr. Walker,&rdquo; replied Job solemnly. &ldquo;Good morning, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a soft customer, you are;&mdash;we've got it all out o' you, any how&rdquo; thought Mr. Weller, as Job walked away.</p>
<p>We cannot state the precise nature of the thoughts which passed through Mr. Trotter's mind, because we don't know what they were.</p>
<p>The day wore on, evening came, and at a little before ten o'clock Sam Weller reported that Mr. Jingle and Job had gone out together, that their luggage was packed up, and that they had ordered a chaise. The plot was evidently in execution, as Mr. Trotter had foretold.</p>
<p>Half-past ten o'clock arrived, and it was time for Mr. Pickwick to issue forth on his delicate errand. Resisting Sam's tender of his great coat, in order that he might have no incumbrance in scaling the wall, he set forth, followed by his attendant.</p>
<p>There was a bright moon, but it was behind the clouds. It was a fine dry night, but it was most uncommonly dark. Paths, hedges, fields, houses, and trees, were enveloped in one deep shade. The atmosphere was hot and sultry, the summer lightning quivered faintly on the verge of the horizon, and was the only sight that varied the dull gloom in which every thing was wrapped&mdash;sound there was none, except the distant barking of some restless house-dog.</p>
<p>They found the base, read the brass-plate, walked round the wall, and stopped at that portion of it which divided them from the bottom of the garden.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will return to the inn, Sam, when you have assisted me over,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<pb n="167" id="p167"/>
<p>&ldquo;Wery well, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And you will sit up, 'till I return.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cert'nly, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Take hold of my leg; and, when I say &lsquo;Over,&rsquo; raise me gently.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;All right, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having settled these preliminaries, Mr. Pickwick grasped the top of the wall, and gave the word &ldquo;Over,&rdquo; which was very literally obeyed. Whether his body partook in some degree of the elasticity of his mind, or whether Mr. Weller's notions of a gentle push were of a somewhat rougher description than Mr. Pickwick's, the immediate effect of his assistance was to jerk that immortal gentleman completely over the wall on to the bed beneath, where, after crushing three gooseberry-bushes and a rose-tree, he finally alighted at full length.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You ha'n't hurt yourself, I hope, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam, in a loud whisper, as soon as he recovered from the surprise consequent upon the mysterious disappearance of his master.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have not hurt <hi rend="italics">myself,</hi> Sam, certainly,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, from the other side of the wall, &ldquo;but I rather think that <hi
rend="italics">you</hi> have hurt <hi rend="italics">me.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hope not, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never mind,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, rising, &ldquo;it's nothing but a few scratches. Go away, or we shall be overheard.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good-bye, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Good-bye.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With stealthy steps Sam Weller departed, leaving Mr. Pickwick alone in the garden.</p>
<p>Lights occasionally appeared in the different windows of the house or glanced from the staircases, as if the inmates were retiring to rest. Not caring to go too near the door, until the appointed time, Mr. Pickwick crouched into an angle of the wall, and awaited its arrival.</p>
<p>It was a situation which might well have depressed the spirits of many a man. Mr. Pickwick, however, felt neither depression nor misgiving. He knew that his purpose was in the main a good one, and he placed implicit reliance on the high-minded Job. It was dull, certainly; not to say, dreary; but a contemplative man can always employ himself in meditation. Mr. Pickwick had meditated himself into a doze, when he was roused by the chimes of the neighbouring church ringing out the hour&mdash;half-past eleven.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's the time,&rdquo; thought Mr. Pickwick, getting cautiously on his feet. He looked up at the house. The lights had disappeared, and the shutters were closed&mdash;all in bed, no doubt. He walked on tip-toe to the door, and gave a gentle tap. Two or three minutes passing without any reply, he gave another tap rather louder, and then another rather louder than that.</p>
<p>At length the sound of feet was audible upon the stairs, and then the light of a candle shone through the key-hole of the door. There was a good deal of unchaining and unbolting, and the door was slowly opened.</p>
<p>Now the door opened outwards: and as the door opened wider and
<pb n="168" id="p168"/>
wider, Mr. Pickwick receded behind it, more and more. What was his astonishment when he just peeped out, by way of caution, to see that the person who had opened it was&mdash;not Job Trotter, but a servant-girl with a candle in her hand! Mr. Pickwick drew in his head again, with the swiftness displayed by that admirable melo-dramatic performer, Punch, when he lies in wait for the flat-headed comedian with the tin box of music.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It must have been the cat, Sarah,&rdquo; said the girl, addressing herself to some one in the house. &ldquo;Puss, puss, puss&mdash;tit, tit, tit.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But no animal being decoyed by these blandishments, the girl slowly closed the door, and re-fastened it; leaving Mr. Pickwick drawn up straight against the wall.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is very curious,&rdquo; thought Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;They are sitting up, beyond their usual hour, I suppose. Extremely unfortunate, that they should have chosen this night, of all others, for such a purpose&mdash;exceedingly.&rdquo; And with these thoughts, Mr. Pickwick cautiously retired to the angle of the wall in which he had been before ensconced; waiting until such time as he might deem it safe to repeat the signal.</p>
<p>He had not been here five minutes, when a vivid flash of lightning was followed by a loud peal of thunder that crashed and rolled away in the distance with terrific noise&mdash;then came another flash of lightning, brighter than the other, and a second peal of thunder louder than the first; and then down came the rain, with a force and fury that swept every thing before it.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick was perfectly aware that a tree is a very dangerous neighbour in a thunder-storm. He had a tree on his right, a tree on his left, a third before him, and a fourth behind. If he remained where he was, he might fall the victim of an accident; if he showed himself in the centre of the garden, he might be consigned to a constable;&mdash;once or twice he tried to scale the wall, but having no other legs this time, than those with which Nature had furnished him, the only effect of his struggles was to inflict a variety of very unpleasant gratings on his knees and shins, and to throw him into a state of the most profuse perspiration.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What a dreadful situation,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, pausing to wipe his brow after this exercise. He looked up at the house&mdash;all was dark. They must be gone to bed now. He would try the signal again.</p>
<p>He walked on tip-toe across the moist gravel, and tapped at the door. He held his breath, and listened at the key-hole. No reply: very odd. Another knock. He listened again. There was a low whispering inside, and then a voice cried&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who's there?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's not Job,&rdquo; thought Mr. Pickwick, hastily drawing himself straight up against the wall again. &ldquo;It's a woman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had scarcely had time to form this conclusion, when a window above stairs, was thrown up, and three or four female voices repeated the query&mdash;&ldquo;Who's there?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick dared not move hand or foot. It was clear that the whole establishment was roused. He made up his mind to remain where
<pb n="169" id="p169"/>
he was, until the alarm had subsided: and then to make a supernatural effort, and get over the wall, or perish in the attempt.</p>
<p>Like all Mr. Pickwick's determinations, this was the best that could be made under the circumstances; but, unfortunately, it was founded upon the assumption that they would not venture to open the door again. What was his discomfiture, when he heard the chain and bolts withdrawn, and saw the door slowly opening, wider and wider! He retreated into the corner, step by step; but do what he would, the interposition of his own person, prevented its being opened to its utmost width.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who's there?&rdquo; screamed a numerous chorus of treble voices from the stair-case inside, consisting of the spinster lady of the establishment, three teachers, five female servants, and thirty boarders, all half-dressed, and in a forest of curl-papers.</p>
<p>Of course Mr. Pickwick didn't say who <hi rend="italics">was</hi> there: and then the burden of the chorus changed into&mdash;&ldquo;Lor'! I am so frightened.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cook,&rdquo; said the lady abbess, who took care to be on the top stair, the very last of the group&mdash;&ldquo;Cook, why don't you go a little way into the garden?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Please ma'am, I don't like,&rdquo; responded the cook.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lor', what a stupid thing that cook is!&rdquo; said the thirty boarders.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cook,&rdquo; said the lady abbess, with great dignity; &ldquo;don't answer me, if you please. I insist upon your looking into the garden, immediately.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here the cook began to cry, and the house-maid said it was &ldquo;a shame!&rdquo; for which partisanship she received a month's warning on the spot.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you hear, cook?&rdquo; said the lady abbess, stamping her foot, impatiently.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you hear your missis, cook?&rdquo; said the three teachers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What an impudent thing, that cook is!&rdquo; said the thirty boarders.</p>
<p>The unfortunate cook, thus strongly urged, advanced a step or two, and holding her candle just where it prevented her seeing any thing at all, declared there was nothing there, and it must have been the wind; and the door was just going to be closed in consequence, when an inquisitive boarder, who had been peeping between the hinges, set up a fearful screaming, which called back the cook and the housemaid, and all the more adventurous, in no time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What <hi rend="italics">is</hi> the matter with Miss Smithers?&rdquo; said the lady abbess, as the aforesaid Miss Smithers proceeded to go into hysterics of four young lady power.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lor, Miss Smithers dear,&rdquo; said the other nine-and-twenty boarders.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, the man&mdash;the man&mdash;behind the door!&rdquo; screamed Miss Smithers.</p>
<p>The lady abbess no sooner heard this appalling cry, than she retreated to her own bed-room, double-locked the door, and fainted away all comfortably. The boarders, and the teachers, and the servants, fell back
<pb n="170" id="p170"/>
upon the stairs, and upon each other; and never was such a screaming, and fainting, and struggling, beheld. In the midst of the tumult, Mr. Pickwick emerged from his concealment, and presented himself amongst them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ladies&mdash;dear ladies,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, he says we're dear,&rdquo; cried the oldest and ugliest teacher. &ldquo;Oh the wretch.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ladies,&rdquo; roared Mr. Pickwick, rendered desperate by the danger of his situation. &ldquo;Hear me. I am no robber. I want the lady of the house.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, what a ferocious monster!&rdquo; screamed another teacher. &ldquo;He wants Miss Tomkins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here there was a general scream.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ring the alarm bell, somebody,&rdquo; cried a dozen voices.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't&mdash;don't,&rdquo; shouted Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;Look at me. Do I look like a robber? My dear ladies&mdash;you may bind me hand and leg, or lock me up in a closet, if you like. Only hear what I have got to say&mdash;only hear me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How did you come in our garden?&rdquo; faultered the house-maid.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Call the lady of the house, and I'll tell her everything&mdash;everything:&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, exerting his lungs to the utmost pitch. &ldquo;Call her&mdash;only be quiet, and call her, and you shall hear everything.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It might have been Mr. Pickwick's appearance, or it might have been his manner, or it might have been the temptation&mdash;so irresistible to a female mind&mdash;of hearing something at present enveloped in mystery, that reduced the more reasonable portion of the establishment (some four individuals) to a state of comparative quiet. By them it was proposed, as a test of Mr. Pickwick's sincerity, that he should immediately submit to personal restraint; and that gentleman having consented to hold a conference with Miss Tomkins, from the interior of a closet in which the day boarders hung their bonnets and sandwich-bags, he at once stepped into it, of his own accord, and was securely locked in. This revived the others; and Miss Tomkins having been brought to, and brought down, the conference began.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What did you do in my garden, man?&rdquo; said Miss Tomkins, in a faint voice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I came to warn you, that one of your young ladies was going to elope to-night,&rdquo; replied Mr. Pickwick, from the interior of the closet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Elope!&rdquo; exclaimed Miss Tomkins, the three teachers, the thirty boarders, and the five servants. &ldquo;Who with?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your friend, Mr. Charles Fitz-Marshall.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">My</hi> friend! I don't know any such person.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well; Mr. Jingle, then.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never heard the name in my life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then, I have been deceived, and deluded,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;I have been the victim of a conspiracy&mdash;a foul and base conspiracy. Send to the Angel, my dear ma'am, if you don't believe me. Send to the Angel for Mr. Pickwick's man-servant, I implore you ma'am.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="171" id="p171"/>
<p>&ldquo;He must be respectable&mdash;he keeps a man-servant,&rdquo; said Miss Tomkins to the writing and ciphering governess.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It's my opinion, Miss Tomkins,&rdquo; said the writing and ciphering governess, &ldquo;that his man-servant keeps him. <hi
rend="italics">I</hi> think he's a madman, Miss Tomkins, and the other's his keeper.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think you are very right, Miss Gwynn,&rdquo; responded Miss Tomkins. &ldquo;Let two of the servants repair to the Angel, and let the others remain here, to protect us.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So two of the servants were despatched to the Angel in search of Mr. Samuel Weller: and the remaining three stopped behind to protect Miss Tomkins, and the three teachers, and the thirty boarders. And Mr. Pickwick sat down in the closet, beneath a grove of sandwich bags, and awaited the return of the messengers, with all the philosophy and fortitude he could summon to his aid.</p>
<p>An hour and a half elapsed before they came back, and when they did come, Mr. Pickwick recognised, in addition to the voice of Mr. Samuel Weller, two other voices, the tones of which struck familiarly on his ear; but whose they were, he could not for the life of him call to mind.</p>
<p>A very brief conversation ensued. The door was unlocked. Mr. Pickwick stepped out of the closet, and found himself in the presence of the whole establishment of Westgate House, Mr. Samuel Weller and&mdash;old Wardle, and his destined son-in-law, Mr. Trundle!</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear friend,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, running forward and grasping Wardle's hand, &ldquo;my dear friend, pray, for Heaven's sake, explain to this lady the unfortunate and dreadful situation in which I am placed. You must have heard it from my servant; say, at all events, my dear fellow, that I am neither a robber nor a madman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have said so, my dear friend. I have said so already,&rdquo; replied Mr. Wardle, shaking the right hand of his friend, while Mr. Trundle shook the left.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And whoever says, or has said, he is,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Weller, stepping forward, &ldquo;says that which is not the truth, but so far from it, on the contrairy, quite the rewerse. And if there's any number o' men on these here premises as has said so, I shall be wery happy to give 'em all a wery convincing proof o' their being mistaken, in this here wery room, if these wery respectable ladies 'll have the goodness to retire, and order 'em up, one at a time.&rdquo; Having delivered this defiance with great volubility, Mr. Weller struck his open palm emphatically with his clenched fist, and winked pleasantly on Miss Tomkins, the intensity of whose horror at his supposing it within the bounds of possibility that there could be any men on the premises of Westgate House Establishment for Young Ladies, it is impossible to describe.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's explanation having been already partially made, was soon concluded. But neither in the course of his walk home with his friends, nor afterwards then seated before a blazing fire at the supper he so much needed, could a single observation be drawn from him. He seemed bewildered and amazed. Once, and only once, he turned round to Mr. Wardle, and said</p>
<p>&ldquo;How did you come here?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="172" id="p172"/>
<p>&ldquo;Trundle and I came down here, for some good shooting on the first,&rdquo; replied Wardle. &ldquo;We arrived to-night and were astonished to hear from your servant that you were here too. But I am glad you are,&rdquo; said the jolly old fellow, slapping him on the back. &ldquo;I am glad you are. We shall have a jolly party on the first, and we'll give Winkle another chance&mdash;eh, old boy?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick made no reply; he did not even ask after his friends at Dingley Dell, and shortly afterwards retired for the night, desiring Sam to fetch his candle when he rung.</p>
<p>The bell did ring in due course, and Mr. Weller presented himself.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, looking out from under the bed-clothes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick paused, and Mr. Weller snuffed the candle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick again, as if with a desperate effort.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Weller, once more.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where is that Trotter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Job, Sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gone, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With his master, I suppose?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Friend or master, or whatever he is, he's gone with him,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller. &ldquo;There's a pair on 'em, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Jingle suspected my design, and set that fellow on you, with this story, I suppose?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, half choking.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just that, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was all false, of course?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;All, Sir,&rdquo; replied Mr. Weller. &ldquo;Reg'lar do, Sir; artful dodge.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't think he'll escape us quite so easily the next time, Sam?&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't think he will, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Whenever I meet that Jingle again, wherever it is,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, raising himself in bed, and indenting his pillow with a tremendous blow, &ldquo;I'll inflict personal chastisement on him, in addition to the exposure he so richly merits. I will, or my name is not Pickwick.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And venever I catches hold o' that there melan-cholly chap with the black hair,&rdquo; said Sam, &ldquo;if I don't bring some real water into his eyes, for once in a way, my name a'nt Weller. Good night, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head>CHAPTER XVII.</head>

<head>SHOWING THAT AN ATTACK OF RHEUMATISM, IN SOME CASES, ACTS AS A QUICKENER TO INVENTIVE GENIUS.</head>

<p>THE constitution of Mr. Pickwick, though able to sustain a very considerable amount of exertion and fatigue, was not proof against such a combination of attacks as he had undergone on the memorable night, recorded in the last chapter. The process of being washed in the night
<pb n="173" id="p173"/>
air, and rough-dried in a close closet, is as dangerous as it is peculiar. Mr. Pickwick was laid up with an attack of rheumatism.</p>
<p>But although the bodily powers of the great man were thus impaired, his mental energies retained their pristine vigour. His spirits were elastic; his good humour was restored. Even the vexation consequent upon his recent adventure had vanished from his mind; and he could join in the hearty laughter which any allusion to it excited in Mr. Wardle, without anger and without embarrassment. Nay, more. During the two days Mr. Pickwick was confined to his bed, Sam was his constant attendant. On the first, he endeavoured to amuse his master by anecdote and conversation; on the second Mr. Pickwick demanded his writing-desk, and pen and ink, and was deeply engaged during the whole day. On the third, being able to sit up in his bed-chamber, he despatched his valet with a message to Mr. Wardle and Mr. Trundle, intimating that if they would take their wine there, that evening, they would greatly oblige him. The invitation was most willingly accepted; and when they were seated over their wine, Mr Pickwick with sundry blushes, produced the following little tale, as having been &ldquo;edited&rdquo; by himself, during his recent indisposition, from his notes of Mr. Weller's unsophisticated recital.</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="quote">
<head>&ldquo;THE PARISH CLERK&mdash;A TALE OF TRUE LOVE.</head>
<p>&ldquo;ONCE upon a time, in a very small country town, at a considerable distance from London, there lived a little man named Nathaniel Pipkin, who was the parish clerk of the little town, and lived in a little house in the little high street, within ten minutes' walk of the little church; and who was to be found every day from nine till four, teaching a little learning to the little boys. Nathaniel Pipkin was a harmless, inoffensive, good-natured being, with a turned-up nose, and rather turned-in legs, a cast in his eye, and a halt in his gait; and he divided his time between the church and his school, verily believing that there existed not, on the face of the earth, so clever a man as the curate, so imposing an apartment as the vestry-room, or so well-ordered a seminary as his own. Once, and only once, in his life, Nathaniel Pipkin had seen a bishop&mdash;a real bishop, with his arms in lawn sleeves, and his head in a wig. He had seen him walk, and heard him talk at a confirmation, on which momentous occasion Nathaniel Pipkin was so overcome with reverence and awe, when the aforesaid bishop laid his hand on his head, that he fainted right clean away, and was borne out of church in the arms of the beadle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This was a great event, a tremendous era, in Nathaniel Pipkin's life, and it was about the only one that had ever occurred to ruffle the smooth current of his quiet existence, when happening one fine afternoon, in a fit of mental abstraction, to raise his eyes from the slate on which he was devising some tremendous problem in compound addition for an offending urchin to solve, they suddenly rested on the blooming countenance of Maria Lobbs, the only daughter of old Lobbs the great saddler over the way. Now, the eyes of Mr. Pipkins had rested on the pretty face of Maria Lobbs many a time and oft before, at church and elsewhere: but the eyes of Maria Lobbs had never looked so bright,
<pb n="174" id="p174"/>
the cheeks of Maria Lobbs had never looked so ruddy, as upon this particular occasion. No wonder then, that Nathaniel Pipkin was unable to take his eyes from the countenance of Miss Lobbs; no wonder that Miss Lobbs, finding herself stared at by a young man, withdrew her head from the window out of which she had been peeping, and shut the casement and pulled down the blind; no wonder that Nathaniel Pipkin, immediately thereafter, fell upon the young urchin who had previously offended, and cuffed and knocked him to his heart's content. All this was very natural, and there's nothing at all to wonder at about it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It <hi rend="italics">is</hi> matter of wonder, though, that any one of Mr. Nathaniel Pipkin's retiring disposition, nervous temperament, and most particularly diminutive income, should from this day forth, have dared to aspire to the hand and heart of the only daughter of the fiery old Lobbs&mdash;of old Lobbs the great saddler, who could have bought up the whole village at one stroke of his pen, and never felt the outlay&mdash;old Lobbs, who was well known to have heaps of money, invested in the bank at the nearest market town&mdash;who was reported to have countless and inexhaustible treasures, hoarded up in the little iron safe with the big key-hole, over the chimney-piece in the back parlour&mdash;and who, it was well known, on festive occasions garnished his board with a real silver tea-pot, cream ewer, and sugar-basin, which he was wont, in the pride of his heart, to boast should be his daughter's property when she found a man to her mind. I repeat it, to be matter of profound astonishment and intense wonder, that Nathaniel Pipkin should have had the temerity to cast his eyes in this direction. But love is blind, and Nathaniel had a cast in his eye: and perhaps these two circumstances, taken together, prevented his seeing the matter, in its proper light.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, if old Lobbs had entertained the most remote or distant idea of the state of the affections of Nathaniel Pipkin, he would just have razed the school-room to the ground, or exterminated its master from the surface of the earth, or committed some other outrage and atrocity of an equally ferocious and violent description; for he was a terrible old fellow, that Lobbs, when his pride was injured, or his blood was up. Swear! Such trains of oaths would come rolling and pealing over the way, sometimes, when he was denouncing the idleness of the bony apprentice with the thin legs, that Nathaniel Pipkin would shake in his shoes with horror, and the hair of the pupils' heads would stand on end with fright.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, day after day, when school was over, and the pupils gone, did Nathaniel Pipkin sit himself down at the front window, and while he feigned to be reading a book, throw sidelong glances over the way in search of the bright eyes of Maria Lobbs; and he hadn't sat there many days, before the bright eyes appeared at an upper window, apparently deeply engaged in reading too. This was delightful, and, gladdening to the heart of Nathaniel Pipkin. It was something to sit there for hours together, and look upon that pretty face when the eyes were cast down; but when Maria Lobbs began to raise her eyes from her book, and dart their rays in the direction of Nathaniel Pipkin, his delight and admiration were perfectly boundless. At last, one day
<pb n="175" id="p175"/>
when he knew old Lobbs was out, Nathaniel Pipkin had the temerity to kiss his hand to Maria Lobbs; and Maria Lobbs, instead of shutting the window, and pulling down the blind, kissed <hi
rend="italics">hers</hi> to him, and smiled. Upon which, Nathaniel Pipkin determined, that, come what might, he would develope the state of his feelings, without further delay.</p>
<p>A prettier foot, a gayer heart, a more dimpled face, or a smarter form, never bounded so lightly over the earth they graced, as did those of Maria Lobbs, the old saddler's daughter. There was a roguish twinkle in her sparkling eyes, that would have made its way to far less susceptible bosoms than that of Nathaniel Pipkin; and there was such a joyous sound in her merry laugh, that the sternest misanthrope must have smiled to hear it. Even old Lobbs himself, in the very height of his ferocity, couldn't resist the coaxing of his pretty daughter; and when she, and her cousin Kate&mdash;an arch, impudent-looking, bewitching little person&mdash;made a dead set upon the old man together, as, to say the truth, they very often did, he could have refused them nothing, even had they asked for a portion of the countless and inexhaustible treasures, which were hidden from the light, in the iron safe.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nathaniel Pipkin's heart beat high within him, when he saw this enticing little couple some hundred yards before him, one summer's evening, in the very field in which he had many a time strolled about till night-time, and pondered on the beauty of Maria Lobbs. But though he had often thought then, how briskly he would walk up to Maria Lobbs and tell her of his passion if he could only meet her, he felt, now that she was unexpectedly before him, all the blood in his body mounting to his face, manifestly to the great detriment of his legs, which, deprived of their usual portion, trembled beneath him. When they stopped to gather a hedge-flower, or listen to a bird, Nathaniel Pipkin stopped too, and pretended to be absorbed in meditation, as indeed he really was; for he was thinking what on earth he should ever do, when they turned back, as they inevitably must in time, and meet him face to face. But though he was afraid to make up to them, he couldn't bear to lose sight of them; so when they walked faster he walked faster, when they lingered he lingered, and when they stopped he stopped; and so they might have gone on, till the darkness prevented them, if Kate had not looked slily back, and encouragingly beckoned Nathaniel to advance. There was something in Kate's manner that was not to be resisted, and so Nathaniel Pipkin complied with the invitation; and after a great deal of blushing on his part, and immoderate laughter on that of the wicked little cousin, Nathaniel Pipkin went down on his knees on the dewy grass, and declared his resolution to remain there for ever, unless he was permitted to rise the accepted lover of Maria Lobbs. Upon this, the merry laughter of Maria Lobbs rang through the calm evening air&mdash;without seeming to disturb it, though; it had such a pleasant sound&mdash;and the wicked little cousin laughed more immoderately than before, and Nathaniel Pipkin blushed deeper than ever. At length, Maria Lobbs being more strenuously urged by the love-worn little man, turned away her head, and whispered her cousin to say, or at all events Kate <hi
rend="italics">did</hi> say, that she felt much honoured by Mr. Pipkin's addresses, that her hand and heart were at her father's disposal, but
<pb n="176" id="p176"/>
that nobody could be insensible to Mr. Pipkin's merits. As all this was said with much gravity, and as Nathaniel Pipkin walked home with Maria Lobbs, and struggled for a kiss at parting, he went to bed a happy man, and dreamed all night long, of softening old Lobbs, opening the strong box, and marrying Maria.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The next day, Nathaniel Pipkin saw old Lobbs go out upon his old grey poney, and after a great many signs at the window from the wicked little cousin, the object and meaning of which he could by no means understand, the bony apprentice with the thin legs came over to say that his master wasn't coming home all night, and that the ladies expected Mr. Pipkin to tea, at six o'clock precisely. How the lessons were got through that day, neither Nathaniel Pipkin nor his pupils knew any more than you do; but they were got through somehow, and, after the boys had gone, Nathaniel Pipkin took till full six o'clock to dress himself to his satisfaction; not that it took long to select the garments he should wear, inasmuch as he had no choice about the matter, but the putting them on to the best advantage, and touching them up previously, was a task of no inconsiderable difficulty or importance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There was a very snug little party, consisting of Maria Lobbs and her cousin Kate, and three or four romping, good-humoured, rosycheeked girls. Nathaniel Pipkin had ocular demonstration of the fact, that even the rumours of old Lobbs's treasures were not exaggerated. There were the real solid silver tea-pot, cream-ewer, and sugar-basin, on the table, and real silver spoons to stir the tea with, and real china cups to drink it out of, and plates of the same, to hold the cakes and toast in. The only eye-sore in the whole place, was another cousin of Maria Lobbs's, and brother of Kate, whom Maria Lobbs called &lsquo;Henry,&rsquo; and who seemed to keep Maria Lobbs all to himself, up in one corner of the table. It's a delightful thing to see affection in families, but it may be carried rather too far, and Nathaniel Pipkin could not help thinking that Maria Lobbs must be very particularly fond of her relations, if she paid as much attention to all of them as to this individual cousin. After tea, too, when the wicked little cousin proposed a game at blind man's buff, it somehow or other happened that Nathaniel Pipkin was nearly always blind, and whenever he laid his hand upon the male cousin, he was sure to find that Maria Lobbs was not far off. And though the wicked little cousin and the other girls pinched him, and pulled his hair, and pushed chairs in his way, and all sorts of things, Maria Lobbs never seemed to come near him at all; and once&mdash;once&mdash;Nathaniel Pipkin could have sworn he heard the sound of a kiss, followed by a faint remonstrance from Maria Lobbs, and a half-suppressed laugh from her female friends. All this was odd&mdash;very odd&mdash;and there is no saving what Nathaniel Pipkin might or might not have done, in consequence, if his thoughts had not been suddenly directed into a new channel.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The circumstance which directed his thoughts into a new channel was a loud knocking at the street-door, and the person who made this loud knocking at the street-door, was no other than old Lobbs himself, who had unexpectedly returned, and was hammering away, like a coffin-maker: for he wanted his supper. The alarming intelligence was no
<pb n="177" id="p177"/>
sooner communicated by the bony apprentice with the thin legs, than the girls tripped up stairs to Maria Lobbs's bed-room, and the male cousin and Nathaniel Pipkin were thrust into a couple of closets in the sitting-room, for want of any better places of concealment; and when Maria Lobbs and the wicked little cousin had stowed them away, and put the room to rights, they opened the street door to old Lobbs, who had never left off knocking since he first began.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now it did unfortunately happen that old Lobbs being very hungry was monstrous cross. Nathaniel Pipkin could hear him growling away like an old mastiff with a sore throat; and whenever the unfortunate apprentice with the thin legs came into the room, so surely did old Lobbs commence swearing at him in a most Saracenic and ferocious manner, though apparently with no other end or object than that of easing his bosom by the discharge of a few superfluous oaths. At length some supper, which had been warming up, was placed on the table, and then old Lobbs fell to, in regular style; and, having made clear work of it in no time, kissed his daughter, and demanded his pipe.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nature had placed Nathaniel Pipkin's knees in very close juxtaposition, but when he heard old Lobbs demand his pipe, they knocked together, as if they were going to reduce each other to powder; for, depending from a couple of hooks, in the very closet in which he stood, was a large brown-stemmed, silver-bowled pipe, which pipe he himself had seen in the mouth of old Lobbs, regularly every afternoon and evening, for the last five years. The two girls went down stairs for the pipe, and up stairs for the pipe, and everywhere but where they knew the pipe was, and old Lobbs stormed away meanwhile, in the most wonderful manner. At last he thought of the closet, and walked up to it. It was of no use a little man like Nathaniel Pipkin pulling the door inwards, when a great strong fellow like old Lobbs was pulling it outwards. Old Lobbs just gave it one tug, and open it flew, disclosing Nathaniel Pipkin standing bolt upright inside, and shaking with apprehension from head to foot. Bless us! what an appalling look old Lobbs gave him, as he dragged him out by the collar, and held him at arm's length.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Why, what the devil do you want here?&rsquo; said old Lobbs, in a fearful voice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nathaniel Pipkin could make no reply, so old Lobbs shook him backwards and forwards, for two or three minutes, by way of arranging his ideas for him.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;What do you want here?&rsquo; roared Lobbs, &lsquo;I suppose <hi
rend="italics">you</hi> have come after my daughter, now.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Old Lobbs merely said this as a sneer: for he did not believe that mortal presumption could have carried Nathaniel Pipkin so far. What was his indignation, when that poor man replied&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Yes, I did, Mr. Lobbs&mdash;I did come after your daughter. I love her, Mr. Lobbs.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Why, you snivelling, wry-faced little villain,&rsquo; gasped old Lobbs, paralysed at the atrocious confession; &lsquo;what do you mean by that? Say this to my face! Damme, I'll throttle you.&rsquo;</p>
<pb n="178" id="p178"/>
<p>&ldquo;It is by no means improbable that old Lobbs would have carried this threat into execution, in the excess of his rage, if his arm had not been stayed by a very unexpected apparition, to wit, the male cousin, who, stepping out of his closet, and walking up to old Lobbs, said&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;I cannot allow this harmless person, Sir, who has been asked here, in some girlish frolic, to take upon himself, in a very noble manner, the fault (if fault it is) which I am guilty of, and am ready to avow. <hi
rend="italics">I</hi> love your daughter, Sir; and <hi rend="italics">I</hi> came here for the purpose of meeting her.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Old Lobbs opened his eyes very wide at this, but not wider than Nathaniel Pipkin.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;You did?&rsquo; said Lobbs: at last finding breath to speak.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;I did.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;And I forbade you this house, long ago.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;You did, or I should not have been here, clandestinely, to-night.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am sorry to record it, of old Lobbs, but I think he would have struck the cousin, if his pretty daughter, with her bright eyes swimming in tears, had not clung to his arm.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Don't stop him, Maria,&rsquo; said the young man: &lsquo;if he has the will to strike me, let him. I would not hurt a hair of his grey head, for the riches of the world.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The old man cast down his eyes at this reproof, and they met those of his daughter. I have hinted once or twice before, that they were very bright eyes, and, though they were tearful now, their influence was by no means lessened. Old Lobbs turned his head away, as if to avoid being persuaded by them, when, as fortune would have it, he encountered the face of the wicked little cousin, who, half afraid for her brother, and half laughing at Nathaniel Pipkin, presented as bewitching an expression of countenance, with a touch of slyness in it too, as any man, old or young, need look upon. She drew her arm coaxingly through the old man's, and whispered something in his ear; and do what he would, old Lobbs couldn't help breaking out into a smile, while a tear stole down his cheek, at the same time.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Five minutes after this, the girls were brought down from the bedroom with a great deal of giggling and modesty; and while the young people were making themselves perfectly happy, old Lobbs got down the pipe, and smoked it: and it was a remarkable circumstance about that particular pipe of tobacco, that it was the most soothing and lightful one he ever smoked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nathaniel Pipkin thought it best to keep his own counsel, and by so doing gradually rose into high favour with old Lobbs, who taught him to smoke in time; and they used to sit out in the garden on the fine evenings, for many years afterwards, smoking and drinking in great state. He soon recovered the effects of his attachment, for we find his name in the parish register, as a witness to the marriage of Maria Lobbs to her cousin; and it also appears, by reference to other documents, that on the night of the wedding, he was incarcerated in the village cage, for having, in a state of extreme intoxication, committed sundry excesses in the streets, in all of which he was aided and abetted by the bony apprentice with the thin legs</p>
</div1></body></text></q>
</div2></div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb id="piv" n="iv"/>
<head>CHEAP AND ENTERTAINING PERIODICAL.</head>
<p>THIS DAY IS PUBLISHED, <lb/> PRICE 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
<lb/> CONTAINING FOUR HUNDRED PAGES OF LETTER-PRESS, AND <lb/> FOURTEEN ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> THE FIRST VOLUME OF <lb/> THE LIBRARY OF FICTION, <lb/> OR <lb/> Family Story Celler.</p>
<div2 type="section">
<head>ADDRESS.</head>
<p>IN completing the First Volume of this Work, the Proprietors take the opportunity of expressing their warmest acknowledgments for the great favour with which it has been received, as issued in monthly parts. Nothing could possibly be more encouraging to them to proceed with energy and spirit in carrying on the publication, which the gradual development of those literary means peculiarly possessed by the Editor will, they confidently anticipate, enable them satisfactorily to do.</p>
<p>The peculiar purpose of the LIBRARY OF FICTION is to put its readers in possession, at an extremely moderate price, of a series of Original Tales or Sketches, all carefully selected from among a host of candidates, and many of the highly-prized contributions of established authors of the very loftiest pretensions in the field of imaginative composition.</p>
<p>But in order to prove that their claims to public notice and approbation are not to be estimated in proportion to the size of the productions comprised in their pages, they subjoin in conclusion, a short abstract from the list of distinguished writers, who either already have contributed, or engaged to contribute, to this publication.</p>
<list>
<item>G. P. R. JAMES, ESQ.</item>
<item>MISS MITFORD.</item>
<item>MISS LANDON.</item>
<item>SHERIDAN KNOWLES, ESQ.</item>
<item>&ldquo;BOZ,&rdquo;</item>
<item>DOUGLAS JERROLD. ESQ.</item>
<item>SAMUEL LOVER, ESO.</item>
<item>ALLAN CUNNINGHAM, ESQ.</item>
<item>CAPTAIN GLASCOCK, AUTHOR OF THE &ldquo;NAVAL SKETCH BOOK.&rdquo;</item>
<item>EDWARD MAYHEW, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;MAKE YOUR WILLS,&rdquo; AND OTHER DRAMAS.</item>
<item>J. AINSWORTH, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;ROOKWOOD.&rdquo;</item>
<item>C. OLLIER, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;INESILLA.&rdquo;</item>
<item>C. WHITEHEAD, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;THE CAVALIER,&rdquo;</item>
<item>T. K. HERVEY, ESQ.</item></list>
<closer>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
