<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI U5-1995//DTD TEI Lite//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="3D">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. IV:
Electronic Edition.
</title><author>Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrated by </resp>
<name>Pailthorpe, F. W. (Frederic W.)</name>
<name>Seymour, Robert, 1798-1836.</name>
<name>Buss, Robert William, 1804-1875.</name>
<name>Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.</name>
</respStmt>

<funder>Funding from the  E. S. P. Das Educational Foundation supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder><respStmt>
<resp>Text transcribed  by</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt><resp>Images scanned by</resp>
<name>Matthew Kern</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Text encoded by </resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc., Harris Henderson, and Jill Kuhn Sexton</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition>First edition, <date>2002</date></edition></editionStmt>
<extent>ca. 110K</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace><date>2002.</date>

<availability>
<p>&copy; This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>


<sourceDesc>

<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="title page">The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club Containing a Faithful Record of the Perambulations, Perils, Travels, Adventures and Sporting Transactions of the Corresponding Members. No. IV</title>
<title type="cover"></title>

<author>Boz</author>

<respStmt><resp>Illustrations by</resp>
<name>R. Seymour and Phiz</name></respStmt>

</titleStmt>

<extent>   37 p., ill.</extent>

<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall, 186, Strand</publisher>
<date>1836</date>
<authority></authority>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt><note>Call number Dickens 13 pt. 4  (Rare Book Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>

<editorialDecl>

<p>The text has been entered using double-keying and verified against the original. 
The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>

<p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>

<p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>

<p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
<p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rdquo; and &ldquo;
respectively.</p>
<p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as &rsquo; and &lsquo; respectively.</p>
<p>All em dashes are encoded as &mdash;</p><p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
<p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
</editorialDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>

<change>
<date>2002-11-18, </date><respStmt><name> Jill Kuhn Sexton </name><resp></resp>
</respStmt><item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2002-09-24, </date><respStmt><name>Harris Henderson</name>
<resp></resp></respStmt><item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item></change>
<change><date>2002-08-01, </date>
<respStmt><name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name><resp></resp></respStmt>
<item> finished transcribing the text.</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<titlePage>

<titlePart> No. IV.]</titlePart>

<docEdition>[PRICE  1<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></docEdition>

<docTitle><titlePart>THE <lb/> POSTHUMOUS PAPERS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> PICKWICK CLUB <lb/> CONTAINING A FAITHFUL RECORD OF THE <lb/> PERAMBULATIONS, PERILS, TRAVELS, ADVENTURES <lb/> AND <lb/> Sporting Transactions <lb/> OF THE CORRESPONDING MEMBERS. </titlePart></docTitle>

<docAuthor>
EDITED BY &ldquo;BOZ.&rdquo; </docAuthor>

<docEdition> WITH ILLUSTRATIONS.
</docEdition>

<docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAPMAN &amp; HALL, 186, STRAND.</publisher>
<docDate>MDCCCXXXVI</docDate>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="section">
<pb n="ii" id="pii"/>
<p>
<figure id="ill1">
<p><hi rend="italics">page 89</hi></p>
</figure>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section">
<pb id="piii" n="iii"/>
<p>
<figure id="ill2">
<p><hi rend="italics">page 94</hi></p>
</figure>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="text">
<pb id="p83" n="83"/>

<head>[POSTHUMOUS PAPERS OF THE PICKWICK CLUB]</head>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER IX.</head>

<head>A DISCOVERY AND A CHASE.</head>

<p>THE supper was ready laid, the chairs were drawn round the table, bottles, jugs and glasses were arranged upon the sideboard, and every thing betokened the approach of the most convivial period in the whole four and twenty hours.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where's Rachael?&rdquo; said Mr. Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Aye, and Jingle?&rdquo; added Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear me,&rdquo; said the host, &ldquo;I wonder I haven't missed him before. Why, I don't think I've heard his voice for two hours at least. Emily, my dear, ring the bell.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The bell was rung, and the fat boy appeared.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where's Miss Rachael?&rdquo; He couldn't say.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where's Mr. Jingle, then?&rdquo; He didn't know.</p>
<p>Every body looked surprised. It was late&mdash;past eleven o'clock. Mr. Tupman laughed in his sleeve. They were loitering somewhere, talking about <hi
rend="italics">him.</hi> Ha, ha! capital notion that&mdash;funny.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never mind,&rdquo; said Wardle, after a short pause, &ldquo;they'll turn unpresently, I dare say. I never wait supper for anybody.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Excellent rule, that,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;admirable.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray, sit down,&rdquo; said the host.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Certainly,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick: and down they sat.</p>
<p>There was a gigantic round of cold beef on the table, and Mr. Pickwick was supplied with a plentiful portion of it. He had raised his fork to his lips, and was on the very point of opening his mouth for the reception of a piece of beef, when the hum of many voices suddenly arose in the kitchen. He paused, and laid down his fork. Mr. Wardle paused too, and insensibly released his hold of the carving-knife, which remained inserted in the beef. He looked at Mr. Pickwick. Mr. Pickwick looked at him.</p>
<p>Heavy footsteps were heard in the passage; the parlour door was suddenly burst open; and the man who had cleaned Mr. Pickwick's boots on his first arrival, rushed into the room, followed by the fat boy, and all the domestics.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What the devil's the meaning of this?&rdquo; exclaimed the host.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The kitchen chimney ain't a-fire, is it, Emma?&rdquo; inquired the old lady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lor grandma! No,&rdquo; screamed both the young ladies.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's the matter?&rdquo; roared the master of the house.</p>
<p>The man gasped for breath, and faintly ejaculated&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;They ha' gone, Mas'r!&mdash;gone right clean off, Sir!&rdquo; (At this juncture, Mr. Tupman was observed to lay down his knife and fork, and to turn very pale.)</p>
<pb n="84" id="p84"/>
<p>&ldquo;Who's gone?&rdquo; said Mr. Wardle, fiercely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mus'r Jingle and Miss Rachael, in a po'-chay, from Blue Lion, Muggleton. I was there; but I couldn't stop 'em; so I run off to tell'ee.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I paid his expenses!&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman, jumping up frantically. &ldquo;He's got ten pounds of mine!&mdash;stop him!&mdash;he's swindled me!&mdash;I won't bear it!&mdash;I 'll have justice, Pickwick!&mdash;I won't stand it!&rdquo; and with sundry incoherent exclamations of the like nature, the unhappy gentleman spun round and round the apartment, in a transport of frenzy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lord preserve us!&rdquo; ejaculated Mr. Pickwick, eyeing the extraordinary gestures of his friend with terrified surprise. &ldquo;He's gone mad! What shall we do!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do!&rdquo; said the stout old host, who regarded only the last words of the sentence. &ldquo;Put the horse in the gig! I'll get a chaise at the Lion, and follow 'em instantly. &ldquo;Where&rdquo;&mdash;he exclaimed, as the man ran out to execute the commission&mdash;&ldquo;Where's that villain, Joe?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here I am; but I han't a willin,&rdquo; replied a voice. It was the fat boy's.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let me get at him, Pickwick!&rdquo; cried Wardle, as he rushed at the ill-starred youth. &ldquo;He was bribed by that scoundrel, Jingle, to put me on a wrong scent, by telling a cock-and-a-bull story of my sister and your friend Tupman!&rdquo; (Here Mr. Tupman sunk into a chair.) &ldquo;Let me get at him!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't let him!&rdquo; screamed all the women, above whose exclamations, the blubbering of the fat boy, was distinctly audible.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I won't be held!&rdquo; cried the old man. &ldquo;Mr. Winkle, take your hands off! Mr. Pickwick, let me go, Sir!&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was a beautiful sight, in that moment of turmoil and confusion, to behold the placid and philosophical expression of Mr. Pickwick's face, albeit somewhat flushed with exertion, as he stood with his arms firmly clasped round the extensive waist of their corpulent host, thus restraining the impetuosity of his passion, while the fat boy was scratched, and pulled, and pushed from the room by all the females congregated therein. He had no sooner released his hold, than the man entered to announce that the gig was ready.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't let him go alone!&rdquo; screamed the females. &ldquo;He'll kill somebody!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I 'll go with him,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a good fellow, Pickwick,&rdquo; said the host, grasping his hand. &ldquo;Emma, give Mr. Pickwick a shawl to tie round his neck&mdash;make haste. Look after your grandmother, girls; she's fainted away. Now then, are you ready?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's mouth and chin having been hastily enveloped in a large shawl: his hat having been put on his head, and his great coat thrown over his arm, he replied in the affirmative.</p>
<p>They jumped into the gig. &ldquo;Give her, her head, Tom,&rdquo; cried the host; and away they went, down the narrow lanes: jolting in and out
<pb n="85" id="p85"/>
of the cart-ruts, and bumping up against the hedges on either side, as if they would go to pieces every moment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How much are they a-head?&rdquo; shouted Wardle, as they drove up to the door of the Blue Lion, round which a little crowd had collected, late as it was.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not above three-quarters of an hour,&rdquo; was everybody's reply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Chaise and four directly!&mdash;out with 'em! Put up the gig afterwards.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, boys!&rdquo; cried the landlord&mdash;&ldquo;chaise and four out&mdash;make haste&mdash;look alive there!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Away ran the hostlers, and the boys. The lanterns glimmered, as the men ran to and fro; the horses' hoofs clattered on the uneven paving of the yard; the chaise rumbled as it was drawn out of the coach-house; and all was noise and bustle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now then!&mdash;is that chaise coming out to-night?&rdquo; cried Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Coming down the yard now, Sir,&rdquo; replied the hostler.</p>
<p>Out came the chaise&mdash;in went the horses&mdash;on sprung the boys&mdash;in got the travellers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Mind&mdash;the seven-mile stage in less than half an hour!&rdquo; shouted Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Off with you!&rsquo;</p>
<p>The boys applied whip and spur, the waiters shouted, the hostlers cheered, and away they went, fast and furiously</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pretty situation,&rdquo; thought Mr. Pickwick, when he had had a moment's time for reflection. &ldquo;Pretty situation for the General Chairman of the Pickwick Club. Damp chaise&mdash;strange horses&mdash;fifteen miles an hour&mdash;and twelve o'clock at night!&rdquo;</p>
<p>For the first three or four miles, not a word was spoken by either of the gentlemen, each being too much immersed in his own reflections, to address any observations to his companion. When they had gone over that much ground, however, and the horses getting thoroughly warmed began to do their work in really good style, Mr. Pickwick became too much exhilarated with the rapidity of the motion, to remain any longer perfectly mute.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We're sure to catch them, I think,&rdquo; said he.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hope so,&rdquo; replied his companion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Fine night,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, looking up at the moon, which was shining brightly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So much the worse,&rdquo; returned Wardle; &ldquo;for they'll have had all the advantage of the moonlight to get the start of us, and we shall lose it. It will have gone down in another hour.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It will be rather unpleasant going at this rate in the dark, won't it?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick,</p>
<p>&ldquo;I dare say it will,&rdquo; replied his friend drily.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's temporary excitement began to sober down a little, as he reflected upon the inconveniences and dangers of the expedition in which he had so thoughtlessly embarked. He was roused by a loud shouting of the post-boy on the leader.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yoe,&rdquo; went the first boy</p>
<pb n="86" id="p86"/>
<p>&ldquo;Yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yoe!&rdquo; went the second.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yoe!&rdquo; chimed in old Wardle himself, most lustily, with his head and half his body out of the coach window.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yo&mdash;yoe!&rdquo; shouted Mr. Pickwick, taking up the burden of the cry, though he had not the slightest notion of its meaning or object. And amidst the yo&mdash;yoing of the whole four, the chaise stopped.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What's the matter?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There's a gate here,&rdquo; replied old Wardle, &ldquo;We shall hear something of the fugitives.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After a lapse of five minutes, consumed in incessant knocking and shouting, an old man in his shirt and trousers emerged from the turnpike-house, and opened the gate.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How long is it since a post-chaise went through here?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How long?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, I don't rightly know. It worn't a long time ago, nor it worn't a short time ago&mdash;just between the two, perhaps.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Has any chaise been by at all?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yes, there's been a chay by.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How long ago, my friend,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;an hour?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, I dare say it might be,&rdquo; replied the man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Or two hours?&rdquo; inquired the post-boy on the wheeler.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, I should n't wonder if it was,&rdquo; returned the old man doubtfully.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Drive on, boys,&rdquo; cried the testy old gentleman: &ldquo;don't waste any more time with that old idiot!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Idiot!&rdquo; exclaimed the old man with a grin, as he stood in the middle of the road with the gate half closed, watching the chaise which rapidly diminished in the increasing distance. &ldquo;No&mdash;not much o' that either; you've lost ten minutes here, and gone away as wise as you came arter all. If every man on the line as has a guinea give him earns it half as well, you won't catch t'other chay this side Mich'lmas, old short and fat.&rdquo; And with another prolonged grin, the old man closed the gate, re-entered his house, and bolted the door after him.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the chaise proceeded, without any slackening of pace, towards the conclusion of the stage. The moon, as Wardle had foretold, was rapidly on the wane; large tiers of dark heavy clouds which had been gradually overspreading the sky for some time past, now formed one black mass over head; and large drops of rain which pattered every now and then against the windows of the chaise, seemed to warn the travellers of the rapid approach of a stormy night. The wind, too, which was directly against them, swept in furious gusts down the narrow road, and howled dismally through the trees which skirted the pathway. Mr. Pickwick drew his coat closer about him, coiled himself more snugly up into the corner of the chaise, and fell into a sound sleep, from which he was only awakened by the stopping of the vehicle, the sound of the hostler's bell, and a loud cry of &ldquo;Horses on directly!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="87" id="p87"/>
<p>But here another delay occurred. The boys were sleeping with such mysterious soundness, that it took five minutes a-piece to wake them. The hostler had somehow or other mislaid the key of the stable, and even when that was found, two sleepy helpers put the wrong harness on the wrong horses, and the whole process of harnessing had to be gone through afresh. Had Mr. Pickwick been alone, these multiplied obstacles would have completely put an end to the pursuit at once, but old Wardle was not to be so easily daunted; and he laid about him with such hearty good-will, cuffing this man, and pushing that; strapping a buckle here, and taking in a link there, that the chaise was ready in a much shorter time than could reasonably have been expected, under so many difficulties.</p>
<p>They resumed their journey; and certainly the prospect before them was by no means encouraging. The stage was fifteen miles long, the night was dark, the wind high, and the rain pouring in torrents. It was impossible to make any great way against such obstacles united: it was hard upon one o'clock already; and nearly two hours were consumed in getting to the end of the stage. Here, however, an object presented itself, which re-kindled their hopes, and re-animated their drooping spirits.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When did this chaise come in?&rdquo; cried old Wardle, leaping out of his own vehicle, and pointing to one covered with wet mud, which was standing in the yard.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not a quarter of an hour ago, Sir;&rdquo; replied the hostler, to whom the question was addressed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Lady and gentleman?&rdquo; inquired Wardle, almost breathless with impatience.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tall gentleman&mdash;dress coat&mdash;long legs&mdash;thin body?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Elderly lady&mdash;thin face&mdash;rather skinny&mdash;eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;By Heavens, it's them, Pickwick,&rdquo; exclaimed the old gentleman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Would have been here before,&rdquo; said the hostler, &ldquo;but they broke a trace.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;'Tis them,&rdquo; said Wardle, &ldquo;it is, by Jove! Chaise and four instantly. We shall catch them yet, before they reach the next stage. A guinea a-piece, boys&mdash;be alive there&mdash;bustle about&mdash;there's good fellows.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And with such admonitions as these, the old gentleman ran up and down the yard, and bustled to and fro, in a state of excitement which communicated itself to Mr. Pickwick also; and under the influence of which, that gentleman got himself into complicated entanglements with harness, and mixed up with horses and wheels of chaises, in the most surprising manner, firmly believing that by so doing, he was materially forwarding the preparations for their resuming their journey.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Jump in&mdash;jump in!&rdquo; cried old Wardle, climbing into the chaise, pulling up the steps, and slamming the door after him. &ldquo;Come along, make haste.&rdquo; And before Mr. Pickwick knew precisely what he was
<pb n="88" id="p88"/>
about, he felt himself forced in at the other door, by one pull from the old gentleman, and one push from the hostler; and off they were again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! we <hi rend="italics">are</hi> moving now,&rdquo; said the old gentleman exultingly. They were indeed, as was sufficiently testified to Mr. Pickwick, by his constant collisions either with the hard wood-work of the chaise, or the body of his companion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hold up!&rdquo; said the stout old Mr. Wardle, as Mr. Pickwick dived head foremost into his capacious waistcoat.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I never did feel such a jolting in my life,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never mind,&rdquo; replied his companion, &ldquo;it 'll soon be over. Steady, steady.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick planted himself into his own corner, as firmly as he could; and on whirled the chaise faster than ever.</p>
<p>They had travelled in this way about three miles, when Mr. Wardle, who had been looking out of the window for two or three minutes, suddenly drew in his face, covered with splashes, and exclaimed in breathless eagerness&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here they are!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick thrust his head out of his window. Yes: there was a chaise and four, a short distance before them, dashing along at full gallop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Go on, go on,&rdquo; almost shrieked the old gentleman. &ldquo;Two guineas a-piece, boys&mdash;don't let 'em gain on us&mdash;keep it up&mdash;keep it up.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The horses in the first chaise started on at their utmost speed; and those in Mr. Wardle's galloped furiously behind them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I see his head,&rdquo; exclaimed the choleric old man, &ldquo;Damme, I see his head.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So do I,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;that's he.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick was not mistaken. The countenance of Mr. Jingle, completely coated with the mud thrown up by the wheels, was plainly discernible at the window of his chaise; and the motion of his arm, which he was waving violently towards the postilions, denoted that he was encouraging them to increased exertion.</p>
<p>The interest was intense. Fields, trees, and hedges, seemed to rush past them with the velocity of a whirlwind, so rapid was the pace at which they tore along. They were close by the side of the first chaise. Jingle's voice could be plainly heard, even above the din of the wheels, urging on the boys. Old Mr. Wardle foamed with rage and excitement. He roared out scoundrels and villains by the dozen, clenched his fist and shook it expressively at the object of his indignation; but Mr. Jingle only answered with a contemptuous smile, and replied to his menaces by a shout of triumph, as his horses, answering the increased application of whip and spur, broke into a faster gallop, and left the pursuers behind.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick had just drawn in his head, and Mr. Wardle, exhausted with shouting, had done the same, when a tremendous jolt threw them forward against the front of the vehicle. There was a sudden bump&mdash;a loud crash&mdash;away rolled a wheel, and over went the chaise.</p>
<p>After a very few seconds of bewilderment and confusion, in which
<pb n="89" id="p89"/>
nothing but the plunging of horses, and breaking of glass, could be made out, Mr. Pickwick felt himself violently pulled out from among the ruins of the chaise; and as soon as he had gained his feet, and extricated his head from the skirts of his great coat which materially impeded the usefulness of his spectacles, the full disaster of the case met his view.</p>
<p>Old Mr. Wardle without a hat, and his clothes torn in several places, stood by his side, and the fragments of the chaise lay scattered at their feet. The post-boys, who had succeeded in cutting the traces, were standing, disfigured with mud and disordered by hard riding, by the horses' heads. About a hundred yards in advance was the other chaise, which had pulled up on hearing the crash. The postillions, each with a broad grin convulsing his countenance, were viewing the adverse party from their saddles, and Mr. Jingle was contemplating the wreck from the coach-window, with evident satisfaction. The day was just breaking, and the whole scene was rendered perfectly visible by the grey light of the morning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hallo!&rdquo; shouted the shameless Jingle, &ldquo;any body damaged?&mdash;elderly gentlemen&mdash;no light weights&mdash;dangerous work&mdash;very.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're a rascal!&rdquo; roared Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ha! ha!&rdquo; replied Jingle; and then he added, with a knowing wink, and a jerk of the thumb towards the interior of the chaise&mdash;&ldquo;I say&mdash;she's very well&mdash;desires her compliments&mdash;begs you won't trouble yourself&mdash;love to <hi
rend="italics">Tuppy</hi>&mdash;won't you get up behind?&mdash;drive on boys.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The postilions resumed their proper attitudes, and away rattled the chaise, Mr. Jingle fluttering in derision a white handkerchief from the coach window.</p>
<p>Nothing in the whole adventure, not even the upset, had disturbed the calm and equable current of Mr. Pickwick's temper. The villany however, which could first borrow money of his faithful follower, and then abbreviate his name to &ldquo;Tuppy,&rdquo; was more than he could patiently bear. He drew his breath hard, and coloured up to the very tips of his spectacles, as he said, slowly and emphatically&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If ever I meet that man again, I'll&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, yes,&rdquo; interrupted Wardle, &ldquo;that's all very well: but while we stand talking here, they'll get their licence, and be married in London.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick paused, bottled up his vengeance, and corked it down.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How far is it to the next stage?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Wardle, of one of the boys.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Six mile, a'nt it, Tom?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rayther better.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rayther better nor six mile, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can't be helped,&rdquo; said Wardle, &ldquo;we must walk it, Pickwick.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No help for it,&rdquo; replied that truly great man.</p>
<p>So sending forward one of the boys on horseback, to procure a fresh chaise and horses, and leaving the other behind to take care of the broken one, Mr. Pickwick and Mr. Wardle set manfully forward on the walk, first tying their shawls round their necks, and slouching down their hats to escape as much as possible from the deluge of rain, which after a slight cessation, had again begun to pour heavily down.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="90" id="p90"/>
<head>CHAPTER X.</head>

<head>CLEARING UP ALL DOUBTS (IF ANY EXISTED) OF THE DISINTERESTEDNESS OF MR. JINGLE'S CHARACTER.</head>

<p>THERE are in London several old inns, once the head quarters of celebrated coaches in the days when coaches performed their journeys in a graver and more solemn manner than they do in these times; but which have now degenerated into little more than the abiding and booking places of country wagons. The reader would look in vain for any of these ancient hostelries, among the Golden Crosses and Bull and Mouths, which rear their stately fronts in the improved streets of London. If he would light upon any of these old places, he must direct his steps to the obscurer quarters of the town; and there in some secluded nooks he will find several, still standing with a kind of gloomy sturdiness, amidst the modern innovations which surround them.</p>
<p>In the Borough especially, there still remain some half dozen old inns, which have preserved their external features unchanged, and which have escaped alike the rage for public improvement, and the encroachments of private speculation. Great, rambling, queer, old places they are, with galleries, and passages, and stair-cases, wide enough and anti-quated enough, to furnish materials for a hundred ghost stories, supposing we should ever be reduced to the lamentable necessity of inventing any, and that the world should exist long enough to exhaust the innumerable veracious legends connected with old London Bridge, and its adjacent neighbourhood on the Surrey side.</p>
<p>It was in the yard of one of these inns&mdash;of no less celebrated a one than the White Hart&mdash;that a man was busily employed in brushing the dirt off a pair of boots, early on the morning succeeding the events narrated in the last chapter. He was habited in a coarse-striped waistcoat, with black calico sleeves, and blue glass buttons: drab breeches and leggings. A bright red handkerchief was wound in a very loose and unstudied style round his neck, and an old white hat was carelessly thrown on one side of his head. There were two rows of boots before him, one cleaned and the other dirty, and at every addition he made to the clean row, he paused from his work, and contemplated its results with evident satisfaction.</p>
<p>The yard presented none of that bustle and activity which are the usual characteristics of a large coach inn. Three or four lumbering wagons, each with a pile of goods beneath its ample canopy, about the height of the second-floor window of an ordinary house, were stowed away beneath a lofty roof which extended over one end of the yard; and another, which was probably to commence its journey that morning, was drawn out into the open space. A double tier of bed-room galleries,
<pb n="91" id="p91"/>
with old clumsy balustrades, ran round two sides of the straggling area, and a double row of bells to correspond, sheltered from the weather by a little sloping roof, hung over the door leading to the bar and coffee-room. Two or three gigs and chaise-carts were wheeled up under different little sheds and pent-houses; and the occasional heavy tread of a cart-horse, or rattling of a chain at the further end of the yard, announced to any body who cared about the matter, that the stable lay in that direction. When we add that a few boys in smock frocks, were lying asleep on heavy packages, woolpacks, and other articles that were scattered about on heaps of straw, we have described as fully as need be, the general appearance of the yard of the White Hart Inn, High Street, Borough, on the particular morning in question.</p>
<p>A loud ringing of one of the bells, was followed by the appearance of a smart chambermaid in the upper sleeping gallery, who, after tapping at one of the doors, and receiving a request from within, called over the balustrades.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hallo,&rdquo; replied the man with the white hat.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Number twenty-two wants his boots.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ask number twenty-two, vether he'll have 'em now, or vait till he gets 'em,&rdquo; was the reply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come, don't be a fool, Sam,&rdquo; said the girl, coaxingly, &ldquo;the gentleman wants his boots directly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, you <hi rend="italics">are</hi> a nice young 'ooman for a musical party, you are,&rdquo; said the boot-cleaner. &ldquo;Look at these here boots&mdash;eleven pair o' boots; and one shoe as b'longs to number six, with the wooden leg The eleven boots is to be called at half-past eight and the shoe at nine. Who's number twenty-two, that's to put all the others out? No, no; reg'lar rotation, as Jack Ketch said, ven he tied the men up. Sorry to keep you a watin', Sir, but I'll attend to you directly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Saying which, the man in the white hat set to work upon a top-boot with increased assiduity.</p>
<p>There was another loud ring; and the bustling old landlady of the White Hart made her appearance in the opposite gallery.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sam,&rdquo; cried the landlady, &ldquo;where's that lazy, idle&mdash;why Sam&mdash;oh, there you are; whydon't you answer?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Vouldn't be gen-teel to answer, 'till you'd done talking,&rdquo; replied Sam, gruffly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here, clean them shoes for number seventeen directly, and take 'em to private sitting-room, number five, first floor.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The landlady flung a pair of lady's shoes into the yard, and bustled away.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Number 5,&rdquo; said Sam, as he picked up the shoes, and taking a piece of chalk from his pocket, made a memorandum of their destination on the soles&mdash;&ldquo;Lady's shoes and private sittin' room! I suppose <hi
rend="italics">she</hi> didn't come in the vaggin.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;She came in early this morning,&rdquo; cried the girl, who was still leaning over the railing of the gallery, &ldquo;with a gentleman in a hackneycoach,
<pb n="92" id="p92"/>
and it's him as wants his boots, and you'd better do 'em, and that's all about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Vy didn't you say so before,&rdquo; said Sam, with great indignation, singling out the boots in question from the heap before him. &ldquo;For all I know'd he vas one o' the regular three-pennies. Private room! and a lady too! If he's anything of a gen'lm'n, he's vurth a shillin' a day, let alone the arrands.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Stimulated by this inspiring reflection, Mr. Samuel brushed away with such hearty good will, that in a few minutes the boots and shoes, with a polish which would have struck envy to the soul of the amiable Mr. Warren, (for they used Day and Martin at the White Hart) had arrived at the door of number five.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come in,&rdquo; said a man's voice, in reply to Sam's rap at the door.</p>
<p>Sam made his best bow, and stepped into the presence of a lady and gentleman seated at breakfast. Having officiously deposited the gentleman's boots right and left at his feet, and the lady's shoes right and left at hers, he backed towards the door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boots,&rdquo; said the gentleman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; said Sam, closing the door, and keeping his hand on the knob of the lock.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know&mdash;what's a-name&mdash;Doctors' Commons?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where is it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Paul's Church-yard, Sir; low archway on the carriage-side, bookseller's at one corner, hot-el on the other, and two porters in the middle as touts for licences.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Touts for licences!&rdquo; said the gentleman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Touts for licences,&rdquo; replied Sam. &ldquo;Two coves in vhite aprons&mdash;touches their hats ven you walk in&mdash;&lsquo;Licence, Sir, licence?&rsquo; Queer sort, them, and their mas'rs too, Sir&mdash;Old Bailey Proctors&mdash;and no mistake.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What do they do?&rdquo; inquired the gentleman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do! <hi rend="italics">You,</hi> Sir! That an't the worst on it, neither. They puts things into old gen'lm'ns heads as they never dreamed of. My father, Sir, vos a coachman. A vidower he vos, and fat enough for anything&mdash;uncommon fat, to be sure. His missus dies, and leaves him four hundred pound. Down he goes to the Commons, to see the lawyer and draw the blunt&mdash;wery smart&mdash;top boots on&mdash;nosegay in his button-hole&mdash;broad-brimmed tile&mdash;green shawl&mdash;quite the gen'lm'n. Goes through the archvay, thinking how he should inwest the money&mdash;up comes the touter, touches his hat&mdash;&lsquo;Licence, Sir, licence?&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;What's that?&rsquo; says my father.&mdash;&lsquo;Licence, Sir,&rsquo; says he.&mdash;&lsquo;What licence?&rsquo; says my father.&mdash;&lsquo;Marriage licence,&rsquo; says the touter.&mdash;&lsquo;Dash my veskit,&rsquo; says my father, &lsquo;I never thought o' that.&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;I think you wants one Sir,&rsquo; says the touter. My father pulls up, and thinks a bit&mdash;&lsquo;No,&rsquo; says he, &lsquo;damme, I'm too old, b'sides I'm a many sizes too large,&rsquo; says he.&mdash;&lsquo;Not a bit on it, Sir,&rsquo; says the touter.&mdash;&lsquo;Think not?&rsquo; says my father.&mdash;&lsquo;I'm sure not, says he; &lsquo;we married a gen'lm'n twice your size, last Monday.&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;Did you, though,&rsquo; said my father.&mdash;&lsquo;To be sure,
<pb id="p93" n="93"/>
ve did,&rsquo; says the touter, &lsquo;you're a babby to him&mdash;this vay, Sir&mdash;this vay!&rsquo;&mdash;and sure enough my father walks arter him, like a tame monkey behind a horgan, into a little back office, vere a feller sat among dirty papers and tin boxes, making believe he was busy. &lsquo;Pray take a seat, vile I makes out the affidavit, Sir,&rsquo; says the lawyer.&mdash;&lsquo;Thankee, Sir,&rsquo; says my father, and down he sat, and stared vith all his eyes, and his mouth vide open, at the names on the boxes.&mdash;&lsquo;What's your name, Sir,&rsquo; says the lawyer.&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;Tony Weller,&rsquo; says my father.&mdash;&lsquo;Parish?&rsquo; says the lawyer.&mdash;&lsquo;Belle Savage,&rsquo; says my father; for he stopped there ven he drove up, and he know'd nothing about parishes, he didn't.&mdash;&lsquo;And what's the lady's name?&rsquo; says the lawyer. My father was struck all of a heap. &lsquo;Blessed if I know,&rsquo; says he.&mdash;&lsquo;Not know!&rsquo; says the lawyer.&mdash;&lsquo;No more nor you do,&rsquo; says my father, &lsquo;can't I put that in arterwards?&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;Impossible!&rsquo; says the lawyer.&mdash;&lsquo;Wery well,&rsquo; says my father, after he'd thought a moment, &lsquo;put down Mrs. Clarke.&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;What Clarke?&rsquo; says the lawyer, dipping his pen in the ink.&mdash;&lsquo;Susan Clarke, Markis o' Granby, Dorking,&rsquo; says my father; &lsquo;she'll have me, if I ask her, I des-say&mdash;I never said nothing to her, but she'll have me, I know.&rsquo; The licence was made out, and she <hi
rend="italics">did</hi> have him, and what's more she's got him now; and <hi
rend="italics">I</hi> never had any of the four hundred pound, worse luck. Beg your pardon, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam, when he had concluded, &ldquo;but vhen I gets on this here grievance, I runs on like a new barrow vith the vheel greased.&rdquo; Having said which, and having paused for an instant to see whether he was wanted for any thing more, Sam left the room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Half-past nine&mdash;just the time&mdash;off at once;&rdquo; said the gentleman, whom we need hardly introduce as Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Time&mdash;for what?&rdquo; said the spinster aunt, conquettishly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Licence, dearest of angels&mdash;give notice at the church&mdash;call you mine, to-morrow&rdquo;&mdash;said Mr. Jingle, and he squeezed the spinster aunt's hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The licence!&rdquo; said Rachael, blushing.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The licence,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Jingle&mdash;</p>
<q><p>&ldquo;In hurry, post-haste for a licence,</p><p>In hurry, ding dong I come back.&rdquo;</p></q>
<p>&ldquo;How you run on,&rdquo; said Rachael.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Run on&mdash;nothing to the hours, days, weeks, months, years, when we're united&mdash;<hi
rend="italics">run</hi> on&mdash;they'll fly on&mdash;bolt&mdash;mizzle&mdash;steam-engine&mdash;thousand-horse power&mdash;nothing to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Can't&mdash;can't we be married before to-morrow morning?&rdquo; inquired Rachael.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Impossible&mdash;can't be&mdash;notice at the church&mdash;leave the licence to-day&mdash;ceremony come off to-morrow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am so terrified, lest my brother should discover us!&rdquo; said Rachael.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Discover&mdash;nonsense&mdash;too much shaken by the break down&mdash;besides&mdash;extreme caution&mdash;gave up the post-chaise&mdash;walked on&mdash;took
<pb n="94" id="p94"/>
a hackney-coach&mdash;came to the Borough&mdash;last place in the world that he'd look in&mdash;ha! ha!&mdash;capital notion that&mdash;very.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't be long,&rdquo; said the spinster, affectionately, as Mr. Jingle stuck the pinched up hat on his head.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Long away from <hi rend="italics">you?</hi>&mdash;Cruel charmer,&rdquo; and Mr. Jingle skipped playfully up to the spinster aunt, imprinted a chaste kiss upon her lips, and danced out of the room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dear man!&rdquo; said the spinster, as the door closed after him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Rum old girl,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle, as he walked down the passage.</p>
<p>It is painful to reflect upon the perfidy of our species; and we will not therefore, pursue the thread of Mr. Jingle's meditations, as he wended his way to Doctors' Commons. It will be sufficient for our purpose to relate, that escaping the snares of the dragons in white aprons, who guard the entrance to that enchanted region, he reached the Vicar General's office in safety, and having procured a highly flattering address on parchment, from the Archbishop of Canterbury, to his &ldquo;trusty and well-beloved Alfred Jingle and Rachael Wardle, greeting,&rdquo; he carefully deposited the mystic document in his pocket, and retraced his steps in triumph to the Borough.</p>
<p>He was yet on his way to the White Hart, when two plump gentlemen and one thin one, entered the yard, and looked round in search of some authorised person of whom they could make a few inquiries. Mr. Samuel Weller happened to be at that moment engaged in burnishing a pair of painted tops, the personal property of a farmer, who was refreshing himself with a slight lunch of two or three pounds of cold beef and a pot or two of porter, after the fatigues of the Borough market; and to him the thin gentleman straightway advanced&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My friend,&rdquo; said the thin gentleman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You're one o' the adwice gratis order,&rdquo; thought Sam, &ldquo;or you wouldn't be so werry fond o' me all at once.&rdquo; But he only said&mdash;&ldquo;Well Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My friend,&rdquo; said the thin gentleman, with a conciliatory hem&mdash;&ldquo;Have you got many people stopping here, now? Pretty busy. Eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sam stole a look at the inquirer. He was a little high-dried man, with a dark squeezed up face, and small restless black eyes, that kept winking and twinkling on each side of his little inquisitive nose, as if they were playing a perpetual game of peep-bo with that feature. He was dressed all in black, with boots as shiny as his eyes, a low white neckcloth, and a clean shirt with a frill to it. A gold watch-chain, and seals, depended from his fob. He carried his black kid gloves <hi
rend="italics">in</hi> his hands, not <hi rend="italics">on</hi> them; and as he spoke, thrust his wrists beneath his coat-tails, with the air of a man who was in the habit of propounding some regular poser.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pretty busy, eh?&rdquo; said the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Oh, werry well, Sir,&rdquo; replied Sam, &ldquo;we shan't be bankrupts, and we shan't make our fort'ns. We eats our biled mutton without capers, and don't care for horse-radish ven ve can get beef.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah,&rdquo; said the little man, &ldquo;you're a wag, a'nt you?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="95" id="p95"/>
<p>&ldquo;My eldest brother was troubled with that complaint,&rdquo; said Sam &ldquo;it may be catching&mdash;I used to sleep with him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is a curious old house of yours,&rdquo; said the little man, looking round him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If you'd sent word you was a coming, we'd ha' had it repaired;&rdquo; replied the imperturbable Sam.</p>
<p>The little man seemed rather baffled by these several repulses, and a short consultation took place between him and the two plump gentlemen. At its conclusion, the little man took a pinch of snuff from an oblong silver box, and was apparently on the point of renewing the conversation, when one of the plump gentlemen, who in addition to a benevolent countenance, possessed a pair of spectacles, and a pair of black gaiters, interfered&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The fact of the matter is,&rdquo; said the benevolent gentleman, &ldquo;that my friend here (pointing to the other plump gentleman,) will give you half a guinea, if you'll answer one or two&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, my dear Sir&mdash;my dear Sir,&rdquo; said the little man, &ldquo;pray allow me&mdash;my dear Sir, the very first principle to be observed in these cases, is this; if you place a matter in the hands of a professional man, you must in no way interfere in the progress of the business; you must repose implicit confidence in him. Really, Mr. (he turned to the other plump gentleman, and said)&mdash;I forget your friend's name.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pickwick,&rdquo; said Mr. Wardle, for it was no other than that jolly personage.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah, Pickwick&mdash;really Mr. Pickwick, my dear Sir, excuse me&mdash;I shall be happy to receive any private suggestions of yours, as <hi
rend="italics">amicus curi&aelig;,</hi> but you must see the impropriety of your interfering with my conduct in this case, with such an <hi
rend="italics">ad captandum</hi> argument, as the offer of half a guinea. Really, my dear Sir, really,&rdquo; and the little man took an argumentative pinch of snuff, and looked very profound.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My only wish, Sir,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;was to bring this very unpleasant matter to as speedy a close as possible.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quite right&mdash;quite right,&rdquo; said the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;With which view,&rdquo; continued Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;I made use of the argument which my experience of men has taught me is the most likely to succeed in any case,&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay, ay,&rdquo; said the little man, &ldquo;very good, very good, indeed; but you should have suggested it to <hi
rend="italics">me.</hi> My dear Sir, I'm quite certain you cannot be ignorant of the extent of confidence which must be placed in professional men. If any authority can be necessary on such a point, my dear Sir, let me refer you to the well-known case in Barnwell and&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Never mind George Barnvell,&rdquo; interrupted Sam, who had remained a wondering listener during this short colloquy; &ldquo;every body knows vhat sort of a case his was, tho' it's always been my opinion, mind you, that the young 'ooman deserved scragging a precious sight more than he did. Hows'ever, that's neither here nor there. You want me to except of half a guinea. Werry well, I'm agreeable: I can't say no fairer than that, can I, Sir? (Mr. Pickwick smiled.) Then the next
<pb n="96" id="p96"/>
question is, what the devil do you want with me, as the man said ven he seed the ghost?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We want to know&rdquo;&mdash;said Mr. Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now my dear Sir&mdash;my dear Sir,&rdquo; interposed the busy little man.</p>
<p>Mr. Wardle shrugged his shoulders, and was silent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We want to know,&rdquo; said the little man, solemnly; &ldquo;and we ask the question of you, in order that we may not awaken apprehensions inside&mdash;we want to know who you've got in this house, at present.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who there is in the house!&rdquo; said Sam, in whose mind the inmates were always represented by that particular article of their costume, which came under his immediate superintendence. &ldquo;There's a vooden leg in number six, there's a pair of Hessians in thirteen, there's two pair of halves in the commercial, there's these here painted tops in the snuggery inside the bar, and five more tops in the coffee-room.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nothing more?&rdquo; said the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stop a bit,&rdquo; replied Sam, suddenly recollecting himself. &ldquo;Yes; there's a pair of Vellingtons a good deal vorn, and a pair o' lady's shoes, in number five.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What sort of shoes?&rdquo; hastily inquired Wardle, who, together with Mr. Pickwick, had been lost in bewilderment at the singular catalogue of visiters.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Country make,&rdquo; replied Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Any maker's name?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Brown.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where of?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Muggleton.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It <hi rend="italics">is</hi> them,&rdquo; exclaimed Wardle. &ldquo;By Heavens, we've found them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hush!&rdquo; said Sam. &ldquo;The Vellingtons has gone to Doctors' Commons.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, for a licence.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We're in time,&rdquo; exclaimed Wardle. &ldquo;Show us the room; not a moment is to be lost.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Pray, my dear Sir&mdash;pray,&rdquo; said the little man; &ldquo;caution, caution.&rdquo; He drew from his pocket a red silk purse, and looked very hard at Sam as he drew out a sovereign.</p>
<p>Sam grinned expressively.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Show us into the room at once, without announcing us,&rdquo; said the little man, &ldquo;and it's yours.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sam threw the painted tops into a corner, and led the way through a dark passage, and up a wide staircase. He paused at the end of a second passage, and held out his hand.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here it is,&rdquo; whispered the attorney as he deposited the money in the hand of their guide.</p>
<p>The man stepped forward for a few paces, followed by the two friends and their legal adviser. He stopped at a door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is this the room?&rdquo; murmured the little gentleman.</p>
<p>Sam nodded assent.</p>
<pb n="97" id="p97"/>
<p>Old Wardle opened the door; and the whole three walked into the room just as Mr. Jingle, who had that moment returned, had produced the licence to the spinster aunt.</p>
<p>The spinster uttered a loud shriek, and, throwing herself in a chair, covered her face with her hands. Mr. Jingle crumpled up the licence, and thrust it into his coat-pocket. The unwelcome visiters advanced into the middle of the room.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&mdash;you are a nice rascal, ar'n't you?&rdquo; exclaimed Wardle, breathless with passion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Sir, my dear Sir,&rdquo; said the little man, laying his hat on the table. &ldquo;Pray, consider&mdash;pray. <hi
rend="italics">Scandalum magnatum,</hi> defamation of character, action for damages. Calm yourself, my dear Sir, pray&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How dare you drag my sister from my house?&rdquo; said the old man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ay&mdash;ay&mdash;very good,&rdquo; said the little gentleman, &ldquo;you may ask that. How dare you, Sir?&mdash;eh, Sir?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who the devil are you?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Jingle, in so fierce a tone, that the little gentleman involuntarily fell back a step or two.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Who is he, you scoundrel,&rdquo; interposed Wardle. &ldquo;He's my lawyer, Mr. Perker, of Gray's inn. Perker, I'll have this fellow prosecuted&mdash;indicted&mdash;I'll&mdash;I'll&mdash;damme, I'll ruin him. And you,&rdquo; continued Mr. Wardle turning abruptly round to his sister, &ldquo;you Rachael, at a time of life when you ought to know better, what do <hi
rend="italics">you</hi> mean by running away with a vagabond, disgracing your family, and making yourself miserable. Get on your bonnet, and come back. Call a hackney-coach there, directly, and bring this lady's bill, d'ye hear&mdash;d'ye hear?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cert'nly, Sir,&rdquo; replied Sam, who had answered Wardle's violent ringing of the bell with a degree of celerity, which must have appeared marvellous to any body who didn't know that his eye had been applied to the outside of the key-hole during the whole interview.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Get on your bonnet,&rdquo; repeated Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do nothing of the kind,&rdquo; said Jingle. &ldquo;Leave the room, Sir&mdash;no business here&mdash;lady's free to act as she pleases&mdash;more than one-and-twenty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;More than one-and twenty!&rdquo; ejaculated Wardle, contemptuously. &ldquo;More than one-and-forty!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I a'nt,&rdquo; said the spinster aunt, her indignation getting the better of her determination to faint.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are,&rdquo; replied Wardle, &ldquo;you're fifty if you're an hour.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here the spinster aunt uttered a loud shriek, and became senseless.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A glass of water,&rdquo; said the humane Mr. Pickwick, summoning the landlady.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A <hi rend="italics">glass</hi> of water!&rdquo; said the passionate Wardle. &ldquo;Bring a bucket, and throw it all over her; it'll do her good, and she richly deserves it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ugh, you brute!&rdquo; ejaculated the kind-hearted landlady. &ldquo;Poor dear.&rdquo; And with sundry ejaculations, of &ldquo;Come now, there's a dear&mdash;drink a little of this&mdash;it'll do you good&mdash;don't give way so&mdash;there's a love,&rdquo; &amp;c. &amp;c. the landlady, assisted by a chambermaid, proceeded to vinegar the forehead, beat the hands, titillate the nose, and unlace the
<pb n="98" id="p98"/>
stays of the spinster aunt, and to administer such other restoratives as are usually applied by compassionate females to ladies who are endeavouring to ferment themselves into hysterics.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Coach is ready, Sir,&rdquo; said Sam, appearing at the door.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come along,&rdquo; cried Wardle. &ldquo;I'll carry her down stairs.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At this proposition, the hysterics came on with redoubled violence.</p>
<p>The landlady was about to enter a very violent protest against this proceeding, and had already given vent to an indignant inquiry whether Mr. Wardle considered himself a lord of the creation, when Mr, Jingle interposed&mdash;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boots,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;get me an officer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stay, stay,&rdquo; said little Mr. Perker. &ldquo;Consider, Sir, consider.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll <hi rend="italics">not</hi> consider,&rdquo; replied Jingle, &ldquo;she's her own mistress&mdash;see who dares to take her away&mdash;unless she wishes it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I <hi rend="italics">won't</hi> be taken away,&rdquo; murmured the spinster aunt. &ldquo;I <hi
rend="italics">don't</hi> wish it.&rdquo; (Here there was a frightful relapse.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Sir,&rdquo; said the little man, in a low tone, taking Mr. Wardle and Mr. Pickwick apart: &ldquo;My dear Sir, we're in a very awkward situation. It's a distressing case&mdash;very; I never knew one more so; but really, my dear Sir, really we have no power to controul this lady's actions. I warned you before we came, my dear Sir, that there was nothing to look to but a compromise.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a short pause.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What kind of compromise would you recommend?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, my dear Sir, our friend's in an unpleasant position&mdash;very much so. We must be content to suffer some pecuniary loss.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll suffer any, rather than submit to this disgrace, and let her, fool as she is, be made miserable for life,&rdquo; said Wardle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I rather think it can be done,&rdquo; said the bustling little man. &ldquo;Mr. Jingle, will you step with us into the next room for a moment?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Jingle assented, and the quartette walked into an empty apartment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now Sir,&rdquo; said the little man, as he carefully closed the door, &ldquo;is there no way of accommodating this matter&mdash;step this way Sir, for a moment&mdash;into this window, Sir, where we can be alone&mdash;there, Sir, there, pray sit down, Sir. Now, my dear Sir, between you and I, we know very well, my dear Sir, that you have run off with this lady for the sake of her money. Don't frown, Sir, don't frown; I say, between you and I, <hi
rend="italics">we</hi> know it. We are both men of the world, and <hi
rend="italics">we</hi> know very well that our friends here, are not&mdash;eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Jingle's face gradually relaxed; and something distantly resembling a wink, quivered for an instant in his left eye.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Very good, very good,&rdquo; said the little man, observing the impression he had made. &ldquo;Now the fact is, that beyond a few hundreds, the lady has little or nothing till the death of her mother&mdash;fine old lady, my dear Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italics">Old,</hi>&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle, briefly but emphatically.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why, yes,&rdquo; said the attorney, with a slight cough. &ldquo;You are
<pb n="99" id="p99"/>
right, my dear Sir, she is <hi rend="italics">rather</hi> old. She comes of an old family though, my dear Sir; old in every sense of the word. The founder of that family came into Kent, when Julius C&aelig;sar invaded Britain;&mdash;only one member of it, since, who hasn't lived to eighty-five, and <hi
rend="italics">he</hi> was beheaded by one of the Henrys. The old lady is not seventy-three now, my dear Sir.&rdquo; The little man paused, and took a pinch of snuff.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; cried Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my dear Sir&mdash;you don't take snuff?&mdash;ah! so much the better&mdash;expensive habit&mdash;well, my dear Sir, you're a fine young man, man of the world&mdash;able to push your fortune, if you had capital, eh?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you comprehend me?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not quite.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't you think&mdash;now, my dear Sir, I put it to you, <hi
rend="italics">don't</hi> you think&mdash;that fifty pounds and liberty, would be better than Miss Wardle and expectation?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't do&mdash;not half enough!&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle, rising.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nay, nay, my dear Sir,&rdquo; remonstrated the little attorney, seizing him by the button. &ldquo;Good round sum&mdash;a man like you could treble it in no time&mdash;great deal to be done with fifty pounds, my dear Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;More to be done with a hundred and fifty,&rdquo; replied Mr. Jingle, coolly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my dear Sir, we won't waste time in splitting straws,&rdquo; resumed the little man, &ldquo;say&mdash;say&mdash;seventy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't do,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Don't go away, my dear Sir&mdash;pray don't hurry,&rdquo; said the little man. &ldquo;Eighty; come: I'll write you a cheque at once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Won't do,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, my dear Sir, well,&rdquo; said the little man, still detaining him; &ldquo;just tell me what <hi
rend="italics">will</hi> do.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Expensive affair,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle. &ldquo;Money out of pocket&mdash;posting, nine pounds; licence, three&mdash;that's twelve&mdash;compensation, a hundred&mdash;hundred and twelve&mdash;Breach of honour&mdash;and loss of the lady&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, my dear Sir, yes,&rdquo; said the little man, with a knowing look, &ldquo;never mind the last two items. That's a hundred and twelve&mdash;say a hundred&mdash;come.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;And twenty,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Come, come, I'll write you a cheque,&rdquo; said the little man; and down he sat at the table for that purpose.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll make it payable the day after to-morrow,&rdquo; said the little man, with a look towards Mr. Wardle; &ldquo;and we can get the lady away, meanwhile.&rdquo; Mr. Wardle sullenly nodded assent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A hundred,&rdquo; said the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And twenty,&rdquo; said Mr. Jingle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Sir,&rdquo; remonstrated the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Give it him,&rdquo; interposed Mr. Wardle, &ldquo;and let him go.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The cheque was written by the little gentleman, and pocketed by Mr. Jingle.</p>
<pb n="100" id="p100"/>
<p>&ldquo;Now, leave this house instantly!&rdquo; said Wardle, starting up.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Sir,&rdquo; urged the little man.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And mind,&rdquo; said Mr. Wardle, &ldquo;that nothing should have induced me to make this compromise&mdash;not even a regard for my family&mdash;if I had not known, that the moment you got any money in that pocket of yours, you'd go to the devil faster, if possible, than you would without it&mdash;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My dear Sir,&rdquo; urged the little man again.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Be quiet, Perker,&rdquo; resumed Wardle. &ldquo;Leave the room, Sir.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Off directly,&rdquo; said the unabashed Jingle. &ldquo;Bye&mdash;bye&mdash;Pickwick.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If any dispassionate spectator could have beheld the countenance of the illustrious man, whose name forms the leading feature of the title of this work, during the latter part of this conversation, he would have been almost induced to wonder that the indignant fire which flashed from his eyes, did not melt the glasses of his spectacles&mdash;so majestic was his wrath. His nostrils dilated, and his fists clenched involuntarily, as he heard himself addressed by the villain. But he restrained himself again&mdash;he did <hi
rend="italics">not</hi> pulverise him.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Here,&rdquo; continued the hardened traitor, tossing the licence at Mr. Pickwick's feet; &ldquo;get the name altered&mdash;take home the lady&mdash;do for Tuppy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick was a philosopher, but philosophers are only men in armour, after all. The shaft had reached him, penetrated through his philosophical harness, to his very heart. In the frenzy of his rage, he hurled the inkstand madly forward, and followed it up himself. But Mr. Jingle had disappeared, and he found himself caught in the arms of Sam.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hallo,&rdquo; said that eccentric functionary, &ldquo;furniter's cheap vere you come from. Self-acting ink, that 'ere; it's wrote your mark upon the wall, old gen'lm'n. Hold still, Sir: wot's the use o' runnin' arter a man as has made his lucky, and got to t' other end of the Borough by this time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's mind, like those of all truly great men, was open to conviction. He was a quick, and powerful reasoner; and a moment's reflection sufficed to remind him of the impotency of his rage. It subsided as quickly as it had been roused. He panted for breath, and looked benignantly round upon his friends.</p>
<p>Shall we tell the lamentations that ensued, when Miss Wardle found herself deserted by the faithless Jingle? Shall we extract Mr. Pickwick's masterly description of that heart-rending scene? His notebook, blotted with the tears of sympathising humanity, lies open before us; one word, and it is in the printer's hands. But, no! we will be resolute! We will not wring the public bosom, with the delineation of such suffering!</p>
<p>Slowly and sadly did the two friends and the deserted lady return next day in the Muggleton heavy coach. Dimly and darkly had the sombre shadows of a summer's night fallen upon all around, when they again reached Dingley Dell, and stood within the entrance to Manor Farm.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter">
<pb n="101" id="p101"/>
<head>CHAPTER XI.</head>

<head>INVOLVING ANOTHER JOURNEY, AND AN ANTIQUARIAN DISCOVERY. RECORDING MR. PICKWICK'S DETERMINATION TO BE PRESENT AT AN ELECTION; AND CONTAINING A MANUSCRIPT OF THE OLD CLERGYMAN'S.</head>

<p>A NIGHT of quiet and repose in the profound silence of Dingley Dell, and an hour's breathing of its fresh and fragrant air on the ensuing morning, completely recovered Mr. Pickwick from the effects of his late fatigue of body and anxiety of mind. That illustrious man had been separated from his friends and followers, for two whole days; and it was with a degree of pleasure and delight, which no common imagination can adequately conceive, that he stepped forward to greet Mr. Winkle and Mr. Snodgrass, as he encountered those gentlemen on his return from his early walk. The pleasure was mutual; for who could ever gaze on Mr. Pickwick's beaming face without experiencing the sensation? But still a cloud seemed to hang over his companions which that great man could not but be sensible of, and was wholly at a loss to account for. There was a mysterious air about them both, as unusual as it was alarming.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And how,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, when he had grasped his followers by the hand, and exchanged warm salutations of welcome; &ldquo;how is Tupman?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Winkle, to whom the question was more peculiarly addressed, made no reply. He turned away his head, and appeared absorbed in melancholy reflection.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Snodgrass,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, earnestly, &ldquo;How is our friend&mdash;he is not ill?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; replied Mr. Snodgrass; and a tear trembled on his sentimental eye-lid, like a rain-drop on a window-frame. &ldquo;No; he is not ill.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick stopped, and gazed on each of his friends in turn.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Winkle&mdash;Snodgrass,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick: &ldquo;what does this mean? Where is our friend? What has happened? Speak&mdash;I conjure, I entreat&mdash;nay, I command you, speak.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There was a solemnity&mdash;a dignity&mdash;in Mr. Pickwick's manner, not to be withstood.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He is gone,&rdquo; said Mr. Snodgrass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gone!&rdquo; exclaimed Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;Gone!&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gone,&rdquo; repeated Mr. Snodgrass.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where?&rdquo; ejaculated Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We can only guess from that communication,&rdquo; replied Mr. Snodgrass, taking a letter from his pocket, and placing it in his friend's hand. &ldquo;Yesterday morning, when a letter was received from Mr. Wardle, stating that you would be home with his sister at night, the melancholy which had hung over our friend during the whole of the
<pb n="102" id="p102"/>
previous day, was observed to increase. He shortly afterwards disappeared: he was missing during the whole day, and in the evening this letter was brought by the hostler from the Crown, at Muggleton. It had been left in his charge in the morning, with a strict injunction that it should not be delivered until night.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick opened the epistle. It was in his friend's hand-writing, and these were its contents:</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="letter">
<opener>
<salute>&ldquo;My dear Pickwick,</salute>
</opener>
<p>&ldquo;You, my dear friend, are placed far beyond the reach of many mortal frailties and weaknesses which ordinary people cannot overcome. You do not know what it is, at one blow, to be deserted by a lovely and fascinating creature, and to fall a victim to the artifices of a villain, who hid the grin of cunning, beneath the mask of friendship. I hope you never may.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Any letter, addressed to me at the Leather Bottle, Cobham, Kent, will be forwarded&mdash;supposing I still exist. I hasten from the sight of that world, which has become odious to me. Should I hasten from it altogether, pity&mdash;forgive me. Life, my dear Pickwick, has become insupportable to me. The spirit which burns within us, is a porter's knot, on which to rest the heavy load of worldly cares and troubles; and when that spirit fails us, the burden is too heavy to be borne. We sink beneath it. You may tell Rachael&mdash;Ah, that name!&mdash;</p>
<closer>
<signed>&ldquo;TRACY TUPMAN.&rdquo;</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</q>
<p>&ldquo;We must leave this place, directly,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, as he refolded the note. &ldquo;It would not have been decent for us to remain here, under any circumstances, after what has happened; and now we are bound to follow in search of our friend.&rdquo; And so saying, he led the way to the house.</p>
<p>His intention was rapidly communicated. The entreaties to remain were pressing, but Mr. Pickwick was inflexible. Business, he said, required his immediate attendance.</p>
<p>The old clergyman was present.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You are not really going?&rdquo; said he, taking Mr. Pickwick aside.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick reiterated his former determination.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Then here,&rdquo; said the old gentleman, &ldquo;is a little manuscript, which I had hoped to have the pleasure of reading to you myself. I found it on the death of a friend of mine&mdash;a medical man, engaged in our County Lunatic Asylum&mdash;among a variety of papers, which I had the option of destroying or preserving, as I thought proper. I can hardly believe that the manuscript is genuine, though it certainly is not in my friend's hand. However, whether it be the genuine production of a maniac, or founded upon the ravings of some unhappy being, which I think more probable, read it, and judge for yourself.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick received the manuscript, and parted from the benevolent old gentleman with many expressions of good-will and esteem.</p>
<p>It was a more difficult task to take leave of the inmates of Manor Farm, from whom they had received so much hospitality and kindness.
<pb n="103" id="p103"/>
Mr. Pickwick kissed the young ladies&mdash;we were going to say, as if they were his own daughters, only as he might possibly have infused a little more warmth into the salutation, the comparison would not be quite appropriate&mdash;hugged the old lady with filial cordiality: and patted the rosy cheeks of the female servants in a most patriarchal manner, as he slipped into the hands of each, some more substantial expressions of his approval. The exchange of cordialities with their fine old host and Mr. Trundle, were even more hearty and prolonged; and it was not until Mr. Snodgrass had been several times called for, and at last emerged from a dark passage followed soon after by Emily (whose bright eyes looked unusually dim) that the three friends were enabled to tear themselves from their friendly entertainers. Many a backward look they gave at the Farm, as they walked slowly away: and many a kiss did Mr. Snodgrass waft in the air, in acknowledgment of something very like a lady's handkerchief, which was waved from one of the upper windows, until a turn of the lane hid the old house from their sight.</p>
<p>At Muggleton they procured a conveyance to Rochester. By the time they reached the last-named place, the violence of their grief had sufficiently abated to admit of their making a very excellent early dinner; and having procured the necessary information relative to the road, the three friends set forward again in the afternoon to walk to Cobham.</p>
<p>A delightful walk it was: for it was a pleasant afternoon in June, and their way lay through a deep and shady wood, cooled by the light wind which gently rustled the thick foliage, and enlivened by the songs of the birds that perched upon the boughs. The ivy and the moss crept in thick clusters over the old trees, and the soft green turf overspread the ground like a silken mat. They emerged upon an open park, with an ancient hall, displaying the quaint and picturesque architecture of Elizabeth's time. Long vistas of stately oaks and elm trees appeared on every side: large herds of deer were cropping the fresh grass; and occasionally a startled hare scoured along the ground, with the speed of the shadows thrown by the light clouds which sweep across a sunny landscape like a passing breath of summer.</p>
<p>&ldquo;If this,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, looking about him; &ldquo;if this were the place to which all who are troubled with our friend's complaint came, I fancy their old attachment to this world would very soon return.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&lsquo;I think so too,&rdquo; said Mr. Winkle.</p>
<p>&ldquo;And really,&rdquo; added Mr. Pickwick, after half an hour's walking had brought them to the village, &ldquo;really for a misanthrope's choice, this is one of the prettiest and most desirable places of residence, I ever met with.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In this opinion also, both Mr. Winkle and Mr. Snodgrass expressed their concurrence; and having been directed to the Leather Bottle, a clean and commodious village ale-house, the three travellers entered, and at once inquired for a gentleman of the name of Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Show the gentlemen into the parlour, Tom,&rdquo; said the landlady.</p>
<p>A stout country lad opened a door at the end of the passage, and the three friends entered a long, low-roofed room, furnished with a large number of high-backed leather-cushioned chairs, of fantastic shapes,
<pb n="104" id="p104"/>
and embellished with a great variety of old portraits and roughly-coloured prints of some antiquity. At the upper end of the room was a table, with a white cloth upon it, well covered with a roast fowl, bacon, ale, and et ceteras; and at the table sat Mr. Tupman, looking as unlike a man who had taken his leave of the world, as possible.</p>
<p>On the entrance of his friends, that gentleman laid down his knife and fork, and with a mournful air advanced to meet them.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I did not expect to see you here,&rdquo; he said, as he grasped Mr. Pickwick's hand. &ldquo;It's very kind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, sitting down, and wiping from his forehead the perspiration which the walk had engendered. &ldquo;Finish your dinner, and walk out with me. I wish to speak to you alone.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Tupman did as he was desired; and Mr. Pickwick having refreshed himself with a copious draught of ale, waited his friend's leisure. The dinner was quickly despatched, and they walked out together.</p>
<p>For half an hour, their forms might have been seen pacing the churchyard to and fro, while Mr. Pickwick was engaged in combatting his companion's resolution. Any repetition of his arguments would be useless; for what language could convey to them that energy and force which their great originator's manner communicated? Whether Mr. Tupman was already tired of retirement, or whether he was wholly unable to resist the eloquent appeal which was made to him, matters not, he did <hi
rend="italics">not</hi> resist it at last.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It mattered little to him,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;where he dragged out the miserable remainder of his days: and since his friend laid so much stress upon his humble companionship, he was willing to share his adventures.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick smiled; they shook hands; and walked back to re-join their companions.</p>
<p>It was at this moment that Mr. Pickwick made that immortal discovery, which has been the pride and boast of his friends, and the envy of every antiquarian in this or any other country. They had passed the door of their inn, and walked a little way down the village, before they recollected the precise spot in which it stood. As they turned back, Mr. Pickwick's eye fell upon a small broken stone, partially buried in the ground, in front of a cottage-door. He paused.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is very strange,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is strange?&rdquo; inquired Mr. Tupman, staring eagerly at every object near him, but the right one. &ldquo;God bless me, what's the matter?&rdquo;</p>
<p>This last was an ejaculation of irrepressible astonishment, occasioned by seeing Mr. Pickwick, in his enthusiasm for discovery, fall on his knees before the little stone, and commence wiping the dust off it with his pocket-handkerchief.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is an inscription here,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Is it possible!&rdquo; said Mr. Tupman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can discern,&rdquo; continued Mr. Pickwick, rubbing away with all his might, and gazing intently through his spectacles: &ldquo;I can discern a cross, and a B, and then a T. This is important,&rdquo; continued Mr. Pickwick, starting up. &ldquo;This is some very old inscription, existing perhaps
<pb n="105" id="p105"/>
long before the ancient alms-houses in this place. It must not be lost.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He tapped at the cottage-door. A labouring man opened it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know how this stone came here, my friend?&rdquo; inquired the benevolent Mr. Pickwick.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, I doan't, Sir,&rdquo; replied the man, civilly. &ldquo;It was here long afore I war born, or any on us.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick glanced triumphantly at his companion.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&mdash;you&mdash;are not particularly attached to it, I dare say,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, trembling with anxiety. &ldquo;You wouldn't mind selling it, now?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Ah! but who'd buy it?&rdquo; inquired the man, with an expression of face which he probably meant to be very cunning.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'll give you ten shillings for it, at once,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick, &ldquo;if you would take it up for me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The astonishment of the village may be easily imagined, when (the little stone having been raised with one wrench of a spade), Mr. Pickwick, by dint of great personal exertion, bore it with his own hands to the inn, and after having carefully washed it, deposited it on the table.</p>
<p>The exultation and joy of the Pickwickians knew no bounds, when their patience and assiduity, their washing and scraping, were crowned with success. The stone was uneven and broken, and the letters were straggling and irregular, but the following fragment of an inscription was clearly to be deciphered:</p>
<p> BILST <lb/> UM <lb/> PSHI <lb/> S. M. <lb/> ARK</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's eyes sparkled with delight, as he sat and gloated over the treasure he had discovered. He had attained one of the greatest objects of his ambition. In a county known to abound in remains of the early ages; in a village in which there still existed some memorials of the olden time, he&mdash;he, the Chairman of the Pickwick Club&mdash;had discovered a strange and curious inscription of unquestionable antiquity, which had wholly escaped the observation of the many learned men who had preceded him. He could hardly trust the evidence of his senses.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This&mdash;this,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;determines me. We return to town, to-morrow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To-morrow!&rdquo; exclaimed his admiring followers</p>
<p>&ldquo;To-morrow,&rdquo; said Mr. Pickwick. &ldquo;This treasure must be at once deposited where it can be thoroughly investigated, and properly understood. I have another reason for this step. In a few days, an election is to take place for the borough of Eatanswill, at which Mr. Perker, a gentleman whom I lately met, is the agent of one of the candidates.
<pb n="106" id="p106"/>
We will behold, and minutely examine, a scene so interesting to every Englishman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We will,&rdquo; was the animated cry of three voices.</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick looked round him. The attachment and fervour of his followers, lighted up a glow of enthusiasm within him. He was their leader, and he felt it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let us celebrate this happy meeting, with a convivial glass,&rdquo; said he. This proposition, like the other, was received with unanimous applause. And having himself deposited the important stone in a small deal box, purchased from the landlady for the purpose, he placed himself in an arm-chair at the head of the table; and the evening was devoted to festivity and conversation.</p>
<p>It was past eleven o'clock&mdash;a late hour for the little village of Cobham&mdash;when Mr. Pickwick retired to the bed-room which had been prepared for his reception. He threw open the lattice-window, and setting his light upon the table, fell into a train of meditation on the hurried events of the two preceding days.</p>
<p>The hour and the place were both favourable to contemplation; Mr. Pickwick was roused, by the church-clock striking twelve. The first stroke of the hour sounded solemnly in his ear, but when the bell ceased the stillness seemed insupportable;&mdash;he almost felt as if he had lost a companion. He was nervous and excited; and hastily undressing himself and placing his light in the chimney, got into bed.</p>
<p>Every one has experienced that disagreeable state of mind, in which a sensation of bodily weariness in vain contends against an inability to sleep. It was Mr. Pickwick's condition at this moment: he tossed first on one side and then on the other; and perseveringly closed his eyes as if to coax himself to slumber. It was of no use. Whether it was the unwonted exertion he had undergone, or the heat, or the brandy and water, or the strange bed&mdash;whatever it was, his thoughts kept reverting very uncomfortably to the grim pictures down stairs, and the old stories to which they had given rise in the course of the evening. After half an hour's tumbling about, he came to the unsatisfactory conclusion, that it was of no use trying to sleep; so he got up and partially dressed himself. Anything, he thought, was better than lying there fancying all kinds of horrors. He looked out of the window&mdash;it was very dark. He walked about the room&mdash;it was very lonely.</p>
<p>He had taken a few turns from the door to the window, and from the window to the door, when the clergyman's manuscript for the first time entered his head. It was a good thought. If it failed to interest him, it might send him to sleep. He took it from his coat-pocket, and drawing a small table towards his bed-side, trimmed the light, put on his spectacles, and composed himself to read. It was a strange handwriting, and the paper was much soiled and blotted. The title gave him a sudden start, too; and he could not avoid casting a wistful glance round the room. Reflecting on the absurdity of giving way to such feelings, however, he trimmed the light again, and read as follows:</p>
<q>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="quote">
<pb n="107" id="p107"/>
<head>A MADMAN'S MANUSCRIPT.</head>
<p>&ldquo;Yes!&mdash;a madman's! How that word would have struck to my heart, many years ago! How it would have roused the terror that used to come upon me sometimes; sending the blood hissing and tingling through my veins, 'till the cold dew of fear stood in large drops upon my skin, and my knees knocked together with fright! I like it now though. It's a fine name. Shew me the monarch whose angry frown was ever feared like the glare of a madman's eye&mdash;whose cord and axe, were ever half so sure as a madman's gripe. Ho! ho! It's a grand thing to be mad! to be peeped at like a wild lion through the iron bars&mdash;to gnash one's teeth and howl, through the long still night, to the merry ring of a heavy chain&mdash;and to roll and twine among the straw, transported with such brave music. Hurrah for the madhouse! Oh it's a rare place!</p>
<p>&ldquo;I remember days when I was <hi rend="italics">afraid</hi> of being mad; when I used to start from my sleep, and fall upon my knees, and pray to be spared from the curse of my race; when I rushed from the sight of merriment or happiness, to hide myself in some lonely place, and spend the weary hours in watching the progress of the fever that was to consume my brain. I knew that madness was mixed up with my very blood, and the marrow of my bones; that one generation had passed away without the pestilence appearing among them, and that I was the first in whom it would revive. I knew it <hi
rend="italics">must</hi> be so: that so it always had been, and so it ever would be; and when I cowered in some obscure corner of a crowded room, and saw men whisper, and point, and turn their eyes towards me, I knew they were telling each other of the doomed madman; and I slunk away again to mope in solitude.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I did this for years; long, long years they were. The nights here are long sometimes&mdash;very long; but they are nothing to the restless nights, and dreadful dreams I had at that time. It makes me cold to remember them. Large dusky forms with sly and jeering faces crouched in the corners of the room, and bent over my bed at night, tempting me to madness. They told me in low whispers, that the floor of the old house in which my father's father died, was stained with his own blood, shed by his own hand in raging madness. I drove my fingers into my ears, but they screamed into my head till the room rang with it, that in one generation before him the madness slumbered, but that his grandfather had lived for years with his hands fettered to the ground, to prevent his tearing himself to pieces. I knew they told the truth&mdash;I knew it well. I had found it out years before, though they had tried to keep it from me. Ha! ha! I was too cunning for them, madman as they thought me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;At last it came upon me, and I wondered how I could ever have feared it. I could go into the world now, and laugh and shout with the best among them. I knew I was mad, but they did not even suspect it. How I used to hug myself with delight, when I thought of the fine trick I was playing them after their old pointing and leering, when
<pb n="108" id="p108"/>
I was not mad, but only dreading that I might one day become so! And how I used to laugh for joy, when I was alone, and thought how well I kept my secret, and how quickly my kind friends would have fallen from me, if they had known the truth. I could have screamed with ecstacy when I dined alone with some fine roaring fellow, to think how pale he would have turned, and how fast he would have run, if he had known that the dear friend who sat close to him, sharpening a bright glittering knife, was a madman with all the power, and half the will, to plunge it in his heart. Oh, it was a merry life!</p>
<p>&ldquo;Riches became mine, wealth poured in upon me, and I rioted in pleasures enhanced a thousand fold to me by the consciousness of my well-kept secret. I inherited an estate. The law&mdash;the eagle-eyed law itself, had been deceived, and had handed over disputed thousands to a madman's hands. Where was the wit of the sharp-sighted men of sound mind? Where the dexterity of the lawyers, eager to discover a flaw? The madman's cunning had over-reached them all.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I had money. How I was courted! I spent it profusely. How I was praised! How those three proud overbearing brothers humbled themselves before me! The old white-headed father, too&mdash;such deference&mdash;such respect&mdash;such devoted friendship&mdash;why he worshipped me. The old man had a daughter, and the young men a sister; and all the five were poor. I was rich; and when I married the girl, I saw a smile of triumph play upon the faces of her needy relatives, as they thought of their well-planned scheme, and their fine prize. It was for me to smile. To smile! To laugh outright, and tear my hair, and roll upon the ground with shrieks of merriment. They little thought they had married her to a madman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stay. If they had known it, would they have saved her? A sister's happiness against her husband's gold. The lightest feather I blow into the air, against the gay chain that ornaments my body!</p>
<p>&ldquo;In one thing I was deceived with all my cunning. If I had not been mad&mdash;for though we madmen are sharp-witted enough, we get bewildered sometimes&mdash;I should have known that the girl would rather have been placed, stiff and cold in a dull leaden coffin, than borne an envied bride to my rich, glittering, house. I should have known that her heart was with the dark-eyed boy whose name I once heard her breathe in her troubled sleep; and that she had been sacrificed to me, to relieve the poverty of the old white-headed man, and the haughty brothers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I don't remember forms or faces now, but I know the girl was beautiful. I <hi
rend="italics">know</hi> she was; for in the bright moonlight nights, when I start up from my sleep, and all is quiet about me, I see, standing still and motionless in one corner of this cell, a slight and wasted figure with long black hair, which streaming down her back, stirs with no earthly wind, and eyes that fix their gaze on me, and never wink or close. Hush! the blood chills at my heart as I write it down&mdash;that form is <hi
rend="italics">her's;</hi> the face is very pale, and the eyes are glassy bright; but I know them well. That figure never moves; it never frowns and mouths as others do, that fill this place sometimes; but it is much more dreadful
<pb n="109" id="p109"/>
to me, even than the spirits that tempted me many years ago&mdash;it comes fresh from the grave; and is so very death-like.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For nearly a year I saw that face grow paler; for nearly a year, I saw the tears steal down the mournful cheeks, and never knew the cause. I found it out at last though. They could not keep it from me long. She had never liked me; I had never thought she did: she despised my wealth, and hated the splendour in which she lived;&mdash;I had not expected that. She loved another. This I had never thought of. Strange feelings came over me, and thoughts forced upon me by some secret power, whirled round and round my brain. I did not hate her, though I hated the boy she still wept for. I pitied&mdash;yes, I pitied&mdash;the wretched life to which her cold and selfish relations had doomed her. I knew that she could not live long, but the thought that before her death she might give birth to some ill-fated being, destined to hand down madness to its offspring, determined me. I resolved to kill her.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For many weeks I thought of poison, and then of drowning, and then of fire. A fine sight the grand house in flames, and the madman's wife smouldering away to cinders. Think of the jest of a large reward, too, and of some sane man swinging in the wind for a deed he never did, and all through a madman's cunning! I thought often of this, but I gave it up at last. Oh! the pleasure of stropping the razor day after day, feeling the sharp edge, and thinking of the gash one stroke of its thin bright point would make!</p>
<p>&ldquo;At last the old spirits who had been with me so often before, whispered in my ear that the time was come, and thrust the open razor into my hand. I grasped it firmly, rose softly from the bed, and leaned over my sleeping wife. Her face was buried in her hands. I withdrew them softly, and they fell listlessly on her bosom. She had been weeping; for the traces of the tears were still wet upon her cheek. Her face was calm and placid; and even as I looked upon it, a tranquil smile lighted up her pale features. I laid my hand softly on her shoulder. She started&mdash;it was only a passing dream. I leant forward again. She screamed, and woke.</p>
<p>&ldquo;One motion of my hand, and she would never again have uttered cry or sound. But I was startled, and drew back. Her eyes were fixed on mine. I know not how it was, but they cowed and frightened me; and I quailed beneath them. She rose from the bed, still gazing fixedly and steadily on me. I trembled; the razor was in my hand, but I could not move. She made towards the door. As she neared it, she turned, and withdrew her eyes from my face. The spell was broken. I bounded forward, and clutched her by the arm. Uttering shriek upon shriek, she sunk upon the ground.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now I could have killed her without a struggle; but the house was alarmed. I heard the tread of footsteps on the stairs. I replaced the razor in its usual drawer, unfastened the door, and called loudly for assistance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;They came, and raised her, and placed her on the bed. She lay bereft of animation for hours; and when life, look, and speech returned, her senses had deserted her, and she raved wildly and furiously.</p>
<pb n="110" id="p110"/>
<p>&ldquo;Doctors were called in&mdash;great men who rolled up to my door in easy carriages, with fine horses and gaudy servants. They were at her bedside for weeks. They had a great meeting, and consulted together in low and solemn voices in another room. One, the cleverest and most celebrated among them, took me aside, and bidding me prepare for the worst, told me&mdash;me, the madman!&mdash;that my wife was mad. He stood close beside me at an open window, his eyes looking in my face, and his hand laid upon my arm. With one effort, I could have hurled him into the street beneath. It would have been rare sport to have done it; but my secret was at stake, and I let him go. A few days after, they told me I must place her under some restraint: I must provide a keeper for her. <hi
rend="italics">I!</hi> I went into the open fields where none could hear me, and laughed till the air resounded with my shouts!</p>
<p>&ldquo;She died next day. The white-headed old man followed her to the grave, and the proud brothers dropped a tear over the insensible corpse of her, whose sufferings they had regarded in her life-time with muscles of iron. All this was food for my secret mirth, and I laughed behind the white handkerchief which I held up to my face, as we rode home, 'till the tears came into my eyes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;But though I had carried my object and killed her, I was restless and disturbed, and I felt that before long, my secret must be known. I could not hide the wild mirth and joy which boiled within me, and made me when I was alone, at home, jump up and beat my hands together, and dance round and round, and roar aloud. When I went out, and saw the busy crowds hurrying about the streets: or to the theatre, and heard the sound of music, and beheld the people dancing, I felt such glee, that I could have rushed among them, and torn them to pieces limb from limb, and howled in transport. But I ground my teeth, and struck my feet upon the floor, and drove my sharp nails into my hands. I kept it down; and no one knew I was a madman yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I remember&mdash;though it's one of the last things I <hi
rend="italics">can</hi> remember: for now I mix realities with my dreams, and having so much to do, and being always hurried here, have no time to separate the two, from some strange confusion in which they get involved&mdash;I remember how I let it out at last. Ha! ha! I think I see their frightened looks now, and feel the ease with which I flung them from me, and dashed my clenched fist into their white faces, and then flew like the wind, and left them screaming and shouting far behind. The strength of a giant comes upon me when I think of it. There&mdash;see how this iron bar bends beneath my furious wrench. I could snap it like a twig, only there are long galleries here with many doors&mdash;I don't think I could find my way along them: and even if I could, I know there are iron gates below which they keep locked and barred. They know what a clever madman I have been, and they are proud to have me here, to show.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Let me see;&mdash;yes, I had been out. It was late at night when I reached home, and found the proudest of the three proud brothers, waiting to see me&mdash;urgent business he said: I recollect it well. I hated that man with all a madman's hate. Many and many a time had my fingers longed to tear him. They told me he was there. I ran swiftly
<pb n="111" id="p111"/>
up stairs. He had a word to say to me. I dismissed the servants. It was late, and we were alone together&mdash;<hi
rend="italics">for the first time.</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;I kept my eyes carefully from him at first, for I knew what he little thought&mdash;and I gloried in the knowledge&mdash;that the light of madness gleamed from them like fire. We sat in silence for a few minutes. He spoke at last. My recent dissipation, and strange remarks, made so soon after his sister's death, were an insult to her memory. Coupling together many circumstances which had at first escaped his observation, he thought I had not treated her well. He wished to know whether he was right in inferring that I meant to cast a reproach upon her memory, and a disrespect upon her family. It was due to the uniform he wore, to demand this explanation.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This man had a commission in the army&mdash;a commission, purchased with my money, and his sister's misery. This was the man who had been foremost in the plot to ensnare me, and grasp my wealth. This was the man who had been the main instrument in forcing his sister to wed me; well knowing that her heart was given to that puling boy. Due! Due to <hi
rend="italics">his</hi> uniform! The livery of his degradation! I turned my eyes upon him&mdash;I could not help it&mdash;but I spoke not a word.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I saw the sudden change that came upon him, beneath my gaze. He was a bold man, but the colour faded from his face, and he drew back his chair. I dragged mine nearer to him; and as I laughed&mdash;I was very merry then&mdash;I saw him shudder. I felt the madness rising within me. He was afraid of me.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;You were very fond of your sister when she was alive&rsquo;&mdash;I said&mdash;&lsquo;Very.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He looked uneasily round him, and I saw his hand grasp the back of his chair: but he said nothing.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;You villain,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;I found you out; I discovered your hellish plots against me; I know her heart was fixed on some one else before you compelled her to marry me. I know it&mdash;I know it.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;He jumped suddenly from his chair, brandished it aloft, and bid me stand back&mdash;for I took care to be getting closer to him, all the time I spoke.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I screamed rather than talked, for I felt tumultuous passions eddying through my veins, and the old spirits whispering and taunting me to tear his heart out.</p>
<p>&ldquo; &lsquo;Damn you,&rsquo; said I, starting up, and rushing upon him; &lsquo;I killed her. I am a madman. Down with you. Blood, blood, I will have it.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I turned aside with one blow, the chair he hurled at me in his terror, and closed with him; and with a heavy crash, we rolled upon the floor together.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was a fine struggle that, for he was a tall strong man, fighting for his life; and I, a powerful madman, thirsting to destroy him. I knew no strength could equal mine, and I was right. Right, again, though a madman! His struggles grew fainter. I knelt upon his chest, and clasped his brawny throat, firmly with both hands. His face grew purple; his eyes were starting from his head, and with protruded tongue, he seemed to mock me. I squeezed the tighter.</p>
<pb n="112" id="p112"/>
<p>&ldquo;The door was suddenly burst open with a loud noise, and a crowd of people rushed forward, crying aloud to each other, to secure the madman.</p>
<p>&ldquo;My secret was out; and my only struggle now, was for liberty and freedom. I gained my feet before a hand was on me, threw myself among my assailants, and cleared my way with my strong arm as if I bore a hatchet in my hand, and hewed them down before me. I gained the door, dropped over the banisters, and in an instant was in the street.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Straight and swift I ran, and no one dared to stop me. I heard the noise of feet behind, and redoubled my speed. It grew fainter and fainter in the distance, and at length died away altogether: but on I bounded, through marsh and rivulet, over fence and wall, with a wild shout which was taken up by the strange beings that flocked around me on every side, and swelled the sound, till it pierced the air. I was borne upon the arms of demons who swept along upon the wind, and bore down bank and hedge before them, and spun me round and round with a rustle and a speed that made my head swim, until at last they threw me from them with a violent shock, and I fell heavily upon the earth. When I woke I found myself here&mdash;here in this gay cell where the sun-light seldom comes, and the moon steals in, in rays which only serve to show the dark shadows about me, and that silent figure in its old corner. When I lie awake, I can sometimes hear strange shrieks and cries from distant parts of this large place. What they are, I know not; but they neither come from that pale form, nor does it regard them. For from the first shades of dusk 'till the earliest light of morning, it still stands motionless in the same place, listening to the music of my iron chain, and watching my gambols on my straw bed.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</q>
<p>At the end of the manuscript, was written, in another hand, this note:&mdash;</p>
<p>[The unhappy man whose ravings are recorded above, was a melancholy instance of the baneful results of energies misdirected in early life, and excesses prolonged until their consequences could never be repaired. The thoughtless riot, dissipation, and debauchery of his younger days, produced fever and delirium. The first effects of the latter, was the strange delusion, founded upon a well-known medical theory, strongly contended for by some, and as strongly contested by others, that an hereditary madness existed in his family. This produced a settled gloom, which in time developed a morbid insanity, and finally terminated in raving madness. There is every reason to believe that the events he detailed, though distorted in the description by his diseased imagination, really happened. It is only matter of wonder to those who were acquainted with the vices of his early career, that his passions, when no longer controulled by reason did not lead him to the commission of still more frightful deeds.]</p>
<p>Mr. Pickwick's candle was just expiring in the socket, as he concluded the perusal of the old clergyman's manuscript; and when the light went suddenly out, without any previous flicker by way of warning,
<pb n="113" id="p113"/>
it communicated a very considerable start to his excited frame. Hastily throwing off such articles of clothing as he had put on when he rose from his uneasy bed, and casting a fearful glance around, he once more scrambled hastily between the sheets, and soon fell fast asleep.</p>
<p>The sun was shining brilliantly into his chamber when he awoke, and the morning was far advanced. The gloom which had oppressed him on the previous night, had disappeared with the dark shadows which shrouded the landscape, and his thoughts and feelings were as light and gay as the morning itself. After a hearty breakfast, the four gentlemen sallied forth to walk to Gravesend, followed by a man bearing the stone in its deal box. They reached that town about one o'clock, (their luggage they had directed to be forwarded to the City, from Rochester,) and being fortunate enough to secure places on the outside of a coach, arrived in London in sound health and spirits, on that same afternoon.</p>
<p>The next three or four days were occupied with the preparations which were necessary for their journey to the borough of Eatanswill. As any reference to that most important undertaking demands a separate chapter, we may devote the few lines which remain at the close of this, to narrate, with great brevity, the history of the antiquarian discovery.</p>
<p>It appears from the Transactions of the Club, then, that Mr. Pickwick lectured upon the discovery at a General Club Meeting, convened on the night succeeding their return, and entered into a variety of ingenious and erudite speculations on the meaning of the inscription. It also appears that a skilful artist executed a faithful delineation of the curiosity, which was engraven on stone, and presented to the Royal Antiquarian Society, and other learned bodies&mdash;that heart-burnings and jealousies without number, were created by rival controversies which were penned upon the subject&mdash;and that Mr. Pickwick himself wrote a Pamphlet, containing ninety-six pages of very small print, and twenty-seven different readings of the inscription. That three old gentlemen cut off their eldest sons with a shilling a-piece for presuming to doubt the antiquity of the fragment&mdash;and that one enthusiastic individual cut himself off prematurely, in despair at being unable to fathom its meaning. That Mr. Pickwick was elected an honorary member of seventeen native and foreign societies, for making the discovery; that none of the seventeen could make anything of it, but that all the seventeen agreed it was very extraordinary.</p>
<p>Mr. Blotton, indeed&mdash;and the name will be doomed to the undying contempt of those who cultivate the mysterious and the sublime&mdash;Mr. Blotton, we say, with the doubt and cavilling peculiar to vulgar minds, presumed to state a view of the case, as degrading as ridiculous. Mr. Blotton, with a mean desire to tarnish the lustre of the immortal name of Pickwick, actually undertook a journey to Cobham in person, and on his return, sarcastically observed in an oration at the club, that he had seen the man from whom the stone was purchased; that the man presumed the stone to be ancient, but solemnly denied the antiquity of the inscription&mdash;inasmuch as he represented it to have been rudely
<pb n="114" id="p114"/>
carved by himself in an idle mood, and to display letters intended to bear neither more nor less than the simple construction of&mdash;&ldquo;Bill Stumps, his mark:&rdquo; and that Mr. Stumps, being little in the habit of original composition, and more accustomed to be guided by the sound of words than by the strict rules of orthography, had omitted the concluding &ldquo;L&rdquo; of his christian name.</p>
<p>The Pickwick Club, as might have been expected from so enlightened an Institution, received this statement with the contempt it deserved, expelled the presumptuous and ill-conditioned Blotton from the society, and voted Mr. Pickwick a pair of gold spectacles, in token of their confidence and approbation; in return for which Mr. Pickwick caused a portrait of himself to be painted, and hung up in the club-room&mdash;which portrait, by the by, he did <hi
rend="italics">not</hi> wish to have destroyed when he grew a few years older.</p>
<p>Mr. Blotton was ejected but not conquered. He also wrote a pamphlet, addressed to the seventeen learned societies, containing a repetition of the statement he had already made, and rather more than half intimating his opinion that the seventeen learned societies aforesaid, were so many &ldquo;humbugs.&rdquo; Hereupon the virtuous indignation of the seventeen learned societies being roused, several fresh pamphlets appeared; the foreign learned societies corresponded with the native learned societies, the native learned societies translated the pamphlets of the foreign learned societies into English, the foreign learned societies translated the pamphlets of the native learned societies into all sorts of languages: and thus commenced that celebrated scientific discussion so well known to all men, as the Pickwick controversy.</p>
<p>But this base attempt to injure Mr. Pickwick, recoiled upon the head of its calumnious author. The seventeen learned societies unanimously voted the presumptuous Blotton an ignorant meddler; and forthwith set to work upon more treatises than ever. And to this day the stone remains an illegible monument of Mr. Pickwick's greatness, and a lasting trophy of the littleness of his enemies.</p>
</div2>
</div1></body>
<back>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<pb n="115" id="p115"/>
<head>CHEAP AND ENTERTAINING PERIODICAL.</head>
<p>THIS DAY IS PUBLISHED, <lb/> PRICE 8<hi rend="italics">s.</hi></p>
<p>CONTAINING FOUR HUNDRED PAGES OF LETTER-PRESS, AND <lb/> FOURTEEN ILLUSTRATIONS, <lb/> THE FIRST VOLUME OF <lb/> THE LIBRARY OF FICTION, <lb/> OR <lb/> Family Story Teller.</p>
<p>ADDRESS.</p>
<p>IN completing the First Volume of this Work, the Proprietors take the opportunity of expressing their warmest acknowledgments for the great favour with which it has been received, as issued in monthly parts. Nothing could possibly be more encouraging to them to proceed with energy and spirit in carrying on the publication, which the gradual development of those literary means peculiarly possessed by the Editor will, they confidently anticipate, enable them satisfactorily to do.</p>
<p>The peculiar purpose of the LIBRARY OF FICTION is to put its readers in possession, at an extremely moderate price, of a series of Original Tales or Sketches, all carefully selected from among a host of candidates, and many of the highly-prized contributions of established authors of the very loftiest pretensions in the field of imaginative composition.</p>
<p>But in order to prove that their claims to public notice and approbation are not to be estimated in proportion to the size of the productions comprised in their pages, they subjoin in conclusion, a short abstract from the list of distinguished writers, who either already have contributed, or engaged to contribute, to this publication.</p>
<list>
<item>G. P. R. JAMES, ESQ.</item>
<item>MISS MITFORD.</item>
<item>MISS LANDON.</item>
<item>SHERIDAN KNOWLES, ESQ.</item>
<item>&ldquo;BOZ,&rdquo;</item>
<item>DOUGLAS JERROLD, ESQ.</item>
<item>SAMUEL LOVER, ESO.</item>
<item>ALLAN CUNNINGHAM, ESQ.</item>
<item>CAPTAIN GLASCOCK, AUTHOR OF THE &ldquo;NAVAL SKETCH BOOK.&rdquo;</item>
<item>EDWARD MAYHEW, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;MAKE YOUR WILLS,&rdquo; AND OTHER DRAMAS.</item>
<item>J. AINSWORTH, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;ROOKWOOD.&rdquo;</item>
<item>C. OLLIER, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;INESILLA.&rdquo;</item>
<item>C. WHITEHEAD, ESQ., AUTHOR OF &ldquo;THE CAVALIER,&rdquo;</item>
<item>T. K. HERVEY, ESQ.</item>
<item>CHAPMAN AND HALL, 186, STRAND.</item>
</list></div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
